[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, this is CS50.
And this is week one, our second week.
And today, recall that we'll focus on
this other programming language called
C.
And we gave you a little glimpse
of this last time, wherein
I proposed that this
code here on the screen
is something that you will soon
know how to program, if not already.
But suffice it to say it looks
quite a bit dissimilar to what
we looked at last week which, of
course, was Scratch, which was much more
playful, much more graphical.
And so allow me to disclaim right from
the get go today that for most of us,
today will feel like
a bit of a fire hose.
In fact, pictured here
as an old hack from MIT,
wherein some industrious seniors
hooked up an actual fire hydrant
to a water fountain.
The saying being that
getting an education from MIT
is like drinking from a fire hydrant.
Today will feel a little bit like that.
Because this is sort of a special
occasion that you don't really have
occasion to describe very often.
But it's one in which we're all
going to learn a new language.
And indeed, that's not
something we do every day.
And so at the first
glance, it's going to look
like a lot of new syntax,
a lot of new ideas.
And yet, allow me to reassure,
that what will soon look like this,
this C code here, is
fundamentally the same thing
that you've seen and now experimented
with last week by way of Scratch.
That is to say, within this
other programming language
C, which is more traditional, which is
more text-based, more keyboard-based,
we're still going to see functions,
conditions, Boolean expressions, loops,
and so on.
They're going to all
look a little different.
But the ideas are the same.
And so much like when walking into
someone's home for the very first time
and getting the lay of the
land and seeing a lot of things
that you haven't seen before, you
typically don't care about all
of those visual details.
You might just simply
walk forward and sit down.
Similarly today, we're about
to see a whole lot of details
in the world of this
programming language.
But the goal at hand is to
ignore things at first glance
that we don't necessarily understand
and latch onto those ideas that
are familiar from last week.
So how do we go about actually
writing computer programs?
How do we go about writing them well?
And so allow me to propose that
there's a few guiding lights that
should guide writing of code.
One, of course, is correctness.
And we explored this last week,
whereby the correctness of your code
just speaks to does it work as intended.
When you double click some
icon, when you run some command,
does the program that you or
someone else wrote behave correctly?
Does it do what it says?
But there's other aspects
to writing good software
and writing good programs.
And that has to do with design.
And we alluded a little
bit this last week.
But with design it's more of a
qualitative, a more subjective measure,
just how well written your code is.
So imagine, for instance, from taking
a class where you have to write essays,
you could certainly make
very correct arguments.
But you could make very correct
arguments by writing very long,
rambling sentences, repeating
yourself, and generally not writing
a very good essay or paper.
Now it might be correct.
There's nothing in that
paper for your English class,
history class, or whatever it may
be that you said that was incorrect.
But you might not get
very good marks on it,
because it's just not
very well-designed.
And so similarly, in
the programming world,
is there this notion of actually
writing not only correct code,
but well-designed code.
Wherein you don't repeat yourself.
You write code that's fairly efficient.
It doesn't do more work
than it actually needs to.
And then lastly, let me propose
for today onward in this class,
that there's a third axis
you should keep in mind when
it comes to writing good code.
And that has to do with style.
This is much more of an aesthetic.
So this, in the analogous
world of writing an essay,
would be are using good
punctuation, capitalisation?
Are you indenting new paragraphs?
And those kinds of
aesthetics that fundamentally
don't change the correctness
of what you're saying,
don't change necessarily the quality
of the arguments that you're making,
but the style of your essay,
much like the style of your code,
makes your code much,
much more readable.
So when it comes to writing
good code, you want it first
and foremost to be correct,
but also well well-designed
and also well-styled.
Much like, again, you would when
writing an essay that you would hope
would reflect well on
your capabilities as well.
So when it comes to writing
code, like this, for instance,
this first C program that
someone last week proposed quite
simply prints out on the
screen, hello, world.
Well, how do we go
about writing this code?
Last week we wrote code by
going to Scratch.MIT.edu
and then dragging and
dropping puzzle pieces.
Today is going to be a little different.
We're going to use a
different tool here on out.
And we're going to use
our keyboard much more
than our mouse to actually program.
But to do so, we're going
to go ahead and introduce
the first of several tools this
semester, this one, known as CS50 IDE.
IDE is an acronym, a term
of art in programming,
that stands for Integrated
Development Environment.
Which is just a fancy way
of saying, in this context,
that CS50 IDE is CS50's own
web-based programming environment.
And it's not specific to CS50 per se.
We've simply added a number of
educationally useful features
on top of a third party cloud tool
that anyone on the internet can use.
And our own version thereof
lives at this URL, ide.cs50.io.
So you're welcome to follow
along at that URL today.
But you need not during lecture itself.
But on this upcoming
problem set and beyond,
will you actually use and get more
familiar with this tool hands on.
So let me go ahead and
open up this tool here.
So I've already logged in in advance.
And what you see here is the basic
user interface that's available to you.
And fortunately, there's only
a couple of salient features
that we need to point out right now.
So at the top of the
screen here, it's just
a big black rectangle that in a moment
is going to be filled with code.
Much like using Google
documents or something
like that, where you can create
new tabs and create new files,
this is where I'm going
to do my programming,
along the top of the screen.
And along the bottom is
what we're, in a moment,
going to start calling
our terminal window.
It's in this terminal window that I can
actually run commands and ultimately
run my actual code.
But let's go ahead and write our very
first program in this environment
and realize that this tool,
indeed, is not very CS50 specific.
It's meant to be representative of
a very common popular programming
environment, where you have
a so-called text editor,
or tabbed windows where
you can write code,
and a terminal window where
you can actually run commands.
Ours happens to exist in the cloud.
But you can alternatively
program, certainly,
on your own Mac, or PC, or
any other device these days.
But frankly, it tends to involve
just a non-trivial number
of technical difficulties early
on, especially when we all
have different versions of Mac
OS and Windows and the like.
So this cloud-based environment
just ensures that on day zero,
we can all have the same
exact programming experience.
So I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and
go up to File and New File.
And this is going to create a new
tab, by default called Untitled1,
not very interesting.
So I'm going to now go
up to File and Save.
And by default, I'm going to
save this file as, for instance,
the name hello.c.
So I want to write my very first
program in this language called
C. I'm going to call my file hello.
But I'm going to end it in
a file extension called .c.
And that's indeed the convention.
When writing C programs,
they should end with .c.
Just like Scratch programs, as
you may recall, end in .sb3.
So I'm going to go ahead and
simply click the green button here
that's called Save.
Nothing is really going to change
except for the name and the tab there.
Now I see at top left that
this tab is called hello.c.
And now I can start
typing anything I want.
And frankly, I'm just
going to type from memory
the very first program we saw
last week and just a moment ago.
I'm going to do include stdio.h,
whatever that is for now.
I'm going then going to do int
main(void), whatever that is for now.
I'm going to use the curly brace.
And then close that curly
brace, so to speak, thereafter.
And in here, I'm going to go ahead
and do printf("hello,world") followed
by a semicolon.
Now that was a whole lot of text
right off the top of my head.
This is the kind of muscle
memory that you'll soon
develop when writing a program.
I've, of course, done
this many times before.
So I was able to just do
it off the top of my head.
But in a moment, we'll tease apart what
all of the various lines and characters
that I typed actually do.
But what I'd now like to
do is run this program.
We conjectured last week that this
is just going to print hello, world.
But how?
Well, in the world of our
Macs and PCs and phones,
we would all just tap an icon if
we want to actually run a program.
That's not going to be the
case today, because now we're
in more of a traditional
programming environment.
The environment that
we're now in requires
that I use my keyboard
a little bit more,
or what's known as a Command
Line Interface, or CLI.
This is in contrast with a Graphical
User Interface, or G-U-I, or GUI,
which is what describes Mac
OS windows, iOS, and Android.
But in a command line interface,
I have to do everything
at a so-called command line.
And by that, I'm
referring to this blinking
prompt along the bottom of my screen.
Along the bottom of my
screen here, again, I
described as the terminal window,
where I'm going to type commands,
and this is my command line interface.
Anything I type here is going
to get sent to this computer
and hopefully execute
on its own hardware.
So how do I do this?
And what do I do?
Well, the catch, of course, is that
when writing code in C or Python
or Java or bunches of other
languages that happen to exist,
that's really meant to be written and
understood by me and you, the humans.
But per last week, what
is the only language,
in a sense, that computers understand?
Brian, could we call
on someone for this?
What language do computers only speak?
Because I think there's a disconnect
between where we left off last week
and where we're currently at if I'm
writing code that now looks like this.
Cindy, what language do
computers speak, would you say?
AUDIENCE: Binary.
DAVID MALAN: Binary.
And just elaborate a little bit.
What do you mean by binary, to recap?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
So they use 1's and 0's
to represent everything.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
They use 1's and 0's to
represent everything.
And last week we focused on only
things like numbers and letters
and colors and images and
videos and sound and so forth.
But we didn't actually speak to built
in functionality, which computers also
use 0's and 1's to represent.
That is to say computers, of course,
have the ability these days to print
something on the screen.
And that notion of printing, that
function, that functionality,
also is represented underneath the
hood of a computer, so to speak,
by some pattern of 0's and 1's.
Which is to say that
everything I just typed,
even though it kind of
sort of looks like English
and kind of sort of clearly says print
hello, world, the computer, ironically,
does not know what it
is I have just typed.
In order for it to understand
what I've just typed,
I need to actually
convert it to 0's and 1's.
And so, indeed, the next
step in this process
is to take what I'll describe as
my source code, written here in C,
and last week, too, we saw source
code, it was just graphical.
It was those puzzle pieces in Scratch.
This is my source code that, even though
cryptic, is something I, at least,
the human, eventually
can read and write.
But I need to literally convert
it to patterns of 0's and 1's
that the computer can understand.
Now how do I get to this point?
Well, thankfully, we have a
mental model from last week
that involves problem solving.
And here's a problem.
How do I take source code, written
in this language supposedly called C,
and convert it to 0's and 1's
that the computer understands?
Well, my input, I daresay, is
going to be my source code.
And my output, ideally, is going
to be what we'll call machine code.
Machine code is just a term
of art describing the 0's
and 1's that computers understand.
We didn't use that expression last week.
But this just refers to 0's and 1's
on the right and C code on the left.
So that invites the question, well, what
is between my source code and machine
code?
If I take my source code and feed
it into the proverbial black box,
how do I get out of this black box
the 0's and 1's that the computer
understands?
Well, I need a special
program that we're
going to start calling a compiler.
A compiler is a program that
you can download for free,
or pay for back in the day,
that is a program designed
to convert source code to machine code.
So all I need do if I
want to actually solve
the problem as stated earlier,
whereby I have written this code in C
and I now need to convert
it to 0's and 1's, I just
need to give myself
access to a compiler.
And it turns out one of
those exists within CS50 IDE.
And this is a tool you could download
on your own Mac or PC or the like.
And for now, we're going to describe
that tool as being quite simply called
"make."
Literally, if I want
to make my program, I'm
going to go ahead and type make hello.
And then I'm going to run it with
a little bit of a cryptic syntax,
./hello.
But let's see that in action
to tie this all together.
I'm going to move my cursor
down into my terminal window,
or my command line interface.
And I'm going to literally type hello.
Notice I am not typing make hello.c.
I'm typing the name of the
program I actually want to make
and I just want to call
this program hello.
The compiler is going to
infer from this command
that I actually intend to
compile a file called hello.c.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
There's some crazy cryptic output.
More on that another day.
But the fact that I don't see
any big scary red error messages
is a good thing.
This means that my program
compiled successfully.
Why?
There's just no yellow or red
messages to say otherwise.
But now, if I want to
actually run this program,
I need to type a different command
that's the analog of double
clicking an icon on
your Mac or PC or phone.
I'm going to type literally ./hello.
./hello essentially is like saying go
into the current folder on the computer
I'm using and look for
a program called hello.
I'm going to go ahead and hit
Enter and voila, hello, world.
Now I see, again, a dollar sign
and some other text on the screen.
And we'll tease apart in
just a bit what this means.
But notice, this dollar sign is
just a constant visual reminder
of where my prompt is, where
I can type more commands.
And the computer has done
literally what I asked.
It printed out hello, world.
And now it's waiting
for my second command.
So that was the analog of just printing
hello, world out of the cat's mouth
last week.
But surely we can do more than this.
But let's tie it back to what
we did last week as well.
So that not everything here
is all that dissimilar.
So recall that last
week, we had functions.
And it turns out we had something
called arguments, even though we didn't
necessarily describe them as such.
So a function is like a mini-program.
It's an action or a verb
that you can use when writing
your own program that does something.
We saw the say block last week.
We saw the wait block last week.
Those were verbs, or actions, or
more generally noticed functions.
But functions can also take inputs,
recall, and we did see that last week.
And nowadays, we're going to start
calling inputs to functions arguments,
so to speak.
Another term for them is parameters.
But for all intents and
purposes, those are synonyms.
Arguments are the inputs to functions.
So let's consider then,
from last week, the say
block that we saw last time,
which simply is trying to say out
of the cat's mouth, hello, world.
Well, let me go ahead and convert this,
if you will, to corresponding C code,
just to emphasize how similar,
fundamentally, these two languages
are, even though syntactically C
absolutely looks visually different.
It turns out that if you
want to say something in C,
using this text-based
language like I just did,
you're not going to write say.
You're instead going to write print.
That's actually a bit of a white lie.
You're not going to say print.
You're actually going to say printf,
for reasons we'll eventually see.
It means print a formatted
something or other.
So printf is the analog
in C of say in Scratch.
Now notice in C, I've
got this open parenthesis
and closed parenthesis that, nicely
enough, are kind of ovular in shape.
And notice that they kind
of mimic the white oval
into which we provided input last week.
So in between those
parentheses are going
to be my inputs to this function
printf, otherwise known as arguments.
But they're going to be a
little different this week.
Yes, I'm going to say hello,
world, with a comma in between,
grammatically, just like last week.
But in the world of C, I have
to be a little more particular.
I also have to add double quotes
on the left and the right.
And, somewhat annoyingly, I
also have to add a semicolon
at the end of this line of code.
So just like in English, or
in a lot of human languages,
you end a sentence, for
instance, with a period,
in many lines of code
you will write in C
you've also got to finish your thought,
in this case, with a semicolon.
So this, then, on the
right, is the closest way
of translating this thing on the
left from Scratch to C respectively.
So the ideas are still the same.
But the syntax looks a little different.
And we've just got to ingrain
in ourselves, ultimately,
what these patterns are and what
these human conventions are.
But notice that what we just did
follows the same paradigm as last week.
But let's add a little
more terminology this week.
Last week, we described the black
box as potentially being algorithms,
initially.
And then we started
calling them functions.
Functions are just a programmed version
of an algorithm, the implementation
of an algorithm in code, in software.
So a function might be represented here
as taking inputs otherwise known now
as arguments.
But it turns out that functions can do
at least two different types of things
in the world of programming.
And we've seen these things
already, but we didn't describe them
quite as particularly as we will today.
When a function takes inputs,
that is to say arguments,
just like hello, world is an
input to the say block in Scratch
or the printf function in C, functions
can have what are called side effects.
And recall, we did see this last time.
When we used the say block,
it did output something.
But more technically, it had a
side effect, a visual side effect.
When I used the say block last week
and the printf function this week,
you see something on the screen.
And that is, yes, some form of output.
But it's a little different
from a different form of output
that we saw last time.
So a side effect of a function
is often something visual
that happens on the screen,
like text or audio in that case.
But there's this other feature of
functions that we're going to see
and leverage today known as return
values, where a function can really
just hand you back a value.
It's not going to say it on the screen.
It's not going to vocalize it audibly.
It's going to just pass it back to
you in a way that you, the programmer,
can reuse whatever the
output of that function
was, ideally storing
it even in a variable.
So for instance, recall last
week that we asked the human
their name by way of this ask block.
And the input to the ask block in
this white oval was, what's your name.
And then recall that this ask block
was a little special last week.
Because it gave us access to whatever
the human ultimately typed in.
And that is to say that the ask block
last week essentially returned a value.
It didn't just blindly display whatever
word the human typed in on the screen.
No, it instead returned it
in some sense metaphorically
and stored it in a special
variable called answer.
And so, again, that's the difference.
The say block literally says
something on the screen.
And there's an immediate visual effect.
With the ask block, after
you type in your name,
you don't see your name printed
or displayed again on the screen.
Instead, your name is sort
of tucked away in a variable,
just like a mathematician would store a
number in a variable like x or y or z.
The onus was then on us,
the programmer, last week
to eventually do something
with the value, my name, that
was in that variable called answer.
So how are we going to translate
last week's ask block to C this week?
Well, it turns out there's different
ways to do this in C, none of which
are very easy unless you
use what's called a library.
A library is code that
someone else has written.
And indeed, one of the
things we'll use today
is the so-called CS50 library, which
is a bunch of code, not terribly much,
that the staff and I wrote just to
make it easier to do simple things.
These are training wheels of sorts
that we'll take off completely
within a few weeks' time.
But in order to get
started quickly, it's
going to make it easier to do things
like getting text from the user.
So string is a term of art
in the programming world.
A string is text.
It's a word.
It's a letter.
It's a paragraph.
It's a page of text.
It's just text in some form.
String is what a computer
scientist would call text.
get_string is a function
that we wrote that we will
provide to you that does take inputs.
Notice, per the parentheses
here in C, it can take input.
What might that input be?
Well, just like the
ask block, it's going
to be a prompt that the
human should ultimately see.
So there's a bit more involved,
though, than just using this function.
When you use get_string in C, as
we will soon see in a live demo,
you want to do something
with the human's name.
And to do something
with the human's name,
it's not quite sufficient
to just trust that Scratch
will put it in a variable for you.
In C, as with most programming
languages, it's a lot more pedantic.
Like, if you want something
to end up in a variable,
you've got to do it yourself.
MIT is not going to magically put
it in an answer variable for you.
You have to do it yourself.
So to do this, you simply come up with
the name of the variable that you want,
be it x or y or z, or
more compellingly, answer,
and you use an equal
sign, a single equal sign.
And even though in math this generally
implies equality, in the context of C,
and most programming languages,
the equal sign actually
means what we'll call assignment.
It means, effectively, copy
whatever is on the right
into whatever's on the left.
So if on the right-hand side there's
a function whose purpose in life
is to ask the human what
their name is, that name
is going to get copied from
right to left ultimately
into this variable called answer.
MIT did that automatically
for us in Scratch.
In C, you have to do it yourself.
But you have to be a little
more particular, too.
It turns out that in the world of
C, you can't just have variables.
You have to tell the computer in
advance what type of variable you want.
And specifically, I'm going to tell
the computer that the type of variable
I want is going to be a string.
And the convention for doing so is you
literally write the name of the type
that you want, string being the
only one we've seen thus far.
Then you write the name of the variable.
And then, again, to assign a value
to that variable from right to left,
we have to use the
single equal sign here.
And now, just a quick pause.
Brian, if we could call
on someone for this,
even if you've never programmed
before, if you've taken to heart
one of my pieces of advice earlier.
I'm still missing something.
How might I want to finish the
translation of this Scratch code
to C on the right-hand side?
What is missing from what you can tell?
If you've programmed before,
odds are it will jump right out.
If you've never
programmed before, you'll
have to think back on
what I said earlier.
Jacob, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: Semicolon?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
There's just one
single, stupid semicolon
missing at the end of the line, which is
necessary to make clear to the computer
that this is the end of this thought.
And I sort of impugn it as stupid.
Because honestly, one of the biggest
frustrations when learning how to code,
as will now happen today
and this week and beyond,
is initially you're going to forget
stupid things like the semicolon,
or you're going to forget a single
quote mark, or a parenthesis,
or things like this.
And the most important
advice I can give today
is just try not to get frustrated
by those kinds of stupid things.
It's a lot more interesting.
It's a lot more useful in life
to understand functions and loops
and conditions and not to
let yourself get frustrated
by the more minor aesthetic things that
honestly will just come with practice.
So if the very first mistake
you make is missing a semicolon,
and it takes you 10 minutes,
an hour to figure out what
is wrong with your code, totally normal.
And those frustrations go
away quite quickly in time.
So we then have this translation
of one function to another.
Where else can we take it from here?
Well, let's take a look
at one other translation
that we used after that ask block.
Last week, after we asked
the human their name,
as by providing an input to the
function and getting some output,
we then proceeded to do something with
the return value or output of ask.
Again, we asked the human their name.
Scratch magically, last week, put
the name into the answer variable.
But then I did something with it.
And this is what I mean to distinguish
side effects, which just kind of happen
to you, like something
printing on the screen,
like the cat saying something out
of its mouth, versus a return value,
which is a piece of information,
like a name a human has typed
in being stored somewhere where you, the
programmer, can make use of it later.
It's not happening to you.
It's being handed to
you for subsequent use.
And last week, in order to say
hello comma world all in one breath,
so to speak, we kind of had
to stack these puzzle pieces
on top of one another, making the
output of join the input of say.
In C, this is actually a little easier
even though it's some new syntax.
Again, printf is going
to be the analog for say.
And we've seen that a moment ago.
We're still going to
have the parentheses.
We're still going to have the semicolon.
So what goes inside now the input?
How do I provide hello, answer to C?
Well, I'm going to go ahead and do
hello, in double quotes, but then,
this strange new syntax here, %s.
This is what we're going to call a
format code, a format code, and hence
the f in printf.
Printf doesn't just print things.
It can print format codes as well.
And this is just fancy syntax for
saying plug in some actual value here.
Don't print out s literally.
This is a placeholder for
what will be s, a string.
Well, what do I want to put there?
Here's something new, too.
In Scratch, if you had
two inputs to a function,
you would have two ovals
like this and this one
here that you could either type words
or numbers into or drag variables into.
In C, there's no notion of
ovals or graphics at all.
So instead, we're just going to go
old school and just use a comma.
If you use a comma in between
the parentheses as the arguments
or inputs to a function, that's
going to separate the one on the left
from the one on the right,
thereby being analogous to having
two ovals in the world
of Scratch now there's
something that's potentially a
little visually confusing here.
There's actually two commas
here, of course, and here.
But notice the important detail.
That first one, that's an
English grammatical comma
that I've put inside of my quoted
string, my quoted phrase of text.
That has nothing to do with programming.
That just has everything
to do with English.
The fact that this comma is
outside of those double quotes,
though, means it's significant
in this language called C.
And it separates first
argument from second argument.
And so in this way do
we have the ability now
to also say something on the screen
using printf in this slightly new way.
So let me go ahead then
and do this for real.
Let me go back to CS50 IDE.
And I'm going to go ahead
and go back into this program
here and consider for
just a moment how we
can improve upon this very first
program which literally just prints
hello, world.
Not that interesting.
I can run it all day long.
It's going to say the same thing.
How do I now get input from the user?
Well, it turns out that I can simply
enhance this code a little bit.
Let me go ahead and per the
translation of Scratch earlier,
let me do something like string answer
equals get_string("What's your name?").
So I'm literally typing out
what we saw in C a moment ago.
I'm going to remember
my semicolon over here.
And then I have to change this second
line of code now to not say hello,
world, but instead to say hello, %s.
And then, outside of the double
quotes, I'm going to do a comma
and then provide literally
the word answer, which
is the name of that variable.
But I'm not quite done.
And this is a little subtle.
And invariably, you'll forget
this at some point, too.
In order to use get_string,
I have to use this thing
called the CS50 library,
code that the staff wrote
that you don't have default access to.
And in order to do that, I
need to add one line of code
that we'll explain in more
detail in a little bit.
But for now, just take it on faith
that by adding this line of code
at the very top, include
CS50.h, that will now
give me access to the get_string
function, which I otherwise
wouldn't have access to.
All right, now I'm going to go
back to the terminal window.
And notice the dichotomy here.
If I just run ./hello,
sort of enthusiastically,
let's see what my new program does.
I'm about to be,
unfortunately, disappointed.
Because it still says hello, world.
And you might realize intuitively
what the problem, of course,
here is I haven't actually
recompiled to the code.
And so any time you make
a change to your code,
it does not suffice to just save
the file via file save or Control
or Command-s, I need to recompile it.
And to recompile my code,
that's not such a big deal.
I just type make hello, enter.
Cross my fingers that there's
no yellow or red scary text.
This is all good.
It seems to have compiled
into machine code.
Now I can retype ./hello.
and enter.
And you'll see now my program
is running and waiting for me.
Let me go ahead and type my
name, David enter hello, David.
Let me go ahead and run it
again after clearing the screen.
Let me run it again.
And this time, let's
say my name is Brian.
And I say hello, Brian.
So quite similar to
what we did in Scratch,
but now we're more powerfully doing
this all thus far via my keyboard alone.
All right, so that was a lot.
We wrote hello, world super
quickly off the top of my memory
and then enhanced it to now
take input from the user.
Let me pause here.
If there are any questions,
you're welcome to ask
via chat for either staff
or classmates to answer.
But if you'd like to raise
your virtual hand in Zoom,
please feel free so that I can
clarify or expound on anything here.
Yeah, question from Ryan?
AUDIENCE: I had asked this in the chat.
But so the string before the answer,
that's not the name of the variable.
So hypothetically, you could make it,
like, string A or string anything else.
It just matters what comes after
string is the name of the variable?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Really good question.
In the world of Scratch,
you were required
to use the variable called "answer."
In C, we have the complete
flexibility over what we want to do.
So as Ryan proposed, I could change my
variable's name to just A for short.
I would have to change
it elsewhere, too,
to make clear that the
variable being used
is the same one by a different name.
That's perfectly fine.
But here's where we now get
into a matter of better style.
Having a variable called just
A, it doesn't really lend itself
to the readability of your code.
I might now glance at
my code and be, like,
what is the variable A.
It's a little better when
it comes to writing good code
to actually be more verbose
and using an actual word
like "answer" in this case.
Indeed, even though I keep
describing x and y and z as the go
to variables for a
mathematician, those really
say nothing outside the
context of a Cartesian plane.
So in a program that you write
in C or Scratch or anything else,
using descriptive variable names
is a matter of good style as well.
Jonathan, over to you.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Just a quick question.
How come we have to compile
the code every single time?
And unlike different IDEs,
which if you just run the code,
it automatically compiles.
Why do we have to manually do it?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Really good question.
Why do you have to keep
recompiling the code?
The short answer is just
because this is the way C is.
It's an older language, decades now old.
And so back then, everything
was very deliberate.
User interface was not the top priority.
Performance instead was, for instance.
And so nowadays, there are fancier
integrated development environments.
And some of you might have used things
like codecademy online, or co.org,
where there's very often literally
a play button that you can just
click in the user interface,
and it just plays your program
or runs your program.
What we're doing in this
class is showing you
what those buttons are doing.
So if you do use in an environment
like that that seems to automate this,
it's still happening.
But for our purposes, certainly
at the beginning of the semester,
we're going to do it manually ourselves.
Later in the term, when we introduce
a different language altogether,
for instance, Python,
then kind of, sort of you
don't need to compile anymore,
but more on that in a few weeks.
Good question.
Sophia?
Over to you.
AUDIENCE: I had a question about--
I noticed in the source
code that there's
a backslash like n at
the end of the string.
Is that necessary for every
time, even if it's just one line?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
This backslash n that you're seeing
elsewhere, a bit of a spoiler.
But yeah, let's go ahead and fix
this problem that we've seen,
even though I'm kind of ignoring it.
You know, this now gets
a little particular.
But this looks kind of stupid, honestly.
It says hello, Brian
tilde slash dollar sign.
Like, that is not my intended output.
I literally only wanted to say
hello, Brian, or hello, David.
This visual artifact here, the dollar
sign and the tilde and the slash
have to do with my terminal window,
this command line environment
that I'm using.
And honestly, just to
be a little nitpicky,
frankly, it should
probably be on a new line.
It should just be on its own line so
it's not confused with my own output.
And as Sophie notes, there
is a solution to this.
But, again, per last week, you
need to m when writing algorithms
and in turn, code, you
have to be super precise.
Nowhere in my code have
I told the computer
to move the cursor to the next line.
So I can do that explicitly by doing
backslash n immediately after the %s
but still inside of the double quotes.
This is shorthand notation for
what would be telling the computer,
move the cursor to the next line.
Now you might think that, well, why
don't I just hit Enter like this?
And even though this is all might be
new to most of us, suffice it to say
this just feels like it's
going to get messy quickly.
If you start hitting Enter
in the middle of your code,
that's probably not the right solution.
So instead, programmers
years ago decided
to come up with shorthand notation
like backslash n, otherwise known
as an escape character that signals
to the computer, put a new line here.
So backslash n is new line.
And let me go ahead and recompile this.
After saving my file, let me
go ahead and do make hello.
It seems to compile OK. ./hello.
And let me go ahead and
type in Brian's name again.
And voila, still the same output,
but it's a little cleaner.
So we're being a little bit
better about housekeeping now.
Really good question.
BJ is it?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
So one question I had
is why don't you have
to call the function get string in
order for you for it to ask for input?
Like, it still asked your input when
you assigned it to the variable answer.
DAVID MALAN: Ah, really good question.
Why don't I have to call
get string, for instance,
by putting it on a line of its own?
The way that C and a lot of
programming languages work is they
will evaluate an entire
line of code, for instance,
what I have here on line six from right
to left, at least in this context.
When you have an equal sign
in the code like I do here,
that's telling the computer
you first have to execute,
that is do what is said
on the right-hand side.
And then whatever the
output of that thing is,
store it on the left-hand side.
So it is indeed getting executed,
we're just now spreading things out
on longer lines of code, if
you will, if that makes sense.
So get string is getting executed
because it appears on that line.
All right.
So we've been taking
for granted, frankly,
a few details of these
programs that it's probably
only fair to start teasing apart.
For instance, there was
that int, main, void,
and a whole bunch of other syntax.
So let's tease apart some
of these other lines of code
that I just typed off the top of
my head from memory, but kind of do
need to be there in every
C program you write.
Let's at least start to make
sense of some of that detail.
Recall that in Scratch, we always
started our programs initially
with when green flag clicked.
We eventually saw some other puzzle
pieces, like when you hear an event,
or when there's camera motion.
But this really kick started most of
the programs that we wrote in Scratch.
What is the analog in C of the when
green flag clicked puzzle piece?
It's essentially this.
We won't spend time in
detail today explaining
why it's int, why it's void, why there's
curly braces, why there's parentheses.
For today's purposes only,
let me just stipulate
that this is the analog for this
when green flag clicked puzzle piece.
You've just got to start
your programs initially
with this kind of boilerplate
code, so to speak.
We will start to explain
this in much more detail.
But for now, just take
on faith that this
is how you start writing a program.
But there's, of course, a little more
to the programs we've written thus far.
And particularly, we've seen a
couple of things called header files.
This is another term of art that refers
to a file written in the language
called C whose name ends
with not .c, but with .h.
So we've seen these before as follows.
Here, recall, was the simplest
program we wrote last week in Scratch.
It just says hello, world when
you clicked on the green flag.
This is the analog, the more
complete analog on the right,
of that program today.
But there's something missing.
And it's probably jumping
out at some of you,
because the program is a little
shorter than it was before.
Something's missing,
which is this line here.
And I just wrote that from memory
earlier, but it's referring to a file
called stdio.h, which stands
for standard input output dot h.
So io is an acronym
in the computer world
that just generally refers
to input and output.
So standard io.h is
just a very popular file
that is used in C programs
that gives you the ability
to get input and output from the user.
And it does so by
providing you with printf,
for instance, which
of course, allows you
to generate some form of
output via those side effects
that we described earlier.
But when I wrote my
other program, recall,
that actually had get
string, as BJ noted earlier,
where I can get a line
of text from the user,
I needed something else altogether.
And that's when we added, a moment ago,
a second header file called CS50.h.
So these header files just give
you access to more functions
than you might automatically get
from the language you're using,
which here is C.
It's similar in spirit,
recall last week,
when I started poking around
Scratch's extension menu
and I used the translate
block and the voice block,
the sort of fancier features that
were buried under the extensions menu.
Using an extension in Scratch is
similar to using a header file in C.
It's giving me access to a bit more
functionality than you otherwise get
for free out of the box, so to speak.
All right, well, let
me go ahead and propose
that there are so many
different ways in which I
could have screwed up over the past
few minutes of writing these programs.
I might have omitted a
semicolon, as I implied.
I might have not closed my quotes.
I might have gotten
my parentheses wrong.
I might have misspelled
words altogether.
There's many different ways I
could have screwed that program up.
And frankly, off the record, I'm sort of
crossing my fingers that I didn't screw
up our very first program together.
But invariably, at some point,
maybe not your first program,
but early on in learning how to program
or learning how to program in C,
you will screw up.
And you're going to make some typo.
There's going to be some disconnect
between what your understanding is
and what you're trying to
get the computer to do.
And this is to say there
are tools, thankfully,
that can help you solve those problems.
And the first of which is called help50.
Any of the tools whose names
end with 50 are specifically
educationally oriented, written by
CS50 staff, that are temporary training
wheels that we'll use for the
first several weeks of the class
but then eventually, optionally,
take away in the sense
that you won't need them anymore.
And so help50 is one
command that's going
to allow you to troubleshoot
problems that you might not otherwise
see obviously in your own code.
And let me go and
simulate this as follows.
Let me go back to the
very first program that we
wrote in C, which was quite simply this
one whereby it only said hello, world.
And there's a few different places
I could have screwed up here.
For instance, suppose I was
getting a little ahead of myself
and I admitted the standard io.h
file at the top of my program.
The implication is that
now my computer is not
going to know what printf is, because it
hasn't been included via standard io.h.
So let's see what the error message is.
Hopefully, it'll be a very
self-explanatory message
that makes perfect sense.
Let me go ahead and
recompile this program,
knowing it already to be incorrect.
And oh, my God.
Like, I have more lines of errors
than I actually have lines of code.
And this is kind of a
reality of programming.
A lot of programming
languages, a lot of tools,
frankly, were not designed
with ease of use in mind,
or user-friendliness in mind.
They were really designed with
succinctness and precision in mind.
And they tend, unfortunately,
to assume that the audience is
as technical as the person
who wrote the program.
This, of course, can backfire
when you're just learning how
to program in the first
place, and you have
to make sense of crazy
cryptic output like this.
Today we don't have to focus
on every single word that's
been outputted on the screen, but
let's start to recognize patterns.
Walking into a new space
and just recognizing
familiar objects in the physical
world, let's now do that with code.
The most important thing, perhaps, to
take notice of is that when you mess up
and you make some mistake in your code
such that your program doesn't even
compile from source
code into machine code,
odds are you're going to see a clue
toward the top of the erroneous output
that tells you the name of
the file where you messed up
and the line number where you messed up.
Three implying line
three, and then five might
imply what column or what
character in that line,
but it depends on the particular
problem if that's that useful.
So on line three, I am getting an error,
implicitly declaring library function
printf with type int const char star.
I mean, like, who knows
what that even means?
You will eventually.
But for today, it just means
something bad went wrong.
And you might not see it.
You might not know,
if I hadn't told you,
that I intentionally deleted that line.
So let's see if we can't make
sense of this by using this tool.
Help50 is a tool written
by CS50 staff that
will help translate
arcane cryptic computer
messages to more human
friendly advice and questions
that you're teaching fellow or
teaching assistant might offer you,
say, in the context of office hours.
So to use help50, instead of running
the same command again and again
and seeing the same erroneous
output, literally just right help50
first, at your terminal window,
then write the same exact command
that you're struggling with for
whatever reason, and hit Enter then.
And what will happen is the
same command will get run.
We will analyze, using the help50
program, what that output is.
And we'll try to highlight in
yellow the stuff we recognize.
And then translate it to
more human friendly language.
For instance, after running help50,
we're asking for help, dot dot dot.
In yellow here is the
thing we recognize,
oh, the staff have seen
this problem before.
And then down here, did you forget
to include stdio.h, in which printf
is declared atop of your file?
So hopefully, if we
recognize the problem,
we can guide you with this
sort of rhetorical question
that makes you realize, oh, yes.
That's what I did wrong.
So now I can go back up here,
move to the top of my file,
and add include stdio.h.
And now notice, if I rerun make hello,
voila, the problem is gone altogether.
And we could do this all day long.
There's so many places to mess up.
For instance, I omit the semicolon now.
Let me go ahead and make hello
now without the semicolon.
Now we're going to get a
different error message.
And you'll see, again, the name of
the file where I messed up, hello.c.
This time it's on line five.
And that's true because
the line numbers moved down
after I added more stuff up there.
And you can see expected
semicolon after expression.
So this one's a little
more straightforward.
But you could run
help50 on this command,
too, just to get back a
little more explicit advice.
So help50 will be your
friend any time you
are having trouble getting
your code to actually compile.
Well, let me do something
else that's bad now.
I've very deliberately been
writing fairly pretty code.
I've indented the word printf.
I included some blank line up here.
Just to make it clear, I've
put these curly braces,
so to speak, on their own lines.
But frankly, my computer, or
CS50 IDE is not so particular.
I could technically get
rid of this blank line.
I could move this curly
brace way up here.
I could get rid of this indentation
altogether and move it on its own line.
And then I could just move
this curly brace up here.
Thereby writing a program that's
now only two lines long, not six.
But hopefully already, even if
you've never programmed before,
this should probably
rub you the wrong way.
This is like people
in the real world that
don't use punctuation in
their social media posts
or their emails or the text messages.
They just kind of go on and on and on.
And yes, the information is there.
You can glean what it is
they're trying to communicate.
But my God, is it annoying.
It's hard to read.
There's probably a higher
probability that there's a mistake
and it's going to be harder to find it
because things aren't nicely balanced
on the left and on the right
and on the top and the bottom.
So this is what would be
described as bad style.
My program is still correct.
I've got the stdio.h, I've got the
semicolon, and everything else.
But it's really bad style.
Because it's just ugly.
There's not much white space.
There's not a lot of
blank lines or indentation
that just make it easier for you and I
to read this thing from top to bottom.
So notice, it does compile.
So help50 is not going to help me fix
this problem because it compiles OK.
But it can run another program
that we're going to call style50.
This is another
educationally oriented tool
that's installed in CS50 IDE
that allows you to figure out
how to improve the style of your code.
So when I run style50 on this
prettier code, it indeed looks good.
But it's still giving me advice.
It's telling me to add
something called comments.
And a bunch of you figured this
out in the world of Scratch.
You can add little sticky
notes or post-it notes
to Scratch that are
sort of notes to self
that remind you what something does, or
maybe explains to your teaching fellow
or teaching assistant
what something does.
C supports these as well.
So for instance, if I just wanted
to be really pedantic here and make
clear to the human reading my
code what I'm trying to do,
I could say something like greet user.
And notice the syntax here.
I've put a new line above
my existing line of code,
and I've similarly indented
it so everything lines up
visually beautifully.
I've done slash slash, which says,
hey, compiler, this is a comment.
This is for human eyes only.
This is not actual C code, per se.
Then I hit the spacebar.
And then I just typed
out an English phrase.
And this could be any spoken language.
But I went ahead and typed greet user.
Why?
Well, it's just a
reminder to myself what
the purpose of the following line
of code is, to greet the user.
This is marginally better, for instance,
than saying print hello, world.
And let me just ask you,
even if you've never
programmed before why is
the first comment a better
comment than the second?
Like, why should I say, if anything,
greet user instead of print
hello, world in the
form of these comments.
Yeah, Olivia, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: OK.
It tells you the purpose of the code.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, the purpose
of the code as opposed to what?
What distinction are you making?
AUDIENCE: Versus telling
you exactly what it's doing.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
If your comment is almost
identical to the actual code,
you're not really conveying much more
information to the reader, let alone
yourself in the future.
Explaining it more generally, what the
purpose of this line of code is to do,
is to greet the user, that's
a little more descriptive.
Now to be super fair,
honestly, this program
is so short that even
though style50, yes, would
prefer that you add some
comment, if your program really
reduces to one line of code, you
probably don't need a comment here.
However, pretty much
every other program we're
going to write here on after is
going to be more than just one
main line of code, like this printf.
So it's going to make
much more sense soon
to come that we're going
to want to actually add
to our code some actual comments.
Well, let me introduce
one final tool here
that will help us solve
problems as we proceed now
to write more sophisticated programs.
And this is check50.
This is a tool specifically that you'll
use either in labs or in problem sets,
the course's programming
assignments, to actually check
the correctness of your code.
So whereas help50 just helps
you compile your code typically,
when it's not compiling
at all, style50 helps
you improve the style
of your code, check50
will check the correctness of your
code against some automated tests
that we, the staff, have written
that are consistent with whatever
the homework problem actually is.
So we write some tests to make sure
that your code is working correctly
as per our own specifications.
So how might I run check50?
This will totally depend on
the problem set or the lab.
And we will always, in
the problem set or lab,
tell you what command
to type for check50.
It's not something you could
necessarily figure out on your own.
I happen to remember that
we have a check, that
is a test, called CS50/problems/hello.
Odds are you will never
run this identical command.
Again, in the problem set or lab, we
will always tell you what to type.
You won't know what otherwise to type
unless we tell you what test to use.
This is going to now upload my
file hello.c to a service called
GitHub, which again is a
popular tool for sharing code.
We use it to collect
submissions for this.
I'm going to then type in my password.
You won't see it.
You'll instead see asterisks
or, like, bullets in a web page.
I'm going to go ahead
and hit Enter then.
It's going to verify my code.
It's going to do some thinking.
It's uploading now, dot dot dot.
And now we're just waiting
for the internet to respond.
Because somewhere on
CS50 servers, we are
running your code after compiling
your code, or in this case mine,
and making sure, yes, it actually
behaved as it should have.
And what you'll typically see,
hopefully, are a bunch of green smiley
faces saying yes, that your code
exists, yes, that your code compiles,
and yes, for instance,
it prints hello, world.
Sometimes you might
see red frowny faces,
which means no, your code did not work
exactly as it should, per the lab,
or of the problem set.
At which point, it's back to the
drawing board on your part to figure out
exactly what needs to be fixed up here.
Sometimes you'll see yellow output
with just a straight yellow face, which
just means we weren't even
able to run a certain test
because some other test already failed.
So it's meant to be
relatively quick feedback
on the correctness of your code before
you even submit it and call it a day.
And check50 instructions will always
be accompanied by the problem itself
in the lab or problem set.
So some final commands here now.
Within this terminal window, I can do
more than just run make and ./hello,
or whatever my program's name is.
And I can do more than
help50 and style50
and Check50 it turns out that I'm
really using, in the form of CS50 IDE,
my own server in the cloud.
So yes, I'm using a website.
But what CS50 IDE really is,
it's like your own server
or your own computer in the cloud.
Somewhere out there on the internet,
you have your own username and password
in the form of CS50 IDE.
And only you can access the files
that you write, the programs that you
write that are stored in this IDE.
And there's a few more features
I'll now draw our attention to.
Perhaps the most friendly one is
this little folder icon at top left.
If I click this little
folder icon, you'll
now see what's generally
called a file browser
or a file tree, which is just
a graphical representation
of the files in my account,
or in my IDE, in this case.
It looks similar to Mac OS.
It looks similar to Windows.
And this is just a graphical
user interface built into the IDE
so that, for instance, if I close my
tab by clicking this little x button up
here, and I want to reopen
the file, much like you
would imagine on a Mac
or PC, it's as simple
as double clicking the
file on the left-hand side.
But notice I didn't click on hello.
Because notice what happens.
If I open hello, my gosh,
like, what is going on here?
This is kind of a mess.
There's redness.
There's dots.
Any thoughts from someone on
why I'm seeing what I'm seeing?
Because odds are you will,
accidentally, at some point,
click on a file like hello
instead of on a file like hello.c.
Sara, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: It's a binary code.
So it's the machine language.
So it doesn't allow the user to see
them, besides the code they write in C.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
What you're trying to look at in
this tab is binary code, 0's and 1's.
However, those 0's and
1's are technically
being misinterpreted at the
moment as ASCII characters,
or Unicode characters.
So recall from last week, ASCII is this
mapping between numbers and letters.
And numbers, of course, are
just patterns of 0's and 1's.
And this looks super cryptic, because
we're trying to misinterpret 0's and
1's as though they're ASCII characters.
And recall that there's many more
characters in ASCII and Unicode
than A through Z. And the numbers,
there's some unprintable characters.
And indeed, all the
funkiness we're seeing here
is just a misinterpretation
of 0's and 1's that
are instructions to the computer,
machine code for the computer being
misinterpreted as text.
So if you can't edit a binary
file like this, so to speak,
you should just close hello
when you do something like that
and make sure you've double clicked
on and opened your actual source code
file as well.
So we've seen strings.
And there's other data types.
And there's other functions.
And there's loops and
conditions and so much more.
I think we're at a good point now to
perhaps take a break, let this sink in.
Why don't we go ahead and
take a seven minute break?
And when we resume, we'll
introduce a few more features of C
and compare them against what
we saw last week in Scratch.
So we'll see you in seven minutes.
All right, we are back.
So recall where we left off was we
were looking at this graphical user
interface at top left.
The file browser, the file tree, that
just gives us more graphical access
to the files in our account.
But let's now do this the old school
command line way in my terminal window.
So it turns out that
using our terminal window,
can we not only compile code and run
code and run check50 style, help50,
and the like, we can
also manipulate files
and folders, even, that
happen to exist in my IDE.
That is in the computer I have
access to here in the cloud.
And the first command I've
proposed is that we type ls.
Ls is shorthand notation for list.
And quite simply, ls lists the files
or folders in your current folder.
So this would be like double clicking
on your My Documents folder in Windows,
or documents in Mac OS.
Ls just lists the contents.
Now, notice hello is a little weird.
It's highlighted in green and
there's an asterisk after it.
And that's just a visual cue
that that file is executable.
That is, that is a program
that you can run with ./hello.
The star is not part of the file name.
And of course, we see hello.c.
Now, suppose that I wanted
to maybe rename my file.
Well, I could, much like
in Mac OS or Windows,
I could go up to the
file browser up here.
I could Control click or Right click.
And notice there's a whole
bunch of menu options
that pop up just like
on your own computer.
And I could rename the
file right up here.
But generally speaking, we're going
to do things at the command line
only because, rudimentary as
some of these operations today
are, it's going to be a much more
powerful command line interface for me.
So suppose I change my
mind, and you know what?
I don't like this version of hello.
I want to delete that
program and start over.
Strictly speaking, I don't
need to delete hello ever.
I can just recompile it, and it will
keep getting changed and changed.
But if I do want to remove it, I can
type rm hello, and then hit Enter.
And then I'll be asked,
remove regular file hello?
That's just a visual confirmation
that I do indeed want to delete.
And I can type y or
yes or some such reply.
And if I hit y and Enter,
nothing seems to happen,
but notice what happened
up here at top left.
Notice that hello is now
gone, leaving only hello.c.
And if I type ls again, now
I see only my code file.
Maybe now I want to change
this program, and I don't
want to write hello.c, but goodbye.c.
Well, let me close the tab up there.
And yes, I could go and Right
click or Control click on it,
but, again, we don't need to
use the graphical interface.
Let me go ahead and instead
do mv hello.c goodbye.c.
Mv is the move command.
And even though it would be nice if
it's called rename instead of move,
move just moves one file to another
location or to another name.
So if I do mv hello.c goodbye.c.
Notice what happened at top left.
Now my same file is called goodbye.c.
And if, again, I type ls, I can
see that it's indeed renamed.
Now, let me go ahead and
move that back because I
want to stay on my hello.c program.
But suppose I want to
start organizing my files.
In a moment we're going to
start writing more programs,
and so my account is
going to get a little bit
messy with more and more files
over the course of today.
So suppose you want to create a
folder, otherwise known as a directory.
I'm going to go ahead and
type mkdir for make directory.
And then the name of the directory I
want to make, for instance, lecture.
You can call it anything you want, but
if I'm in lecture, I'm writing code,
maybe I want to store all of today's
files in a lecture directory.
When I hit Enter there, notice what
happens in my file tree up here.
I now see a lecture folder.
If I click the triangle, it's empty
because I haven't put anything in it.
So let me go ahead and move
hello.c into the lecture folder.
Mv hello.c lecture, and
now let me hit Enter.
And voila, now notice that it's
nested inside of this lecture folder.
And indeed, if I now type ls for
list, I only see the lecture folder.
Unfortunately, I kind
of now don't have access
to hello.c within this
command line environment
unless I change into that directory.
Now, in the world of Macs
and PCs we, obviously,
would just double click on a folder
and voila we're inside of it.
In a command line interface
you need to be more deliberate.
So I'm going to do cd,
for change directory,
then lecture, and then I'm
going to go ahead and hit Enter.
And now notice, and now
it might make more sense
why this whole time we've been seeing
in blue this tilde lecture slash.
The tilde just means my
so-called home directory.
Like my own account, my own default
folder, like my documents and windows,
or documents on Mac OS.
That's what tilde represents
in shorthand notation.
Lecture is the name of the
folder that I am now inside.
So it's as though I double clicked
on lecture in Mac OS or Windows
to open a folder.
Now I'm inside this lecture
directory in my terminal window.
So if I now type ls
enter, I should see voila,
the hello.c file that I moved into it.
Now, let me undo this
because I'm going to go ahead
and keep things a
little simpler for now.
And suppose that I want to move
hello.c into where it previously was.
Last piece of syntax.
There's this shorthand notation for
what we'll call a parent folder.
So just like in family trees, there's
the notion of parents, and children,
and grandchildren, and so forth.
That's also true in computer
systems that have folders.
And folders inside of folders.
And folders inside of
folders inside of folders.
There's a hierarchy there
much like a family tree.
So if I want to move
hello.c one level up,
I can actually do mv
hello.c space dot dot.
And that's like saying move this
file to the folder up above.
When I do that, notice
what happened at top left.
Now hello.c is not inside of the
lecture folder, but below it.
And indeed, if I type ls now in the
lecture folder, there's nothing there.
How do I move myself up one level in
the family tree that are these folders?
Let me go ahead and
type cd space dot dot.
So change directory to my parent.
Dot dot just means your parent.
The folder up above, Enter.
And now, I'm apparently
in just tilde slash,
which is, again, cryptic shorthand
notation for your own home directory--
your My Documents or documents folder.
And if, lastly, I type ls here,
I'm done with this lecture folder.
I don't want to bother
storing things in a folder.
I can do not rm for remove,
like I did to get rid of hello,
but rmdir to remove a directory.
And voila, it's gone.
And I've undone all of the various
changes that I made earlier.
But perhaps now it makes
a little more sense
why I was doing something earlier.
Let me open up my hello.c file.
Let me make hello again, which
is way back where we left off.
And recall that all this time
I've been doing dot slash hello.
Well, why is that?
Well, just as dot dot refers
to your parent directory,
a single dot refers to
your current directory.
So even though this
looks a little silly,
dot slash hello is just
a very explicit way
of telling the computer,
run the program called hello
that's right here in
my current directory.
Dot means current directory.
Dot dot means parent directory.
And so there we see,
finally, why I've been
typing dot slash hello all this time.
But again, it's just the textual
analog of doing something
like double clicking on an
icon in Mac OS or Windows.
So there's other commands too, and
over time you'll get exposed to these
and use them for various problems.
Cp for copy, for
instance, is yet another.
And many others, but these are
all just standard commands.
They are not CS50 specific.
Standard commands that allow us
to manipulate files and folders
in a computer like this.
And question from Max.
AUDIENCE: Hi.
Yeah, sorry.
I was just wondering.
I don't really understand the
difference between the hello program
and the hello.c program.
It seems like the one that doesn't have
dot c on it isn't used for anything.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, it is though.
So recall that we have
two things in the story.
We have source code, which is
the C code I've been writing.
And then machine code,
which is the zeros
and ones that the computer understands.
I have been writing all of my
code in the file called hello.c.
But after I compile it
with make, the make program
creates a new file called hello
that technically contains only zeros
and ones.
And that is the machine
code that I'm actually
running when I do dot slash hello.
So again, I can use rm and I
can get rid of the hello program
just like I did before.
And now we're back at the
very beginning of the story
where we wrote this code from scratch.
If I now type make, and
let me do this now, ls.
Notice I've only got one file.
Let me now do make hello.
I see that cryptic output, but if I
type ls again, now I have two files.
And that's because only the green
one with the asterisk is executable.
That is the machine code that
the compiler has created for me.
And I should say and disclaim, I've
been telling a little bit of a white lie
today.
Make itself is not actually a compiler.
We'll see next week
exactly what make is doing.
But it's making it easier for
us to actually compile our code,
but more on that next time.
All right.
So we've seen only strings thus
far, but it turns out in C,
and in a lot of languages, there's other
things known as types or data types.
That is to say, you can
have variables and values
that aren't just strings of text,
but that are maybe integers,
like numbers, one, two, three, four.
Or maybe floating point values,
like 3.14159, or other such values.
You can have Boolean values,
which are only true or false.
You can have characters or chars,
which are single characters.
This is to say, within a language like
C there's actually a whole bunch of data
types that are available to you.
String is only one of them.
And there's even more than
are on this list here,
but this is just a list of some of the
most common ones that we'll see today
and we'll use this coming
week in the first problem set
that allow you to tell the computer not
only to store a value in a variable,
but what type of value
to store in a variable.
Moreover, we have in the CS50
library a whole bunch more functions.
We've seen get_string already.
But similarly have we
created functions that you
can use for problem sets,
labs, and beyond that
allow you to get a single
character via a get_char.
That can allow you to get
an integer via get_int.
That can allow you to
get a floating point
value, which is a fancy way
of describing a real number,
with a decimal point using get_float.
But it turns out that each of these
data types, like int and float,
only have a finite number of bits.
And recall from last week that
we played around with light bulbs
and we played around with bits
and zeros and ones more generally.
It turns out that every
one of these data types,
char, double, floats, int,
long, string, and so forth, all
use a specific number of bits.
And it turns out that int, for instance,
integers in C, only use 32 bits.
And that's great until such time as
you want to count higher than roughly 4
billion, at which point you can't.
We'll see later today that if you're
only using a specific number of bits
you can only count so high, and
so there exist other data types.
For instance, a long.
A long is another type of number
in C that just uses 64 bits.
So it gives you way more expressiveness,
way more patterns of zeros and ones
to count even higher.
Similarly, a double is like
a floating point value.
A real number with a decimal point
and some number of digits after it.
A double allows you to have even more
digits after it than a float would.
So we'll see and use some of
these data types in just a bit.
Printf, similarly, has the ability
to print out not only strings
as we saw, but also using different
format codes other data types as well.
These are a little more cryptic and it's
fine to look these things up as needed,
but you'll eventually ingrain
them for common use cases.
Percent c is going to be the placeholder
for printing a single character.
Percent c for a char, so to speak.
Percent f is going to be
for a floating point value.
So if you want to print out a
real number with a decimal point,
you're going to use percent f.
If you want to print an
integer using print f,
you're going to use
percent i for integer.
If you want to print a string
we've already seen percent s.
And if you want to print
a long integer, a.k.a.
long, you're going to use percent li.
And there's even others, but these
are perhaps some of the most common.
And it just means that, again, C
really needs you, the programmer,
to be precise.
You can't just say, print this.
You have to tell printf how to
print the variable or the value
that you're passing into it.
And then lastly, it turns
out that in C there's
a whole bunch of operators, certainly
mathematical ones and bunches of others
as well.
Just like Scratch out a
whole toolkit of operators.
And suffice it to say for now that C
also supports addition, subtraction,
multiplication, division,
and even the remainder
operator, which a little cryptically
is represented with a percent sign.
Not to be confused with
printf's format codes,
but this is to say that some of the
earliest uses of computers, of course,
were all mathematically oriented
in spreadsheet programs.
Programs like VisiCalc and the like
back before there was Excel and Google
spreadsheets.
And they certainly, computers,
are very good at supporting math.
And so these are just some of
the operators that will now see
are available to us.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go back to my IDE
after cleaning things
up, and starting fresh with just nothing
in my terminal window and no tabs open.
And let me go ahead and write
my next program this time
using some more of these functions.
I'm going to go ahead and create
a file up here called addition.c.
So addition.c, but I could
call this anything I want,
but it's important to add the dot c.
Otherwise the computer will not
know that it's actual source
code as opposed to machine code.
And let me go ahead and make
use of the CS50 library.
So let me include cs50.h.
Let me include stdio.h, so that I can
use things like get_int and printf.
And then, again, for today's purposes,
I'm just going to do int main
void, and then the curly braces.
And again, for today, just take
on faith this is necessary.
But we'll explain within
a week or two exactly why
we keep writing int main void.
But for now, it's like the win
green flag clicked puzzle piece.
Let me go ahead now and get
an integer from the user.
Suppose my goal now is not
to write a program that
gets a string of text and prints
out hello, Brian, or hello, David.
Let me go ahead and write
a program that maybe asks
for two integers, two numbers,
and then just adds them together.
So let me make the simplest
of calculators using code.
Well, I'm going to go ahead
and declare a variable called
x, just like a mathematician would.
And I'm going to assign it
the value of calling get_int.
And I'll just say
something like x colon.
I could say anything I want, what is x?
But I'm going to keep it
simple and just say x colon.
Semicolon to end my thought.
So again, similar in spirit to
what I did with string before,
but now I'm using get_int to get a
number or an integer from the user.
The quoted parameter here
or argument is the input
to get_int, which is going to be
the prompt that the human sees.
The equals sign, recall,
is the assignment operator,
which says, copy the
return value on the right--
the integer that the human
hopefully will type in--
over to the left.
And the left says, give
me a variable called, x,
and let me store integers in it.
So before, we use string on the left
and we used get_string the right.
The only difference
now is int on the left,
because I want a number,
and get_int on the right.
Then let me go ahead and do this
again and get another number.
Get_int, and I'll just say, y colon.
But again, I could say, what is y
question mark, or anything in English.
But the last line is going
to be the interesting one.
Now, I'm going to go ahead
and print out for instance,
the sum of these two numbers.
But printf, again, takes an input that
tells it what to print out exactly.
So I can't really type a number
here yet because I don't know
what the human is going to type in.
So I'm going to put a placeholder.
I'm going to percent i, which
says, put a number here,
I just don't know yet what it is.
And then just to keep
things clean, I'm going
to do backslash n, which just
says, give me a new line also.
That's just an aesthetic detail to
move the cursor to the next line just
to keep things clean.
But now printf is going
to take a second argument.
And whether you've
programmed or not before--
Brian, let's go to someone
in the audience if we could--
what should I type after the comma
if the purpose of this program
is quite simply to add
two numbers together?
Even if you've never programmed before,
based on the operators that exist
and some of the syntax
we've seen thus far,
what would your instincts
have you type here?
Even if you've never done this before.
Santiago, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: I would say
to just write x plus y.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it is simple
and as straightforward as that.
X plus y is the right intuition.
I'm going to add a semicolon to the
very end just to finish my thought.
But indeed, computers,
and C in this case,
absolutely understand arithmetic and
mathematical operations, so just type
what you mean.
I'm going to go ahead now and
save the file and go down below.
And I'm not going to
type make hello anymore.
Now I want to type make addition,
because that is the name of my file
implicitly.
Addition.c.
I want to compile into a
program called addition.
Hopefully, this is where I cross my
fingers, I didn't make any mistakes.
And I'm going to go ahead
and run make addition.
All this well, no error messages.
If I had made a mistake
and it didn't even compile,
help50 might have been my next instinct.
Now I'm going to go ahead
and run dot slash addition.
And notice, I'm first prompted for x.
I'm going to go ahead and do one.
I'm next prompted for y.
I'm going to go ahead and do one again.
And voila, as Santiago proposed, I
indeed see on the screen x plus y,
or the value two.
And I didn't hardcode two.
I substituted in using i whatever
the result of x plus y actually is.
Now notice, some of the features
of the get_int function for you.
Suppose that you're not being very
cooperative and you type in cat for x.
Notice that get_int just ignores
you and prompts you again.
If I type in dog it ignores
me and prompts me again.
If I type in 1.23, it ignores
me and prompts me again
because it wants an
integer in this case.
A number like one, two, three, four.
Or negative one, two, three, four,
or zero, or anything above or below.
So fine, I'll cooperate now
and give it the number one.
Same for y.
It's going to ignore
any non-integer input.
So if I give it a number
like two this time,
I'll hopefully get the answer of three.
All right.
So we have a basic calculator in
C. We're using some basic building
blocks as before.
We've got these header files, which just
give me access to get_int and printf
respectively.
But suppose now I want
to count up even higher.
You know what?
Let me try something like this.
Let me run this program once more.
And let me get a little greedy.
How about 4,000,000,000.
So roughly-- well, exactly--
4 billion.
That's the number I want to type in.
Notice that x does not like that.
So get_int does not accept 4 billion.
Well, let me try it maybe 3 billion.
Uh-huh.
Didn't like that.
How about 2 billion?
OK, that one worked.
Let me pause here.
What's going on perhaps?
Now again, we the staff
wrote get_int, so we
are the ones that are rejecting cats,
and rejecting dogs, and rejecting
4 billion, and even 3 billion.
But in this case, it's
a little less clear.
Why did we reject 4 billion
and 3 billion do you think?
Based on some of the
definitions thus far today.
Why might this be?
Nathaniel, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: There's a cap
on the size of the number
since it would take too many bits and
bytes after the size of 2 billion.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So integers, again, are implemented
in C as these things ints.
Ints only use, it turns
out, 32 bits total.
And you would only know that
by having been taught it
or looked it up for a
particular computer system.
But they on CS50 IDE, and most modern
systems, an integer is only 32 bits.
And that then invites
the question, well,
if you've got 32 bits or light
bulbs, how high can you count?
Well, it turns out with
32 light bulbs, or bits,
you can count roughly
as high as 4 billion.
You can absolutely count
as high as 3 billion.
And yet, get_int still rejecting it.
But that's because the get_int
function supports integers broadly
speaking, which includes
not only positive numbers,
but also negative numbers and zero.
And the catch is that if you want
to support both positive numbers
and negative numbers, you can represent
4 billion or so total possible values.
But if you want to go as far to the left
and as far to the right on the number
line that I'm describing.
You can only really count as high as
2 billion in the positive direction
and negative 2 billion in
the negative direction.
Because that still gives
you a total of 4 billion,
but not nearly as high as
3 billion or 4 billion.
So what might the solution here be?
Well, I recall earlier noting
that there's other data types.
Not just ints and strings, but
also longs, which literally
are longer integers, namely 64 bit.
So let me go ahead and try this.
Let me go ahead and change
get_int to get_long.
This get_int to get_long.
Let me change this int a
long, and this int to a long.
So same program, same
calculator, but I'm
now using a different
data type that's just
going to use more bits to store values.
Let me run make addition
again to recompile my program.
And, oh, damn it.
I screwed up.
So let's see if we can't
glean what's wrong here.
Let me scroll up.
And I can't emphasize this enough.
Sometimes-- I got lucky here and I
only have one mistake, apparently,
in the error messages-- it
is not going to be uncommon
for you to have two errors, 10
errors, in like two lines of code.
This is because sometimes when
you have errors in your code,
the compiler sometimes
just gets confused.
And if it gets sufficiently confused,
it starts thinking everything
is an error in your actual code.
So the most important
takeaway is that no matter
how many errors you seem to have, always
scroll up to the top of the output
and address the first error first.
So that's why I scrolled up in my window
to look immediately below what I typed,
make addition, and
here's the first error.
Addition.c on line 10.
All right.
I can't see line 10, so
let me scroll my code up.
And it's saying something about
format specifies type int,
but the argument has type long.
We haven't seen this error before,
but I think I can infer from this.
It's not super cryptic even
though it's unfamiliar.
I think what this means is that
percent i recall was for integers.
I think what I need is a different
format code for long integers, which
is going to be li instead.
And that was from my
little cheat sheet earlier.
So let me go ahead and try this again.
Make addition after
changing the i to an li.
That indeed works.
Now let me do--
oops, typo.
Now let me dot slash addition.
And now I'll type in 4,000,000,000.
4 billion.
Now get_long is happy, and it
will accept such a long integer
because it has enough bits.
All right, questions on
types like ints and longs,
or functions like get_int or get_long.
Yeah, Peter.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
When I typed 2 billion and
both were integers, well,
eventually it just gives
you the wrong answer.
Some negative numbers.
Is that because of the bits and bytes?
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
It's the same answer.
So I didn't demonstrate that,
but if you inputed both 2 billion
for x and 2 billion for y and then
you try to add those together,
that would give you
mathematically 4 billion.
But again, an int is not big
enough to store 4 billion
if we want to also be able to
represent negative numbers.
So Peter what you're seeing
is that you can't fit
the result in the data type allowed.
And we'll see in a moment--
in a little bit today, actually,
what the ramifications of that
are, but the symptom you're
describing is exactly.
That you tried to cram too big of a
number into finitely many bits, 32.
You can avoid that problem though,
of course, by switching over to long.
Let me try one other thing
that's a bit curious.
Let me go ahead and write a
slightly different program now.
And I'm going to describe
this as truncation.c.
Fancy term, but we'll see what
this means in just a moment.
I'm going to give myself
at the top, cs50.h.
And I'm going to give myself stdio.h.
And it's certainly fine, once you get
started with the first lab or problem
set, if it takes you much longer
to type some of these things out.
I'm just doing it for muscle memory.
Int main void.
And now we're good to go with a new
program in a file called truncation.c.
I'm going to go ahead and
prompt a user for an int, again.
So just like before.
I'm going to prompt the user for
another int, just like before.
And then I'm going to
go ahead and do this.
I want to do division this time.
So not just a addition,
that was a little too easy.
Let me do a division.
So let me give myself another
variable, z equals x divided by y.
And let me pause here
for a moment and just ask
the question, what data type
should I perhaps use for z?
This line of code is not yet correct,
because recall that any time you
create a new variable
on the left here, I'm
going to need to put something to
the left of that variable's name
so that C knows what
type of variable I want.
And thus far we've seen
string and int and long.
So would you propose we use one
of those or something else for z?
How about Jack.
What do you think?
AUDIENCE: Would it be a float?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so float.
So float, which is short for floating
point value, which is the programmer's
way of describing a real number.
Let me go ahead and do that.
A float.
And I'm guessing your instincts
for float were that, well,
if you type in one number
for x and another for y
and the result is a fraction
of some sort, so something
with a decimal point.
We need to store it in a
float so that we can actually
store whatever the numbers
are after the decimal point.
So let's go ahead and do this.
Let me now go ahead and print this out.
Percent f backslash n, because
I'm printing a float this time.
And then let me go ahead and
print out the value of z.
And you know what?
Just for good measure, let me start
practicing good style here too.
So get a number from user.
Let me give myself another comment.
Get another number from user.
Or you know what?
This seems a little silly.
I can combine these lines.
And why don't I just say, get,
for instance, numbers from user.
That's a reasonable way
to comment your code.
And then let's just go
ahead and divide x by y.
But even this is getting
a little pedantic
because you can kind of
read that from the code.
So at some point we might not
even need a comment for that.
So let's just simplify as such.
Let's go ahead now and compile this.
Make-- come on--
make truncation.
All right, it compiles OK.
And I like how we used a float here.
That does feel correct.
So let me run truncation.
And let me go ahead and type in,
for instance, 4 for x and 2 for y.
OK, I like that.
It's 2.000, so that's the
correct math calculation.
How about 1 divided by 2.
So x is 1, y is 2, and it's 0.000000.
All right, well, maybe
that was just a fluke.
Let me try running it again.
How about 2/3?
2 divided by 3.
That's not right either.
All right.
How about 4/3?
Let's put a bigger
number for the x, so 4/3.
OK, it's closer to right.
But this is an example,
this week, of a bug.
So my code compile.
So syntactically it's fine,
but this is a logical bug.
Like I've somehow used
C code improperly.
So what might be going on here?
Why is 1 divided by 2 and 2
divided by 3 both apparently zero,
followed by six zeros
after the decimal point.
And even 4/3 gives me
1.000000 instead of 1.33333.
Nina, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: Because with int
they don't recognize decimals.
So 4/3 question three only goes
into 4 one time, so it returns a 1.
And you need to use
other types of character,
like a float or a double if
you want the actual decimal.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
This one's more subtle than
the mistakes I've made before.
But C, like most programming languages,
is going to take you literally.
So if on the right hand side
of this expression, on line 11,
I am literally doing x divided by y.
You first have to ask yourself,
well, what is the type of x?
What is the type of y?
If they are both ints, by
definition of how C works,
you are going to get back
an integer as your answer.
So if you do 1 divided by 2.
Yes, mathematically that's 0.50000.
However, if you convert that to an
int, in so far as x and y are ints,
the way C works is it truncates
everything after the decimal point.
So it does the math correctly, but
because you cannot fit floating point
values, you cannot fit decimal points
and numbers thereafter in an integer,
you get you lose all of those digits
after the decimal point because you can
only fit the integer part of
the answer into an integer.
It's not relevant that I'm saving
the result ultimately in a float
because that's too late.
The math has already been
done on the right hand side.
And so yes, I'm storing an integer in
a float so I can print it as a float,
but it's too late.
Everything after the decimal point
has already been thrown away.
So what are the implications
of this, or how could I fix?
Well, I could go through and
just change all of this right.
Well, if the problem is
that x and y are ints,
well, let me just change them to floats.
And change this up here, change x
to a float, change y to a float,
and so forth.
That would fix the problem.
But that's kind of a heavy
handed solution to this problem.
Go through and change all of your code.
You can instead be a
little more clever, and you
can convince the computer to
convert an integer to a float
by something known as casting.
So I can actually go in here, and
using a new syntax I can say float y.
And I can even, for good measure,
but it's not strictly necessary,
also do it to x.
You can in C, cast or typecast
one data type to another
by literally in parentheses just
putting the new data type that you want.
And if it makes mathematical sense for
one to be converted into the other,
the computer will do it for you.
So in this way I'm telling the
computer, convert x to a float,
convert y to a float, then do the math.
And so before when I typed in one
and two respectively for x and y,
now it's like I typed in 1.0 and 2.0.
And 1.0 divided by 2.0 is
going to be mathematically 0.5,
but because x and y now were
converted in advance to floats,
the answer is going to
remain a float, 0.5.
And that's what's going to get
stored in z and ultimately printed.
So if I rerun truncation
having now fixed this problem.
Let me do dot slash truncation.
Type in one, type in two.
I don't have to type the 0.0 myself.
The computer's doing that for me
via these casts in parentheses.
Now I see that the answer is indeed 0.5.
All right.
So we seem to have now some
very basic low level control
over what you can do with the program.
Let's now add back all
of the fancy features
that we had from Scratch
last week so we can
start making more interesting programs.
So variables and another term of
art called syntactic sugar is also
among C's features here.
So recall from last week when we
wanted to have a variable called
counter set equal to zero.
We can go ahead and define it like this.
In C, starting today, we're
going to instead say something
like, counter equals zero.
But we additionally need to specify
the data type of that variable,
and we need to end our
thought with a semicolon.
So whereas we set counter to
zero like this last week, now
it's going to translate quite simply
to this on the right hand side.
Well, what comes after that?
Well, if we wanted to increment a
counter variable last week by one,
adding one to it, we used
quite simply this puzzle piece.
This week we need to be a little more
explicit and say something like this.
Counter equals counter plus one,
and semicolon to finish the thought.
Now, this might seem very
mathematically paradoxical.
Like, how can counter
equal counter plus one?
Like, that just doesn't work logically.
But that's not the
equal sign in this case.
In C, as with other
languages we'll encounter,
the equals sign is the assignment
operator from right to left.
So this is saying,
take counter plus one,
and store that mathematical
result on the left.
So whatever counter is, add one, store
the result in counter thereafter.
Effectively, increasing
its total by one.
Now this is a very common
operation in programs
we'll see over the term where
you just want to add something up
because you want to keep track
of the count of something.
So it turns out there's
some syntactic sugar, which
means there's a different way of doing
this syntactically that doesn't give
you any new capabilities
that you didn't already
have in C. It just makes it marginally
more pleasant or quicker to type.
So this line of code in C is
identical to saying this line of code
in C. Counter plus equals one semicolon
means take the variable on the left
and just add one to it.
And it's slightly more
succinct, and it just
makes your code a little more readable
because it's just fewer things for us
humans to have to read.
But you can even do one step further.
Additional syntactic
sugar exists, whereby
you don't even need to type this.
You can instead just
do counter plus plus.
Counter plus plus is the
shortest hand notation
in C for just adding one to a variable.
All right.
Besides variables, what else do we
have in our toolkit as of last week?
Well, we also had in our toolkit
last week the notion, of course,
of conditions.
A condition was like a
fork in the road that
could allow you to do this thing,
this other thing, or something else
altogether.
In Scratch for instance, if we wanted
last week to compare two variables,
x and y for inequality.
Is x less than y?
And if so, say x is less than y.
How can we translate this to C?
Well, the syntax is going
to be quite simply this.
Some new stuff.
Some more parentheses,
some more curly braces.
But it kind of visually looks
the same, albeit in text form.
I literally say, if a
space, then in parentheses I
include my Boolean expression,
recall those from last week.
X less than y is my Boolean expression.
Then notice I use an open curly
brace and a close curly brace.
And then I'm just leaving a blank
line for one or more lines of code
just like I might of last week.
And in fact, let's put the
equivalent line of code here.
Print out using printf, x
is less than y, backslash n.
So we've already done
that translation before.
Say is just like printf,
just like if now is like if.
Strictly speaking, especially
if you've programmed before,
you do not need these two
curly braces if you only
have one line of code
inside of the condition.
However, stylistically for
CS50 and for style50's sake,
always include these curly braces
nonetheless, and on their own lines.
All right, what else
can we do in Scratch?
Recall that we can do if else.
And we can go either one way in the
fork or the other way in the fork.
In C, the corresponding code
is going to look like this.
So it's almost the same as before.
I've just added else, and then another
curly brace and a close curly brace.
And let me just add in the printf's.
And you can see that in C this is
really like the black and white,
the text based version of what
was very graphical last week,
but the idea is the same.
You just got to start to recognize
where the parentheses go,
where the curly braces
go, the semicolons,
and all that sort of visual stuff.
All right, let's make one
more Scratch comparison.
Here is one where I said if x is
less than y, say x is less than y.
Else if x is greater than
y, say x is greater than y.
Else if x equals y,
then say x equal to y.
Now, here is where
Scratch and C diverge.
Because Scratch is meant
to be very user friendly
and not require long explanations of
assignment operators, MIT for Scratch
just use the equal sign for equality.
Whereas C uses the equal sign for
assignment from left to right,
but this means equality as before.
All right.
Now, notice the difference here.
Everything is a line
by line translation,
although we can put else if on the
same line and else if on the same line.
Except here is kind of a
stupid workaround, right?
In some sense humans decades ago
realized, oh, shoot, at one point.
We've already used the
equal sign for assignment.
What do we use now for equality?
Well, MIT ignored that problem and just
used a single equal sign for equality.
Computer scientists inventing
C and subsequent languages
when comparing two values on
the left and right for equality
used two equal signs just because.
One equal sign is assignment
from right to left.
Two equal signs is equality comparisons.
Are these two values equal?
But you know what?
This is not necessarily well designed.
It is correct.
Logically both my scratch
code and my C code is correct,
but can anyone make an observation
as to why the code is not
necessarily well designed?
I'm doing a little more
work than I need to.
I could tighten this
code up a little bit.
I could type slightly fewer
characters and accomplish
the same correct decision making.
Any thoughts on in what sense this
code is not perfectly designed?
[INAUDIBLE], over to you.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so you
used else if two times.
You could have used else in the
end and without the condition.
DAVID MALAN: Really good observation.
I'm using else if twice,
which logically is fine.
This code is correct.
It's asking and answering the
right questions, but consider this.
If x is less than y, is one
possibility, one fork in the road.
Else if x greater than y is the second.
What's the only other possibility
logically in the world of math?
Either it's less than or
greater than or equal to.
There's no reason to belabor the point
and ask that third question explicitly.
Let's simplify the code and
marginally better design it as this.
Just get rid of the
else if as you proposed.
Which isn't that much cleaner,
isn't that much shorter,
but it does avoid asking
an additional question.
So instead of maybe three questions
being asked, now there's only two.
And frankly, if you're writing a lot
of code or doing this again and again
and again, that kind of difference
might very well add up and indeed
give us now some better code.
So now that I have the ability
to use these conditions.
Let's actually try converting
this into a program.
Let me go ahead and
open up a program that I
wrote in advance called conditions.c.
And I have at the top of the
file my two includes as usual.
And then down here, I have pretty
much what we just saw on the slide,
plus two calls, or uses, of get_int.
And then I'm just asking this
question down here, if x less than y.
Else if x greater than y.
Else go ahead and do the following.
So it's just a copy paste pretty
much of the Scratch translation.
Let me go ahead and make conditions,
which again, conditions.c
is the name of the file.
No apparent mistakes.
So let me go ahead and run
dot slash conditions, Enter.
And x will be 1, y is 2.
And indeed, x is less than y.
If I go ahead and run this, this time
for instance, with how about 10 and 5.
X is greater than y.
And then lastly, if I go ahead
and run this with 4 and 4.
X is equal to y.
So I now have a C program
that is adding conditions
for me, which is actually then allowing
me to make decisions and print out
one thing potentially or the other.
But let me do something
slightly fancier.
Let me go ahead and open up another--
let me write this program from Scratch.
Suppose I want to write
a program called agree.c
that stimulates the idea
of like these stupid forms
that you have to agree to
when using a piece of software
for the first time or the like.
Or even when I deleted a file before
I had to type in yes or y in order
to proceed.
Let me go ahead and
include cd50.h at the top.
include stdio.h at the top.
And then my int main void,
which is copy paste from before.
And now let me do this.
Let me go ahead and get, not an input
from the user, and not even a word.
Let's keep it simple and just ask
the user for y or n, for yes or no.
Let me go ahead and give myself
a char, and I'll call it c.
But I could call it
anything, like answer.
But c seems reasonable
if I only have one char.
Let me go ahead and call
the function, get_char.
And let me just ask, do
you agree, question mark.
And then let me go
ahead and compare this.
So if c equals y, then let me go ahead
and print out agreed backslash n.
Else if c equals n, let me go ahead
and print out for instance, not agreed.
Now unfortunately, I've made a couple
of mistakes here that at least one
of which might be a little
more obvious than the other.
Any thoughts on what mistakes or
bugs I might have introduced already
into this program?
Anyone at all?
Yeah, how about, Olivia.
What do you think?
AUDIENCE: For one thing
that for the Boolean
you did use a single equals
sign instead of the double.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
So I use the single equal sign instead
of double, so I need to fix that.
And there's another
even more subtle bug.
And this is because C is very specific
when it comes to its data types.
All this time I've been using
double quotes for strings,
but it turns out in C you
have to use single quotes when
you're comparing individual characters.
So I'm going to go in here and
change only the quotes around y and n
to be single quotes.
Why?
Because I'm now dealing
with the world of chars.
Chars are individual
characters like y or n.
And when you are talking
about characters,
you need to quote them
literally like this.
The variable name, c,
doesn't need to be quoted.
But y and n do need to be quoted.
But I don't need to change any
of my other quotes in the file
because those are still strings of text
that is actual phrases or sentences.
So let me go ahead and
try running make agree.
It compiles OK.
Let me go ahead and run dot slash agree.
Do I agree?
Let me go ahead and type in y.
Agreed, I like that.
So let me try n, no.
Not I agreed.
And I left off a backslash n, so
let me fix that real quick just
for consistency.
Let me recompile my program and
pretend that never happened.
But let me very reasonably now do this.
Dot slash agree.
I want to agree.
And yes, capital y.
Huh, nothing happened.
What about n, capital N?
Nothing happened.
But the program still works.
If I do lower case it works.
And if I do lower case there it works.
So what's going on?
Well, again, the computer's only
going to take you literally.
And even though we humans
might be, oh, it's fine.
It's upper case or a lower case.
You have to be more explicit.
So we can ask two questions as follows.
We could do something
like else if c equals
equals capital Y in single quotes.
You could imagine, again,
saying agreed like this.
But just like last week when I started
copying and pasting Scratch blocks,
that's probably not very good design.
Similarly, this block of code, lines
11 through 14, is almost identical to 7
through 10.
Let's just get rid of one of them.
And let's see if we can't
combine these thoughts.
Let me express if c equals equals
y, or c equals equals capital Y.
And indeed, you can
use this vertical bar
operator, which is the
logical or operator,
and actually say two questions at once.
It turns out you can do this
with the notion of and, a logical
and, by using ampersand ampersand.
More on those another time.
But two vertical bars is the
equivalent of just saying,
if this on the left
or this on the right.
And now if I save and
recompile the program with make
agree, and dot slash agree.
You'll see that I can type in y
in lowercase, or Y in uppercase,
and now it works.
So again, it would have
been correct to just add
another else if and another else if.
But again, not necessary because
I can combine these thoughts
and make my program better designed.
And notice too, all this time
I've been very religiously
indenting every time I'm
inside of curly braces.
Indenting every time I have
an if condition or an else if.
So I'm manifesting, hopefully,
good style aesthetics as well.
All right.
Well, now let's consider
that we have the ability not
only to express conditions, but how
about also these things called loops.
Well, turns out in Scratch we
had very straightforward loops.
Do the following forever.
C is a little clunkier.
There's no forever keyword in C, but
we can mimic this idea as follows.
The closest way to
translate forever in C
is actually to say while, which kind
of has the right semantics in English.
Like, while something
is the case, do this,
but you have to be even more explicit.
You can't just say while and
then say printf hello, world.
It turns out in C that while,
similar to a condition,
is constantly asking a question to
decide whether or not to continue.
Very similar, again, to a condition
with its own Boolean expression.
So with while in C, you have to have
parentheses after the word while,
and you have to ask a
question in those parentheses.
You have to say something like,
x greater than y, x less than y,
or the like.
But this is a bit of a
corner case in the sense
that if you want to
do something forever,
who cares what the question is.
You just want the
answer always to be yes.
Or in computer terms, always to be true.
And the most blunt way
to express true always
is literally to write the word true.
So even though this looks
a little weird, this in C
is how you deliberately
induce what we'll
call an infinite loop that never stops
because true is always by definition
true.
You don't even have to ask
a more complicated question.
You could put a less than sign,
a greater than sign, or the like.
But if you just want
something to happen forever,
this is the most canonical way
to express something forever.
Well, what if you want to do
something finitely many times?
Well, we can do that in
C as well using what's
going to be called a for
loop, or a while loop.
Well, let's consider
both of these in turn.
So if I want to do something 50
times, the most mechanical manual way
I can think of is like just
count on my fingers, right?
Like, one, two, three, all
the way up to 50 somehow.
Or 10 maximally on my hands.
So how can I do something
finitely many times in C?
Well, I have at my disposal variables.
So let me give myself a
variable called counter.
Initialize it to zero semicolon.
And the data type will
be int, because I just
need to count much like on my fingers.
But you know what?
Counter is a little verbose.
Programmers whenever they're counting
frequently, just counting up from zero
on up, they'll often just use i
for integer, or c for character,
or s for string.
You don't want to do
that always in your code.
It's sometimes better for your variables
to be more descriptively named,
but for a stupid variable that's
just going to count from zero on up,
let's just keep it simple and call it i.
I can now do a while
loop again, but now I
have to ask a question because I
don't want this running forever.
I want it running 50 times.
What question could I ask?
Well, why don't I just check.
While i is less than 50.
So it's like counting up on 50 fingers.
Let me start at zero and count up
to, but not through i equals 50.
So so long as i is less
than 50, do the following.
What do I want to do?
I want to keep printing
out hello, world.
Hello, world.
But I'm not done.
Because on every iteration of this
loop, on every cycle of this loop,
I need to do one more
thing mathematically.
I need to add another
finger, add another finger.
Or in other words, I
need to add one to i.
So let me go ahead and set i equal
to whatever it is now, plus one.
But again, we have some
syntactic sugar just
to make this a little
cleaner, a little tighter.
I could do i plus equals one.
Or even more succinctly, i plus plus.
So even though this is way more
annoying to implement than in Scratch
where MIT just gives you what you want,
in C we have all of the building blocks
now with variables and with loops
to implement the notion of repeating
some finite number of times.
But there's another way to do this.
And as you might have discovered
with problem set zero,
there's different ways to achieve
the same goals in Scratch.
Similarly in C, I could do this.
I could just start counting at
one and count up through 50.
So there's no greater than or
equal sign key on your keyboard,
most likely, or less than or equal to.
So in C, as with other languages,
you just use two characters.
You do less than sign
followed by the equals sign.
And that expresses
less than or equal to.
So this is also correct.
If I start counting at one
I need to count through 50.
You can do this.
Don't do this.
This is unconventional.
And like programmers
will conventionally,
per last week when we started
always counting from zero with all
the light bulbs off, they'll instead
start at zero and count up to 50.
Which gives you zero
through 49 implicitly.
So do this, not that.
But this does speak to the
fact that you can solve
problems in so many different ways.
There's another way, fundamentally, too.
We could start counting
from 50 down to zero.
The only difference being we have to do
i minus minus instead of i plus plus.
So again, that's three different
ways to solve the same problem.
And again, you'll start to have the
right instincts and muscle memory,
and you'll also start to see common
patterns in lecture code, your TF
or teaching assistants code,
books and references online.
There just tend to be the ways to
do things even though all of these
are still right.
All right.
One more approach to loops here.
It turns out there's another loop
construct that's a little more cryptic,
and it's called a for loop.
And it allows you to
automate-- or rather,
allows you to express all of those
steps a little more concisely.
So for printf hello, world is going
to get us one step closer to printing
hello, world 50 times.
But the for statement, just
like the while statement,
comes with necessary
parentheses after it,
but this time you can put
more stuff in the parentheses.
It's not just a Boolean expression.
First, the first thing
in the parentheses
is you can initialize any
variable you want to some value.
I might say encounter equals
zero, or more succinctly,
int i equals zero semicolon.
But the way the for loop
looks, it's a little funky.
You can do multiple things on one line.
The second thing inside of
the parentheses to a for loop
is a condition that you want to
check again and again and again.
And the last thing in the
parentheses of a for loop
is an update, or an
incrementation or decrementation
whereby you can do i equals i plus one.
Or rather, let's just
do i plus equals one.
Or even more succinctly, i plus plus.
This is perhaps the
most conventional way
in C and in other programming
languages to do something 50 times,
or a finite number of times.
It's different looking from
the things we've seen thus far.
There's semicolons in weirder places.
There's more stuff in parentheses.
So again, you'll develop
the muscle memory overall.
But for now just realize this
says, initialize i to zero.
Check the condition.
And if i is less than
50 print hello, world.
Then update i.
Then check the condition.
If it's less than 50,
print hello, world.
Then increment i.
Then check the condition.
Then if it's less then,
print hello, world.
So the initialization of
the variable happens once.
Everything else happens
again and again and again
until you've done this some 50 times.
All right.
So with those building
blocks, that's kind of it
for our translation of Scratch
into C. Let's now start
to build up some more
interesting programs in practice
for instance, abstraction.
So abstraction, recall, was
this problem solving principle
whereby you can simplify otherwise
more complicated details.
And abstraction is a simplification
on top of more complicated details
or implementation details
as a programmer might say.
So for instance, let
me go ahead and write
a program here called meow, similar
to last week, but this time in C.
And in order to make
a cat meow textually,
let me give myself stdio.h at the top.
Int main void down here.
Again, I'm in a file called meow.c.
And I've included stdio.h
and int main void.
And now I'm going to go ahead
and just do something like this.
Printf, quote unquote,
"meow", backslash n.
And I want this cat to
meow textually three times.
Let me save that file.
Make meow.
All right.
Now, dot slash meow.
Meow, meow, meow all in text.
So not nearly as cute or pretty
as the one with the cat last week,
but it's correct.
But it's not very well designed, right?
Because I'm repeating myself.
I literally copied and pasted,
and those are bad instincts.
But now we have the ability
to do things with loops.
So let me actually delete
this part of the function.
And let me try to remember
from the example before.
If I want to do something three
times I could use a while loop,
but that felt like a
bunch of lines of code.
Let me do this.
Int i equals zero.
i less than three.
i plus plus.
So cryptic, but this, again, is
the de facto way of doing something
a finite number of times.
Initialize some variable, like
i to zero, check a condition,
and keep incrementing your
variable again and again
so that it executes a
total of that many times.
Now, let me go ahead and printf meow--
mellow-- meow on the inside.
Let me go ahead and
recompile meow by make meow.
Let me dot slash meow, and voila.
Now the program is
arguably better designed.
But let me take this one step further.
Recall that the trajectory last
week was to not only implement meow
with better design, without repeating
yourself, thereby using a loop.
But remember we introduced
the abstraction that
was a custom puzzle piece called meow.
So in C, turns out we have the ability
to make our own functions as well.
And the syntax is going to take a little
getting used to, but let me go ahead
and do this.
Let me get rid of my printf here.
And at the bottom of my file--
actually, at the top of my file
I'm going to go ahead
and type void meow void.
Which is very cryptic for
today, but again, this
is fine to be boilerplate,
copy pasted for now.
Let me go ahead and
just printf meow here.
Even though we haven't explained
and won't explain today
what this keyword void means, what
I've done in lines three through six
is create my own custom function.
C does not come with a
function called meow.
CS50's library does not come
with a function called meow.
But now thanks to me,
there exists a function
called meow whose sole purpose in
life is just to print out meow.
But what's cool about this
now is that down here, just
like with Scratch last week, I can
now call a function called meow.
And my code is a little more
readable because it rather
says what it does by just by
way of the function's name.
And let me go ahead
now and compile this.
Make meow.
So far so good.
Dot slash meow, and it seems to work OK.
But I don't love the fact
that I've implemented meow
at the top of the file.
It's not a big deal.
By convention we'll typically put custom
functions at the bottom of the file.
Why?
Only because when a
programmer, or in our case,
a teaching fellow wants to understand
your code from top to bottom.
It's just human convention to put the
main program, the main function rather,
at the top of your file.
The problem is when I do this, I'm going
to have created a problem for myself.
When I run make meow now, darn it.
Two errors generated, and so there's
a couple of bugs to be solved.
But first, Brian, a
question from the group.
BRIAN YU: There was a question that
came in from the chat about why
it is that on line five,
for example, you don't have
a semicolon at the end of the for loop.
And on line 11 you
don't have a semicolon
at the end of the function name.
So why do some lines need semicolons
at the end, but other lines don't?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
Why do some of these lines not
have semicolons, but others do?
The short answer, not to be
glib, is honestly just because.
The way the language was designed
was that you should generally
finish your thoughts when expressing
verbs or actions or functions
with semicolons.
And we've seen that after
printf for instance.
We've just seen that after meow.
However, when you're using
other programming constructs,
like loops or like custom functions,
you don't have semicolons there.
Why?
Some humans years ago
just decided that we
don't need semicolons in those places.
And this is one of those things that it
will take a while to develop the muscle
memory and the mental model for
recognizing where those things go
and don't.
But thus far the only
places we've seen semicolons
are at the ends of functions,
like meow and printf here.
And now, admittedly weirdly, inside
of the parentheses for the for loop.
But again, when tackling problem sets
one and the first lab and so forth,
you'll often want to refer back to
examples like these in the slides
and the references in your
section so that you can
wrap your mind around these patterns.
So let me go ahead now and solve the two
problems I seem to have created here.
It's a little non obvious, but it's
reminiscent of what we've seen before.
Implicit declaration of
function meow is invalid in C99.
C99 is referring to the 1999 version
of C the language we're using,
but it's just getting
confused, C is right now.
Well, why is that?
Well, let me scroll up here and let
me make the point that frankly C,
and in turn my compiler,
they're not that bright.
Like, they're only going to do
what I tell them to do explicitly.
And the problem at the moment is
that when the compiler reads my code
from top to bottom, left or
right, it is not until line 11
the meow function even exists.
However, I am trying on line seven at
the moment to use that meow function.
So my compiler, frankly,
just doesn't know
what meow is because it
hasn't gotten to meow later.
And the compiler is not
smart enough, or not
user friendly enough to read
everything first and then decide
if there's a problem.
It's only going to read it
once through top to bottom,
and it's going to yell at you the
moment it encounters the problem.
So the solution to this is
quite simply, move the function
to the top of your file.
But again, that just gets annoying
eventually because then you
have to go fishing for your
main function which might
be dozens of lines down in the file.
Or there's another way, and we'll
explain this in due time too.
But you can also copy the very first
line only of your custom function.
Put it at the top of
your file above main.
And then, to Brian's question
end that with a semicolon.
So this is weird.
This is what's generally known as
a prototype, which is a hint only.
It's sort of a clever way of
telling the compiler there
will exist a function called
meow, but just not yet.
But know that it will.
And it's just kind of a
workaround, a common workaround,
for that particular problem.
All right.
So let me go ahead and make one
more change, one more change here.
Suppose that I want to really
finish off this meow example
just like we did in Scratch.
Whereby we also allow meow to take
some number of meows as input.
So I don't want to have this for
loop anymore in my main function.
Suppose I just want to be able to say,
meow three, inside of my main function.
Three thereby being the
input to the meow function.
I now need to change my custom function,
just like I did last week, as follows.
It turns out-- and more on
this in the weeks to come--
that this mention a void here on line
11 refers to the return value or output
of this function.
Long story short, my custom meow
function today has no return value.
It doesn't output anything
per se, it instead only
has a side effect of printing
visually on the screen.
But it does have an input.
And if you want to function in
C to take input or arguments,
you can literally do something
like, the name of the type you want
and the name of the
variable that you want.
So suppose I want meow to take as
input some number, we'll call it n.
And I want to use that number in a loop.
I could then do something like this.
For int i gets zero, i is
less than n, i plus plus.
I can then surround my
printf with curly braces.
And now notice just like last week
with my final implementation of meow,
my custom function can take input
as denoted by the parentheses. i
doesn't have output per se,
that's why I'm leaving void here.
But again, we'll explain void
more in detail down the road.
But now I'm using that input
inside of the for loop.
So even though this is a
new implementation in C,
I'm using the same building blocks.
I'm using a for loop like before,
but instead of hard coding three,
or 50 like I did earlier, now I'm
actually going to go ahead and just
plug-in that variable just like
Scratch allowed me to do as well.
Well, what if I want to
do something even fancier.
You know what?
Let me go ahead and do this.
Suppose that we want to
get input from the user,
but we really want them to
provide a specific type of input.
Let me go ahead and introduce
one other type of loop.
And this one I'm going to go ahead
and grab from my archives, the code
that I brought with me today.
And I'm going to go ahead and copy
over a file called positive.c,
which is going to insist that the
user give me a positive value.
So this too is on the course's website.
And let me just walk us through
code that I already wrote.
Here at the top of my file, I'm
including some now familiar header
files.
And down here, I'm
including a prototype.
That is a hint for a function
that's going to be called,
quite simply, get_positive_int.
So this is a function that's only
going to get a positive integer.
Then in my main function,
notice I'm going to use this.
I'm going to get a variable
called i on line 10,
and I'm going to get a
positive int from the user.
And then I'm just going to print it out.
But what's interesting now is I
have this additional abstraction.
The CS50 library does not come with
a function called get_positive_int,
but it does come with a
function called get_int.
And notice what I've done down
here between lines 15 and 24.
Down here I've declared a
function called get_positive_int,
and notice that's my own
custom function name.
It doesn't take any inputs, it just
gets a positive integer from the human.
But now notice it does
have a return value.
Previously I used the word void
to say the absence of input
or the absence of output.
Here I'm using it's
still to say, no inputs.
It just always gets a positive int.
But I'm saying int on the left hand
side of this custom function's name
because this function does have output.
What is the output going to be?
We'll, notice here on line 17, I give
myself a variable and I call it n.
Then I have one final new feature of
C today, this loop which is called,
not a while loop, but a do while loop.
A do while loop is almost
the same as a while loop,
except that it blindly does one thing
first before checking a condition.
So notice here I'm going
to do the following.
Call get_int with this
prompt, positive integer,
and then store the return value
into the variable called n.
Then down here, notice I'm
saying while n less than one.
So this is kind of a weird
syntax, but if mathematically I
want the user to give
me a positive integer,
that's technically the same thing as
wanting the user to give me an integer
and just make sure that
it is not less than one.
Because if it's less than one, it's
zero or negative one or negative two,
that's obviously not a positive integer.
So how can I express this in code?
The only new thing at the
moment now is the fact
that there exists this
thing called do while.
And again, the value of do while
is that you will do things at least
once and then check a condition.
A while loop checks the condition
first and then does something instead.
This is what I want
in this case, though.
I want to do this.
Get an integer from the user
prompting them for a positive integer.
Then while n is less than
one-- so if the human
typed in zero, or negative one, or
negative two, what do I want to do?
The same thing again
and again and again.
So it reads rather grammatically.
Do the following while
n is less than one.
And then lastly, and the only
other new line here is return n.
This is the way that a program can
actually return some value to you.
It can hand you back a value,
not by printing it on the screen,
not by saying it audibly or
visually from a cat's mouth.
It returns it in the sense
that what's being returned here
is n, which is an integer that
matches the output of this function.
Why is this useful?
Well let's scroll back up.
Let's now take for granted that we
get_positive_int function exists.
And now notice how we
can use it in main.
I call get_positive_int on the right.
It returns a value I claim
that is of type integer.
I'm storing that return value on
the left in this variable called i.
And then I'm printing out i.
And just like last week with
the meow example in Scratch,
now that I have implemented
get_positive_int,
it sort of out of sight, out of mind.
I know that it can be done,
and I can abstract away
the underlying implementation details
by just calling it by its name.
But there's one weird thing
that I do want to point out
about these implementation details.
Why did I declare n out here?
Every other time I've created
a variable, I've done this.
It turns out we've been
getting lucky this whole time,
and any time I've declared
variables they've technically
been in between curly braces.
The curly braces belonging to the
main function or my other functions
that I've written thus far.
But in this case, the
problem is when you
declare a variable
inside of curly braces,
you run into what we'll
call an issue of scope.
The scope of a variable is the
lines of code in which it exists.
The scope of a variable are the lines
of code where you can use that variable.
And the rule of thumb
for today is that if you
declare a variable
inside of curly braces
like those here on line
26 and 28, which you
must do for a do while
loop, that variable, n,
only exists inside of
those curly braces.
Which means you cannot compare
it against one in line 29.
Which means you cannot
return it in line 30.
It just no longer exists.
So you're doing all of this work
getting the variable n, and then boom.
It's gone once you exit top
to bottom these curly braces.
So the workaround for that,
stupid though it is frankly,
is that you can declare n
initially on its own line, 25.
You don't need to assign it
a value even, because you're
going to assign it a value eventually.
But again, to create a variable, as I
keep saying, is to declare a variable.
You don't need to define it as having
a value necessarily right away.
So this is a way to work around what's
otherwise known as an issue of scope.
All right, with all of these puzzle
pieces now in place so to speak,
let me go ahead and
propose that we solve
something a little more graphical.
So you'll recall, of course, Super Mario
Brothers is one of the first problem
sets that we alluded to last week.
And within this game there's
a whole bunch of visuals.
For instance, there's
this visual early on where
there's four question marks in the sky.
And these question marks, if
you jump up and underneath them,
give you coins for instance.
So let me draw our attention
to that, and let me ask, well,
how could I write a program in C that
just prints out four question marks?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and write
a program called mario.c.
Let me go ahead and include
stdio.h in a file called mario.c.
Give myself a main
function, int main void.
I'm going to keep this simple.
Printf one, two, three,
four, backslash n semicolon.
This is not nearly as cool or
pretty as the old school game,
but if I run make mario and
then do dot slash mario, voila.
I get a very poor approximation
of these four blocks in the sky
using just Ascii, or
really called Ascii art.
But I can do a little better than that.
Recall that now we have
the ability to use loops.
So I could say for int i gets zero.
i is less than four, i plus plus.
And then I could just print out
one question mark at a time.
And then at the very
end of my program, I
could print out a new line just to move
the cursor at the very last moment.
I don't want to do that
every question mark,
because then it would be vertical.
I want to do it only at the end.
So now if I make mario,
and I run mario now.
Same exact result, but a
little better in the sense
that now it's using a loop
instead of a hard coded value.
But let me be a little more clever
now, and let me do this instead.
Let me borrow the logic of
that positive integer example
and do something like this.
Let me give myself a variable
called, n, for a number.
And let me do the
following just like before.
Let me get an integer from
the user, and ask the user
for the width of the bricks
that I want to print.
So it's not always four.
Maybe it's a variable number.
And then let me go ahead and do
this while n is less than one.
So identical to my logic before.
And then you know what?
Once I have a value of n--
so let me go ahead up here
and give myself a comment.
Get positive integer from user.
That rather says what all
of these lines of code do.
I don't need to comment
every single line.
You can comment every few if it
makes logical sense to do so.
Let me go ahead now and print
out that many question marks.
So I can do a loop.
For int i gets zero, i is less
than n this time, i plus plus.
And now I can print out a single
question mark without a new line.
And then at the very
end of my program, I
can print out a single
new line semicolon.
Let me go ahead now and increase
the size of my terminal window.
Let me do make mario.
And now-- oh, darn it.
Implicit declaration
of function get_int.
Here's where help50 might be my friend.
So let me go ahead and
run help50 make mario.
It's going to ask for help.
You seem to have an error
in mario.c on line nine.
By implicit declaration
of function get_int,
clang means-- which is the name of the
compiler, which we'll see next week--
means that it doesn't recognize get_int.
Did you forget to include
cs50.h in which get_int
declared at top of your file.
And indeed, I did.
So let me fix this.
So include cs50.h.
Save the file.
Recompile with make mario.
And now let me go ahead
and do dot slash mario,
and I'll give myself a width of four.
It's the same.
Let me give myself a width of 40.
Now I get that dynamism.
Let me give myself a
width of 50, and so forth.
So now we have a program that's much
more dynamic, but you know what?
Let's go ahead and enhance
this a little further.
Later on in Super Mario Brothers,
there's like a lot of this underworld
here where you see
these grids of bricks,
and let me draw our attention to this.
This looks like multiple bricks
both horizontally and vertically.
So there's a width and a height.
So how can I go about printing
out, maybe that's three by three.
Three bricks across
by three bricks down.
Let me actually go into my program here.
Get rid of all the question
mark stuff from before.
And consider how I could print
out a three by three grid.
Well, the bad approach here,
if I go back into my code,
would be to print out three of these.
And then maybe three more.
Maybe three more, and then three more.
But of course, this copy paste
is not going to fly long term,
but that's fine.
Let me do make mario.
Dot slash mario.
All right.
I kind of sort of have a grid
that looks like this thing here.
It's not exactly, but at
least it's the right idea.
But this is not necessarily
the best way to do this.
I really want to go three
across and three down.
Well, it turns out using C we can
actually express that as well.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and print out
for instance, the following.
not just hash, hash, hash, again
and again and again.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me print out one row at a time.
So for int i gets zero, i
less than three, plus plus.
I don't know what I'm
about to do yet, but I know
that I'm going to do it three times.
What do I want to do three times?
Well, I want three rows, and on
every row I want three hashes.
So you know what you can do?
You can nest loops.
Let me do for int j gets zero, j is
less than three, and j plus plus.
I don't know what I'm
going to do yet, but I do
know I'm going to do this three times.
And you can perhaps see
where this is going.
Three things three times, that's
going to give me all nine bricks.
So long as inside of this inner
loop, so to speak, this nested loop,
I print one of those hashes.
So long as after that loop, I
print out a new line over here.
So to be clear, even if it's not
obvious at first glance what's
going on, we already know that this is
the type of syntax you use for doing
something finitely many times, three.
This is the same syntax, but I'm
using a different variable name.
So I can keep track of
two different values.
Essentially, rows and columns.
And then I'm just printing
a single brick each time.
But after I'm done
printing a whole row, I
do want to move the
cursor to a new line.
So let me try this.
Let me go ahead and do
make mario on my code.
Dot slash mario, and voila.
Now I'm using a nested loop
to print out bricks like this.
And I can change this.
If I want to do a 10 by 10, all I have
to do is change that in one place.
Or if I really wanted to be fancy,
I could go use get_int again.
I could get the width and
the height from the user
and do it completely dynamically.
But now if I do 10 by 10 for instance,
I can at least see an even bigger grid.
So if you wonder how things like
Super Mario Brothers, or frankly
any game nowadays on a PC or
console or phone are made,
it's with this kind
of generation of maps.
Maybe back in the day they were hard
coded, maybe they were generated.
Using code you can absolutely
imagine generating brick after brick
after brick like that so that,
ultimately, your game even, your world,
is partly dynamically generated.
And we already have the building
blocks via which to do that.
Unfortunately, we haven't
really spoken to the limitations
of what computers can do.
And in our final minutes we thought
we'd set the stage for things
that computers aren't very good at.
And in fact, problems that are
latent in pretty much everything
we've done today, but I've been very
carefully avoiding tripping over.
This picture here is a picture
of a typical computer's memory,
or RAM, random access memory.
It's just one of the pieces
of hardware that you'd
have in your phone, your
desktop, your laptop these days.
And it's where programs are
stored when they're running.
So in a Mac or PC, if you
double click a program
it's ultimately stored in a piece
of hardware that looks like this.
When you dot slash mario and hit
Enter in a program like this,
you're using CS50 IDE's
RAM, but same idea, albeit,
somewhere else in the cloud.
So it turns out, though, that if you
only have a finite amount of memory,
like this, you can only
do so much with it.
You can't solve all of
the world's problems
if you only have a
finite amount of memory.
And what do I mean by that?
Well, let me go ahead and create another
program here called imprecision.c,
and we'll see why I've named
it that in just a moment.
Let me go ahead and include stdio.h,
again, and int main void just
to give myself some set up here.
And then let me go ahead
and very reasonably very
simply ask the user for a
variable called x as a type float.
Let me ask for the
value just like before.
Let me ask for another one in
the form of y, quote unquote "y."
And then let me go
ahead, and you know what?
Let me go ahead and print out with
percent f the value of x divided by y.
So I'm pretty sure we did this earlier.
We did division with values.
This time I'm using floats, but
let's go ahead and just run this.
Make imprecision-- and I goofed here.
Implicit-- I keep doing it-- implicit
declaration of function get_float.
I didn't practice what
I've been preaching.
I also need to include cs50.h, which
is where it get_float is defined.
Now, let me recompile.
Now it works.
Now, let me go ahead
and run imprecision.
And let me go ahead
and type in one tenth.
OK.
So one tenth it turns out, according
to my very simple calculator here,
is 0.100000.
But I'm getting a little curious now.
It turns out that printf is even
more powerful than we've seen,
and you can actually print out
more than just single digits.
Suppose I want to print out not six
significant digits, but maybe 10.
It's a little funky the syntax,
but instead of saying percent f,
you can instead say literally,
percent dot the number of digits
you want to see and then the f.
So let me go ahead and recompile
this, make imprecision.
Now let me do dot slash
imprecision and one tenth--
uh-huh.
Well, that's a little curious.
I don't recall knowing that there's
a 15 at the end of one tenth.
Well, let's get a little more curious.
Let's print out 50 decimal points to
really dig into what's going on here.
Let me recompile my code.
And let me rerun dot slash
imprecision and do one divided by ten,
and oh my God.
I am quite sure in grade school when
we all learned one divided by ten,
the teacher did tell
us one tenth or 0.1.
And they never mentioned the fact that
it's 0.10000000149011, and so forth.
So what is going on?
Well, it turns out as
powerful as computers
are and is as sophisticated as all of
the syntax we've been looking at today
is, my God, a computer can't even
calculate one tenth correctly.
And so we're bumping up against
a fundamental limitation here,
which is that if computers
are finite in their capacity.
They only have so much RAM, so
much hardware, so many bits.
Well, it stands to reason that if you
only are using a finite number of bits,
32 for instance, or 64.
Yes, you can count pretty
high or pretty precisely.
You cannot count infinitely
high or infinitely precisely.
At some point you have to
start to approximate values.
And indeed, that's what
the computer is doing.
If it only has a finite number of bits,
32, via which to represent a float.
There's an infinite number of floating
point real numbers in the world.
Unfortunately, if you have
a finite number of bits,
you've got to start
cutting some corners.
And that's what the computer is doing.
It's representing one
tenth as closely as it can,
and this is what you then see when you
look enough significant digits out.
Now, for most problems that's
probably not a big deal.
But it could very well be a
big deal if you're doing math,
you're dealing with finance or
monetary values or military operations
where a lot of small numbers,
scientifically, really start to add up.
And indeed, there have been
many examples in the real world
where bad things happen because
of this so-called imprecision.
And there's another issue
that computers run into.
Not only this floating point
imprecision, even integers
have their limitations.
Recall that integers, of course, can
be represented in decimal or in binary.
And if we have three
light bulbs or three bits,
let's consider how we
might count in binary.
Zero, zero, zero is
where we began last week.
001, 010, 011, 100, 101, 110, 111.
And now, this recall from last week is
the number we know is seven in decimal.
How do I count one digit higher?
Well, I just carry the one, so to speak.
But if I only have three light bulbs or
in turn three bits, or heck, 32 bits.
That additional bit,
the carry, disappears.
And so there's this
problem with integers too.
And someone noted earlier when you
tried to do 2 billion plus 2 billion,
it couldn't fit in the result.
That's because integers
too if they're only 32 bits or a long in
C. If it's only 64 bits, those are big
numbers, but they're
not infinitely large.
And we humans have tripped
over this again and again.
You might recall hearing about if
not living through the Y2K problem.
Where a lot of stuff in
the world broke or was
worried to be broken on January
1st, 2000, because humans
had made the reasonable
but not very long sighted
decision to store years
using just two digits.
So 1995 would be represented
as 95, 96, 97, 98, 99.
Then around the change of
the year from 1999 to 2000,
any computer program or system
that was still using two digits
would, of course, add one
at the stroke of midnight.
Unfortunately, if there's no third
digit available it disappears.
And the entire world confuses
the year 2000 for the year 1900,
because 1900 was assumed
as being the prefix.
And if you can believe it, we
humans are about to do this again
in the year 2038, which is
not that far off from now.
We are going to run out of bits
via which to keep track of time.
Because years ago, humans
decided reasonably at the time,
they are going to use 32
bits to represent numbers.
And we are going to use 32 bits
to count up the number of seconds
from the year a date, January 1st, 1970.
So that's when time began
computing wise, in some sense,
and we've been counting
the seconds ever since.
Unfortunately, with 32 bits you
can only count as high as 4 billion
give or take.
And unfortunately, we are going to hit
the four billionth second on January 19
in the year 2038.
So unless all of us upgrade
our Macs and PCS, and worse,
embedded systems and satellites and
any hardware baked into various devices
that we now use, we're about
to run into this problem
again where all of a sudden and it's
going to be like January 1st, 1970
again.
Unless we stay ahead of this problem.
So with all the power we've seen
in C and all of the capabilities
that we've seen in C and
in Scratch, there are still
these fundamental limitations.
So when it comes to solving your
own problems in C and in turn CS50,
it's going to be ever so important
to be mindful of these constraints
and to, ultimately, find
solutions even to these problems.
But for now, we'll adjourn
here, and leave you
for your first problem set
in C on Mario and more.
We'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]