[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, Harvard
University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
And ordinarily we would all be here
on campus in this beautiful Sanders
Theater together.
This, of course, is a little
bit different this year,
for more than one reason.
But we're here instead in the Loeb
Drama Center at Harvard University.
Thanks to our friends in collaboration
with the American Repertory Theater,
we have this new space, including even
such amenities as a prop shop in back,
where we've been working with
an amazingly talented team
over the course of the summer to
prepare for this semester and CS50.
And so I daresay we'll have some new and
improved demonstrations along the way.
So our thanks to our hosts,
the American Repertory Theater.
Now we wanted to evoke
memories, at least,
or some imagery of the
campus itself, particularly
for the many of you who could not
be here in person this semester.
And so we went into the Harvard
Archives, where among their collections
was this watercolor painting,
painted by a Harvard graduate student
over 200 years ago in the year 1794.
Jonathan Fisher, who sat in
what is now Harvard Square,
looking in on some of the earliest
buildings of Harvard's campus.
And thanks to technology, we took
what is a relatively small watercolor
that this graduate student
painted some 200 years ago,
and now adorns the stage here
in the Loeb Drama Center.
So if unfamiliar, we have
Holden Chapel here at left,
Hollis Hall to its right, which is
one of the undergraduate dormitories
in Harvard Yard, Harvard Hall,
which is one of the classroom
buildings on campus, and
then Massachusetts Hall,
where both first years and Harvard's
president live and work respectively.
So welcome, then, to CS50.
And I can say that
not quite as long ago,
but, nonetheless, feels rather
long ago, some 20 years ago,
did I take the same class.
But as you know, I myself
had some trepidation
when it came to studying CS50, when
it came to studying computer science.
Because it was a very unfamiliar field.
I had followed a path when I got to
college of sticking within my comfort
zone, studying government early
on, thinking I would major
or concentrate in government.
And it wasn't until I got up the
nerve to shop, that is, sit in
on this class CS50, that I realized
that homework can actually be fun.
And I found that computer science and
CS50 is not about programming per se,
even though that's how many of
us perceive it in high school,
whether it's us or our
classmates taking the class.
But it really is about problem solving.
And as such, it's so
very applicable not only
to computer science and
the engineering fields,
but really to the arts, humanities,
social sciences, sciences, and beyond.
And so if you're feeling
a little uncomfortable
with the idea of taking
a class like CS50,
know that almost every year, nearly two
thirds of the students who take CS50
have never taken a computer
science course before.
So if you look up, down, left, right,
right now, odds are more than many
of the classmates joining you here
today are in a very similar position.
You're indeed in very good company.
And what's ultimately important in CS50
too, we emphasize, as in the syllabus,
that what ultimately matters in
this course is not so much where
you end up relative to your
classmates, but where you end
up relative to yourself when you began.
Indeed, taking into account
where you currently are, perhaps
with no prior background,
and considering
where you will be in
just three or so months
is ultimately meant to be the
measure of your own success.
And so toward that end, we'll
start off this class programming
a little something from yesteryear.
An image here of Super Mario
Brothers and the pyramid
that the character has to ascend.
We'll recreate a portion of
this game, albeit using text--
otherwise known as ASCII art-- but we'll
do that in just the course's second
or so week.
So this will be among the
first programs you write.
And then fast forward just several
problem sets or programming
assignments later, or
several weeks later, too,
and you'll be building what
we call CS50 Finance, a web
application of your very own
that runs on the internet,
pulling down nearly real-time stock
quotes from a third party service,
allowing your own users to log in
and register to buy and sell stocks,
so to speak, using virtual currency.
So over the course of the
class's several months,
will you go, truly, from
building a pyramid in Mario
to building your very own
web application and more,
followed by the course's
capstone experience, which
will be your very own final project.
But what exactly is computer science?
What we thought we would do in this week
zero, the very first week of the class,
is consider exactly what
it means to solve problems.
And let me propose that
this is computer science.
This is problem solving.
You have some input, which
is the problem you care about
that you want to solve, and you care
about the solution to that problem,
which is the so-called output.
And in between that input
and output is this black box
of sorts, inside of which
is the magic that happens,
the magic that you'll eventually be
able to harness and compel computers
to solve problems for you.
Inside of that black box, ultimately,
is going to be the code that you write.
But for us to begin doing
that, we all kind of
need to agree on how we're going to
represent these inputs and outputs.
We all kind of have to speak a
common language, so to speak.
And so we need to agree how these
inputs are going to be represented.
So how might we typically
represent information?
Well, maybe the simplest thing to do
at the very first class, whether we're
online or in person,
is to take attendance
or to count the number
of people in the room.
And so you might do this old
school style on your hands
so as to represent
every person in a room
with just a finger raised on your hands.
So how we might represent
information boils down
to very simple digits on your hand.
Of course, you can't count
very high with just this hand.
And there's actually a fancy
word for what we're doing,
old school here, and that's unary
notation-- uno, implying one,
or one finger being up or down.
And so you can count, it
would seem, as high as five.
And of course, if I
bring in a second hand,
I can go as high as 10, and then
things get a little more difficult.
But it's a system for
representing information
and it's fairly universal, certainly
when we're all quite young.
But you and I tend to
use a more useful system.
Not just digits on the hand,
but other sorts of digits.
Namely, the decimal digits
that you and I know.
So the numbers that are otherwise
more technically called base 10--
and that's just a fancy
way of describing the fact
that there's 10 digits that you and I
as humans really tend to use typically.
Those digits, of course,
are zero through nine,
and using these several digits,
we can pose numbers like zero
through nine, but also 10
and 11 and 12, and as high up
as we want to go by using
multiple digits still.
But computers don't really
speak the same language as us.
They're, in some sense,
much simpler than we humans,
even though they seem so complicated or
so sophisticated and certainly so fast.
At the end of the day, these
are all human-made devices,
and they're relatively
simple at their core.
In fact, even if you don't
quite know what you're saying,
but you've at least heard
this to be the case,
what language do you
understand computers to speak?
What language do computers speak,
if not the system that you and I use
of zeros through nines or decimal?
Brian, could we see
who might answer this?
What system do computers
use, so far as you've heard,
whether or not you've
taken a CS class before?
Keith, can we go to you first?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
The computers use binary.
DAVID J MALAN: Binary.
And can you elaborate a little bit?
What do you mean by binary?
AUDIENCE: It's zeros and ones.
So, like, while we use zero
through nine for base 10,
they use zero through one for base 2.
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
So computers use the so-called
binary system, bi implying two.
And they, indeed, only use, as Keith
notes, zero and one, two digits.
So on the one hand, this is
actually pretty encouraging,
because, wow, this is actually a
pretty simple system if we're only
using two of these digits.
But, of course, if you
only have two digits,
how are we going to represent
the number two or three or four
or any much larger number?
It would almost seem
like a step backwards.
But it isn't actually.
And it turns out that this
so-called system, or base 2--
two because there's two digits in
the vocabulary, otherwise known,
as Keith says, as binary--
uses just zeros and ones, and it turns
out there's other nomenclature here
we can toss out.
These zeros and ones are
otherwise known as bits.
And bits actually derive from
just two words, binary digits.
Binary, implying two
possibilities, digits,
just being symbols on the screen.
So binary digits, or
otherwise known as bits.
And computers speak binary
using these things called bits.
But what does that mean
and why is it the case?
Like, why didn't they
invent computers decades ago
that just use zero
through nine, rather than
come up with a whole new system for us
to think about, let alone talk about?
Well, at the end of the day, computers
are using what as their input?
Really just electricity.
Probably the only thing all of us
do every day or every couple of days
with our laptop or desktop or phone is
either make sure it's still plugged in,
or to plug it in so as to charge it.
So the only physical
input to our devices
these days is electricity in some form.
And we don't have to get into the
nuances of what electricity is,
but I think it's about electrons flowing
into the device so as to charge it.
So it suffices for our
purposes to know that there's
some physical input to the device,
these computers and phones that we use.
But that's it.
And so if we harness this
electricity, maybe we
can start to represent
information with it.
For instance, here is a light bulb,
this old ghost light in the theater here
that's currently off.
But it has the ability to turn on.
We just need to plug it
in or throw on a switch.
And if that's the case,
what's really quite
compelling about the
metaphor of using lights
is that right now, this
light bulb is currently off,
but as soon as I allow
electricity to flow
as by plugging it in or maybe throwing
a switch, now it's, of course, on.
And if I unplug it or throw
the switch again, it's off.
Or if I plug it back in, it's on.
And the implication of
this very simple idea
is that we can take a physical
device, like a single light bulb,
and by plugging it in or unplugging
it, we can represent information.
What did I just do?
I represented the light
bulb being off or on,
but we can just call off
and on something else.
We can call them zeros and ones.
And so this really is
the germ of an idea
that gave us computers, and with
it, their use of the binary system.
If, at the end of the day, all they
have is physical input as electricity,
well, let's just use that to harness
and keep track of information.
Let's store a little bit of electricity
when we want to represent a one,
and let's let go of that
electricity in some sense
when we want to
represent a zero instead.
And so because the input
to computers is so simple,
thus gives us the zeros
and ones that we now use.
But we seem to have created
a problem for ourselves.
If we only have one light bulb
or one switch, if it's off,
it might be zero, if it's
on, it might be a one,
but how do I count higher than one?
That problem still
fundamentally remains.
Well, I could, of course,
use more light bulbs.
So let me ask this.
If we were to use three light
bulbs, how high could we count?
So with one light bulb, we can count
from zero to one, two possibilities.
But with three light bulbs,
how high could we count?
Let me go ahead and ask this
question here on the screen.
In just a moment you'll see on your
side this particular question via which
you can respond on your device.
How high can you count
with three light bulbs?
So instead of one, I give you three,
each of which can be on or off.
How high can we, perhaps, count?
So you'll see on the screen
here the answers coming in.
We have a lot of folks thinking,
60-plus percent that it's
eight is the highest you can count.
A lot of you think it's
seven, and some of you
also think it might be three or two.
So that's actually an
interesting range of answers.
And let's see what might
actually be the case.
Well, let me cut back over to three
actual light bulbs here, all of which
are off.
And most naively, I think, if we
were to turn these light bulbs on,
if they currently represent zero,
obviously, I could turn one on
and we could call it one.
Then I could turn the second one on
and call it two, turn on the third one,
and now with all three on, we could
say now we're representing three.
But we're not really being clever
enough just yet, if we're only
counting as high as three.
Because I'm just turning them
on, in this story, left to right.
But what if we were
a little more clever?
Maybe we turn them on right to left,
or maybe we kind of permuted them
in different directions?
That is, we took into account
not just how many bulbs are on
or how many fingers are in the
air, but rather the pattern of on
and off light bulbs that we've created.
So let's just count this up.
So let me somewhat systematically
turn some of these bulbs on here,
albeit virtually.
Here might be one, here might
be two, here might be three.
But then we're kind of
done with that story.
So how might we do it a little better?
Well, let's start again at zero.
Here might be one.
Why don't we call this two?
Why don't we call this three?
Why don't we call this four?
Call this five, this
six, and this seven.
Now, it's fine if you didn't quite
see what pattern I was following,
but take my word for it that that
was a unique pattern of light bulbs,
eight total times.
I started at off, off, off,
and I ended at on, on, on.
But along the way, there
were, indeed, eight.
But how high can I count?
Well, it kind of depends on what
number you start counting from,
and just as we thus far have been doing,
computer scientists do all the time.
Computer scientists and,
in turn, computer programs,
typically start counting from
zero, just because it makes sense
because when everything is off,
you might as well call that zero.
So if we start counting at zero,
and we have eight possible patterns
that we just saw
pictorially, well, that would
allow us to count as high as seven.
So from zero to seven,
so seven is the highest
we can count with three light bulbs.
So those of you who propose that
seven was the answer, 36% of you
were indeed correct.
57% of you who said eight are correct
if you assume we start counting at one,
and that's fine.
But at least in the computing world
now, we'll generally, by convention,
start counting from zero.
But you are correct to say that
there's eight such possibilities.
All right, well, this
is all fine and good
to represent things with
patterns of light bulbs.
But how do we actually now
get to the zeros and ones
that a computer is actually using?
Because what's inside of a
computer, at the end of the day,
are not light bulbs but
tiny, tiny little switches,
millions of little switches that can
either be on, or one, or off, or zero.
Those switches happen to
be called transistors.
And these days computers
do have millions
of these things that can be on
and off in different patterns.
So if you have the ability to turn on
and off all of these switches, well,
what can we all agree on representation
when it comes to using those switches?
How will we represent
information with them?
Well, wonderfully, we don't
really need to think very hard
or go past our very
comfortable roots as kids.
If we consider for a moment
not just zero and one,
but the whole decimal
system, zero through nine,
that you and I all started
our day with today.
How does that system work?
Well, here on the screen is 123.
So yes, you're probably thinking
that's one hundred twenty three,
but not quite.
All I've shown on the
screen is a pattern
of symbols, 123, or three digits.
And all of us probably are
instinctively just saying, obviously,
it's a hundred and twenty three.
But it's probably been
years since you considered
why it is one hundred twenty three.
Well, let's consider what each of
these digits or symbols represents.
If you're like me, you grew up learning
that the rightmost digit is the ones
place, the middle is the tens place,
the left one is the hundreds place.
And so how do we get from
these three symbols or digits,
123, to the mathematical idea we
know as one hundred twenty three?
Well, all of us instantaneously, these
days, did 100 times 1 plus 10 times
2 plus 1 times 3, which, of
course, is just 100 plus 20 plus 3,
or the mathematical value we all
know as one hundred twenty three.
So a bit of a circular
argument, but just to remind us
how we got from 123 to
one hundred twenty three.
Well, it turns out that in the
world of computers, the system
they use is exactly,
fundamentally the same.
The only difference is that computers
only have access to zeros and ones,
not zeros through nines.
So if we consider now in the
abstract, just three possible digits
represented here, let's consider for
a moment why those columns are places
where one, 10, and 100, and so forth.
Well, why was that the case?
Well, there was a pattern,
in fact, and it just
has to do with exponents or powers.
So the rightmost column, technically,
if we really get into the weeds,
is 10 to the zeroth power,
which if you recall,
just means one, 10 to the
first power, which is just 10,
and 10 to the second power,
or 10 squared, is 100.
But what's interesting about
representing it in this way
is that it jumps out
that 10 is involved.
There's 10 digits, zero through nine, so
the columns are using this base of 10.
So you can perhaps now
get even ahead of me
here by considering, well, if in
the binary system that computers
use, you only have two
digits, zeros and ones,
odds are the only thing that's going to
change is the meaning of these columns.
Now we have the ones place still,
because 2 to the zero is one,
but then we have 2 to the first,
2 to the second, and so forth.
And of course, if we
just do out that math,
in the world of binary
that computers use,
we have the ones place, twos
place, fours place, and so forth.
And now we're good to go.
Even though we have to now think
in a different base system,
now we can start counting more properly.
And now we can move away from
the metaphor of light bulbs
and consider that if all of
those light bulbs are off,
we're, again, just going to start
thinking of those things as zeros.
So that would be a pattern of symbols
or digits that's 000 in binary.
But in our human world,
the mental math you
would probably do now
instantaneously after today
would be, well, that's obviously 4
times 0 plus 2 times 0 plus 1 times 0,
or, of course, zero in decimal.
But how does a computer represent
the number one, for instance?
Well, it's just going to change that
rightmost bit from a zero to a one,
or, more metaphorically, it's going
to turn that switch on and illuminate
that rightmost light bulb
just like I did earlier.
How do I represent two?
It's going to be 010 in binary.
How do I represent three?
This is where we're about to differ.
Now I'm putting on
two of those switches,
because I need something in the twos
place and the ones place to give me,
mathematically, three.
Next, if we go ahead and choose--
count up to four,
that's going to be 100.
if I want to count up to
five, that's going to be 101,
six is going to be 110, and finally,
the number seven is going to be 111.
So it would seem that using three bits,
each of which can be a zero or one,
yes, you can permute them
in eight different ways.
Two possibilities for the first
times two for the second times two
for the third gives us eight.
But as per this math and the intuition
of starting counting from zero,
we can only count up as
high as seven in total.
Well, let's go ahead and actually
take this out for a spin.
When we don't have just, say, let's say,
one light bulb or three light bulbs,
we have, actually, the
fortune of having like
a whole stage worth of light bulbs.
64 light bulbs adorn the stage here.
And you know what?
Sumner, could we go ahead and put up
a random number on the screen here?
All right, so if you can see these
light bulbs from your perspective,
we have eight light bulbs
plus another bunch of them,
and all the others are off.
So let's go ahead and
ask a question then.
If these light bulbs now represent not
just one light bulb or two or three,
but several more-- in this
case, at least six light bulbs,
what value do we actually get?
Well, let me go ahead and put
a question on the screen here,
which should pop up on
yours in just a moment.
And you should see now on
your end this same question.
Put in binary terms, what number--
in decimal, does binary
number 110010 represents?
What decimal number does binary number
110010 represent, from left to right?
So here we have an
overwhelming response.
50 is indeed the correct answer.
Now why is that?
Well, if I go over to the
physical light bulbs here, let's
just consider for a moment
what the pattern actually is.
This here is the ones place, the
twos place, four, eight, 16, 32,
and we could keep going.
But it's not going to matter
because they're all off.
So we have 32 plus 16 plus
2, which indeed gives us
the number you and I
know in decimal as 50.
And just imagine how high we could
count with all of the other light bulbs
as well.
All right.
So we started with the
story with electricity.
We then moved on to numbers
and representing things,
either in decimal or in binary.
But we've kind of painted
ourselves into a corner,
because if we only have at our disposal
switches or the metaphorical light
bulbs, which we can think
of as zeros and ones,
it would seem that the only things
computers can do is compute.
That is, behave as calculators.
And in fact, early on, that's exactly
what computers were designed to do,
was really facilitate mathematical
calculations that were otherwise quite
tedious or impossible for humans.
But, of course, what you
and I are using right now,
what we use every day on our phones and
our laptops and desktops is much more
sophisticated.
So let's consider how could a
computer represent not just numbers,
but letters of the alphabet.
Brian, could we call on
someone for this one?
If you'd like to raise
your virtual hand,
how could a computer go about
representing letters of an alphabet
like English if, again, all we
have at our disposal is switches?
AUDIENCE: We can assign the numbers
that we're getting from binary
to specific letters of the alphabet.
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah.
We can assign the specific numbers
in binary to letters of the alphabet.
That's pretty much our
only option, it would seem.
If we only have the ability to permute
these switches or light bulbs or bits,
well, we just all have to agree how
to represent letters in the same way.
Now, maybe the simplest way for us
to do this would be, you know what?
Let's just all agree that a capital
A is going to be the number one.
So you turn on one light bulb, or
represent the binary number one.
Well, how about for B, we
could use the number two.
For C we could use the number three.
D could be four, and so forth.
We all just have to agree to
number the letters in that way.
But it turns out humans
did exactly that,
but a little bit differently years ago.
They decided for reasons that
we won't get into just now,
that, actually, the capital
letter A is actually
going to be represented by the
decimal number you and I know as 65.
Now in bitwise form, that's
going to look like this.
So this is the pattern of
bits that a computer would
use to represent the decimal
number we now know as 65,
and now what the computer is going
to do is just be mindful of what
type of program you're using.
So yes, if you're using a calculator
or maybe using something like Excel
to crunch numbers, well, in that
context when running software,
like a calculator or a spreadsheet
program doing numerical analysis,
the program is going to see
inside of the computer's hardware
the pattern of switches that
represents the decimal number 65.
And because it's in the context of
a calculator or spreadsheet, what
you, the human, might see on the screen
is literally the decimal number 65.
But if you and I are using text
messaging or email or any number
of social media apps
where we're communicating
not numerically but in
letters, say, English letters,
in that context your computer
is going to be smart enough
to know, well, that same pattern
of bits that represents 65,
in the context of a text message
or in an email or the like
actually represents the capital
letter A. So the pattern is the same.
The representation is the same.
But the context is what differs.
And the system that humans came up with
years ago that maps 65 to A, 66 to B,
67 to C, is called ASCII,
the American Standard
Code for Information Interchange.
And that just means that there is
a well-defined mapping that a bunch
of humans decades ago decided on, in
order to map letters of the alphabet--
English in this case--
to numbers starting with 65.
And there's a whole mapping, too for
punctuation, for lowercase letters,
and the like.
So given that, suppose that you did
receive a text message containing
a pattern of bits, or, really, just
a sequence of decimal numbers that
happened to be this.
72, 73, 33.
Suppose that you received a text message
containing these patterns of numbers.
72, 73, 33.
What message might you
have just received?
Let me go ahead and pull up
the abbreviated chart here
to consider exactly what
message you've received.
72, 73, 33.
And Sumner, could we go ahead and
throw this same three-letter word
on the lights?
If you'd like to see it in
bitwise form, so to speak,
it will appear here on these
light bulbs now as well.
What pattern does this represent?
Lanham, can we go to you?
AUDIENCE: That would be HI with
an exclamation point, correct?
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah so it's indeed
HI with an exclamation point.
And it's probably pretty
easy now, in retrospect,
to glean that, yes, the 72 and
the 73 were H and I respectively.
But Lanham also noted the exclamation
point, which isn't in this chart,
but per the dot dot dots,
there is a well-defined mapping
for all of the letters of the
alphabet that we might care about.
And so HI is perhaps more
obvious than the other.
That 33, we need a bigger chart.
And so if you actually
go on your computers
now to asciichart.com,
asciichart.com, you'll
see a little something like this.
Though you can also just
google ASCII in general
and get copies of the same chart.
You'll see here that H is
indeed 72, I is indeed 73,
but if we look to the left, 33 is,
apparently, an exclamation mark.
And you would only know that by
having looked it up or just having
committed it to memory.
But the computers you and I use
and the phones you and I use just
know this intrinsically.
That's, indeed, how they're programmed.
But it turns out, too,
that we should consider
just how many zeroes
and ones we're using now
to represent the 72, the 73, and the 33.
So let's look for one last time at
the binary representation, which,
as per the light bulbs, are
these patterns of bits here.
So when you receive a text
message from a friend saying HI!
H-I exclamation point,
in all caps, you're
technically receiving a pattern
of bits, some kind of frequency,
if it's wireless, that
represents this pattern of bits.
And typically, computers
these days use eight bits
to represent each of those characters.
When ASCII first came
out, they typically
used seven for efficiency reasons,
because space was expensive back then.
But here we used eight,
and, indeed, that's now
the norm when it comes to representing
characters in multiples of eight.
So we have eight bits here,
eight bits here, eight bits here,
which means to receive the message HI!
you are sending or receiving 24 bits
total.
Now, frankly, bits are not a
very useful unit of measure,
typically, because they're so small.
Just a zero or a one.
But each of these patterns
of eight bits, actually
have a vocabulary word, if
you will, which is bytes.
And odds are, all of us have
used this term in some context,
but generally in the context
of megabytes or even gigabytes.
Indeed when you talk about the
sizes of your files these days,
you're speaking in bytes in some
form, either million or billion bytes.
But each of those bytes, quite simply,
is a pattern of eight zeros and ones.
So, in fact, if we have as many
as 64 bulbs at our disposal,
that's 64 divided by 8.
That's eight characters.
So it would seem we could spell on
this stage, even an eight-letter word--
if, Sumner, we could put up
a random eight-letter word,
that we'll keep up now--
can you now spell from
left to right, your left
to your right, an eight-letter word
using the system known as ASCII.
But, of course, we're being
a little bit biased here,
as ASCII is the American Standard
Code for Information Interchange.
And on a typical US English keyboard,
there's more characters, certainly,
than uppercase letters,
like A through H and I.
There's also some punctuation and some
numbers, but there's also quite a bit
missing as well.
And any of you who are elsewhere
in the world, odds are,
would find using a keyboard like this
especially limiting or frustrating.
Why is that?
What seems to be missing from ASCII?
Well, let me ask this
one other question here.
If we do use ASCII, and we therefore
give ourselves eight bits or one byte,
how many different characters could we
potentially actually display, actually
represent?
So on your screen, you
should see this question now.
How many symbols can you
represent with eight bits?
And this speaks to, really,
at the end of the day, how
many letters of the
alphabet plus punctuation,
plus uppercase and lowercase, can
ASCII, or really, can computers support?
Well, it looks like 72% or so of
you think that the answer is 256.
And it is indeed the case that you
can represent 256 possibilities.
Why?
You can actually do out the math.
If you've got eight bits, each
of which can be a zero or a one,
that means you have two
possibilities for the first,
times two possibilities for the
second, times two times two times two.
That happens to be 2
to the eighth, or 256.
It's fine if that's not
immediately obvious,
but if you do have eight bits, each
of which can be one of two values,
you can come up with 256 possibilities.
Those of you who chimed in to say
that the answer is 255 in this case,
are wrong, only because now we're
talking about the total number
of patterns, which is indeed 256.
But the highest value we could represent
with eight bits or eight light bulbs,
it would seem to be, indeed, 255.
And that's because of all of the
different patterns we can permute.
But let me open the question
to the audience now.
Why might a US English keyboard
be especially limiting,
and in turn, why is ASCII
really not quite appropriate
when it comes to
representing human language,
even though this is what
computers began with years ago?
What is missing from ASCII?
Why might 256 total
possibilities not be sufficient?
Kevin, can we go to you?
AUDIENCE: Sure.
I mean, for one thing, missing a lot
of the accents in other languages.
But if you just consider,
like, Asian languages,
there are a lot more
than 256 characters.
DAVID J MALAN: Exactly.
So not only are we missing
accented characters
that you might need in
some languages, we're
also missing the characters that
you might need in Asian languages,
in languages like Arabic and the like.
There are way more symbols that we
humans use to communicate in print
and electronically than 256.
English, we can get away with
fitting into this keyboard,
but not once we introduce
things like these characters,
let alone other symbols as well.
And it turns out there's other things
we humans like to say these days
and express using characters that have
come into vogue, which is, namely,
these things.
Odds are, probably
sometime today you have
sent or received one of these things
here, otherwise known as an emoji.
Now, even though these emojis look
like pictures, they look like images--
and they are, technically-- the way
they're implemented in computers
is actually as patterns
of zeros and ones.
These are actually just characters
in an alphabet, the emoji alphabet.
Which is to say there's some
pattern of zeros and ones
that represents each one of these
faces, and the many other emojis that
nowadays exist.
And this is because the world has
transitioned over the years from ASCII,
which only used seven,
and in some sense,
eight bits total to represent
all possible characters,
to using either eight
or 16 or 24 or even 32 .
Bits nowadays there's a system called
Unicode, which humans have come up
with that support not only English,
but also all of the human languages,
is the aspirational goal, both written
in print or electronically is the goal.
And in addition to that, this is to
say we can represent things like this.
So this is the so-called
face with tears of joy.
And this face of tears
of joy, as of last year,
was the most popular emoji
sent via text messages, emails,
social media, and the like.
But at the end of the
day, all you're receiving
is, like, a key on a keyboard.
So, in fact, you wouldn't
know it to look at it.
But in fact, the decimal
number representing this face
with tears of joy happens to be 128,514.
So to Kevin's point, to represent
not only certain human languages,
but certainly these emojis, we
need way more than 256 characters
so we can use not just eight
bits, but 16 or 24 or 32.
That's a huge amount
of possibilities now.
In fact, now, to really take
the fun out of these things,
if you receive that face
with tears of joy or send it,
you're technically just sending a
pattern of bits that looks like this.
That's all that's going
on underneath the hood,
every time you use these things.
All right.
So we started again with electricity.
We then represented numbers.
Now we have the ability to
represent letters and even
emotions in the form of emojis.
What else is there out there?
Well, the emojis themselves, of course,
at least the ones we've looked at,
are pictorial in nature.
And so that invites the
question, how does a computer
represent things like color?
Like, that face with tears of
joy had a lot of yellow in it.
So how is yellow or any color, for
that matter, represented in a computer?
Well, let me ask the audience again.
If all you have at your disposal
is bits, zeros and ones,
and we just as humans need to
agree how to represent colors,
what might be one possibility?
It doesn't need to be the answer.
But what might your own instinct be
if designing this for the first time
yourself?
How might a computer
represent colors now?
Yasmin, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: You would like members
to different colors and shapes
and just do the same system.
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
Perfect instincts.
You would just assign numbers
to the different colors,
and we all just have to agree on what
that mapping is actually going to be.
So it turns out there's
different ways to do this.
And if any of you are artistic and
use Photoshop or the like digitally,
you're probably familiar with
acronyms like RGB, red, green, blue.
But there are other
acronyms and other ways
to implement Yasmin's idea
where we just somehow map
zeros and ones to actual colors.
Well, RGB just happens to
represent red, green, and blue.
And this is a system humans came up
with years ago that says, you know what?
We can actually get every
color of the rainbow
by mixing together some amount of red
and green and blue light, essentially.
So that just invites the question, well,
how do we represent the amount of red,
how do we represent the
amount of green, and how do we
represent the amount of blue?
And we have, as Yasmin
says, bits at our disposal.
So we just have to
decide how to do this.
So suppose we receive a pattern
of bits, that 72, 73, 33 again,
but this time it's not an email.
It's not in a text message.
It's in the context of a file
that I've opened in Photoshop.
So it's as though I've opened
up a photograph that someone
sent me and I want to do some editing
and I see this pattern of numbers,
or, in turn, bits.
Well, what is that
representing in this case?
In the context of an email or
a text message, it's still HI!
But in the context of
Photoshop or Instagram
or anything that is
oriented around images,
it's actually going to represent some
amount of red, some amount of green,
some amount of blue.
And as we discovered
earlier, the total number
of possibilities you can represent
with eight bits happens to be 256.
The highest value you can represent
is 255 if we start counting from zero.
So this is to say that
each of these three numbers
is a number between zero and 255.
So 72 feels like a medium amount of red,
73 is like a medium amount of green, 33
is a little bit of blue.
And if you combine those three amounts
of color, eight bits plus eight
bits plus eight bits,
using 24 bits total,
using the first third to represent
redness, the second third greenness,
and the third third blueness,
you get, it turns out,
a dot that looks like
this, a yellow dot.
And so, indeed, that emoji, when
it's being displayed on the screen,
is the result of the
computer interpreting--
the 128,514 value is
knowing oh, that's the emoji
with the face of tears of joy.
But when it comes to displaying
the information on your screen,
now your computer is going to be
using different patterns of bits
to control the colors of
the dots on the screen.
And this term you might already know.
The dots you and I see on our computer
screens or even TVs these days
are called pixels.
They're tiny little squares
that represent some color
such as this yellow one here.
And you can actually see
them in some contexts.
If I go ahead and pull up the same face
with tears of joy and zoom in a bit,
zoom in a bit more, and
really zoom in a bit more,
now you can actually see
what we call pixelation.
And odds are, you have seen
this on Facebook, Instagram,
wherever you might be resizing or
editing photos that don't quite
have enough resolution.
The resolution of an image is
just how many pixels or dots there
are horizontally and vertically.
So if you really zoom in on an image,
you'll eventually see those pixels.
And this is to say that even
in this zoomed-in happy face,
there's a huge number of
yellow dots and a whole bunch
of black and gray and
brownish dots as well
that compose this very colorful image.
And so you can see them in that case,
and every one of those dots now,
a pixel, is using, I claim,
like 24 bits or three bytes.
Now, you can imagine, there's probably
what, hundreds, maybe thousands of dots
in that image if we zoom out
and look at all of them again.
So if every one of those dots
or pixels is three bytes,
this is why the
photographs you and I take
and the images you and I
download from the internet
are typically measured not even in
bytes, per se, but in kilobytes,
for thousands of bytes, or
megabytes for millions of bytes,
or if it's a video file, it might get
even bigger, billions, or gigabytes.
But that's all that is
happening underneath the hood.
We're just representing
information in this way.
Well, let me ask a
follow up question now.
If we've now, thanks to
Yasmin, represented colors,
and in turn, images, because all
an image is is a grid of pixels.
You take the same
principle Yasmin proposed,
where you represent each color of a dot
and you have a whole bunch of dots that
gives us images, how would you propose
computers represent video files?
Again, even if you don't
know the answer, how might
a computer represent video files
now using, again, only bits
at their disposal?
Who might like to field this one?
How might a computer represent a video?
Justin, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: I-- maybe just, like,
rapidly changing the bites?
DAVID J MALAN: Just
rapidly changing the bites.
I hear-- can you elaborate a little bit?
What do you mean by changing the bites?
AUDIENCE: Like rapidly changing
the RGB of individual pixels--
DAVID J MALAN: Exactly.
AUDIENCE: --to match
the image of that second
of the video or portion of the video.
DAVID J MALAN: Perfect.
So if you think about, like, the
rectangular screen that is your phone,
or your laptop, or your
desktop monitor, if you just
keep changing the colors of
those dots once per second
or a whole bunch of
times per second, we'll
get the illusion that there's actually
motion on the screen, ergo video.
So really, a video, in some sense,
it's just a whole bunch of images,
to Yasmin's definition, flying
across the screen really quickly.
And so you can see this
even old school style.
For instance, let me go ahead
and open up on my screen
a short video that
represents a flipbook.
So you might have made one of these
as a kid or maybe your teacher
did or you saw them, at
least, in person somewhere.
Where if you take a whole bunch
of pieces of paper and staple
or clip them together in some way, draw
a whole lot of pictures, all of which
are similar but slightly
different on each page,
you can create an animation,
or, really, a video.
And this is all a video is
in a purely electronic world.
Even though this happens
to be implemented
in paper, what happens
in the computer world
is indeed just a whole
sequence of images
flying across the screen at some rate.
And that's what actually gives us the
video files that you and I know today.
And there's even more
rabbit holes we can go down.
For instance, how might
you represent music?
Well, music, could be represented,
gosh, in different ways.
Like, if you play the
piano, for instance, you
might know that there are
notes, like A through G.
But there's also sharps
and flats and so forth.
But you know what?
Maybe we just need a number to
represent each of those possible notes.
And maybe also we could
use another number,
just like images use multiple
numbers to represent dots,
we could use a number to
represent the notes in a song,
but also another number to
represent the duration of that note.
How many seconds or milliseconds or
beats should you hear that note for.
So you could come up with
other formulations, too,
but music, really, can be
quantized in the world of computers
into just small pieces of information.
And so long as you and I
agree on how to represent it,
that's how these things all work.
And if you've ever wondered why there
are JPEGs and PNGs and GIFs and Word
documents and Excel files and all of
these different file formats or file
extensions on computers, those
file extensions or formats just
represent a whole bunch
of humans agreeing
how to store patterns of
zeros and ones in a file
so that when those zeros and ones are
loaded into a computer for display
or for interpretation, it knows
what those patterns represent.
Images are represented
slightly differently,
sound and video are represented
but it's all zeros and
ones at the end of the day.
So this is all to say, so long as we
all agree, ideally around the world,
how to represent information, now
we can represent inputs to problems
and hopefully solve
problems and get outputs.
So all that remains in problem solving,
or really, computer science broadly,
is to look inside of this black box
and to consider how you take inputs,
whether it's numbers,
letters, images, video, sound,
and convert them into actual solutions.
And so inside of this black
box is what we would typically
describe as algorithms.
Algorithms are step by step
instructions for solving problems.
They don't even have
to involve computers.
We humans can execute algorithms just by
following someone else's instructions.
If you've ever prepared something
from a cookbook, following a recipe,
you are executing an
algorithm step by step.
But unlike a lot of
recipes or unlike a lot
of instructions that we
humans give to each other,
there's no room for
ambiguity in computers.
Computers' algorithms, when
implemented by machines,
they really have to
be not only correct so
that you get the right
outputs that you care about,
but they also need to be precise.
You need to be ever so precise, because
unlike we humans who can kind of like
read between the lines and,
yeah, I get what you mean,
computers are going
to take you literally.
And so when programming a computer,
that is, translating an algorithm,
step by step instructions, into some
language the computer understands,
the onus is on you to make sure that the
computer cannot misinterpret what you
want.
So let's consider one such algorithm.
So on all of our phones, whether
iOS or Android or the like,
you have some contacts application.
And that contacts application's
probably storing all of your friends
and family members and colleagues,
probably alphabetically.
Maybe by first name, maybe
by last name, or however
you've organized that device.
Well, the old school
version of this happens
to be in paper form, which looks a
little something like this, a phone
book.
And inside of an old school phone
book really is that exact same idea.
It's much larger.
It's much more much more printed.
But it's the same thing.
There's a whole bunch of names and
numbers in a typical phone book,
sorted alphabetically just like
your own Android phone or iOS
phone might be as well.
So suppose we want to solve a problem.
And the input to that problem is
not only this phone book, but also
the name of someone to
look up the number for.
So my own name, for instance.
If I want to look up my phone number,
or you do, you might open up this book
and start looking for
David, for instance,
if we assume that it's
sorted by first name.
I don't see David on the first
page, so I move on to the second.
I don't see myself there,
so I move on to the third.
I don't see myself there
so I move on to the fourth.
And so forth, one page at a time,
looking for my name and, in turn,
my number.
Well, if correctness is important--
let me ask that question first.
Is this algorithm, turning
the pages, step by step,
looking for David correct?
What do you think?
Within Zoom, you should see some
icons under the participants
window labeled yes and no.
If you'd like to go ahead and
vote virtually, yes or no,
is this algorithm correct?
One page at a time, looking for myself.
Never mind the fact that
this is yellow pages,
and so I'm not going to be
anywhere in the phone book,
but indeed, we'll assume
it contains humans as well.
All right.
So it looks like the
algorithm is indeed correct,
but it's terribly, terribly slow.
And that's OK, because
one of the ideas we're
going to consider in CS50 and
in turn, computer science,
is not only the correctness of an
algorithm, but also the efficiency.
How well designed is the algorithm?
This is correct.
It's just incredibly,
incredibly tedious and slow.
But I will find myself.
But, of course, we can do better.
Instead of looking for myself one page
at a time, why don't I do one page,
let me do two, four, six, eight, 10.
It sounds faster and it is faster.
I'm going twice as fast through
the phone book looking for myself.
Is this algorithm correct?
Let me go to someone in
the audience this time.
Is this algorithm of searching for
someone's name two pages at a time
correct?
Because I claim it's more efficient.
I claim it's better designed because
I'll solve the problem twice as fast.
Aneka, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: No, because you
might skip your name on a page.
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah, I might
skip my name on a page.
And let me ask a follow up question.
Can I fix this?
Do I have to throw out
the whole algorithm
or can we at least fix
this problem, do you think?
AUDIENCE: I think whatever page
you flip to, it would help to see,
like, what name is there and
maybe see if your name would
come before or after.
DAVID J MALAN: Nice.
So that's exactly the right intuition.
I don't think we have to completely
sacrifice the idea of speeding up
this algorithm by moving twice as fast.
But as you propose, if I go too
far-- maybe I get to the E section,
which is one letter too late--
I should at least double back one page.
Because I could get
unlucky, and maybe David
is kind of sandwiched in between
two pages, at which point
I might fly by, get to the end of the
phone book, say, no, there's no David,
and I just got unlucky
with 50% probability.
But as you propose, I can at least
recover and sort of conditionally
ask myself, wait a minute, maybe
I just missed it, and double back.
So I can get the overall
speed improvement,
but then at least fix that
kind of mistake or bug.
And bug, a term of our--
in programming, a bug
is just a mistake in a
program, or a mistake, more
generally, in an algorithm.
But honestly, none of
us are going to do that.
When we actually go to search
for someone in a phone book,
just like our phones do, they
typically don't start at the top
and go to the bottom.
And computers do exactly what
you might do more intuitively.
They'll probably go
roughly to the middle.
Maybe they'll skew a little
to the left, if you know
D is toward the start of an alphabet.
But, no I open to the middle sort of
sloppily, and I'm in the M section.
So what do I know when I'm in
the M section about this problem?
Let me call on one more person.
I'm in the M section.
What would you do as a human now, taking
this as input to solve this problem?
What do I know about the location, of
course, of my name in the phone book?
What decision can I make here?
What decision can I make?
Kyle, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So from the M onwards, you know that
your name won't be there for sure.
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah, so my name is
not going to be in the M section.
But thanks to the alphabetization
of the phone book, I at least know,
you know what?
I can take a huge bite
out of this problem
and tear the problem in half, both
metaphorically and also literally,
in the case of a phone book.
And I can literally throw
half of the problem away.
And so if I started with something
like 1,000 pages in this phone book
or 1,000 contacts in my phone,
just by going to the middle,
roughly, and taking a look to the
left and the right, I can decide,
as you note, well, it's not
on the page I'm looking for.
But I can decide it's to
the left or to the right.
I know D comes before M. And
so now I can go to the left.
And you know what's
interesting here, is that I
can use that exact same algorithm.
I don't have to think any differently.
I can apply the same logic, open to the
middle of this half of the phone, book
and now I see I'm in the G section.
So I'm still a little too far.
But again, I can tear half the
problem away, throw it down
and now I've gone from, like 1,000
pages to 500 pages to 250 pages.
If I do this again, I might find myself,
oh, I made it to the C section now.
I can tear the problem in half
again, throw the left half away,
and now I'm down to just 125 pages.
Now, that's still a lot, but my god.
I've gone from 1,000
to 500 to 250 to 125.
That is way faster than going
from 1,000 to 999 to 998,
and it's even faster than going
from 1,000 to 998 to 996 to 994.
Both of those algorithms are going
to take me much longer as well.
We have this visualization
made by Brian, wonderfully,
that depicts 1,024 page phone book
with one page being flipped at a time.
And now we're down to 996, 995.
I mean, honestly, this
isn't all that enlightening.
It's going to take forever to find
David or any name in a phone book
when starting at that kind
of pace with that algorithm.
But what if, instead,
I'm a little smarter
and I'm a little more intuitive?
And I harness the intuition
that probably you had and I
start with 1,024 pages
again, and this time
divide and conquer, half at a time,
splitting the problem in half?
Tearing the phone book in half,
I get down to just one page.
And if we actually do out the math,
if you start at like 1,000-plus pages,
it will only take me 10 total tears of
that phone book in order to get down
to my number, 949-468-2750.
So that just is to say that the third
algorithm is not only correct, just
as the first one definitely was and the
second one could be with that bug fix,
but it's also much better designed.
It's much more efficient.
And so we can see this a
little graphically as well.
Let me go ahead and propose not
a numerical analysis or anything
like that.
But just something that's
a little visual like this.
So if I have an x-axis
here that represents
horizontally the size of the problem,
the number of pages in a phone book,
and vertically on the y-axis, the amount
of time required to solve a problem.
What co these algorithms look like,
if we just kind of chart them?
Well, the first algorithm, depicted
here in red, it's just a straight line.
It's a slope of one because
there is this one to one
relationship between number of
pages and the amount of time
it takes me to solve it.
For every new page of that phone
book, maybe year after year,
if the phone book grows,
it's going to take me
one more step to look for
myself or anyone else,
potentially, in that phone book.
Unless I get lucky and they're early
in the phone book, but one more
page means one more page turn.
The second algorithm is actually better.
It's still a straight line.
So it's still a linear relationship.
But for every two pages in the phone
book it takes me one more step.
Two pages, one turn.
So it's strictly better
than the first algorithm.
Why?
Well, if we consider this--
if the size of the problem is,
maybe, here, for instance.
So if we assume, for the
sake of discussion, maybe
the phone book has this many pages
depicted with this dotted line.
Well, how much time is it going
to take the second algorithm
to find someone in that phone book?
It's going to take this
amount of time, right?
Where those two lines intersect.
If you're using the first algorithm,
though, going one page at a time,
it's actually going to take this much
time, which is literally twice as much.
So they're both correct,
assuming we double back as needed
if I go too far past a name.
But both of those are sort
of fundamentally the same.
They're the same shape,
and, honestly, they both
felt slow to say and to act out.
The third algorithm,
if we were to graph it,
has a fundamentally
different relationship
between the size of the problem and
the time required to solve the problem.
The line goes up, up,
up, up, as it should,
because the more pages there are, the
more time it's going to take to solve,
but notice how much
more slowly it goes up.
This thing barely starts to
rise as the size of the problem
gets bigger and bigger and bigger.
And why is that, intuitively?
Well, here, what's powerful is,
suppose that phone book, next year,
for whatever reason, doubled in size.
Maybe Cambridge and Allston,
Massachusetts merged together into one
big phone book, so there's
2,000-some-odd pages now instead.
How many more steps
would it take next year
to search for someone
in that phone book?
One.
One more step.
And so if you look way out
here along this green line,
doubling the size of
the phone book, the line
itself is only going to rise ever
so slightly because no big deal.
With that third algorithm you're taking
much bigger bites out of the problem.
And so this, too, speaks to what
computer science and what programming
are ultimately like.
Harnessing ideas that you
come into the class with
and that you might use
in your everyday life,
but you don't necessarily think about
how you might represent problems
using those algorithms and how you
might translate them to computer speak.
And indeed, one way we'll
start to think about algorithms
is not only their correctness,
but how well designed they are.
And so for instance
here, I've deliberately
labeled these three lines n, n
over 2, and log base 2 over n.
That just means that if we use n as
number-- so computer scientists tend
to use n as a variable, much like a
mathematician might say x or y or z,
n for number.
And so the first red
line is the running time,
the number of steps it might
take to solve a problem
might be, in the worst case, n.
If there's n pages in the phone book,
maybe I'm looking for someone way
at the end of the phone
book and it's going
to take me all n steps to find them.
The second algorithm is going
to take half as many steps.
So we express that as n
divided by 2, because if we're
doing two pages at a time we'll
get to the end of the phone book--
if we're looking for someone whose
name starts with Z, for instance--
twice as fast.
But the third algorithm, if you're
a little rusty on the mathematics,
is represented as a
logarithm with a base of 2.
And this just means that
this graph, the green line
describes how much time it takes to
solve a problem when on each pass,
on each step, you are dividing the
problem, in this case, by half.
The other two algorithms are taking
one or two bites out of the problem.
The third algorithm was taking half
of the whole problem at a time.
And that's what made it
all the more powerful.
So when it comes to
programming now, we need
to translate these things
called algorithms to code.
Or, in this case, let's
call it pseudocode.
And in just a bit, we'll focus on
an actual programming language,
albeit a graphical one.
But for now let's just consider
some of the constructs or sort
of fundamental ideas that are
going to be useful to leverage
here on out in this class.
So let me propose that what
I really just did verbally
can be translated into pseudocode,
which is like an algorithm implemented
in English, or whatever your
spoken or written language is.
But the key is that
it's got to be correct,
and ideally it had better be precise
so that there's no ambiguity.
Step one was, indeed, what I did.
Pick up phone book.
Step two, open to middle of phone book.
Step three, look at page.
And indeed I did that.
And now things got interesting.
Step four, if person--
David, in my case-- is on the
page, what do I want to do?
Well, I should probably
call that person.
The problem is solved.
I've gotten my output,
the person's number.
But there's another possibility,
not if the person's on the page
but, rather if the person
is earlier in the book--
and that is what happened a moment ago.
If I ended up on M, but I'm looking
for David, that's to the left,
I should then do what?
Open to the middle of the
left half of the book.
And that's indeed what I did.
And I sort of gratuitously
tore the problem in half.
But algorithmically, I just looked
at the left half of the book next.
What do I do next?
Well, really, that's
the point at which I
proposed that the algorithm is now
just repeatable, again and again,
and so we'll say go back to line three.
Why?
Well, starting at line
three, I have an algorithm
for looking up someone in a phone book.
It just so happens the phone
book now is half as large.
But there's another case.
What if the person is later in the book?
I wasn't searching for
David, which starts with D,
but someone else's name that's
toward the end of the alphabet.
Well, then if that person is
later in the book, same idea.
Open to the middle of the
right half of the book,
and then again, go back to step three.
But lastly, there's
a fourth possibility.
There's a fourth possibility.
Either the person's in the phone
book, or they're to the left
or they're to the right, or, frankly,
they are just not there at all.
And this last point, though
somewhat subtle, is so important.
Odds are all of us on our Macs, PCs.
Maybe even phones, have had that
very frustrating experience where
your computer hangs, you get the
stupid spinning beachball or hourglass,
the thing freezes or just reboots,
you know, something goes wrong
and it's sort of inexplicable.
And you might think it's
your fault, but really it's
usually the programmer's fault
who wrote the software that you're
using on your computer or your device.
Why?
Very often, that programmer,
for whatever reason,
did not anticipate a possible scenario.
In this case, there's
four scenarios, but you
could imagine kind of forgetting the
fact that, oh, well maybe David's
not even in this phone book.
But you'd better handle that scenario.
And when you have a computer
that freezes or hangs
or reboots or just
something goes awry, that
is quite often quite simply
because a human did not
code for some possible scenario.
So what are the fundamental
constructs we've
seen here that we're going
to continue seeing in class?
Well, highlighted in yellow now
are really some verbs or actions
that we exercised with that phone book.
These are, in general, in
programming called functions.
A function is an action or a verb.
It's a statement that gets
the computer to do something.
Next highlighted here are what
we'll call conditions or branches.
These are sort of the
proverbial forks in the road.
You could either do this or
this or maybe this other thing.
And you can have one decision
to make or two or three or four,
however many conditions
make sense logically.
We'll call those conditions.
But how do you decide which
fork in the road to take?
Whether to do this or
that or this other thing?
For that we need something
called Boolean expressions.
A Boolean expression
it's just a question
whose answer is yes or no, or true
or false, or, frankly, one or zero.
All of those would be
equivalent for our purposes.
So person on page.
That's a yes or no question.
Person earlier in book?
That too is a question.
Person later in book is
a third question as well.
So if you can imagine a yes-no answer,
a true-false answer, a one-zero answer,
that is what gives us these
things called Boolean expressions.
And then lastly, in yellow
here are these things.
Go back to line three.
This will induce what we'll
call a loop or a cycle,
which is just a programming construct
or principle of an algorithm that
gets you to do something
again and again so you
don't have to write 100-line algorithm.
You can write a 13-line algorithm and
reuse parts of it again and again.
And so we'll begin now, and
we'll begin CS50 with a look
at an actual programming language,
one that you might have used recently
or as younger kids, known as Scratch,
which is a graphical programming
language which, while it might
be very familiar to some of you,
it actually represents a lot of
these programming fundamentals
that we'll use as this ground for
transitioning in just one week
to a more traditional
more old school language,
known as C, which is entirely
text and keyboard-based.
But we'll see in all of the
languages we look at in CS50,
these things called functions and
conditions, Boolean expressions
and loops, and today,
in just a moment, we'll
also see some other features that we
describe as variables, not unlike x, y,
and z in math, threads, which allow
a computer to do, it would seem,
multiple things at once, events,
and yet other features as well.
And so from here, we transition
from pseudocode to actual code.
And what you see on the
screen here is an example
of a language called C, where
we'll spend a good amount of time
this semester.
This is the older school
text-based, keyboard-based language
to which I referred earlier.
But this language is a bit cryptic.
And certainly at first glance, you might
wonder why is the hash symbol there,
the angled brackets, the parentheses,
the curly braces, the semicolon,
the quotes, I mean, my god, there is
so much syntax to what is on the screen
now.
And you can probably guess
what this program does.
Let me just go quickly to the audience.
What, anyone, does this program
probably do, even if you've never
programmed a computer before?
AUDIENCE: It just prints
out hello, comma, world.
DAVID J MALAN: Exactly.
It just prints hello, world.
And my god, like, look at all of
the syntax and all of the keystrokes
we had to type just to command
the computer to do that.
And so by contrast today is Scratch.
We'll allow ourselves for just
today to look at something much more
friendly, much more graphical, that will
allow us to explore these very ideas
and set the stage for more
sophisticated, more traditional
languages next week and
beyond, but in the context
where we don't have to worry about
parentheses, semicolons, curly braces,
and where even these
keys are on the keyboard.
So allow me to introduce
you, then, to Scratch,
developed by some of our
friends down the road
here in Cambridge at MIT's Media Lab.
You can play along at home here on out
if you would like at scratch.mit.edu.
It's web-based, but there's
also an offline version
if you tend not to have
the best of internet.
But the user interface would
typically look like this.
And a quick tour.
So here on scratch.mit.edu,
when you go to create
a project via the button on the
interface, you'll see first Scratch,
the namesake of the
program, this cat who
lives in this little rectangular
world in which you can move up,
down, left, or right.
But the cat can be transformed into
any number of other characters,
or what we'll call sprites,
visual representations thereof.
On the left here, now, are all of the
building blocks that come with Scratch.
All of the programming
constructs available to you
in the form of puzzle pieces.
And you'll notice that
they're categorized according
to color and description and there's
a whole bunch of puzzle pieces
that rather say what they do.
And today the goal is not to go into
the weeds of all of these various puzzle
pieces, but to highlight some of the
fundamental ideas that are possible.
And we'll explore those ideas via
the middle of the screen here.
We'll be able, in just a moment,
to start dragging and dropping
these puzzle pieces
onto this larger screen
and interlock them together, if
it makes logical sense to do so.
Finally, for the most
sophisticated programs,
we can actually create yet
more characters or sprites
and actually have a lot of
interactions on the screen as well.
But let's go ahead and dive in
with just an example quite quickly.
I'm going to go ahead on my screen
and go, indeed, to scratch.mit.edu.
And you're welcome to play
along at home as well.
And I'm going to click Create in order
to get into exactly that interface.
You do not need to make an account
from the get go unless you would like.
And let me go ahead and
start creating a program.
The very first program that
was once written, by lore,
was quite simply what Iris proposed
as "Hello World," a program that
prints on the screen hello, world.
Well, how can we do that?
Well, I can probably
do this quite quickly
because I've used the
interface before, but the goal
for you at hand if you've
never used this before,
with the course's first problem set
or programming assignment, really
is just to get your hands dirty
and explore and poke around.
And odds are, the ideas you are looking
for, you'll find eventually pop out.
And the first one I'm going
to try out is this one here.
This puzzle piece that's a
little yellow or orange in color.
It's in the Events category, and
it's called when green flag clicked.
This is of interest, because if I
go to Scratch's stage over here,
you'll see at top left there's a
green flag that's going to signify go,
and a red stop sign that's
going to signify stop.
So if I want something to happen
when I click that green flag,
I'm going to start with
this puzzle piece here.
Now I'm going to go over
into the Looks category.
And in the Looks category,
there's a whole bunch of blocks.
But we're going to keep it simple here.
I'm going to go ahead and just say the
canonical, as Iris noted, hello, comma,
world.
I'll zoom back out.
I'll move over to Scratch here, and
I'm going to click now the green flag.
And voila, hello, world.
So that is my-- and perhaps,
soon, your-- very first program,
using in this language Scratch.
But, of course, this isn't
terribly interesting.
Might be gratifying for
the very first time.
But it's not something you'd
want to play again and again.
But we can make this thing
much more interactive
and we can start to layer
these building blocks
and have an algorithm more
like searching that phone book,
that has multiple steps.
So let me go ahead
and stop that program.
And let me explore a little bit instead.
Let me go under Sensing this
time, this blue category.
And you'll see this block here.
Ask what's your name, and wait.
But notice that what's your
name is in this white oval,
and that implies that I can change
what the question is if I want,
but I'm fine with that question for now.
And let me go ahead and first
get rid of these blocks,
and give myself when green flag clicked,
and this time start under Sensing
with ask what's your name and wait.
But notice that this is
kind of a special block.
It comes with a second
block, a so-called variable.
It turns out that this ask
puzzle piece is literally
going to ask the human who's
playing this game a question,
and it's going to store the answer to
that question in a variable, depicted
here as this blue oval, called answer.
Just like in math, an x, a y, or a z.
So what could I do with that.
Well, let me again go to Looks.
Let me go to say hello, but
this time, you know what?
Let me go ahead and say hello,
comma, and then-- all right,
let me give myself a second say block.
But I don't want to say hello again.
So I'm going to delete that.
But I'm going to go back to Sensing
and I'm going to drag and drop answer.
Now it looks a little too big,
but notice if I get close to it,
it sort of magnetically
wants to connect.
And indeed, Scratch will grow
to fill the puzzle piece for me.
So now I have a program, it would
seem, a program written in Scratch,
a piece of software written in Scratch
that's going to, when the green flag is
clicked, ask what's your name,
and wait-- that's our function--
say hello--
that's another function--
and then it's going
to say answer, whatever
the human typed in.
Well, let me go over to Scratch's
world here and click the green flag.
Notice the cat is asking
me what's your name.
I type in David and enter.
Huh.
I only see David.
Well, maybe I did something wrong.
Let me do it again.
Green flag, D-A-V-I-D, enter.
Hmm.
What's going on?
This seems to be a bug, because I'm
pretty sure I have three functions,
ask, say, and say.
But I feel like I'm missing
the second instruction.
Any thoughts on what bug I have made?
What might explain this?
Natalie, is it?
AUDIENCE: So you replaced the
output with the same function.
DAVID J MALAN: Yeah.
I replaced the output
with the same function.
And honestly, even though we're using
a fairly simple program, Scratch,
my Mac is actually pretty fast.
And your PC or your Mac or
your phone is pretty fast.
And even though Scratch is saying hello
and saying answer, as Natalie notes,
the answer is sort of overwhelming to
say, because I didn't so much as pause.
So I could go in and
find a block-- there's
a wait block that could allow
me to insert an arbitrary pause.
But I really want this to be one breath.
I want it to be hello,
comma, David, all at once.
So how can I do that?
Well, let me go under Operations.
And it turns out there's a whole
bunch of math-related things here,
but also some English or
language-related things down here.
Join apple banana.
Now this has nothing to do
with apples and bananas.
Those are just placeholders, but
there's this puzzle piece here
that I can drag and drop.
And you know what?
Let me go ahead and do this.
Let me replace the first input to say,
and let me join hello comma, and then
not banana, but let me drag the answer--
and notice that will drop in place.
Let me throw this other block away.
To delete things, you can just drag
them over to the left and let go.
And now notice that I have a program
that's asking what's your name
and then I'm going to say the
result of joining hello and answer.
And let me go ahead and play this
now, after stopping the old one.
What's your name?
I type in David, enter, and voila.
As Natalie notes, now it's
not tripping over itself,
clobbering what was previously there.
Now I'm getting it all in one breath.
Now the program is getting
a little more interesting,
but the paradigm is no
different from before.
In fact, let me propose that
everything we've just done
is fitting perfectly into this
whole mental model of what
it means to solve problems and
what computer science itself is.
So for instance, if this
is the problem to be solved
and I've got inputs and outputs are
my goal and an algorithm in between,
let's consider how Scratch even
fits into this mental model.
My input to the very first
program that we wrote a moment ago
was literally hello,
world in its own oval.
The algorithm was implemented as
a function in Scratch called say.
So an algorithm, step
by step instructions,
a function is the computer's
implementation of an algorithm.
In this case, a function called say.
The output, of course, was
the cat saying hello, world.
But things got more interesting just now
after Natalie's remark, whereby when I
introduce something like ask
what's your name and then wait,
notice what happens
this time in the model.
Now the input to the problem
is what's your name--
that's the string that comes by default,
and I could change it but I didn't.
That's being fed now into the ask block.
And the ask block's purpose
in life is to get the cat
to give me an answer like this.
Now, that answer is interesting
because I can now join it
in with the word hello as a prefix.
So this block is interesting
because notice, the input,
the white oval to the say block actually
has another puzzle piece and then
two more puzzle pieces on top of it.
And what's cool here is that
when programming functions,
you can have the outputs of one function
become the input to another function.
And so the flow here
is quite simply this.
Now I have two inputs to the
function, both hello, which I wrote,
and answer, which came
from the ask block.
The algorithm in question now is the
join function, which I just used.
And its output is hopefully
going to be hello, comma, David.
But I don't want to see a white oval on
the screen saying hello, comma, David.
I want the cat to say
hello, comma, David.
So let me go ahead and
focus only on the output.
Make it become the input to a final
function, which is that say block,
and voila, now the cat
says what I want it to.
So again, even as you start to nest,
that is, place these puzzle pieces
one on top of the other, all
we're doing is passing in inputs
and getting outputs.
Doing something with those outputs
and making them inputs, and so forth.
That really is the paradigm,
ultimately, of what it means to program.
But we can make the cat do
more interesting things.
And just to have a little
bit of fun with this,
let me go ahead and dig
in to this bottom icon
at the bottom left of the screen.
Scratch has these so-called
extensions, where you can really
make it do fancier things as well.
And let me go to Text to
Speech at the top right.
So this is using a cloud-based service--
that is some internet-based service--
that's going to send the words
that I type out on the internet.
The internet, some server there, is
going to respond with a verbalization
now of what it is I just typed.
So let me go ahead and try this.
Let me get rid of the
purple say function
and replace it with this speak block.
And let me go ahead and drag
in the join puzzle piece
here-- notice it's
going to grow to fill,
and I'm not going to
use this one anymore.
This time I'm going to hit
Stop and I'm going to go ahead
and hit Play once more
and type in my name.
And--
COMPUTER: (FEMININE
ROBOTIC) Hello, David.
DAVID J MALAN: OK, not a
very natural cat sound,
but notice we can set
the voice differently.
So notice I can drag this puzzle piece.
And you can even squeeze
blocks inside of others.
Notice that it can go wherever you want.
I'll put it at the very top here.
So I could put it in a
couple of different places.
Right now the default voice is alto.
Squeak sounds appropriate.
Let's try that.
Typing in my name, David.
COMPUTER: (HIGH PITCHED) Hello, David.
DAVID J MALAN: All right.
Still not very catlike.
Ironically, there is a kitten voice,
which if I change it to kitten,
we'll now hear this.
Type in my name and enter.
COMPUTER: (HIGH PITCHED) Meow meow.
DAVID J MALAN: OK, so it doesn't really
matter at that point what I type in.
But now this is amazing.
Like, we've gone from just
saying hello, world to hello,
David, which is dynamically changing.
If you were to type
your name, obviously,
it would say your name instead.
And now, thanks to the cloud,
that is, servers on the internet,
we're converting automatically
text that the human has just
provided into a sound file--
notes and durations and all of that--
into something my computer can now play.
Well, let's actually make this cat
sound a little more like a cat.
Let me go ahead and
get rid of those blocks
here, and let me go and give
myself now from the sound category,
how about this?
Play sound meow until done.
Now, this is a simple program.
When the green flag is clicked,
play sound meow until done.
Here we go.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Play.
[MEOW]
All right, that's it.
If I want to hear the cat meow
again, I got to do it again.
[MEOW]
OK, that's great.
I could kind of amuse myself
for a while by just clicking--
[MEOW]
--play, but--
--surely we can do better than this.
You can imagine this--
[MEOW]
--getting tedious quickly.
So how might I get the cat
to do this again and again?
Well, you know what?
Let me go ahead and let me just
kind of grab a few of these.
Meow, meow, meow, three times.
So now that's two fewer times
I have to hit the button.
[MEOWING THREE TIMES RAPIDLY]
All right.
It doesn't seem like the happiest cat.
So let me actually go to Control and let
me give him a second break in between.
Wait one second in between here.
Now let me do it again.
[MEOWING THREE TIMES]
OK, slightly happier cat.
But this seems a little messy now.
This is correct.
It is meowing three times.
But let me go to the audience.
Let's now consider design.
Recall that we considered design
in the context of the phone book.
The third algorithm was better
designed in that it was faster,
it was more efficient, but
there's another element
to design, which is that you
shouldn't repeat yourself if possible.
So those of you who
have programmed before
might know what the
solution here might be.
Well, it turns out that go back
to line three, we call a loop.
Turns out Scratch supports
these things called loops.
And, in fact, there's one
staring at me right here.
If I zoom in on the left, notice
that under the control blocks,
these orange blocks
there's a repeat block.
And even though it says 10 by
default, I bet we can change that.
So let me drag that over here.
Let me throw away a lot of this
redundancy, this copy paste.
Let me move these puzzle pieces
inside of the repeat block,
and it, too, will grow to fit them.
Not a problem.
Let me change the repeat to three.
And now let me reconnect everything.
And now the program is just tighter.
It's using fewer puzzle
pieces, or fewer lines of code,
fewer steps, if you will,
to achieve the same result.
So now if I click the green flag--
[MEOWING THREE TIMES]
--it's still working.
So you could imagine changing
this to any number you want.
There's even a forever block,
where we could do it forever,
if the cat's going to
do this in perpetuity.
But it's a better program now.
Now it is better designed, because if
I want to change the amount of time
the cat is waiting or
if I want to change
the total number of
times the cat meows, I
can change those details in one
place, not in one or two or three,
as by copying and pasting
those same puzzle pieces.
Well, what about that forever loop?
What if you do want to
do something forever?
What might I want to do?
Well, let's get the cat up and moving.
Let me go under the motion category now.
Let me go to point
towards mouse pointer.
So let me zoom in on this.
And every time the cat points
toward the mouse pointer,
let's have him take one step.
So I'm going to grab the
move some number of steps,
and I'm going to change the 10 to a one.
And now I'm going to hit Play.
And now we have our first
program where the cat is
kind of responding to my Mac's cursor.
And I can move it around, and I
can kind of get a little goofy,
but it's taking me literally.
It's pointing at the mouse cursor
and it's then moving one step.
Now, I can make it move faster.
Let me stop this for a second.
What if I move not one step at
a time, but two steps at a time?
And we'll see that now the
cat is moving a little faster.
Not quite super fast.
Let's do 20 steps at a
time and see what happens.
And this is really the
essence of animation.
The more you adjust the number of steps
or the number of changes happening
to those pixels per second
or per unit of time,
the more that's going to
happen visually on the screen.
Well, what more can we
do from just following?
Well, you know what?
If I have the ability now
to have the cat follow me,
let me try something else altogether.
Let me go ahead and open
up another extension.
Let me go into the Pen
tool, which is going
to allow me now to draw with, like,
a pencil or pen on the screen.
And let me go ahead and still
have the cat follow me, I think--
actually, you know what?
Let's change this.
Let's just have him go to where I am.
So there's another block that
says go to random position.
I don't want that.
So I'm going to change it
by the little triangle menu
here, to go to the mouse pointer.
So now, forever, the cat's just going
to go to where the mouse pointer is.
It's not going to glide or
do it slowly or quickly.
It's just going to go to
wherever the cursor is.
And let me go now to this
new Pen category down below.
And how might I do this?
You know what I want?
I want this cat to be
able to draw for me.
When I move the cursor
up, down, left, right, I
want to actually draw something
with ink on the screen.
But I only want to draw
something when the pen is down.
Notice on the left that two of the two
puzzle pieces I just introduced over
here at left are pen down and pen up.
But there's a piece
of missing logic here.
Let me ask the audience how might
we go about enhancing this program
so not only does the cat follow my
cursor, but I also draw on the screen?
Nicholas, what kinds of
solutions would you propose?
AUDIENCE: So what you could
do is take an if statement--
so you can control when the pen
is up or when the pen is down,
depending on some
condition that you have.
Like, I know a lot of things,
you draw with the mouse click,
if the mouse is on, then
you can say the pen is down.
And when the mouse click
is not on, your pen is up.
And then while it follows
it forever it also
senses to see if your
mouse click is on or off.
I don't really know.
DAVID J MALAN: No, you really do know.
That was, like, perfect.
Because you took this
principle of having the forever
block not only go to the mouse
pointer, but you proposed
asking a question by a condition.
So let me actually go
under Control, where
I happen to know this puzzle piece is,
and notice similar to our phone book
pseudocode, where I said if
else, if else, if else, well,
here there's only two questions,
I think, as you're proposing.
Is the mouse button down or up?
So I think we can get
away with just an if else.
So let me go ahead and drag this
below the go to mouse pointer.
And then notice this little
trapezoid-like shape in the middle
here.
Let me go to Sensing here.
And notice if I scroll
down-- yep, there it is.
On the left, notice this one?
Mouse down, question mark?
These are our Boolean expressions.
Let me drag that Boolean
expression into that similar shape.
It's going to grow to fit it.
And then what do I want to do?
If the mouse is down, I think
I want to put the pen down.
Else, if the mouse is implicitly up,
let me go ahead and put the pen up
like this.
Well, let me go ahead and
full screen this, just
so we can see a little better.
Let me hit Play.
And now the cat is
following me, as promised.
But this is now a drawing cat.
If I click the mouse button, I can say
something like, very poorly in cursive,
Hello.
Sort of.
Been a long time since
I've done cursive.
So we now have the cat
actually drawing something.
And honestly, it's a little
ridiculous that it's a cat drawing.
But you know what?
Scratch has these costumes.
We could go at top left here, and
even though Scratch comes with two cat
costumes, we could change it to be a
pen or a marker or, really, anything
we want.
Because at the end of
the day, this sprite
is really just a character
on the screen that
can take any form that we might want.
Well, how can we take this further?
I like this introduction
of conditions and loops,
but there's some other
principles we can introduce here.
Let me go ahead and start a
new program here altogether.
And let's see if we
can't start counting up
and start keeping track of information.
So for this time, let's do this.
When the green flag is clicked,
this time let's go under variables
and let's give ourselves a new variable.
Scratch lets you create puzzle
pieces, this one being a variable,
and I'm going to call this a counter.
Just something that's going
to keep count from one on up.
Now this has given me some
custom puzzle pieces over here
called counter, and then the default
my variable, which was there already.
And I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to set the counter
initially equal to one.
And then I'm going to
do something forever.
Let me grab one of those forever blocks.
And I want the cat now
to do this forever.
I want it to just say
whatever the current count is.
So I don't want it to say
hello for two seconds.
I want it to say something
for one second, let's say.
So I'm going to go back to variables.
And I'm going to grab this new
circular shape, counter, that I created
and drag it right there.
So you can read this
literally top to bottom.
So counter to one, then forever
say the counter for one second.
But if we don't want the cat to say the
same number again and again and again,
let's go ahead and change
the counter by one.
And that's implicitly going
to add one to the counter.
Now if I go ahead and
hit Play, we see a cat
that's counting from
one to two to three,
and it's going to count up,
ideally, all the way to infinity.
The difference being
now, we have this feature
of actually using a variable,
a variable that's keeping
track of some amount of information.
In this case, the number that's
constantly being updated,
and the screen is being
redrawn again and again.
Well, now let me go ahead
and just start opening
a few programs that I
wrote in advance, just
so that we can get a
tour of some of those.
I've got this program called Bounce
that works a little something like this.
And this, too, is part of programming.
Not only writing your own code,
but reading your own code.
And let me go ahead and zoom in on
this, which I've already created,
and consider what it says.
First set, rotation style, left, right.
This is just a fix what would otherwise
be a bug where the cat accidentally
ends up upside down.
But let me wave my hand at that.
This is the interesting part.
Forever have the cat moved 10 steps.
And then if it's touching the
edge, then turn around 180 degrees.
So now we can reintroduce
the idea of animation.
But not that's driven by me,
the human, with my cursor.
I can now make a game, and
interactive piece of art, or anything
now where the cat is self-driven.
Because when I hit Play
now, notice that it's
moving back and forth, back and forth.
And if it is touching
the edge and the answer
to that Boolean question is,
actually, yes or true or one,
then it's going to turn 180 degrees.
But this looks kind
of stupid, admittedly.
You know, one, the cat, yes,
is bouncing off the screen,
which is maybe a little unrealistic.
But he's not really walking.
He's gliding.
But this is the thing about animation.
Just as we noted before that
videos, at the end of the day,
are really just images
flying across the screen--
you know what?
I bet we can create our own illusion
of movement, just like in a real video,
by taking not just one costume,
the cat with his feet like this.
What if we gave ourselves a second
costume, where it's almost the same
but his feet are slightly
differently positioned?
Just like the paper based flipbook
that we looked at earlier.
And you know what?
I bet if I toggle between
these two costumes,
changing the condition of
the cat again and again,
I bet we can create the
illusion of actual movement.
And that's what we have here
in this other bounce example.
In this other bounce example,
we have the cat now moving
not only back and forth, but
notice this purple puzzle piece.
After it bounces off the edge, or
considers bouncing off the edge,
it constantly changes its costume
to the next one, to the next one,
to the next one, essentially
alternating between the two.
So now it's not quite perfect.
Like, it has what we
call very low frame rate.
This is like watching a
really bad animated GIF online
that only has two
different frames in it.
But it looks more like
he's walking and much less
like he's gliding back
and forth on the screen.
So we can actually have
some fun with this, too.
Scratch support sounds.
So, for instance, here's
the meow we've heard before.
[MEOW]
I can record my own, though, if I
click this little plus icon down here.
Click Record, and allow Scratch
to access my microphone.
Click OK a couple of times.
Here we go.
Let me record my own voice.
Ouch.
All right.
That's what the word Ouch looks
like, at least when I pronounce it.
I can trim off the beginning here.
Let me save that.
I'm going to give this
recording a name, Ouch,
and now let me go back to my code.
And under the sound
block, you know what?
Let me go ahead and say this.
If I'm touching the edge, not only
do I want to turn 180 degrees.
Now I can kind of make
this a little more playful.
COMPUTER: Ouch.
Ouch.
DAVID J MALAN: All right.
Still not very catlike, but again,
we're just layering and layering.
And the takeaway here
really is, as these programs
get more and more complicated, the goal
should never be, when writing code,
whether it's in Scratch
or C or eventually
Python in this class or
others, to just start and try
to implement your entire vision.
Notice with every one of these
programs that I wrote from scratch,
no pun intended, did I start small
and add one or two or three puzzle
pieces, building up from something
simple to something more complex.
And you know what?
I bet if we synthesize some of these
ideas, we can do yet other things too.
Here's another example that
involves, perhaps, petting a cat.
Let me go ahead and see
inside this program.
This one's relatively simple, but
it's not doing anything just yet.
I already hit the green flag.
Let me Zoom in on the code, and you
can, perhaps, now read my own code
that I wrote in advance.
The cat is forever asking the question,
if touching mouse pointer then
play that sound meow until done.
Well, it would seem that even
though the program is running,
it's not doing anything.
But it is.
It's waiting for something to happen.
So let me move my cursor
over the cat like--
[MEOW]
--this.
So it would seem, and if I leave
it on there, he'll keep meowing.
And it's kind of like a
program that's petting a cat.
And so you can imagine
now having conditions
inside of loops that are using
Boolean expressions to decide
exactly what you want something to do.
And even more powerfully, even in a
language like Scratch can we do this.
Let me open up the sea lion here,
who has a very distinct bark.
But he's demonstrative now of a
program that has multiple scripts.
So inside of this Scratch project now,
we're not just one program but two.
Notice both of which start
when a green flag is clicked.
And let me put them
both onto the screen.
And it looks longer.
But that's just because the puzzle
pieces are growing to fit each other.
Let's go ahead and hit Play on this.
Play
[SEA LION BARKING]
Notice that every second or
so, the sea lion is barking.
And frankly, this gets annoying quickly.
But how can I stop it?
Well, let me go ahead and look over here
on the left while it's still barking.
Notice the sea lion is
forever asking a question.
If muted equals false, start sounds sea
lion, think hi hi hi for two seconds.
So what is muted?
Well, the shape of
it, recall, represents
a variable, like x or y or z, which is
just some way of retaining information.
So this is like saying, is the
value of the muted variable false?
If so, you should bark, because if
it's false muted, if it's not muted,
go ahead and play the sea lion sound.
But my god, lets-- on the right
here, notice there's another program.
When the green flag is clicked,
forever ask the question.
If the spacebar is pressed,
then if muted is true,
set muted to false,
else set muted to true.
So the program on the right is
going to change the value of muted
from false to true or true to false.
Because, my god.
I've hit the space bar--
[SEA LION BARKING]
And now it's over.
The program is still
running, but it's no longer
playing because muted is
now true and not false.
Well, what else can we do?
Things can get pretty
fancy pretty quickly.
Let me go ahead and create
one other program here.
And I'll go ahead and do
one with just two blocks.
This one-- let me go into the extensions
again, video sensing this time,
and notice there's different
types of ways to start programs.
Not every program has to start
when you click the green flag.
There's a similar shape here,
but this one in green, that
says when video motion
is greater than 10.
Like 10% of the screen is moving.
Let me increase that to 50%.
And let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and find
the sound puzzle piece.
Play sound meow until done.
So now I have a two block program.
When video motion is more than
50, play sound meow until done.
Let me zoom out.
And you'll notice that I'm
actually in the screen here.
Let me move off stage.
And now nothing is happening.
Let me go and pet the cat, though.
[MEOW]
Let me do it again.
And again.
So it's using my computer's camera--
[MEOW]
--detecting motion, and then
executing that particular program.
So again, with just these
simple building blocks,
can we get more and more
interesting things to happen.
And you know what?
We can even have multiple sprites.
Let me go ahead and open
up an old school game
that you might have played in,
like, a swimming pool, perhaps,
growing up, where one person yells
out Marco and the other people
are supposed to yell out Polo.
Notice here we have a
program with two sprites.
So two puppets, an orange
puppet and a blue puppet.
And down here at the bottom,
for the very first time,
We have two different sprites'
abilities to write programs.
So right now the orange
puppet is selected,
which means the program
at top left here,
up here, belongs to the orange puppet.
And the orange puppet
has been programmed
to say forever, if the
keyboard's space key is pressed,
then say Marco for two seconds.
And then here's the new feature.
There's a way in programming
to have, like, one program talk
to another, or in this case,
one sprite talk to another.
Sort of passing a secret message
that you don't see on the screen.
But one program can hear from another.
And that's called broadcasting an event.
And that's what the
orange puppet is doing.
If I click on the blue
puppet's icon here,
he's not going to do very much at all.
But instead of doing anything
when the green flag is clicked,
instead of doing something
when the camera sees motion,
he instead is going to, when he receives
the event, say Polo for two seconds.
And so in this case, if I hit
Play now, nothing happens yet.
But when I do hit the spacebar,
orange says Marco, blue says Polo.
But they are written independently.
I've written one program for
orange, one program for blue,
and they're somehow communicating.
And speaking of
communicating, there's even
more things you can do these days
thanks to the internet and the cloud.
Let me go ahead and open up
one other new canvas here.
Very quickly give myself
a when green flag clicked.
Let me go ahead and ask that same
question before, ask what's your name
and wait.
But now let me go into
these extensions and let
me find the translate
extension, which is, again,
going to use the cloud to send
whatever I type in out on the internet
and get back a response, and
then say it on the screen here.
So let me go ahead and say something
on the screen, like say hello.
But I don't want to say hello.
I want to go back to
the Translate category,
and I want to go ahead and translate--
you know what?
I like this block.
Translate something to another language.
But let me get one of those join
blocks again, and let me go ahead
and join the word hello and then the
name that the person has typed in.
So to get that, I need
the answer block again.
So I'm just recreating some
of our blocks from earlier.
And notice, before I just did this.
I said the result of joining hello and
answer, albeit with a comma last time.
But now let's do this.
Let me take the output of join,
make it the input to translate.
Let me translate, say, to Arabic here.
Let me drag and drop into the say block.
So now we have two inputs going
into join, join's output going
into the input of translate, and the
output of translate going into say.
But the net result is going to be I'll
type in my name David and hit Enter.
Hello, David, now in Arabic.
All thanks to these principles of
functions, conditions, and loops,
and now even adding in the internet.
Now let's consider finally, before
we play a final couple of games.
In conclusion, there's
a way to even improve
the design of a lot of what we've done.
In fact, let me go back just a moment
to where we left off with that meowing.
And in one of our
meowing examples, we had
code that looked like this,
where I repeated three times,
recall, and I played the sound
meow again and again and again.
And I argued at the time that
this was better designed.
Why?
Because I didn't just drag and
drop the same puzzle piece again
and again and again.
I used a repeat block, I threw
away all of the redundancy,
and I've arguably kept it simple.
I'm using some fancier ideas,
but the code is simpler
and it's fewer puzzle pieces now.
But it turns out that
there's a missed opportunity
here to apply another
principle of computer science,
and this is what we would
generally describe as abstraction.
Abstraction is this
amazing problem solving
technique that's really
just a fancy way of saying
let's take a very complicated idea,
or a slightly complicated idea
and simplify it in such a way that we
all agree that you can implement it
the complicated way, but
let's now just stipulate
that we're going to think about
it as on a more simple level.
So let me go over to this same program.
And you know what?
Scratch, curiously, did not
anticipate having a meow block.
Like, there is a say block and there's a
think block, but there's no meow block.
And that seems appropriate for a program
where it comes with a cat built in.
So we can do this.
Just as you can create your own
variables, notice at bottom left here,
you can create your own blocks
with this pink category.
And if I go here, I'm
going to make a block
and I'm going to call this block meow.
And quite simply, I'm going to click OK.
Now notice I get this new puzzle
piece that says define meow.
And it's ready to have other
pieces connected to it.
How am I going to define meow?
I'm just going to go ahead and drag
this over here, because I already
implemented meow before.
And now, notice what I
have on the left hand side.
Because I've just made this
custom block or puzzle piece,
I now have a pink piece called meow,
just as though it came with Scratch.
And now what's compelling about
this is that I can sort of think
of this as out of sight, out of mind.
Who cares how meow is implemented?
We know we implemented it earlier.
Let's now just stipulate that we
can take for granted it exists.
And if I zoom in now on the new program,
now it's more readable in some sense.
It's a little shorter.
It has a fewer puzzle piece.
But it also is more self-descriptive.
I can read my code.
I can look at this
code and say, OK, it's
obviously going to repeat
three times a meow block.
But let's play that.
[MEOW]
It's no different.
Two.
[MEOW]
But I bet we can simplify
this one step further and make
it a little more flexible.
Let me go ahead and right click or
control click on the meow custom block.
And let me actually add an
input here that we'll call n.
And let me just add a
label that says times.
And let me go ahead and click OK.
And notice that my puzzle
piece now looks different.
It looks more like some of
MIT's blocks that take input
with these little white ovals.
And, in fact, now notice what I can do.
I can change the definition of
meow, as Scratch already has for me,
such that I can now do more inside.
Let me actually disconnect
all of this stuff.
Let me move the repeat block to
the definition of meow itself.
Let me go ahead and play the sound
and wait inside of that repeat block,
but notice this little
circle around the end.
Let me just repeat an
arbitrary number of times now.
I don't have to worry about hard
coding three or 10 or anything else.
And now, out of sight, out of mind,
don't have to worry about that anymore.
Let's now just whittle down that
increasingly complicated program
that we wrote earlier into,
really, just two puzzle pieces.
When the green flag is clicked,
meow, sure, three times.
I don't have to know or care any
more how meow is implemented.
I just need to know that someone
did it for me, whether MIT or maybe
myself, minutes ago.
I'll click play again.
[MEOWING THREE TIMES]
Two, and three.
And so now we have an
implementation of abstraction.
Taking a somewhat complicated
idea, like getting a cat to meow,
not worrying about the so-called
implementation details,
and just defining a puzzle
piece or function called meow.
Well, now let's take
all of this together
and see some of the creations of some
of your predecessors in past terms.
Here, for instance, is a sort of story
that one of your classmates years ago
made involving a gingerbread tale.
Let me go ahead and full
screen this and click Play.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
And you'll see now that we have
multiple sprites already, each of which
have different costumes, and
I'm being asked a question.
Would you like an apple?
Yes or no.
So I'm no longer being asked my name.
I'm being asked arbitrary questions.
Sure.
Let me go ahead and have an apple.
I type in yes and hit Enter.
Notice the movement.
We've seen movement before.
[CHOMPING SOUNDS]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
OK, unfortunately, that was the
wrong decision to make in this story.
So that's OK.
Let's start it again.
Red stop sign.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Green flag.
Hello dearie, would you like an apple?
No, let's learn from that lesson.
Cupcake sounds much better.
I'll type yes this time.
Notice, again, the motion.
So there's some animation there.
It's touching the other sprite.
That, too, was unfortunate.
Let's try one last time with this art.
And now we have an apple, no.
Learned a lesson.
Cupcake, no.
OK, now let's see what
happens with that loop.
[CACKLING]
[SCREAMING]
[CHOMPING SOUNDS]
OK, surprise ending.
But this is all to say that by taking
these building blocks of loops,
conditions, and functions,
can you start to make things
that are a little more interactive.
In fact, I myself did something
years ago-- the very first thing
I myself wrote in Scratch was
actually when I was in graduate school
and cross-registered for a class
at MIT, the professor for which
was the author of and the
originator of Scratch itself.
And let me go ahead and
full screen this and propose
how I thought about solving, now, a
fairly large problem back in the day.
Drag as much falling trash
into the can as you can.
So what's happening now?
A piece of trash is
falling on the screen.
You'll see that it's moving
from the top to the bottom,
and we've seen animations like that.
But watch this.
I bet using a condition
and a forever loop,
we can make it possible to pick this up.
Notice now the trash is following
my cursor, just like the cat was.
And notice if touching this
other trash can sprite,
maybe we can even get Oscar
to pop out of the can.
And he, then, starts counting up
my score, thereby using a variable,
and indeed, as more sprites
or more trash falls,
I can continue to play
a game in this way.
But here, too, even though things
are starting to happen more quickly,
there's more on the screen, the
song is playing in the background,
it all reduces to basic building blocks.
And I can't emphasize enough.
When I wrote that first
program years ago,
I did not implement what you just saw.
I think the very first thing
I did was I googled around
and found Sesame Street's street
lamp and I put that on the screen.
And that was sort of version one.
It didn't do anything, but
it looked like what I want.
Then I added the trash can.
Then I think I programmed one piece
of trash or one sprite to fall.
So I changed the cat to
a piece of trash and then
I had it animate from top to bottom.
Then version four or five,
I then added a forever loop
and a condition that checks
if the mouse button is down,
and if so, I have it
follow the mouse pointer.
So I took a big problem and
broke it down bit by bit
into much smaller steps.
And this was the same approach that
CS50's own Andrew Berry took years ago,
one of our teaching fellows.
The very first year I taught CS50,
created his very own first Scratch
project that I thought I'd
leave us with here today.
This is a program that
he called Raining Men.
It might have a familiar
tune, and I would
propose that you consider,
when watching this,
our final Scratch program today, how it
is that Andrew went about programming
everything that you see.
Now Andrew went off into the real world
and didn't pursue computer science,
per se.
He's actually now the general
manager for the Cleveland Browns,
which is an American football team.
But this, too, speaks to just
what kind of foundation you
can form, irrespective of your
intended major, your possible major,
considering, after all, that a lot
of the ideas we're going to focus on
in this class are ultimately
about problem solving,
programming being just
one tool for the trade.
And, indeed, even within
the world of sports,
are there so many opportunities
nowadays for algorithms, for analysis,
for video simulations thereof,
and so many of Andrew's worlds
and your worlds will
invariably start to collide
as you begin to build
up your own toolkit
and your own understanding thereof.
So in conclusion, we'll take a
look at this, Andrews program.
In the meantime, this was
CS50, and now it's raining men.
[MUSIC - "IT'S RAINING MEN]
COMPUTER: Hi.
Hi.
We're your weather girls.
Uh huh.
And have we got news for you.
You better listen.
Get ready, all you lonely girls,
and leave those umbrellas at home.
All right.
(SINGING) Humidity's rising,
barometer's getting low.
Oh.
Uh oh.
According to all sources--
What sources now?
The street's the place to go.
'Cause tonight for the first
time, at just about half past 10,
for the first time in history
it's gonna start raining men!
It's raining men, hallelujah,
it's raining men--
[MUSIC PLAYING]