[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, so this is CS50.
And this is week 2, wherein we're
going to dive in a little more deeply
to see this new language.
And we're also going to
take a look back at some
of the concepts we looked at last week
so that you can better understand some
of the features of C
and some of the steps
you've been taking to
make your code work.
So we'll peel back some of the
layers of abstraction from last week
so that you better understand
really what's going
on underneath the hood of the computer.
So, of course, last week, we began with
perhaps the most canonical of programs
in C, the most canonical
of programs you can
write pretty much in any
language, which is that which
says, quite simply, "hello, world."
But recall that before
actually running this program,
we have to convert it into the language
that computers themselves speak,
which we defined last week as
binary, 0's and 1's, otherwise known
as machine language in this context.
So we have to go somehow from
this source code to something
more like this machine code, the 0's
and 1's that the computer actually
understands.
Now, you may recall too that we
introduced a command for this.
And that command was called make.
And literally via this command,
"make hello," could we make a program
called hello.
And make was a little fancy.
It assumed that if you want to
make a program called hello,
it would look for a file called hello.c.
That just happens automatically for you.
And the end result, of course, was
an additional file called hello
that would end up getting put
into your current directory.
So you could then do
./hello and be on your way.
But it turns out that make
is actually automating
a more specific set of
steps for us that we'll
see a little more closely now instead.
So on the screen here
is exactly the same code
that we wrote last week to say,
quite simply, "hello, world."
And recall that any time you
run "make hello" or "make mario"
or "make cash" or "make
credit," any of the problems
that you might have
tackled more recently,
you see some cryptic
output on the screen.
Hopefully, no red or yellow error
messages, but even when all is well,
you see this white text which is
indicative of all having been well.
And last week, we just kind of ignored
this and moved on and immediately did
something like ./hello.
But today, let's actually
better understand
what it is that we've been
turning a blind eye to
so that each week, as it passes, there's
less and less that you don't understand
the entirety of with respect
to what's going on your screen.
So again, if I do ls here, we'll
see not only hello.c, but also
the executable program called hello
that I actually created via make.
But look at this output.
There's some mention of
something called Clang here.
And then there's a lot of other words or
cryptic phrases, something in computer
speak here that has all of
these hyphens in front of them.
And it turns out that
what make is doing for us
is it's automating execution of a
command more specifically called clang.
Clang is actually the compiler that
we alluded to last week, a compiler
being a program that converts
source code to machine code.
We've actually been using
Clang this whole time.
But notice that Clang requires
a bit more sophistication.
You have to understand a bit more about
what's going on in order to use it.
So let me go ahead and remove
the program called hello.
I'm going to use the rm command
that we saw briefly last time.
I'm going to confirm by hitting y.
And if I type ls again now, hello.c
is the only file that remains.
Well, temporarily, let me take
away the ability to use make.
And let's now use Clang directly.
Clang is another program
installed in CS50 IDE.
It's a very popular compiler that you
can download onto your own Macs and PCs
as well.
But to run it is a little different.
I'm going to go ahead and say
clang and then the name of the file
that I want to compile,
hello.c being this one.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
And now nothing happens, seemingly.
But frankly, as you've
probably gleaned already,
when nothing bad seems to
happen, that implicitly
tends to mean that
something good happened.
Your program compiled successfully.
But curiously, if I type ls now,
you don't see the program, hello.
You see this weird
file name called a.out.
And this is actually
a historical remnant.
Years ago, when humans would use
a compiler to compile their code,
the default file name that
every program was given
was a.out for assembly output.
More on that in a moment.
But this is kind of a
stupid name for a program.
It's not at all descriptive
of what it does.
So it turns out that programs like Clang
can be configured at the command line.
The command line, again, refers to
the blinking prompt where you can
type commands.
So indeed, I'm going to go ahead and
remove this file now-- rm space a.out,
and then confirm with y.
And now I'm back to where
I began with just hello.c.
And let me go ahead now and do
something a little different.
I'm going to do "clang -o hello"
and then the word "hello.c."
And what I'm doing here
is actually providing
what we're going to start
calling a command-line argument.
So these commands, like
make and rm, sometimes
can just be run all by themselves.
You just type a single
word and hit Enter.
But very often, we've seen that
they take inputs in some sense.
You type, "make hello."
You type, "rm hello."
And the second word,
"hello," in those cases,
is kind of an input to
the command, otherwise
now known as a command-line argument.
It's an input to the command.
So here, we have more
command-line arguments.
We've got the word "clang," which is
the compiler we're about to run, "-o,"
which it turns out is shorthand
notation for "output,"
so please output the following.
What do you want to output?
Well, the next word is "hello."
And then the final word is "hello.c."
So long story short, this
command now more verbose
though it is, is saying, run
Clang, output a file called hello,
and take as input file called hello.c.
So when I run this command after hitting
Enter, nothing again seems to happen.
But if I type ls, I don't see that
stupid default file name of a.out.
Now I see the file name, hello.
So this is how ultimately Clang
is helping me compile my code.
It's kind of automating
all of those processes.
But recall that that's not the only
type of program we ran last week
or wrote last week.
We rather took code like
this and began to enhance it
with some additional lines.
So version 2 of Hello,
World actually involved
prompting the user for input
using CS50's get_string function,
storing the output in
a variable called name.
But recall that we also had to
add cs50.h at the top of the file.
So let me go ahead and do that.
Let me go ahead and remove hello
because that's now the old version.
Let me go in now and start updating my
code here and go into my hello.c file,
include cs50.h, now get
myself a string called name,
but we could call it anything,
call the function get_string,
and ask, "What's your name," question
mark with a space at the very end
just to create a gap.
And then down here, instead of
printing out "hello, world" always,
let me print out "Hello, %s,"
which is a placeholder recall,
and output the person's name.
So last week, the way we
compiled this program was just
"make hello," no different from now.
But this week, suppose I were
to instead get rid of make, only
because it's sort of automating
steps for me that I now
want to understand in more detail.
I could compile this program again
with clang -o hello hello.c, so just
a reapplication of that same idea of
passing in three arguments, -o, hello,
and hello.c.
But the catch now is
that I'm actually going
to see one of these red error messages.
And let's consider what
this is actually saying.
There's still going to be a
bunch of cryptic stuff here.
But notice, as always, we're
going to see, hopefully,
something that's a little familiar.
So "undefined reference to get_string."
I don't yet know what an undefined
reference is, necessarily.
I don't know what a linker command is.
But I at least recognize there's
something going on with get_string.
And there's a reason for this.
It turns out that when using a library,
whether it's CS50's library or others'
as well, it's sometimes not
sufficient only to include the header
file at the top of your own code.
Sometimes, you additionally
have to tell the computer
where to find the 0's and 1's that
someone has written to implement
a function like get_string.
So the header file, like
cs50.h, just tells the compiler
that the function exists.
But there's a second
mechanism that, up until now,
has been automated for us,
that tells the computer where
to find the actual 0's and 1's that
implements the functions in that header
file.
So with that said, I'm going to need
to actually add another command line
argument to this command.
And instead of doing clang -o hello
hello.c, I'm going to additionally,
and admittedly, cryptically,
do -lcs50 at the end
of this command, which quite simply
refers to link in the CS50 library.
So "link" is a term of
art that we'll see what it
means in more detail in just a moment.
But this additional final
command-line argument tells Clang,
you already know that a
function like get_string exists.
-lcs50 means when
compiling hello.c, make
sure to incorporate all of the
machine code from CS50's library
into your program as well.
In short, it's something you have to
do when you use certain libraries.
So now when I hit Enter, all seems to
be well because nothing bad got printed.
If I type ls, I see hello.
And voila, I can do ./hello,
type in my name, David.
And voila, "hello, David."
So why didn't we do
all of this last week?
And frankly, we've made
no fundamental progress.
All we've done is reveal what's
going on underneath the hood.
But I'll claim that, frankly,
compiling your code by typing out
all of these verbose command-line
arguments just gets tedious quickly.
And so computer scientists and
programmers, more specifically,
tend to automate monotonous steps.
So what's happening ultimately
with make is that all of this
is being automated for us.
So when you typed "make hello"
last week-- and henceforth,
you're welcome to continue
using make as well--
notice that it generates this
extra long command, some of which
we haven't even talked about.
But I do recognize
clang at the beginning.
I recognize hello.c see here.
I recognize -lcs50 here.
But notice there's a bunch
of other stuff as well,
not only the -o hello,
but also -lm, which
refers to a math library,
-lcrypt, which refers
to a cryptography or
an encryption library.
In short, we the staff
have preconfigured
make to just make sure that
when you compile your code,
all of the requisite dependencies,
libraries, and so forth,
are available to you without
having to worry about all
of these command-line arguments.
So henceforth, you can
certainly compile your code
in this way using Clang directly.
Or you can come back full circle
to where we were last week
and just run "make hello."
But there's a reason we run make hello,
because executing all of those steps
manually tends to just
get tedious quickly.
And so indeed, what we've
done here is compile our code.
And compiling means going from
source code to machine code.
But today, we revealed that
there's a little more, indeed,
going on underneath the
hood, this "linking"
that I referred to and a
couple of other steps as well.
So it turns out when you compile your
code from source code to machine code,
there's a few more steps
that are ultimately involved.
And when we say "compiling," we
actually mean these four steps.
And we're not going to dwell on
these kinds of low-level details.
But it's perhaps
enlightening just to see
a brief tour of what's going on
when you start with your source code
and end up trying to
produce machine code.
So let's consider this.
This is step 1 that
the computer is doing
for you when you compile your code.
So step 1 takes your
own source code that
looks a little something like this.
And it preprocesses your code,
top to bottom, left to right.
And to preprocess your
code essentially means
that it looks for any lines that
start with a hash symbol, so
#include cs50.h, #include stdio.h.
And what the preprocessing step does is
it's kind of like a find and replace.
It notices, oh, here's a #include line.
Let me go ahead and copy the contents of
that file, cs50.h, into your own code.
Similarly, when I encounter
#include stdio.h, let me,
the so-called preprocessor, open
that file, stdio.h, and copy/paste
the contents of that file so that what's
in the file now looks more like this.
So this is happening automatically.
You never have to do this manually.
But why is there this
preprocessing step?
If you recall our discussion last
week of these lines of code that
tend to go at the top of
your file, does anyone
perceive what the preprocessor
is doing for me and why?
Why do I write code that has these
hash symbols, like #include cs50.h
and #include stdio.h, but
this preprocessor apparently
is automatically replacing those
lines with the actual contents
of those files?
What are these things
here in yellow now?
Yeah, Jack, what do you think?
JACK: Is it defining all the
functions for you to use in your code,
otherwise the computer
wouldn't know what to do?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
It's defining all of
the functions in my code
so that the computer knows what to do.
Because remember that we ran into
that sort of annoying bug last week,
whereby I was trying to
implement a function called,
I think, get_positive_int.
And recall that when I implemented
that function at the bottom of my file,
the compiler was kind of dumb
in that it didn't realize
that it existed because
it was implemented
all the way at the bottom of my file.
So to Jack's point, by putting a mention
of this function, a hint, if you will,
at the very top, it's
like training the compiler
to know in advance that I don't
know how it's implemented yet,
but I know get_string is going to exist.
I don't know how it's implemented yet,
but I know printf is going to exist.
So these header files that we've been
including for the past week essentially
contain all of the prototypes--
that is, all of the hints for all the
functions that exist in the library--
so that your code, when
compiled, know from the top down
that those functions will indeed exist.
So the preprocessor just
saves us the trouble
of having to copy and paste all
of these prototypes, if you will,
all of these hints, ourselves.
So what happens after that step there?
What comes next?
Well, there might very
well be other header files.
There might very well be
other contents in those files.
But for now, let's just assume that
only in there is the prototype.
So now compiling actually
has a more precise meaning
that we'll define today.
To compile your code now
means to take this C code
and to convert it from source code here
to another type of source code here.
Now, this is probably going to be
the most cryptic stuff we ever see.
And this is not code
you need to understand.
But what's on the screen here
is what's called assembly code.
So long story short, there's a lot
of different computers in the world.
And specifically, there's
a lot of different types
of CPUs in the, Central Processing
Units, the brains of a computer.
And a CPU understands certain commands.
And those commands tend to be expressed
in this language called assembly code.
Now, I honestly don't really
understand most of this myself.
It's certainly been a while even since
I thought hard about assembly code.
But if I highlight a few
operative characters here,
notice that there's mention
of main, get_string, printf.
So this is of like a lower-level
implementation of main,
of get_string and printf, in a
different language called assembly.
So you write the C code.
The computer, though, converts it
to a more computer-friendly language
called assembly code.
And decades ago, humans
wrote this stuff.
Humans wrote assembly code.
But nowadays, we have C. And nowadays,
we have languages like Python--
more on that in a few weeks--
that are just more user friendly,
even if it didn't feel
like that this past week.
Assembly code is a little closer to
what the computer itself understands.
But there's still another step.
There's this step called assembling.
And again, all of this is
happening when you simply run
make and, in turn, this command, clang.
To assemble your code means to take this
assembly code and finally convert it
to machine code, 0's and 1's.
So you write the source code.
The compiler assembles
it into assembly code.
Then it compiles it into assembly code.
Then it assembles it into machine code
until we have the actual 0's and 1's.
But there's actually one final step.
Just because your code that you wrote
has been converted into 0's and 1's, it
still needs to be linked in with
the 0's and 1's that CS50 wrote
and that the designers of the
C language wrote years ago
when implementing the
CS50 library in our case,
and the printf function in their case.
So this is to say that when you
have code like this that's not only
including the prototypes for functions
like get_string and printf at the very
top, these lines here in yellow
are what are ultimately converted
into 0's and 1's.
We now have to combine those 0's and
1's with the 0's and 1's from cs50.c,
which the staff wrote some
time ago, and even a file
called stdio.c, which the
designers of C wrote years ago.
And technically, it might be
called something different
underneath the hood.
But there's really three
files that are getting
combined when you write your program.
The first, I just claimed, once
it's preprocessed and compiled
and assembled, it's then in
this form of all 0's and 1's.
Somewhere on the CS50
IDE, there's a whole bunch
of 0's and 1's representing cs50.c.
Somewhere in CS50 IDE,
there's another file
representing the 0's and 1's for stdio.c
So this final fourth step, a.k.a.
linking, just takes all of my 0's
and 1's, all of CS50 0's and 1's, all
of printf's 0's and 1's, and links
them all together into one big blob,
if you will, that collectively
represent your program, hello.
So, my god, like, that's quite
a mouthful and so many steps.
And none of the steps have I described
are really germane to you implementing
Mario's pyramid or cash or
credit, because what we've really
been doing over the past
week is taking all four
of these fairly low-level,
sophisticated concepts and, if you will,
abstracting them away so that we
just refer to this whole process
as compiling.
So we even though, yes,
technically, compiling
is just one of the four steps,
what a programmer typically
does when saying compiling is
they're, just with a wave of the hand,
referring to all of those
lower-level details.
But it is the case that there's multiple
steps happening underneath the hood.
And this is what make and, in
turn, Clang are doing for you,
automating this process of going
from source code to assembly code
to machine code and then linking it
all together with any libraries you
might have used.
So no longer take for
granted what's happening.
Hopefully, that offers
you a glimpse a bit more
of what's actually happening
when you compile your own code.
Well, let me pause there,
because that's quite a mouthful,
and see if there's any questions
on preprocessing, compiling,
or assembling, or linking, a.k.a.
compiling.
And again, we won't
dwell at this low level.
We'll tend to now just abstract this
all away if we can sort of agree
that, OK, yes, there's those steps.
But what's really important is the
whole process, not the minutia.
Sophia?
SOPHIA: I had a question about
with the first step, when
we're replacing all the
information at the top,
is that information
contained within the IDE?
Or where do we--
are there files saved somewhere
in that IDE, like, where
it's getting all this information from?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, really good question.
Where are all these files coming from?
So yes, when you are using
CS50 IDE, or frankly,
if you're using your
own Mac or your own PC,
and you have preinstalled a compiler
into your Mac or PC just like we have
to CS50 IDE, what you get is a
whole bunch of .h files somewhere
on the computer system.
You might also have a whole bunch of
.c files, or compiled versions thereof,
somewhere on the system.
So yes, when you download
and install a compiler,
you are getting all of these
libraries added for you.
And we preinstalled an additional
library called CS50's library that
additionally comes with its own .h
file and its own machine code as well.
So all of those files are
somewhere in CS50 IDE,
or equivalently, in your own Mac
or PC if you're working locally.
And the compiler, Clang,
in this case, just
knows how to find that because one
of the steps involved in installing
your own compiler is making
sure it's configured to know,
per Sophia's question,
where all those files are.
[? Basili? ?] I'm sorry
if I'm mispronouncing it.
[? Basili? ?]
[? BASILI: ?] So whenever
we're compiling hello,
for example, is the compiler also
compiling, for example, CS50?
Or does CS50 already exist in
machine code somewhere beneath?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
really good question too.
So I was kind of skirting
this part of Sophia's question
because technically speaking, probably
cs50.c is not installed on the system.
And technically, stdio.c is probably
not installed in the system.
Why?
It just doesn't need to be.
It would be kind of
inefficient, that is,
slow, if every time you
compiled your own program,
you had to additionally compile
CS50's program, and stdio's program,
and so forth.
So it actually stands to reason
that what computers typically do
is they precompile all of
those library files for you
so that more efficiently
they can just be linked in.
And you don't have to keep
preprocessing, compiling,
and assembling third-party code.
You only perform those steps on your own
code and then link everything together.
And indeed, that's the case.
It's all done in advance.
Iris, question from you.
IRIS: When we replace the
header files with prototypes,
are we only replacing it with
the prototypes that get used?
Or are all the prototypes
technically substituted?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so I was
kind of sweeping that detail
under the rug with my dot, dot, dot.
There's a whole lot of
other stuff in those files.
You're getting the entire
contents of those files,
even if the only thing
you need is the prototype.
But, and this is why I alluded
to the fact too that technically,
there probably isn't a
stdio.c file, because there
would be so much stuff in it.
There's probably not just one
stdio.h file with everything in it.
There's probably some smaller files
that get magically included as well.
But yes, there are many more
lines of code in those files.
But that's OK.
Your compiler is only going to use the
lines that it actually cares about.
Good question.
All right, so with that
said, this past week
undoubtedly was a bit
frustrating in some ways
because you probably ran into problems.
You ran into bugs,
mistakes in your own code.
You probably saw one or more
yellow or red error messages.
And you might have struggled a little
bit just to get your code to compile.
And again, that's normal.
That will go away over time.
But honestly, whenever I write
C, let's say 20% of the time,
I still have a compilation error, let
alone logical errors, in my own code.
So this is just part of the
experience of writing code.
Humans make mistakes
in all forms of life.
And that's ever more true in the
context of code, where again,
per our first two weeks precision
is important as is correctness.
And it's hard sometimes to
achieve both of those goals.
So let's consider now
how you might be more
empowered to debug your own code-- that
is, find problems in your own code.
And this word actually
has some etymology.
This isn't necessarily the first bug.
But perhaps the most famous
bug is this one pictured
here from the research
notebook of Grace Hopper,
a famous computer scientist,
who had discovered
that there were some problems with
the Harvard Mark II computer, a very
famous computer nowadays
that actually lives over soon
in the new engineering
school on campus--
used to live in the Science Center.
The computer was having problems.
And sure enough, when the engineers
took a look inside of this big mainframe
computer, there was actually
a bug, pictured here
and taped to Grace Hopper's notebook.
So this wasn't necessarily the
first use of the term "bug,"
but it is a very well-known example of
an actual bug in an actual computer.
Nowadays, we speak a little more
metaphorically that a bug is just
a mistake in one program.
And we did give you a few tools
last week for troubleshooting bugs.
Help50 allows you to better understand
some of the cryptic error messages.
And that's just because the
staff wrote this program that
analyzed the problem
you're having, and we try
to translate it to just
more human-friendly speak.
We saw a tool called style50, which
helps you not with your correctness,
but just with the
aesthetics of your code,
helping you better indent things
and add white space-- that
is, blank lines or space characters--
so it's a little more user
friendly to the human to read.
And then check50, which,
of course, the staff
write so that we can give
you immediate feedback on
whether or not your code is correct
per the problem sets or the lab
specification.
But there's some other tools that
you should have in your toolkit.
And we'll give those to you today.
And one, frankly, is this universal
debugging tool just called,
in the context of C, printf.
So printf, of course,
is just this function
that prints stuff out onto the screen.
But that in and of itself is
a wonderfully powerful tool
via which you can chase
down problems in your code.
And even after we leave C
in a few weeks and introduce
Python and other languages, almost
every programming language out there
has some form of printf.
Maybe it's called print.
Maybe it's called say,
as it was in Scratch,
but some ability to display information
or present information to a human.
So let's try to use this
primitive, this notion of print f,
to chase down a bug in one's code.
So let me go ahead and
deliberately write a buggy program.
I'm going to even call
the file buggy0.c.
And at the top of this file, I'm going
to go ahead and #include stdio.h.
No need for the CS50
library for this one.
And then I'm going to do int
main(void), which we saw last week,
and we'll explain in more detail today.
And then I'm going to
give myself a quick loop.
I just want to go ahead and print
out, oh, I don't know, like,
10 hashes on the screen.
So I want to print a vertical
column, kind of like one
of those screenshots from Super
Mario Bros., not a pyramid,
just a single column of
hashes, and 10 of them.
So I'm going to do
something like, int i = 0,
because I feel like I learned
in class that I generally
should start counting from 0.
Then I'm going to have my
condition in this for loop.
And I want to do this 10 times.
I'm going to do it less
than or equal to 10.
Then I'm going to go ahead
and have my increment,
which quite simply can
be expressed as i++.
And then inside this loop, I'm just
going to go ahead and print out
a single hash followed by a new line.
I'm going to save the program.
I'm going to compile it with
clang -o buggy0 buggy0--
I mean, no.
You don't have to use
Clang manually in this way.
It's a lot simpler to
just abstract that away--
that's not a command--
to abstract that away
and run make buggy0.
And make will take care of the
process of invoking Clang for you.
I'm going to go ahead and run it.
Seems to be compiling successfully,
so no need for help50.
It's already pretty well styled.
In fact, if I run style50 on this
buggy0, I don't have any comments yet.
But at least it looks
very nicely indented.
So I think I'm OK with that.
But let me add that comment
and do "Print 10 hashes" just
to remind myself of my goal.
And now let me go ahead and
run this, ./buggy0, Enter.
And I see, OK, good.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
8, 9, 10, 11, I think.
All right, so it's a stupid bug.
And maybe it's jumped out
obviously to some of you.
But maybe it's a little more
subtle to others of you.
But where do you begin?
Suppose I were to run check50.
And check50 were to say, nope, you
printed out 11 hashes instead of 10.
But my code looks right to
me, at least at first glance.
Well, how can I go about
debugging this or solving this?
Well, again, printf is your friend.
If you want to understand
more about your own program,
use printf to temporarily print
more information to the screen,
not that we want in the final version,
not that your TF wants to see,
but that you, the programmer,
can temporarily see.
So before I print this
hash, let me print something
a little more pedantic like this--
"i is now %i backslash n."
So I literally want to know, just for my
own mental math, what is the value of i
at this point before I print that hash?
Now I'm going to go ahead
and paste in the value of i.
So I'm using %i as a placeholder.
I'm plugging in the
value of the variable i.
I'm going to save my code now.
I'm going to recompile
it with make buggy0.
And I'm going to rerun it now.
And let me go ahead and
increase the size of my window
just so we can focus now on the output.
And I'm going to go ahead
and ./buggy0, Enter.
OK, so now I see not
only my output, but also
commingled with that output, some
diagnostic output, if you will,
some debugging output.
And it's just more pedantically
telling me, "i is now 0," "i is now 1,"
"i is now 2," dot, dot, dot,
"i is now 9," "i is now 10."
OK, I don't hate the fact that i is 10.
But I'm not loving the fact that if
I started at 0 and printed a hash,
and I'm hitting 10 and printing
another hash, well, obviously,
there's my problem.
So it might not have been
all that much more obvious
than looking at the code itself.
But by using printf, you
can just be a lot more clear
to yourself what's going on.
So if now I see, OK, well, if I
start at 0, I have to go up to 10.
I could change my code to
do this to be less than 10.
I could leave that alone
and go from 1 through 10.
But again, programmer convention
would be to go from 0 up to 10.
So I think I'm good now.
And in fact, now I'll go ahead
and recompile this, make buggy0.
Let me go ahead and increase the size
of the window again just so I can
temporarily see this and ./buggy0.
OK, I start now at 0,
1, 2, dot, dot, dot.
Now I stop at 9.
And that, of course, gives me 10 hashes.
So again, I don't need
this in the final output.
And I'm to go ahead and delete this now.
It's temporary output.
But again, having those
instincts-- if you don't quite
understand why your code is
compiling but not running properly,
and you want to better see what
the computer is clearly seeing,
its mind eye, use printf
to just tell yourself
what the value of some variable or
variables are anywhere in your code
that you want to see
a little more detail.
All right, let me
pause for just a moment
to see if there's any questions on
this technique of just using printf
to begin to debug your code and
to see the values of variables
in a way that's a little more explicit.
No?
All right.
Well, let me propose an even more
powerful tool that admittedly
takes a little getting used to.
But this is kind of
one of those lessons,
trust me, if you will, that if you
spend a few more minutes, maybe even
an hour or so this week,
learning the following tool,
you will save yourself
hours, plural, maybe even
tens of hours over the
course of the next many weeks
because this tool can help you truly
see what's going on inside of your code.
So this tool we're going to add to
the list today is called debug50.
And while this one does end with
50, implying that it's a CS50 tool,
it's built on top of an industry
standard tool known as GDB, the GNU
DeBugger, that's a standard tool that
a lot of different computer systems
use to provide you with the ability to
debug your code in a more sophisticated
way than just using printf alone.
So let's go ahead and do this.
Let me go back to the buggy
version of this program
which, recall, had me going from 0
through 10, which was too many steps.
A moment ago, I proposed that we just
use printf to see the value of i.
But frankly, the bigger our
programs get, the more complicated
they get, the more output they
need to have on the screen.
It's just going to
get very messy quickly
if you're printing out stuff
that shouldn't be there, right?
Think back to Mario.
Mario's pyramid is this
sort of graphical output.
And it would very quickly get ugly and
kind of hard to understand your pyramid
if you're comingling that pyramid
with actual textual output from printf
as well.
So debug50, and in turn a
debugger in any language,
is a tool that allows you to
run your code step by step
and look inside of variables and other
pieces of memory inside of the computer
while your program is running.
Right now, pretty much every program
we run takes a split second to run.
That's way too fast for me,
the human, to wrap my mind
around what's going on step by step.
A debugger allows you
to run your program,
but much more slowly, step by step,
so you can see what's going on.
So I'm going to go ahead
now and run debug50 ./hello.
No, sorry, debug50 ./buggy0.
So I write debug50
first, a space, and then
dot slash and the name
of the program that's
already compiled that I want to debug.
So I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
And notice that, oh, it was smart.
It noticed that I changed my code.
And I did a moment ago.
I reverted it back to the buggy version.
So let me fix this-- make buggy0.
All right, no errors.
Now let me go ahead
and run debug50 again.
And if you haven't noticed this already,
sometimes I seem to type crazy fast.
I'm not necessarily typing that fast.
I'm going through my
history in CS50 IDE.
Using your arrow keys, Up
and Down, you can scroll back
in time for all of the commands
you've typed over the past few minutes
or hours or even days.
And this will just start
to save you keystrokes.
So I'm going to go ahead and hit Up.
And now I don't have to bother
typing this whole command again.
It's a helpful way to just save time.
I'm going to go head
in now and hit Enter.
And now notice this error message--
I haven't set any breakpoints.
"Set at least one breakpoint by clicking
to the left of a line number and then
re-run debug50!"
Well, what's going on here?
Well, debug50 needs me to tell the
computer in advance at what line
I want to break into and
step through step by step.
So, I can do that.
I'm going to go over to the side
of the file here, as it says.
And you know what?
The first interesting line
is this one here, line 6.
So I clicked in the so-called gutter,
the left-hand side of the screen,
on line 6.
And that automatically put a
red dot there, like a stop sign.
Now, one last time, I'm going to go
ahead and run debug50 ./buggy0 and hit
Enter.
And now notice this fancy new panel
opens up on the right-hand side.
And it's going to look a
little cryptic at first.
But let's consider what
has changed on the screen.
Notice now that highlighted in this
sort of off-yellow color is line 6.
And that's because what debug50 is
doing is it's running my program,
but it has paused execution on line 6.
So it's done everything
from line 1 through 5,
but now it's waiting for me on line 6.
And what's interesting
over here is this-- let
me zoom in on this window over here.
And there's a lot going
on here, admittedly.
But let's focus for just a moment not
on Watch Expressions, not on Call Stack,
but only on Local Variables.
And notice, I have a variable
called i whose initial value is 0,
and it's of type int.
Now, this is kind of interesting because
watch what I can do via these icons
up here.
I can click on this Step Over line
and start to step through my code line
by line.
So let me go ahead and zoom out.
Let me go ahead and click Step Over.
And watch what happens to
the yellow highlighting.
It moves down to the next line.
But notice, if I zoom in again up
here, the value of i has not changed.
Now let me go ahead and step over again.
And notice the yellow
highlighting doubles back.
That makes sense because I'm in a loop.
So it should be going back
and forth, back and forth.
But what next happens in a loop?
Every time you go back to
the beginning of the loop,
remember that your incrementation
happens, like the i++.
So watch now closely in
the top right-hand corner,
when I Step Over now, notice that
the value of i in my debugger
has just been changed to 1.
So I didn't have to use printf.
I didn't have to mess up
the output of my screen.
I can literally see in this
GUI, this Graphical User
Interface on the right-hand
side, what the value of i is.
Now if I just start clicking
a little more quickly,
notice that as the loop is executing,
again and again, the value of i
keeps getting updated.
And you know what?
I bet, even though we started
at 0, if I do this enough times,
I will see that the
value is 10 now, thereby
giving me another printf at the bottom,
thereby explaining the 11 total hashes
that I saw.
So I haven't gotten any
new information here.
But notice I've gotten
unperturbed information.
I've not messily and sloppily printed
out all of these printf statements
on the screen.
I'm just kind of watching
a little more methodically
what's happening to the state of my
variable over on the top right there.
All right, let me pause here too to
see if there's any questions on what
this debugger does.
Again, you compile your code.
You run debug50 on your code, but only
after setting a so-called breakpoint,
where you decide in advance where do you
want to pause execution of your code.
Even though here I did it pretty
much at the beginning of my program,
for bigger programs,
it's going to be super
convenient to be able to pause
halfway through your code
and not have to go
through the whole thing.
Peter, question.
PETER: About the debugger, what's
the difference between Step Over
and Step Into and Step Out and--
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
Let me come back to
that in just a moment,
because we'll do one other example
where Step Into and Step Out actually
are germane.
But before we do that.
Any other questions about debug50
before we reveal what Step Into and Step
Over do for us as well?
Oh, all right.
Well, let's take Peter's
question right there.
Let me go ahead now and
get out of the debugger.
And honestly, I don't see
an obvious way to get out
of the debugger at the moment.
But Control-C is your
new friend today too.
Pretty much any time you
lose control of a program
because the debugger's running,
and you've lost interest in it.
Or maybe last week, you
wrote a program that
has an infinite loop that just
keeps going and going and going,
Control-C will break
out of that program.
But let's now write quickly
another program that, this time,
has a second function.
And we'll see one other
feature of the debugger today.
I'm going to go ahead and create
a new file now called buggy1.c.
Again, it's going to
be deliberately flawed.
But I'm going to first going to go
ahead and #include cs50.h this time.
And I'm going to #include stdio.h.
I'm going to do int main void.
And I'm going to go ahead and
do the following-- give myself
a variable called i.
And I'm going to try to get
a negative int by calling
a function called get_negative_int.
And then quite simply, I'm going to
print out this value, "%i backslash n",
i, semicolon.
Now, there's only one problem--
get_negative_int does not exist.
So like last week, where we
implemented get_positive_int,
this week, I'll implement
get_negative_int.
But I'm going to do it
incorrectly at first.
Now, get_negative_int, as the name
implies, needs to return an integer.
And even though we only spent
brief time on this last week,
recall that you can specify
the output of a function,
a custom function that you wrote,
by putting its so-called return
value first on this line.
And then you can put the name of
the function, like get_negative_int,
and then in parentheses, you can
put the input to the function.
But if it takes no input, you can
literally write the word "void,"
which is a term of art that
just means, nothing goes here.
I'm going to go ahead now and
implement get_negative_int.
And frankly, I think it's going
to be pretty similar to last week.
But my memory is a little hazy.
So again, it will be
deliberately flawed.
But I'm going to go ahead and
declare a variable called n.
Then I'm going to do the following--
I'm going to set n equal to get_int.
And I'm just going to explicitly ask
the user for "Negative integer" followed
by a space.
And then I'm going to keep doing
this while n is less than 0.
And then at the very last
line, I'm going to return n.
So again, I claim that
this function will
get me a negative int from the user.
And it's going to keep doing it again
and again until the user cooperates.
However, there is a bug.
And there's a couple of bugs, in fact.
Right now, let me go ahead and make
a deliberate mistake-- make buggy1,
Enter.
And I see a whole bunch of errors here.
I could use help50 on this.
But based on last week, does anyone
recall what the error here might be?
"Error-- implicit declaration
of function 'get_negative_int'
is invalid in C99."
So I don't know all of that, but
implicit declaration of function
is something you're
going to start to see
more often if you make this mistake.
Anyone recall what this means and what
the fix is without resorting to help50?
Yeah, Jasmine, what do you think?
JASMINE: So basically,
since you declared it
after you already used
it in your code, it
doesn't know what to read that
as when it's processing it.
So you have to move the first line
above when you actually start the code.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
And this is the only time I
will claim that copy/paste
is acceptable and encouraged.
I'm going to copy the very first
line only of that function.
And as Jasmine proposed, I'm going to
paste it at the very top of the file,
thereby giving myself a hint
otherwise known as a prototype.
So I'll even label it as such to
remind myself why it's there--
prototype of that function.
And here, I'm going to go ahead and
"Get negative integer from user."
And then this function
is as left as written.
So I now have this
prototype at the very top
of my file, which I think will
indeed get rid of this error.
Let me go to make buggy1 again.
Now I see that indeed compiled OK.
But when I run it now, ./buggy1--
let me go ahead and input a
negative integer, negative 1.
Hm.
Negative 2, negative 3--
I feel like the function should be
happy with this, and it's obviously not.
So there's a bug.
I'm going to go ahead and hit
Control-C to get out of my program
because otherwise, it would
run potentially forever.
And now I'm going to use debug50.
But debug50 just got really
interesting, to Peter's question
earlier, because now I have
things I can step into.
I'm not writing all of my code in main.
There's this other function
now called get_negative_int.
So let's see what happens now.
Let me go ahead and set a breakpoint
on the first interesting line of code,
line 10.
And it's interesting only in
the sense that everything else
is kind of boilerplate at this point.
You just have to do it to
get your program started.
I'm going to now go down here.
And I'm going to do debug50 ./buggy1.
And in a moment, it's going
to open up that sidebar.
And I'm going to focus now
not only on local variables--
like I did before, notice that i is
again equal to 0 here by default.
But I'm also going to reveal
this option here, Call Stack.
So Call Stack is a fancy way of
referring to all of the functions
that your program at this point in time
has executed and not yet returned from.
So right now, there's only
one thing on the call stack
because the only function that is
currently executing is, of course,
main, because why?
I set a breakpoint at line 10, which
is, by definition, inside of main.
But to Peter's question earlier,
I feel like lines 10 and 11--
frankly, they look
pretty correct, right?
It's hard at this point
to have screwed up
lines 10 and 11 except syntactically,
because I'm getting a negative int.
I'm storing it in i, and then
I'm printing out the value of i
on those two lines.
But what if instead, I'm
curious about get_negative_int?
I feel like the bug--
logically, it's got
to be in there because that's
the harder code that I wrote.
Notice this time, instead
of clicking Step Over,
let me go ahead and click on Step
Into, which is one of the buttons Peter
alluded to.
And when I click Step Into, notice that
you sort of go down the rabbit hole.
And debug50 jumps into the
function get_negative_int,
and it focuses on the first
interesting line of code.
So do, in and of itself,
really isn't that interesting.
Int n isn't that
interesting because it's not
assigning a value to it even yet.
The first juicy line of
code seems to be line 19.
And that's why the debugger
has jumped to that line.
Now, n = get_int feels pretty correct.
It's hard to misuse get_int.
But notice now on the right-hand
side what has happened.
Under Call Stack, you now see
two things, not only main,
but also get_negative_int in a stack.
It's like a stack of
trays in a cafeteria.
The first tray at the
bottom is like main.
The second tray on the stack in the
cafeteria is now get_negative_int.
And what's cool about this is
that notice that right now, I
can see my local variables, n.
And that's indeed the variable I used.
So I no longer see i.
I see n because I'm into the
get_negative_int function.
And now if I keep clicking
Step Over again and again
after typing in a number.
Let me type in negative 1 here.
Now notice on the top right of the
screen, you can see in the debugger
that n equals negative 1.
I'm going to now go ahead
and click Step Over.
And I think I'm going
to end up in line 22.
If the human has typed in a
negative integer like negative 1,
obviously, that's negative.
Let's proceed to line 22.
But watch what happens
when I click Step Over.
It actually seems to be going back
to the do loop again and again
and again, as it will, I keep
providing negative integers.
So my logic then should be,
well, OK, if n is negative 1,
but my loop is still running, what
should your logical takeaway here be?
If n is negative 1, and that is
by definition a negative integer,
but my loop is still running, what
could be your diagnostic conclusion
if the debugger is essentially revealing
this hint to you? n is negative 1,
but the loop is still going.
Omar, what would you conclude?
OMAR: Either the condition is wrong,
or maybe some sort of Boolean logic
could be flawed.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So obviously, either
the condition is wrong,
or there's something wrong
with my Boolean logic.
And Boolean logic just
refers to true or false.
So somewhere, I'm saying
true instead of false,
or I'm saying false instead of true.
And frankly, the only
place where I have code
that's going to make this loop go again
and again must logically be on line 21.
So even if you're not quite sure how
to fix it yet, just by deduction,
you should realize that, OK,
negative 1 is what's in the variable.
But that's not good enough.
The loop is still going.
I must have screwed up the loop.
And indeed, let me just now call it out.
Line 21 is indeed the source of the bug.
So we've isolated it.
Out of 23 lines, we've at
least found the one line
where I know the solution has to be.
What's the solution?
How do I fix the logic now thanks to the
debugger having led me down this road?
How do I fix line 21 here?
What's the fix?
What do you propose?
Yeah, Jacob?
JACOB: You would have to change
it from while n is less than 0
to while n is greater than 0.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So instead of n less than 0, I
want to say n greater than 0.
And I think-- slight
clarification, I think
I want to include 0 here
because 0 is not negative.
And if I want a negative int,
I think what I'm probably
going to want to say is while n
is greater than or equal to 0,
keep doing the loop.
So I very understandably sort
of just inverted the logic.
No big deal.
I'm thinking negatives,
and I did less than.
But the fix is easy.
The point is the debugger
led you to this point.
Now, those of you who have
programmed before probably
saw the bug jumping out at you.
Those of you who haven't programmed
before, probably with some time,
would have figured out what the
bug was, because out of 23 lines,
it's got to be one of those.
But as our programs
get more sophisticated,
and we start writing more lines of
code, debug50 and debuggers in general
will be your friend.
And I realize that this is easier
said than done because at first,
when using a debugger, you're
going to feel like, ah, I'm
just going to use printf.
Ah, I'm just going to
fight through this.
Because there's a bit
of a learning curve,
you will gain back that
time and more by just
using a debugger as your first instinct
when chasing down problems like this.
All right, so that's it for debug50,
a new tool in your toolkit in addition
to printf.
But debug50 is hands down
the more powerful of the two.
Now, some of you have wondered
over the past couple of weeks
why there's this little
rubber duck here.
And there actually is
a reason for this too.
And there's one final debugging
technique that, in all seriousness,
we'll introduce you today to
known as rubber duck debugging.
And you can google this.
There's a whole Wikipedia
article about it.
And this is kind of a thing in computer
science circles for computer scientists
or programmers to have
rubber ducks on their desk.
And the point here is
that sometimes, when
trying to understand what
is wrong in your code,
it helps to just talk it through.
And in an ideal world, we would just
talk to our colleague or our partner
on some project.
And just in hearing yourself
vocalize what it is your code
is supposed to do, very often, that
proverbial light bulb goes off.
And you're like, oh, wait a
minute, never mind, I got it,
just because you heard yourself
speaking illogically when
you intended something actual logical.
Now, we don't often all have colleagues
or partners or friends with whom we're
working on a project with.
And we don't often have
family members or friends
who want to hear about
our code of all things.
And so a wonderful proxy
for that conversant partner
would be literally a rubber duck.
And so here in healthier times, we
would be giving all of you rubber ducks.
Here on stage, we brought a
larger one for us all to share.
If you've noticed in some
of the wide shots on camera,
there's a duck who's been
watching this whole time.
So that any time I screw
up, I literally have
someone I can sort of talk
to nonverbally, in this case.
But we can't emphasize enough that
in addition to printf, in addition to
the more sophisticated debug50,
talking through your problems with code
is a wonderfully valuable thing.
And if your friends or
family are willing to hear
about some low-level code you're
writing and some bug you're
trying to solve, great.
But in the absence of that, talk
to a stuffed animal in your room.
Talk to an actual rubber
duck if you have one.
Talk even aloud or think aloud.
It's just a wonderful
compelling habit to get
into because just in hearing yourself
vocalize what you think is logical
will the illogical very often
jump out at you instead.
All right, so with that
said, that's been a lot.
Let's go ahead here and
take a five-minute break,
give everyone a bit of a breather.
And when we come back,
we'll take a look now
at some of the more
powerful features of C
now that we can trust that we
can solve any problems with all
of these new tools.
So we'll be back in five.
All right, we are back.
So let's take a look underneath
the hood, so to speak,
of a computer, because
as fancy as these devices
are and as powerful
as they seem, they're
relatively simple in their capabilities
and what they can actually do.
And let's reveal as much by way
of last week's discussion of type.
So recall that C supports
different data types.
So we saw char, and string,
and int, and so forth.
So to recap, we had all of these.
Well, it turns out that
each of these data types
is defined on a typical computer system
as taking up a fixed amount of space.
And it depends on the computer,
whether it's Mac or PC, or old or new,
just how much space is used
typically by these data types.
But on CS50 IDE, the sizes of all
of these types are as follows--
a bool, true or false, uses just 1 byte.
Now, that's actually a little wasteful
because 1 byte is 8 bits, and gosh,
for a bool, you should only need 1 bit.
You can't work at the
single-bit level easily in C.
And so we just typically
spend 1 whole byte on a bool.
Char is going to be 1 byte as well.
And that might sound familiar, because
last week when we talked about ASCII,
we proposed that the total
number of possible characters
you can represent with a char
was 256 because of 8 bits and 2
to the eighth power.
So one char is 1 byte.
And that's fixed in C, no matter what.
Then there were all of
these other data types.
There was float, which is a real
number with a decimal point.
That happens to use 4 bytes.
A double is also a real
number with a decimal point,
but it uses 8 bytes, which
gives you even more precision.
You can have more significant digits
after the decimal point, for instance.
Ints, we've used a bunch.
Those are 4 bytes, typically.
A long is twice as big,
and that just allows
you to represent an even bigger number.
And some of you might have done
that exactly on credit when
storing a whole credit card number.
Strings, for now, are a
variable number of bytes.
It could be a short string of text, a
long string of text, a whole paragraph.
So that's going to vary.
So we'll come back to this
notion of string next time.
But today, focus on just these
primitive types, if you will.
And here is a picture of what
is inside of your computer.
So this is a piece of memory
or RAM, Random Access Memory.
And it might be a little smaller.
It might be a little bigger
depending on whether it's a laptop,
or desktop, or phone, or the like.
But it's in memory,
or RAM, that programs
are stored while they're running.
And it's where files are
stored when they are open.
So typically, if you save,
install programs, or save files,
those are saved on what's generally
called your hard drive, or hard disk,
or solid-state disk, or CD,
or some other physical medium.
And that, the [INAUDIBLE] of which is
that they don't require electricity
to store your data long term.
RAM is different.
It's volatile, so to speak.
But it's much faster than a hard
disk or a solid-state disk, even.
It's much faster because
it's purely electronic.
And indeed, there are no moving parts.
It's purely electronic,
as pictured here.
And so with RAM, you have the ability
to open files and run programs
more quickly because when you
double-click a program to run it,
or you open a file in
order to view or edit it,
it's stored temporarily in RAM.
And long story short, if your
laptop battery has ever died,
or your computer's gotten
unplugged, or your phone dies,
the reason that you and I tend to
lose data, the paragraph that you just
wrote in the essay that
you hadn't yet saved,
is because RAM, memory, is volatile.
That is, it requires electricity
to continue powering it.
But for our purposes, we're
only going to focus on RAM,
not so much long-term disk
space yet, because when
you're running a program in C,
it is indeed, by definition,
running in your computer's memory.
But the funny thing about
something as simple as this picture
is that each of these black
rectangles is kind of a chip.
And in those chips are stored all
of the 0's and 1's, the little
switches that we alluded to in week 0.
So let's focus on and just zoom
in on just one of these chips.
Now, it stands to reason that I don't
know how big this stick of RAM is.
Maybe it's 1 gigabyte, a billion bytes.
Maybe it's 4 gigabytes.
Maybe it's even smaller or bigger.
There's some number of bytes
represented physically by this hardware.
So if we zoom in further, let
me propose that, all right,
I don't know how many bytes are here.
But if there's some number of bytes,
whether it's a billion or 2 billion,
or fewer or more, it
stands to reason that we
could just number all of these bytes.
We could sort of think of this
physical device, this memory,
as just being a grid, top
to bottom, left to right.
And each of the squares I've just
overlaid on this physical device
might represent an individual byte.
And again, in reality,
maybe there's more of them.
Maybe there's fewer of them.
But it stands to reason, no
matter how many there are,
we can think of each of
these as having a location.
Like, this is the first byte, second
byte, third byte, and so forth.
Well, what does it mean, then,
for a char to take up 1 byte?
That means that if your computer's
memory is running a program maybe
that you wrote or I wrote that's
using a char variable somewhere in it,
the char you're storing in
that variable may very well
be stored in the top left-hand corner
physically of this piece of RAM.
Maybe it's there.
Maybe it's elsewhere.
But it's just one physical square.
If you're storing something like
an int, which takes up 4 bytes,
well, that frankly might take up
all four squares along the top there
or somewhere else.
If you're using a long, that's going
to take up twice as much space.
So representing an even bigger
number in your computer's memory
is going to require that you
use all of the 0's and 1's
comprising these 8 bytes instead.
but let's now move away
from physical hardware.
Let's abstract it away, if you will, and
just now start to think of our memory
as just this grid.
And technically, it's not a
two-dimensional structure.
I could just as easily draw all
of these bytes from left to right.
I could just fit fewer
of them on the screen.
So we'll take the physical
metaphor a bit further
and just think of our computer's memory
as this grid, this grid of bytes.
And those bytes are each 8 bits.
Those bits are just 0's and 1's.
So what we've really done is zoom in
metaphorically on our computer's memory
to start thinking about where things
are going to end up in memory when you
double-click on a program on
your Mac or PC or, in CS50 IDE,
when you do ./hello or
./buggy0 or ./buggy1,
it's these bytes in your computer's
memory that are filled with all
of your variables' values.
So let's consider an example here.
Suppose I had written some code that
involved declaring three scores.
Maybe it's a class that's
got, like, three tests.
And you want to average the student's
grade across all three of those tests.
Well, let's go ahead and write a
quick program that does exactly this.
In CS50 IDE, I'm going to create
a program called scores.c.
And in scores.c, I'm going to
go ahead and #include stdio.h.
I'm going to then do my
int main(void) as usual.
And then inside of here, I'm
going to keep it very simple.
I'm going to give myself
one int called score1.
And just to be a little
playful, I'm going
to set it equal to 72, like last week.
I'm going to give myself
a second score and set
it equal to 73, and then a third
score whose value is going to be 33.
And then let me go ahead and print
out the average of those three values
by plugging in a placeholder
for floating point value, right?
If you add three integers
together and divide them by 3,
I may very well get a fraction or
a real number with a decimal point.
So I'm going to use %f instead of
%i because I don't want to truncate
someone's grade.
Otherwise, if they have, like, a 99.9%,
they're not being rounded up to 100%.
They're going to get the 99% because of
truncation, as we discussed last week.
So how do I do now the
math of an average?
Well, it's pretty
straightforward-- score1
plus score2 plus score3
in parentheses, just
like in math, divided by 3, semicolon.
Let me save that file.
Let me do make scores at the bottom.
Again, we're not going
to use Clang manually.
No need to, because it's
a lot easier to run make.
But I did mess up here.
"Format specifies type 'double',
but the argument has type 'int'."
So I don't quite understand that.
But it's drawing my attention to the
%f and the fact that my math looks like
this.
So any thoughts here?
I don't think printf is going to
help me here because the bug is
within the printf line.
I don't think that debug50 is going to
really help me here because I already
know what line of code the bug is in.
This feels like an opportunity
to talk to the physical duck
or some other inanimate object.
Or we can perhaps think about what
errors we ran into even last week.
[? Arpan, ?] what do you think?
[? ARPAN: ?] I think it's
telling you this because it's
receiving in all the
values are integer type,
but you are telling it to be in float.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
So score1, score2,
score3 are all integers,
and the number 3 is
literally an integer.
And so this time, the compiler is
smart enough to realize, wait a minute,
you're trying to coerce an integer
result into a floating point value,
but you haven't done any floating
point arithmetic, if you will.
So you know what?
There's a few ways to fix this.
Last week, recall we proposed
that you could use a cast,
and you could explicitly cast one
or more of those values to a float.
So I could do this, for instance.
Or I could cast all of these to
floats or one of these to floats.
There's many different possibilities.
But frankly, the simplest fix is
just to divide, for instance, by 3.0.
I can avoid some of the headaches of
casting from one to another by just
making sure that there's
at least one floating point
value involved in this arithmetic.
So now let me recompile scores.
This time, it compiles OK.
Let me do ./scores, and voila, my
average isn't so high, 59.333333.
All right, so what is
actually going on inside
of the computer irrespective of the
floating point arithmetic, which was,
again, a topic of last week?
Well, let's consider these three
variables, score1, score2, score3--
where are they actually being
stored in the computer's memory?
Well, let's consider that grid again.
And again, I'm going to start
at top left for convenience.
But technically speaking--
we'll see this down the road--
your computer's memory is
just like this big canvas.
And values can end up
in all different places.
But for today, we'll keep it clean.
The first variable, score1,
I claim is going to be here,
top left, for simplicity.
But what's important
about where score1--
that is, 72-- is being stored, is
it's taking up four of these boxes.
Each of these boxes,
recall, represents 1 byte.
And an integer, recall,
in CS50 IDE is 4 bytes.
Therefore, I have used 4 bytes of
space to represent the number 72.
The number 73 in score2
similarly is going
to take up four boxes, as is score3
going to take up four boxes as well.
But what's really going on
underneath the hood here?
Well, if each of these
squares represents a byte,
and each of those bytes is 8
bits, and a bit is just a 0 or 1,
what's really going on underneath
the hood is something like this.
Somehow, this electronic
memory is storing
electricity in just the right
way so that it's storing
this pattern of 0's and 1's, a.k.a.
72 in decimal, this pattern
of 0's and 1's, a.k.a.
73 in decimal, this pattern
33 in decimal.
But again, we don't have to
keep thinking about or dwelling
on the binary level.
But this is only to say that
everything we've discussed thus far
is coming together now
in this one picture
because a computer is just
storing these patterns for us,
and we are allocating space
now thanks to our programming
language via code like this.
But this code, correct though it may
be, indeed 59.333333 and so forth
was my average if my test
scores were 72, 73, and 33.
But I feel like there's an
opportunity for better design here.
So not just correctness, not
just style, recall that design
is this other metric of code quality.
And it's a little more
subjective, and it's
a little more subject to
debate among reasonable people.
But I don't really love what I
was doing with this naming scheme.
And in fact, if we look
at the code, there really
wasn't much more to my program
than these three lines.
I worry this program isn't
particularly well designed.
What rubs you the wrong way, perhaps,
about those three lines of code?
What could be better?
And even if you don't know
the solution, especially
if you've never programmed before, what
kind of smells about those three lines?
This is actually a term of art.
"Code smell" is like something--
not loving that for some reason.
If you can't put your finger on
it, it's not the best design.
The code smells.
What's smelly, if you will,
about score1, score2, score3?
Ryan, what do you think?
RYAN: If you're doing
an average calculation,
you don't need to add them
up all together in the code.
You can add them up beforehand
and store it as one variable.
DAVID MALAN: Absolutely.
If I'm computing the average, I
don't need to keep all three around.
I can just keep a sum and then divide
the whole sum by the total number.
I like that, that instinct.
What else might you not like
about the design of this code now?
Score1, score2, score3.
Might there be opportunity
still for improvement?
I feel like any time you start
to see this repetition, maybe.
Andrew, your thoughts?
ANDREW: Not hard code the
three scores together?
DAVID MALAN: OK, so not
hard code the three scores.
And what would you do instead?
ANDREW: Maybe take an
input, or I would--
yeah, I wouldn't write
out the scores themselves.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
another good instinct.
It's kind of stupid that I've written
a program, compiled a program,
that only computes the average for some
student who literally got those three
test scores and no others.
Like, there's no dynamism here.
Moreover, it's a little
lazy too that I called
my variables score1, score2, score3.
I mean, where does it end after that?
If I want to have a fourth
test next semester, now
I have to go and have score4.
If I've got a fifth, score5.
That starts to be reminiscent
of last week's copy/paste, which
really wasn't the best practice.
And so let me propose
that we clean this up.
And it turns out we can
clean this up by way
of another topic, another
feature of C that's
also present in other
languages, known as arrays.
And if you happened to use
something called a list in Scratch,
very similar in spirit
to Scratch's lists.
But we didn't see those in
lecture that first week.
An array in C, as in other
languages, is a sequence
of values stored in memory
back to back to back,
a sequence of contiguous values,
so to speak, back to back to back.
So in that sense, it's like a
list of values from left to right
if we use the metaphor of the
picture we've been drawing.
So how might this be germane here?
Well, it turns out that if you want
to store a whole bunch of values,
but they're all kind of interrelated,
like they're all scores,
you don't have to resort to this sort
of lazy, score1, score2, score3, score4,
score5, up to score99, depending
on how many scores there are.
Why don't you just call all
of those numbers scores,
but use a slightly different syntax?
And that syntax gives you access
to what are called arrays.
So the syntax here on
the screen is an example
of declaring space for
three integers all at once
and collectively referring to
all of them as the word "scores."
So there's no more scores 1, 2, and 3.
All three of those scores are
in a variable called "scores."
And what's new here is the
square brackets, inside of which
is a number that literally
connotes how many integers do you
want to store under the name "scores."
So what does this allow me to do?
It allows me still to define
three integers in that array.
So this array is going
to be a chunk of memory
back to back to back
that I can put values in.
And the way I put those values is
going to look syntactically like this.
I still use numbers, but now
I'm using a new notation.
And it's similar to what
I resorted to before,
but it's a little more
generalized now and dynamic.
Now if I want to update the
very first score in that array,
I literally write the name
of the variable scores,
bracket[0] and then assign it the value.
If I want to get at the
second score, I do scores[1].
If I want the third
score, it's scores[2].
And the only thing that's a little
weird and takes some getting used to is
the fact that we are
"zero-indexing" our arrays.
So in past examples, like
for loops and while loops,
I've sort of said, eh, it's
a convention in programming
to start counting from 0.
When it comes to arrays,
which are contiguous
sequences of values in a computer's
memory, they have to start at 0.
So otherwise, if you
don't start counting at 0,
you're literally going to be wasting
space by overlooking one value.
So now if we were to rename
things on the screen,
instead of calling these three
rectangles score1, score2, score3,
they're all called scores.
But if you want to refer
specifically to the first one,
you use this fancy bracket notation, and
the second one, this bracket notation,
and the third one,
this bracket notation.
But notice the dichotomy.
When declaring the array, when creating
the array, saying, give me three ints,
you use [3] where [3] is
the total number of values.
When you index into the array--
that is, when you go to a specific
location in that chunk of memory--
you similarly use numbers.
But now those are referring to their
relative positions, position 0,
position 1, position 2.
This is the total number of spaces.
This is the specific space
first, second, and third.
All right, so pictorially,
nothing has changed,
just our nomenclature really has.
So let me go ahead and start
to improve this program,
taking in the advice that was offered
too on how we can improve the design
and get rid of the smelliness of it.
Let me take the first--
let me take the easiest
of these approaches
first by just getting rid of
these three separate variables
and instead giving me one variable
called scores, an array of size 3.
And then I don't need to
declare score1, score2.
Again, that's all going away.
That's all going away.
Now if I want to initialize that
array with these three values,
I say scores[0].
And down here, I say scores[1].
And down here, I say scores[2].
So I've added one line of code.
But notice the dynamism now.
If I want to have a fourth one,
I can just allocate here and then
put in the value with another line
of code, or 5, or 6, or 7, or 8.
I don't have to start
copying and pasting
all of these different
variable names by convention.
But I think if we take some of the
advice that was offered a moment ago,
we can also clean this up by
way of a loop or such as well.
So let's do that.
Let me go ahead and give myself,
actually, first the CS50 library so
that I can use get_int.
And let's take this first
piece of advice, which is,
let's start asking for
a score using get_int.
And I'm going to do this three times.
And yeah, I'm getting a little lazy.
I'm getting a little bored already.
So I'm going to copy/paste.
And again, that does not
bode well in general.
When copying and pasting, we
can probably do better still.
But now I think I need to
change just one more thing here.
When doing the math, I want scores[0]
plus scores[1] plus scores[2].
But before I solve this problem
here-- the logic is still the same,
but I'm now taking in
dynamically three integers--
there's still a smell to it as well.
It's still not as well designed.
And so just to make clear, what
could I do be doing better now?
How could I clean up this code and
make it not just correct, not just
well styled, but better designed?
What remains here?
Nina?
What do you think?
NINA: The code is specific
for only three scores.
So you could, as an input,
[INAUDIBLE] how many scores
it wants at the very beginning.
And then instead of having
scores[0], scores[1],
you could use a for loop that goes
through from 0 to n minus 1 or less
than n that will ask, and it
should be one line of code instead.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, really good.
It's the fact that we have
get_int, get_int, get_int.
That's the first sign that you're
probably doing something suboptimally.
It might be correct, but it's
probably not well designed
because I did literally
resort to copy/paste.
There's sort of a pattern
here that I could certainly
integrate into something like a loop.
So let me do that.
Let me actually get rid of
two of these lines of code.
Let me go up here and do something like
for int i get 0, i less than 3 for now,
i++.
Let me open up this for loop.
Let me indent that
remaining line of code.
And instead of scores[0]--
this is where arrays
get really powerful--
you can use a variable
to index into an array--
that is, to go to a specific location.
What do I want to use for my variable?
Well, I would think i here.
So now I've whittled my lines of code
down from all three triplicate, three
nearly identical lines,
into just one really
inside of a loop that's going to do
the same thing for me again and again.
And as Nina proposed too,
I don't have to hard code
these 3's all over the place.
Maybe I could do something like this.
I could say something like,
int total gets get_int.
And I might ask, "Total
number of scores."
And I could literally ask
the human from the get-go
how many total scores are there.
Then I can even more powerfully use
this variable, total, in multiple places
so that now, I'm doing my
math much more dynamically.
This, though-- I'm afraid,
Nina, this broke a bit.
I'm going to be a little more--
I need to exert a little more
effort here on line 14 because now I
can't hard code scores[0], [1], and [2]
because if the total number of scores
is more than that, I
need to do more addition.
If it's fewer than that, I
need to do less addition.
So I think we've introduced
a bug, but we can fix that.
But let me propose for just a moment.
Let's not make it dynamic because I
worry that's just made my life harder.
Let's at least introduce one
other feature here first.
I'm going to go ahead up here and
define a new feature of C today, which
is known as a constant.
If I know in advance that I want
to declare a number that I want
to use again and again and again
without copying and pasting
literally that number 3, I
can give myself a constant int
by a const int total = 3.
This declares what's called
a constant in programming,
which is a feature of many languages
whereby you declare a variable of sorts
whose value can never change.
Once you set it, you cannot change it.
And that's a good thing
because, one, it shouldn't
change in the context of this program.
And two, just in case you,
the human, are fallible,
you don't want to accidentally
change it when you don't intend.
So this is a feature of
a programming language
that sort of protects you from yourself.
So now I can sort of take an amalgam
of my instincts and Nina's and use
this variable, total.
And actually, another convention
when declaring constants
is to capitalize them just to
make visually clear that there's
something different or
special about this variable.
So I'm going to change this to TOTAL,
and I'm going to use that value here
and here and also down here.
But I'm afraid both Nina and I have
a little bit of cleanup here to do
in that I still have hard coded
scores[0], scores[1], and scores[2].
And I want to add a changing
number of values together.
So you know what?
I've got an idea.
Let me go ahead and
create a function that's
going to compute an average for me.
So if I want to create my own
function that computes an average,
I want it to return a
floating point value,
just so that we don't truncate any math.
I'm going to call this average.
And the input to this function
is going to be the length
of an array and the actual array.
And this is the last piece
of funky syntax for now.
It turns out that when you want to pass
an array as input to a custom function,
you literally use those square brackets
again, but you don't specify the size.
And the upside of this is
that your function then
can support an array that's got
one space in it, two spaces, three,
a hundred.
It's more dynamic this way.
So how do I compute an average here?
I can do this a few different ways.
But I think what was
suggested earlier makes
sense, where I can do
some kind of summation.
So let me do int sum = 0.
Because how do you compute the
average of a bunch of numbers?
Well, you add them all together,
and you divide by the total.
Well, let's see how I might do that.
Let me do for int i
gets 0, i less than--
what should this be?
Well, if I'm being passed as this
custom function the length of the array
and the actual array, I think I
can iterate from i up to length,
and then i++ on each iteration.
And then on each
iteration, I think I want
to do sum plus whatever is in the
array's i-th location, so to speak.
So again, this is shorthand
notation per last week for this.
Sum equals whatever sum is plus
whatever is in location i of the array.
And once I've done all
of that, I think what
I can do is return the total sum
divided by the length of the array.
And what I like about this whole
approach-- assuming my code's correct,
and I don't think it is just yet--
notice what I can do back up in main.
Now I can abstract away the
notion of calculating an average
and just do something like this
with this line of code here.
So what did I just do?
A lot's going on, but let's focus
for a moment on line 14 here.
On line 14, I'm still just printing
the average of some floating point
placeholder.
But what I'm passing as input
now is this function, average,
whose inputs are going to be
TOTAL, which again is just
this constant at the very
top-- oh, sorry, I goofed.
I should have capitalized it, which
is just that constant at the very top.
And I'm passing in scores,
which again, is just
this array of all of those scores.
Meanwhile, in the function, in
the context of the function,
notice that the names of
the inputs to a function
do not need to match the
names of the variables being
passed into that function.
So even though in main, they're
called TOTAL and scores,
in the context of my
function, average, I
can call them x and y, a and b, or
more generically, length and array.
I don't know what the array
is, but it's an array of ints.
And I don't know how long it is, but
that answer is going to be in length.
But there's still a bug here.
There's still a bug.
And if we ignore main for a
moment, this is a subtle one.
Does anyone see a mistake that I've
made probably for the third time
now over the past two weeks?
What mistake subtle have
I made here with my code
only in this average function?
This one's a little more subtle.
But the goal is to compute the
average of a whole bunch of integers
and return the answer.
Nicholas?
NICHOLAS: You've declared the
variable within the function.
DAVID MALAN: I've declared the
That's OK because I've declared my
variable sum here, I think you mean.
But that's inside of
the average function.
And I'm using sum inside of
the outermost curly braces
that was defined.
And so that's OK.
That's OK.
Let's take another thought here.
Olivia, where might the bug still be?
OLIVIA: The return type's
a float, but you're
returning an int divided by an int.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So I again made that same
stupid mistake that's
just going to get more
obvious as time goes on
that if I want to do floating point
arithmetic, just like the Ariane rocket
discussion, the Patriot missile--
like, these kinds of details
matter in a program.
Now it's correct because
I'm actually going
to ensure that even
though the context here
is much less important than
those real-world contexts,
just computing some average of scores,
I'm not going to accidentally truncate
any of my values.
So again, in the context
here of this function,
average is just applying some
of last week's principles.
I've got a variable.
I've got a loop.
And I'm doing some floating
point arithmetic, ultimately.
And I'm now creating a
function that takes two inputs.
One is length, and one is the length--
one is the array itself, and the
return type, as Olivia notes,
is a float so that my
output is also well defined.
But what's nice about
this is, again, you
can think of these
functions as abstractions.
Now I don't need to worry about how
I calculate an average because I now
have this helper function,
a custom function
I wrote that can help
me answer that question.
And here, notice that the
output of this average function
will become an input into printf.
And the only other feature
I've added to the mix here
now are not only arrays,
which allow us to create
multiple variables, a variable
number of variables, if you will,
but also this notion of a constant.
If I find myself using the same
number again and again and again,
this constant can help
me keep my code clean.
And notice this.
If next year, maybe another semester,
there's four scores or four tests,
I change it in one place.
I recompile.
Boom, I'm done.
A well-designed program
does not require that you
go reading through the entirety of it,
fixing numbers here, numbers there.
Changing it in one place can
allow me to improve this program,
make it support four tests next
year instead of just the three.
But better still would
be to take, I think,
Nina's advice before, which was to
maybe just use get_int and ask the human
for how many tests they actually have.
That too would work.
Well, let me pause
here to see if there's
any questions then about
arrays or about constants
or passing them around as
inputs and outputs in this way.
Yeah, over to Sophia.
SOPHIA: I had question about the use
of float and why the use of one float
causes the whole output to be a float.
Why does that occur?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, really good question.
That's just how C behaves.
So long as there is one or more
floating point values involved
in a mathematical formula, it is
going to use that data type, which
is the more powerful one, if you will,
rather than risk truncating anything.
So you just need one
float to be participating
in the formula in question.
Good question.
Other questions on arrays or constants
or this passing around of them?
Yeah, over to Alexandra.
ALEXANDRA: I have a question about
the declaring of the array, scores.
When you declared it in
main, you said int scores.
And in the brackets, you have TOTAL.
Can you declare it without the TOTAL--
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
ALEXANDRA: --only the brackets?
DAVID MALAN: Short answer, no.
So the way I did it is the
way you do have to do it.
And in fact, if I highlight what I
did here, now it currently says TOTAL.
If I get rid of that, and I go back
to our first version where I said
something like 3 and 3 and 3 over here,
you cannot do this, which I think,
Alexandra, is what you were proposing.
The computer needs to know how big
the array is when you are creating it.
The exception to that
is that when you're
passing an array from
one function to another,
you do not need to tell
that custom function
how big the array is because,
again, you don't know in advance.
You're writing a fairly generic,
dynamic function whose purpose in life
is to take any array as input
of integers and any length
and respond accordingly with an average
that matches the size of that thing.
And those of you, as an aside, who have
programmed before, especially in Java,
unlike in Java and certain other
languages, the length of an array
is not built into the array itself.
If you do not pass in the length
of an array to another function,
there is no way to determine
how big the array is.
This is different from
Java and other languages,
where you can ask the array, in
some sense, what is its length.
In C, you have to pass
both the array itself
and its length around
separately. [? Sina? ?]
[? SINA: ?] I just-- I'm still
a little bit confused about how,
when we write that second command,
when is it void in the parentheses?
And when do we define the int?
Because as I remember when we did the--
get a negative number, we get
a positive number, it was void,
but we still kind of gave it an input.
I'm just not completely sold on that.
DAVID MALAN: Sure, good question.
Let me go ahead and open
up that previous example,
which was a little buggy, but
it has the right syntax here.
So here was the get_negative_int
function from before.
And, [? Sina, ?] you know
it was void as input.
So there was one comment you
made where it still took input.
That was not so.
So get_negative_int
did not take any input.
And case in point, if
we scroll up to main,
notice that when I
called it on line 10, I
said get_negative_int, open
parenthesis, close parenthesis,
with no inputs inside
of those parentheses.
This keyword "void," which we've
seen a few times now last week
and this week, is just an
explicit keyword in C that says,
do not put anything here, which is to
say, it would be incorrect for me up
here to do something like
this, like to pass in a number,
or to pass in a prompt, or anything
inside of those parentheses.
The fact that this
function, get_negative_int
takes void as its input means it
does not take any inputs whatsoever.
That's fine.
For get_negative_int, the name
of the function says it all.
Like, there's no need to
parameterize or customize
the behavior of getting
negative int itself.
You just want to get a negative int.
By contrast, though, with
the function we just wrote,
average, this function does make
conceptual sense to take inputs,
because you can't just
say, give me the average.
Like, average of what?
Like, it needs to take input so as
to answer that question for you.
And the input, in this case,
is the array itself of numbers
and the length of that array
so you can do the arithmetic.
And so, [? Sina, ?] hopefully,
that helps make the distinction.
You use void when you
don't want to take input.
And you actually specify a
comma-separated list of arguments
when you do want to take input.
All right, so we focused up
until now on integers, really.
But let's simplify a little
bit because it turns out
that arrays and memory
actually intersect
to create some very familiar features
of most any computer program, namely
text or strings more generally.
So suppose we simplify further, no more
integers, no more arrays of integers.
Let's just start for a moment
with a single character
and write a program that just creates
a single brick from that Mario game.
Let me go ahead and create a
program here called brick.c.
And in brick.c, I'm
just going to #include
stdio.h, int main(void) And more
on this void a little later today.
Char c gets, quote unquote, '#'.
And then down here, let me just go ahead
and print very simply a placeholder,
%c, backslash n, and then output c.
So this is a pretty stupid program.
Its sole purpose in life
is to print a single hash
as you might have in a Mario
pyramid of height 1, so very simple.
Let me go ahead and make brick.
It seems to compile OK.
Let me run it with ./brick.
And voila, we get a single brick.
But let's consider for just a moment
exactly what just happened here
and what actually was going
on underneath the hood.
Well, you know what?
I'm kind of curious.
I remember from last week, we could
cast values from one thing to another.
What if I got a little curious,
and I didn't print out c,
which is this hash character, as %c,
which is a placeholder for a character?
What if I got a little
crazy and said %i?
I think I could probably coerce
this char by casting it to an int
so I can see its decimal equivalent.
I could see its actual ASCII code.
So let me rebuild this with make brick.
Now let me do ./brick.
And what number might we see?
Last week, we saw 72 a
lot, 73, and 33 for "HI!"
This week, you can see 35.
It turns out it's the code
for and an ASCII hash.
And you can see this, for instance,
if I go to a website like--
let's go to asciichart.com.
And sure enough, if I go to
the same chart from last week,
and I look for the hash symbol
here, its ASCII code is 35.
And it turns out, in C, if it's
pretty straightforward to the computer
that, yes, if this is a character,
I know I can convert it to an int,
you don't have to explicitly cast it.
You can instead implicitly cast one data
type to another just from context here.
So printf and C are smart enough
here to know, OK, you're giving me
a character in the form of variable c.
But you want to display
it as a %i, an integer.
That's going to be OK.
And indeed, I still see the number 35.
So that's just simple casting.
But let's now put this into
the context of today's picture.
How is that character laid out?
Well, quite simply, if
this is my memory again,
and we've gotten rid of
all of the numbers, c,
otherwise storing this hash, is just
being stored in one of these bytes.
It only requires one square because,
again, a char is a single byte.
But equivalently, 35 is the number
that's actually being stored there.
But I wonder, I wonder.
Last week, we spent quite
a bit of time storing
not just single characters, but actual
words like "hi" and other expressions.
And so what if I were to
do something like this?
Let me go back to my code.
And let me not quite yet
practice what I just preached.
And let me give myself three
variables this time-- c1, c2, and c3.
And let me deliberately store in those
three variables H, I, in all caps,
followed by an exclamation point.
And per last week, when you're
dealing with individual characters,
you must, in C, use single quotes.
When you're dealing with
multiple characters,
otherwise known last week as
strings, use double quotes.
But that's why I'm using single
quotes, because we're only playing
at the moment with single characters.
Now let me go ahead and
print these values out.
Let me print out %c, %c,
%c, and output c1, c2, c3.
So this is perhaps the stupidest way you
could print out a full word like "HI!"
in C by storing every single character
in its own variable, but so be it.
I'm just using these
first principles here.
I'm using %c as my placeholder.
I'm printing out these characters.
So let me do make brick now.
Compiles OK.
And if I do a dot slash--
you know, I really should
have renamed this file,
but we'll rename it in a moment--
./brick, "HI!"
And let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead now and
actually close the file.
And recall from last week, if I
want to rename my file from brick.c,
let's say, to hi.c, I can
use the move command, mv.
And now if I open up this file,
sure enough, there's hi.c.
And I've fixed my renaming mistake.
All right, so again, if I now do
make hi, and I do ./hi, voila,
I see the "HI!"
But again, this is kind of a stupid
way of implementing a string.
But let's still look
underneath the hood.
Let me go ahead and get curious.
Let me print out %i, %i, and %i.
And Let me include spaces
this time just so I
can see separation between the numbers.
Let me make hi again, ./hi.
OK, there's that 72.
There's that 73.
And there's that 33 from last week.
So that's interesting too.
So what's going on underneath the
hood in the computer's memory?
Well, when I'm storing
these three characters,
now I'm just storing them in three
different boxes, so c1, c2, c3.
And when you look at it collectively,
it kind of looks like a whole word
even though it's, of course,
just these individual characters.
So what's underneath the hood,
of course, though, is 72, 73, 33.
Or equivalently, in binary, just this.
So the story is the same
even though we're now talking
about chars instead of integers.
But what happens when I do this?
What happens when I do string
s gets, quote unquote, "HI!"
using double quotes?
Well, let's change this
program accordingly.
Let me go ahead and do what we
would have done last week, string--
I'll call it s just for s for string--
"HI!"
in all caps.
I can simplify this next line.
I'm going to use %s as a
placeholder for string s.
But let's, for now, reveal
what a string really
is, because string is a term of art.
Every programming language has
"strings" even if it doesn't technically
have a data type called string.
C does not technically have
a data type called string.
We have added this type to
C by way of CS50's library.
But now if I do make hi, notice
that my code compiles OK.
And if I do ./hi Enter,
voila, I still see "HI!",
which is what I would have
seen last week as well.
And if we depict this in the computer's
memory, because "HI!" is three letters,
it's kind of like saying,
well, give me three boxes,
and let me call this string s.
So this feels like a
reasonable artist's rendition
of what s is if it's storing
a three-letter word like "HI!"
But any time we have sequences
of characters like this,
I feel like we're now seeing the
capability of a proper programming
language.
We introduced a little bit
ago the notion of a string.
So maybe could someone
redefine string as we've
been using it in terms of
some of today's nomenclature?
Like, what is a string?
There's an example of one,
"HI!", taking up three boxes.
But how did we, CS50 maybe implement
string underneath the hood,
would you say?
What is it?
Tucker?
TUCKER: Well, it's an array
of characters and integers.
Well, it's integers
are used in the string,
but it's an array of
basically single characters.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
If we now have the ability to express--
very nicely done, Tucker.
If we now have the ability to represent
sequences of things, integers,
for instance, like
scores, well, it stands
to reason that we can take another
primitive, a very basic data type
like a char.
And if we want to spell things with
those chars, like English words,
well, let's just think of
a string really as an array
of characters, an array of chars.
And indeed, that's exactly
what string actually is.
So this thing here, "HI!", technically
speaking is an array called s.
And this is s[0] This is s[1].
This is s[2].
It's just an array called s.
Now, we didn't use the
word array last week
because it's not as familiar as
the notion of a "string of text,"
for instance.
But a string is
apparently just an array.
And if it's an array, that means
we can access, if we want to,
the individual characters of that
array by way of the square bracket
notation from today.
But it turns out there's something
a little special about strings
as they're implemented.
Recall in our example
involving scores, the only way
we knew how long that
array was was because I
had a second variable
called length or TOTAL
that stored the total number
of integers in that array.
That is to say in our scores
example, not only did we
allocate the array itself.
We also kept track of how many things
were in that array with two variables.
However, up until now, every time you
and I have used the printf function,
and we have passed to that
printf function a string like s,
we have only provided printf
with the string itself.
Or logically, we have
only provided printf
with the array of characters itself.
And yet somehow, printf is magically
figuring out how long the string is.
After all, when printf
prints the value of s,
it is printing H, I, exclamation
point, and that's it.
It's not going and printing 4
characters or 5 or 20, right?
It stands to reason that there's
other stuff in your computer's memory
if you've got other variables
or other programs running.
Yet printf seems to be
smart enough to know,
given an array, how long the
array is because, quite simply, it
only prints out that single word.
So how then does a computer know where
a string ends in memory if all a string
is is a sequence of characters?
Well, it turns out that if your string
is length 3, as is this one, H, I,
exclamation point, technically a
string, implemented underneath the hood,
uses 4 bytes.
It uses 4 bytes.
It uses a fourth byte to
be initialized to what
we would describe as backslash 0,
which is a weird way of describing it.
But this just represents a
special character, otherwise known
as the null character, which
is just a special value that
represents the end of a string.
So that is to say when
you create a string, quote
unquote with double quotes, "HI!"--
yes, the string is length 3.
But you're wasting or
spending 4 total bytes on it.
Why?
Because this is a clue to the
computer as to where "HI!"
ends and where the next
string maybe begins.
It is not sufficient to just
start printing characters inside
of printf one at a time, left to right.
There needs to be this sort
of equivalent of a stop sign
at the end of the string, saying,
that's it for this string.
Well, what are these values?
Well, let's convert
them back to decimal--
72, 73, 33.
That fancy backslash 0 was just a way
of saying, in character form, it's 0.
More specifically, it is eight
0 bits inside of that square.
So to store a string, the
computer, unbeknownst to you,
has been using one extra byte all, 0
bits, otherwise written as backslash 0,
but otherwise known as
literally the value 0.
So this thing, otherwise
colloquially known as null,
is just a special character.
And we can actually see it again.
If I go back to my
asciichart.com from before,
notice number 0 is known
as NUL, N-U-L in all caps.
All right, so with that said, what
is powerful then about strings
once we have this capability?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go back into my
code from a moment ago.
And let me go ahead and enhance
this program a little bit
just to get a little curious
as to what's going on.
You know what I can do?
I bet what I can do here in
this version here is this.
You know what?
If I want to print out all
of these characters of s,
I can get a little curious
again and print out %c, %c, %c.
And if s is an array, per today's
syntax, I can technically do s[0],
s[1], s[2].
And then if I save this, recompile
my code with make hi, OK, ./hi,
I still see "HI!"
But you know what?
Let me get a little more curious.
Let me use %i so I can
actually see those ASCII codes.
Let me go ahead and
recompile with make hi, ./hi.
There's the 72, 73, 33.
Now let me get even more curious.
Let me print a fourth
value like this here, s[3],
which is the fourth location, mind you.
So if I now do make hi and
./hi, voila, now you see 0.
And what this hints at is actually a
very dangerous feature of C. You know,
suppose I'm curious at
seeing what's beyond that.
I could technically do
s[4], the fifth location,
even though according to my picture,
there really shouldn't be anything
at the fifth location, at least
not that I know about just yet.
But I can do it in C.
Nothing's stopping me.
So let me do make hi, ./hi.
And that's interesting.
Apparently there's the number 37.
What is the number 37?
Well, let me go back to my ASCII chart.
And let me conclude that
number 37 is a percent sign.
So that's kind of weird because I
didn't print out an explicit percent.
Now I'm kind of poking around
the computer's memory in places
I shouldn't be looking, in some sense.
In fact, if I get really curious,
let's look not at location 4.
How about location 40, like
way off into that picture?
Make hi, ./hi, 24, whatever that is.
I can look at location 400,
recompile my code, make hi, ./hi.
And now it's 0 again.
So this is what's both powerful
and also dangerous about C.
You can touch, look at,
change any memory you want.
You're essentially just
on the honor system
not to touch memory that
does it belong to you.
And invariably,
especially next week, are
we going to start accidentally touching
memory that doesn't belong to you.
And you'll see that it actually can
cause computer programs to crash,
including programs on your own Mac and
PC, yet another source of common bugs.
But now that we have this ability
to store different strings
or to think about
strings as arrays, well,
let's go ahead and
consider how you might
have multiple strings in a program.
So for instance, if you were to store
two strings in a program-- let's call
them s and t respectively.
Another programmer convention--
if you need two strings,
call the first one s
then the second one t.
Maybe I'm storing "HI!"
then "BYE!"
Well, what's the computer's
memory going to look like?
Well, let's do some digging.
"HI!", as before, is
going to be stored here.
So this whole thing
refers to s, and it's
taking 4 bytes because the last one
is that special null character that
just is the stop sign that
demarcates the end of the string.
"BYE!", meanwhile, is going to take
up another B, Y, E, exclamation point,
five bytes because I need a fifth byte
to represent another null character.
And this one deliberately wraps around.
Though again, this is just
an artist's rendition.
There's not necessarily
a grid in reality.
B, Y, E, exclamation point,
backslash 0 now represents t.
So this is to say, if I had a
program like this, where I had "HI!"
and then "BYE!", and I started
poking around the computer's memory
just using the square
bracket notation, I
bet I could start accessing
the value of B or Y
or E just by looking a
little past the string s.
So again, as complicated
as our programs get,
all that's going on underneath the
hood is you just plop things down
in memory in locations like these.
And so now that we have this
ability or maybe this mental model
for what's going on
inside of a computer,
we can consider some of the
features that you might want
to now use in programs that you write.
So let me go ahead here and
whip up a quick program,
for instance, that goes
ahead and, let's say,
prints out the total length of a string.
Let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and create
a new program here in CS50's IDE.
And I'm going to call this one string.c.
And I'm going to very quickly at
the top include as usual cs50.h.
And I'm going to go ahead
and #include stdio.h.
And I'm going to give
myself int main(void).
And then in here, I'm going
to get myself a string.
So string s equals get_string.
Let me just ask the human for
some input, whatever it is.
Then let me go ahead and print
out literally the word "Output"
just so that I can
actually see the result.
And then down here, let me go ahead and
print out that string, for int i get 0,
i is less than--
huh, I don't know what the
length of the string is yet.
So let me just put a question mark
there, which is not valid code,
but we'll come back to this-- i++.
And then inside of the loop, I
want to go ahead and print out
every character one at a time
by using my new array notation.
And then at the very
end of this program,
I'm going to print a
new line just to make
sure the cursor is on its own line.
So this is a complete
program that is now,
as of this week, going to treat a string
as an array, ergo, my syntax in line 10
that's using my new fancy
square bracket notation.
But the only question I
haven't answered yet is this--
how do I know when to
stop printing the string?
How do I know when to stop?
Well, it turns out, thus far,
when we're using for loops,
we've typically done something like
just count from 0 on up to some number.
This condition, though,
is any Boolean expression.
I just need to have a yes/no
or a true/false answer.
So you know what I could do?
Keep looping so long as
character at location i
and s does not equal backslash 0.
So this is now definitely
some new syntax.
Let me zoom in here.
But s[i] just means the i-th
character in s, or more specifically,
the character at position i in s.
Bang equals-- so bang is
how a programmer pronounces
exclamation point because it's
a little faster-- bang equals
means does not equal.
So this is how you would do an equal
sign with a slash through it in math.
It's, in code, exclamation
point, equals sign.
And then notice this
funkiness-- backslash
0 is again, the "null character,"
but it's in single quotes
because, again, it is by
definition a character.
And for reasons we'll
get into another time,
backslash 0 is how you express it.
Just like backslash n is kind of a
weird escape character for the new line,
backslash 0 is the
character that is all 0's.
So this is kind of a different for loop.
I'm still starting at 0 for i.
I'm still incrementing i as always.
But I'm now not checking
for some preordained length
because just like a computer, I do not
know a priori where these strings end.
I only know that they end
once I see backslash 0.
So when I now go down
here and do make string--
it compiles OK-- ./string, let me type
in something like "HELLO" in all caps.
Voila, the output is "HELLO" again.
Let me do it again--
"BYE" in all caps, and
the output is "BYE."
So it's kind of a useless program
in that it's just printing
the same thing that I typed in.
But I'm conditionally using
this Boolean expression
to decide whether or not to
keep printing characters.
Now thankfully, C comes with a
function that can answer this for me.
It turns out there is a
function called strlen
so I can literally just
say, well, figure out
what the length of the string is.
The function is called
strlen for string length.
And it exists in a file called,
not surprisingly, perhaps,
string.h, string.h.
So now let me go ahead down
here and do make string--
compiles OK-- ./string.
Type in "HELLO," and it still works.
So this function strlen that does
exist in a library via the header file
string.h already exists.
Someone else wrote it.
But how did they write it?
Odds are they wrote the
first version that I
did by checking for that backslash 0.
But let me ask a subtle question here.
This program is correct.
It iterates over the whole
length of the string,
and it prints out every
character therein.
Can anyone observe a poor design
decision in this function?
This one's subtle, but
there's something I don't
like about my for loop in particular.
And I'll isolate it to line 9.
I've not done something
optimally on line 9.
There's an opportunity
for better design.
Any thoughts here on
what I might do better?
Yeah, Jonathan?
JONATHAN: Yeah, to create basically
another variable for the string length
and to remember it.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, and why
are you suggesting that?
JONATHAN: If you want to use a
different value for the string length,
or if it might fluctuate
or change, you want
to just have a different variable as
a sort of placeholder value for it.
DAVID MALAN: OK, potentially.
But I will claim in this case
that because the human has
typed in the word, once you type in
the word, it's not going to change.
But I think you're going down
the right direction because
in this Boolean expression here, i
less than the string length of s,
recall that this expression gets
evaluated again and again and again.
Every time through a for loop,
recall that you're constantly
checking the condition.
The condition in this case is
i less than the length of s.
The problem is that strlen in
this case is a function, which
means there's some piece
of code someone wrote,
probably similar to what I wrote a few
minutes ago, that you're constantly
asking, what's the length of the string?
What's the length of the string?
And recall from our picture, the way
you figure out the length of a string
is you start at the beginning of
the string, and you keep checking,
am I at backslash 0?
OK.
Am I at backslash 0?
So to figure out the length of "HI!",
it's going to take me 1, 2, 3, 4 steps,
right, because I have to
start at the beginning.
And I iterate from
location 0 on to the end.
To find out the length
of "BYE!", it's going
to take me five steps
because that's how long it's
going to take me from left to
right to find that backslash 0.
So what I don't like about
this line of code is,
why are you asking for the string
length of s again and again
and again and again?
It's not going to
change in this context.
So Jonathan's point is taken if we
keep asking the user for more input.
But in this case, we've
only asked the human once.
So you know what?
Let's take Jonathan's advice and do
int n equals the string length of s.
And then maybe you
know what we could do?
Put n in this condition instead.
So now I'm asking the same
question, but I'm not foolishly,
inefficiently asking the same
question again and again,
whereby the same question
requires a good amount of work
to find the backslash 0
again and again and again.
Now, there's some cleaning
up we can do here too.
It turns out there's this other
subtle feature of for loops.
If you want to initialize
another variable to a value,
you can actually do this all at once.
And you can do so before the semicolon.
You can do comma n equals strlen of s.
And then you can use
n, just as I have here.
So it's not all that
much better, but it's
a little cleaner in that now
I've taken two lines of code
and collapsed them into one.
They both have to be
of the same data types,
but that's OK here
because both i and n are.
So again, the inefficiency
here is that it was foolish
before that I kept asking the same
question again and again and again.
But now I'm asking the question once,
remembering it in a variable called n,
and only comparing i against that
integer which does not actually change.
All right, I know that too was a lot.
Let's go ahead here and take a 3-minute
break just to stretch legs and whatnot.
In 3 minutes, we'll come back
and start to see applications
now of all of these features
ultimately to some problems that
are going to lie ahead this week
on the readability of language
and also on cryptography.
So we'll see you in 3 minutes.
All right, so we're back.
And this has been a whole bunch
of low-level details, admittedly.
And where we're going with this
ultimately this week and beyond
is applications of some
of these building blocks.
And one of those applications this
coming week and the next problem set
is going to be that of cryptography,
the art of scrambling or encrypting
information.
And if you're trying
to encrypt information,
like messages, well, those
messages might very well
be written in English or
in ASCII, if you will.
And you might want to convert some of
those ASCII characters from one thing
to another so that if your message
is intercepted by some third party,
they can't actually decipher or figure
out what it is that you've sent.
So I feel like we're almost toward--
we're almost at the
ability where, in code, we
can start to convert one word to
another or to scramble our text.
But we do need a couple
of more building blocks.
So recall that we left
off with this picture
here, where we had two words in the
computer's memory, "HI!" and "BYE!",
both with exclamation points, but
also both with these backslash 0's
that you and I do not
put there explicitly.
They just happen for you any time you
use the double quotes and any time
you use the get_string function.
So once we have those in memory, you can
think of them as s and t respectively.
But a string, s or t, is just an array.
So again, you can also refer to all of
these individual characters or chars
via the new square bracket notation
of today, s[0], s[1], s[2], s[3],
and then t[0], t[1], [2], [3],
and [4], and then whatever else is
in the computer's memory.
But you know what you can even do
is this-- suppose that instead we
wanted to have an array of words.
So before, we had an array of
scores, an array of integers.
But now suppose we wanted in the
context of some other program
to have an array of words.
You can totally do that.
There's nothing stopping you
from having an array of words.
And the syntax is going to be identical.
Notice, if I want an array called
words that has room for two strings,
I literally just say, string words[2].
This means, hey, computer, give me an
array of size 2, each of whose members
is going to be a string.
How do I populate that array?
Same as before with the scores--
words[0] gets, quote unquote, "HI!"
Words[1] gets, quote unquote, "BYE!"
So that is to say with this code, could
we create a picture similar to the one
previously?
But I'm not calling
these strings s and t.
Now I'm calling them both "words"
at two different locations, 0 and 1
respectively.
So we could redraw that
same picture like this.
Now this word is
technically named words[0].
And this one is referred to by words[1].
But again, what is a string?
A string is an array.
And yet, here we have
an array of strings.
So we kind of sort of
have an array of arrays.
So we've got an array of words,
but a word is just a string.
And a string is an array of characters.
So what I really have on the
board is an array of arrays.
And so here-- and this will be
the last weird syntax for today--
you can actually have multiple
square brackets back to back.
So if your variable's called words,
and that variable's an array,
if you want to get the first word
in the array, you do words[0].
Once you're at that
word, "HI!", and you want
to get the first character in that
word, you can similarly do [0].
So the first bracket refers to
what word do you want in the array.
The second bracket refers to what
character do you want in that word.
So now the I is that words[0][1].
The exclamation point
is that words[0][2].
And the null character's at words[0][3].
Meanwhile, the B is that words[1][0],
[1][1], [1][2], [1][3], [1][4].
So it's almost kind of like a
coordinate system, if you will.
It's a two-dimensional
array, or an array of arrays.
So this is only to say that if we
wanted to think of arrays of strings
as individual characters, we can.
We have that expressiveness
now to encode.
So what more can I do now that I
can manipulate things at this level?
Let me do a program that'll
be pretty applicable,
I think, with some of our
upcoming programs as well.
Let me call this one uppercase.
Let me quickly write a
program whose purpose in life
is just to convert an
input word to uppercase.
And let's see how we can do this.
So let me go ahead and #include cs50.h.
Let me go ahead and #include stdio.h.
Let me also include this
time string.h, which is
going to give us functions like strlen.
And then let me do int main(void).
And then let me go ahead here and get
a string from the user like before.
So I'm just going to ask
the user for a string.
And I want them to give me
whatever the string should
be before I uppercase everything.
Then I'm just going to go ahead
and print out literally "After,"
just so I can see what happens after
I capitalize everything in the string.
And now let me go ahead and
do this-- for int i get 0,
i less than string length of s, i++.
Wait a minute, I made
that mistake before.
Let's not repeat this question.
Let's give myself a second variable-- n
gets string length of s, i less than n,
i++.
So again, this is now
becoming boilerplate.
Any time you want to iterate over
all of the characters in the string,
this probably is a
reasonable place to start.
And then let me ask the question--
I want to iterate over every
character in the string
that the human has typed in.
And I want to ask myself a question,
just as we've done with any algorithm.
Specifically, I want to ask if
the current letter is lowercase,
let me somehow convert it to uppercase.
Else, let me just
print it out unchanged.
So how can I express that using last
week and this week's building blocks?
Well, let me say something like this--
if the character at location i in
s, or if the i-th character in s
is greater than or equal to a lowercase
a, and the i-th character in s
is less than or equal to a lower
case z, what do I want to do?
Let me go ahead and
print out a character.
But that character should
be what? s bracket i,
but I'm not sure what to do here yet.
But let me come back to that.
Else, let me go ahead and just print
out that character unchanged, s[i].
So minus the placeholder, the question
marks I've put, I'm kind of all the way
there.
Line 10 initializes i to 0.
It's going to count all the way up to
n, where n is the length of the string.
And it's going to keep incrementing i.
So we've seen that before.
And again, that's going to
become muscle memory before long.
Line 12 is a little new,
but it uses building blocks
from last week and this.
This week, we have
the new square bracket
notation to get the i-th
character in the string s.
Greater than or equal to, less than
or equal to-- we saw at least one
of those last week.
That just means greater than or
equal to, less than or equal to.
I mentioned &amp;&amp; last week, which
is the logical AND operator,
which means you can check
one condition and another.
And the whole thing is true
if both of those are true.
This is a bit weird today.
But if you want to express,
is the current character
between lowercase a and
lowercase z, totally fine
to implicitly treat a and z as
numbers, which they really are.
Because again, if we come back
to our favorite ASCII chart,
you'll see again that lowercase a
has a number associated with it, 97.
Lowercase z has a number
associated with it, 122.
So if I really wanted to be pedantic,
I could go back into my code
and do something like, well, if
this is greater than or equal to 97,
and it's less than or equal
to 122, but bad design.
Like, I'm never going to
remember that lowercase z is 122.
Like, no one is going to know that.
It makes the code less obvious.
Go ahead and write it in
a way that's a little more
friendly to humans like this.
But notice this question mark.
How do I fill in this blank?
Well, let me go back to the ASCII chart.
This is subtle, but
this is kind of cool.
And humans were
definitely thinking ahead.
Notice that lowercase a is 97.
Capital A is 65.
Lowercase b is 98.
Capital B is 66.
And notice these two numbers--
65 to 97, 66 to 98, 67 to 99.
It would seem that no matter what
letters we compare, lowercase
and uppercase, they're always 32 apart.
And that's consistent.
We could do it for all
26 English letters.
So if they're always 32 apart,
you know what I could do--
if I want to take a
lowercase letter, which
is what I'm thinking about
in line 14, I could just
subtract off 32 in this case.
It's not the cleanest,
because again, I'm
probably going to forget
that math at some point.
But at least mathematically,
I think that'll do
the trick because 97 will become 65.
98 will become 66, which is forcing
those characters to lowercase.
But they're not being
printed as numbers.
I'm still using %c to
coerce it to be a char.
So if I didn't mess any syntax
up here, let me make uppercase.
OK, ./uppercase.
And let me go ahead and type in, for
instance, my name in all lowercase.
And voila, uppercase.
Now, it's a little ugly.
I forgot my backslash
n, so let me go ahead
and add one of those real
quick just to fix the cursor.
Let me recompile the
code with make uppercase.
Let me rerun the program with
./uppercase and now type in my name,
David.
Let me do it again with Brian.
And notice that it's capitalizing
everything character by character
using only today's building blocks.
This is correct.
It's pretty well styled because
everything's nicely indented.
It's very readable even though it might
look a little cryptic at first glance.
But I think I can do better.
And I can do better by
using yet another library.
And here's where C, and really
programming in general, gets powerful.
The whole point of
using popular languages
is because so many other people
before you have solved problems
that you don't need to solve again.
And I'm sure over the past, like,
50 years, someone has probably
written a function that
capitalizes letters for me.
I don't have to do this myself.
And indeed, there is another
library that I'm going
to include by way of its header file.
In ctype.h, type which is the language
C and a bunch of type-related things.
And in ctype.h, it turns out
there's a function call--
there's a couple of functions.
Specifically, let me get
rid of all of this code.
And let me call a function called
islower and pass to islower s[i].
And islower, as you might
guess, its purpose in life
is to return essentially a
Boolean value, true or false,
if that character is lower.
And if so, well, let me go ahead
and print out a placeholder
followed by the
capitalization of that letter.
Now, before I had to do that annoying
math with minus 32 and figure it out,
uh-uh, toupper of parentheses s[i].
And now I can otherwise just print
out that character unchanged,
just as before, s[i].
But now notice my program--
honestly, it's definitely
a little shorter.
It's a little simpler in
that there's just less code.
And hopefully, if the person that wrote
islower and toupper did a good job,
I know it's correct.
I'm just standing on their shoulders.
And frankly, my code's more readable
because I understand what islower
means, whereas that crazy &amp;&amp; syntax
and all of the additional code--
that was just a lot harder to
wrap your mind around, arguably.
So now if I go ahead and
compile this-- make uppercase.
OK, that seemed to work well.
And now I'm going to go ahead and do
./uppercase and type in my name in all
lowercase again.
David seems to work.
Brian seems to work.
And I could do this all day long.
It seems to still work.
But you know what?
I don't think I have to
be even this explicit.
You know what?
I bet if the human who
wrote toupper was smart,
I bet I can just blindly pass
in any character to toupper,
and it's only going to uppercase it
if it can be converted to uppercase.
Otherwise, it'll pass
it through unchanged.
So you know what?
Let me get rid of all of this stuff
and really tighten this program up
and print out a placeholder
for c and then toupper of s[i].
And sure enough, if you read the
documentation for this function,
it will handle the case where it's
either lowercase or not lowercase.
And it will do the right thing.
So now if I recompile my code,
make uppercase, so far so good.
./uppercase, David again.
Voila, it still works.
And notice truly just how much
tighter, how much cleaner,
how much shorter my code is.
And it's more readable in the sense
that this function is pretty well named.
Toupper is what it's indeed called.
But there is an important detail here.
Toupper expects as input a character.
You cannot pass a whole word to it.
It is still necessary at this
point for me to be using this loop
and doing it character by character.
Now, how would you know this?
Well, you'll see multiple examples
of this over the weeks to come.
But if I go to what's called the
manual pages for the language C,
we have our own web-based
version of them.
And we'll link this for
you in the course's labs
and problem sets as needed.
You can see a list of all of
the available functions in C
at least that are
frequently used in CS50.
And if we uncheck a box at the top,
we can see even more functions.
There's dozens, maybe hundreds
of functions, most of which
we will not need or use in CS50.
But this is going to be
true in any language.
You sort of pick up the building
blocks that you need over time.
So we'll refer you to
these kinds of resources
so that you don't rely only on what
we show in section and lecture,
but you have at your disposal these
other functions and toolkits as well.
And we'll do the same with Python
and SQL and other languages as well.
So those are what we
call, again, manual pages.
All right, a final
feature before we even
think about cryptography and scrambling
information as for problem set 2.
So a command-line argument
I mentioned by name before--
it's like a word you can
type after a program's name
in order to provide it
input at the command line.
So make hello-- hello is a command-line
argument to the program, hello.
Rm space a.out-- a.out was an argument,
a command-line argument to the program
rm when I wanted to remove it.
So we've already seen
command-line arguments in action.
But we haven't actually
written any programs
that allow you to accept words or other
inputs from the so-called command line.
Up until now, all of the input you
and I have gotten in our programs
comes from get_string,
get_int, and so forth.
We have never been able to look at words
that the human might very well have
typed at the prompt when
running your program.
But that's all about to change now.
Let me go ahead and create
a program called argv.c,
and it'll become clear
why in just a moment.
I'm going to go ahead and
include, shall we say, stdio.h.
And then I'm going to give
myself int main(void).
And then I'm just going to very
simply go back and change the void.
So just as our own custom
functions can take inputs--
and we saw that with get_negative_int.
We saw that with average today--
so does main potentially take inputs.
Up till now though,
we've been saying void.
And we told you to say void last week.
And we told you to say
void in problem set 1.
But now it turns out that C does allow
you to put other inputs into main.
You can either say, nope, main does
not take any command-line arguments.
But if it does, you can
say literally, int argc
and string argv with square brackets.
So it's a little cryptic.
And technically, you don't have
to type it precisely this way.
But human convention would have you
do it, at least for now, in this way.
This says that main,
your function, main,
takes an integer as one
input and not a string
but an array of strings as input.
And argc is shorthand
notation for argument count.
Argument count is an integer that's
going to represent the number of words
that your users type at the prompt.
Argv is short for argument vector.
Vector is a fancy way of saying list.
It is a variable that's going to
store in an array all of the strings
that a human types at the prompt
after your own program's name.
So we can use this, for
instance, as follows.
Suppose that I want to let the user type
their own name at the command prompt.
I don't want to use get_string.
I don't want to have to prompt
the human later for their name.
I want them to be able to run my program
and give me their name all at once,
just like make, just like rm, and
Clang, and other programs we've seen.
So I'm going to do this-- if argc == 2--
so if the number of arguments
to my program is 2--
go ahead and print out, "hello, %s",
and plug in whatever is that argv[1].
So more on this in just a moment.
Else, if argc is not equal to 2, let's
just go with last week's default,
"hello, world."
So what is this program's
purpose in life?
If the human types two
words at the prompt,
I want to say, "hello, David,"
"hello, Brian," "hello, so-and-so."
Otherwise, if they don't
type two words at the prompt,
I'm just going to say the
default "hello, world."
So let me compile this, make argv.
And, hm, I didn't get it right here--
unknown type string, unknown type
string.
All right, I goofed.
If I'm using string, recall that now I
need to start using the CS50 library.
And again, we'll see all the
more why in the coming weeks as
we take those training wheels off.
But now I'm going to do
this again, make argv.
There we go.
Now it works-- ./argv,
Enter, "hello, world."
That's pretty much equivalent
to what we did last week.
But notice if I type in, for instance,
argv[1] David, Enter, it says, "hello,
David."
If I type in argv Brian, it says that.
If I type in Brian Yu,
it says "hello, world."
So what's going on?
Well, the way you write programs in C
that accept zero or more command-line
arguments-- that is, words at the
prompt after your program's name--
is you change what we have been
doing all this time from void
to be this into argc string
argv with square brackets.
And what the computer is going
to do for you automatically
is it's going to store in argc a
number of the total number of words
that the human typed in, not
just the arguments, technically
all of the words, including
your own program's name.
It's then going to fill this
array of strings, a.k.a. argv,
with all of the words the human
typed at the prompt, so not just
the arguments like Brian or David,
but also the name of your program.
So if the human typed in two total
words, which they did, argv Brian,
argv David, then I want
to print out, "hello"
followed by a placeholder and
then whatever value is at argv[1].
And I'm deliberately not doing 0.
If I did 0, based on the
verbal definition I just gave,
if I recompile this program, I don't
want to see this, hello, ./argv.
So the program's own name is
automatically always stored for you
at the first location in that array.
But if you want the first
useful piece of information,
you actually would, after recompiling
the code here, access it at [1].
And so in this way do we see
in argv that we can actually
access individual words.
But notice this too--
suppose I want to print out all of
the individual characters in someone's
input.
You know what?
I bet I could even do this.
Let me go ahead and do this.
Instead of just printing out
"hello," let me do for int i get 0,
n equals the string length of argv[1].
And then over here, I'm going
to do i is less than n, i++.
All right, so I'm going to
iterate over all of the characters
in the first real word in argv.
And what am I going to do?
Well, let me go ahead and print
out a character that's at argv[1]
but at location i.
So I said a moment ago
with our picture that we
could think of an array of strings as
really just being an array of arrays.
And so I can employ that syntax here by
going into argv[1] to get me the word
like "David" or "Brian" or so forth,
and then further index into it with more
square brackets that get me the D, the
A, the V, the I, the D, and so forth.
And just to be super clear, let
me put a new line character there
just so we can see
explicitly what's going on.
And let me go ahead now and
just delete this "hello, world"
because I don't want to see any hellos.
I just want to see the
word the human typed in.
Make argv-- whoops, what did I do wrong?
Oh, I used strlen when I shouldn't have
because I haven't included string.h
at the top.
OK, now if I recompile this
code and recompile make argv--
there we go-- ./argv David,
you'll see one character per line.
And if I do the same with
Brian's name or anyone's name
and change it to Brian, I'm
printing one character at a time.
So again, I'm not sure why
you would want to do that.
But in this case, my goal simply
was to not only iterate over
the characters in that first
word, but print them out.
So again, just by applying twice
over this time this principle,
can we actually see that
a program has access
to the individual characters
in each of these strings.
All right, and one last
explanation before we
introduce the crypto
and application thereof.
This thing here, this
thing here-- does anyone
have any idea as to why main,
last week and this week,
seems to return an int even though
it's not an average function?
It's not a get_positive_int function.
It's not get_negative_int.
Somehow, for some reason, main keeps
returning an int even though we
have never seen this int in action.
What might this mean?
This is the one last
piece that we promised
last week we would eventually explain.
What might this mean?
And this one's a tough one.
Brian, who do we have?
How about [? Gred, ?] is it?
[? GRED: ?] Usually, the functions
in the end have returned 0.
And that means that the function stops.
And the 0 is the integer that
pops out of the main function.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, and this one's subtle
in that if you had programmed before,
odds are-- and I'm guessing you have,
[? Gred-- ?] you've seen this in use
before.
We humans, though, in the real
world of using Macs and PCs--
you've actually seen numbers,
integers in weird places.
Frankly, almost any time your computer
freezes or you see an error message,
odds are you see an English or some
spoken language in the error message.
But you very often see a numeric code.
For instance, if you're
having Zoom trouble,
you'll often see the number 5 in
the error window in Zoom's program.
And 5 just means you're
having network issues.
So programmers often
associate integers with things
that can go wrong in a program.
And as [? Gred ?] notes, they use 0 to
connote that nothing has gone wrong,
that all as well.
So let me write one final
program here just called exit.c
that puts this to the test.
Let me go ahead and write a
program in a file called exit.c
that's going to introduce what
we're going to call an exit status.
This is a subtlety that will
be useful as our programs get
a little more complicated.
I'm going to go in here
and do #include cs50.h.
And I'm going to go ahead
and #include stdio.h.
And I'm going to give myself the longer
version of main, so int argc, string
argv with the square brackets.
And in here, I'm going to
say, if argc does not equal 2,
uh-uh, the human is not
doing what I want them to,
and I'm going to yell
at them in some way.
I'm going to say missing
command-line arguments.
So any kind of error message that I
want the human to see on the screen,
I'm just going to tell
them with that message.
But I'm going to very
subtly return the number 1.
I'm going to return an error code.
And the human is not necessarily
going to see this code.
But if we were to have a graphical
user interface or some other feature
to this program, that
would be the number
they see in the error
window that pops up,
just like Zoom might show you the
number 5 if something has gone wrong.
Similarly, if you've ever
visited a page, frankly,
and the web page doesn't
exist, you see the integer 404.
That's not technically the
exact same incarnation of this,
but it is representative of programmers
using numbers to represent errors.
So that one, you probably have seen.
Here, I'm going to go ahead, though,
and by default, say, "hello, %s,"
just like before, passing
in whatever's in argv[1].
So same program as before, but I'm not
going to do any of this lame, "hello,
world" if the human doesn't
type in their name as I expect.
Instead, I am going to
check, did the human
give me two words at the command line?
If not, I'm going to print,
"missing command-line argument,"
and then return this exit code.
Otherwise, if all is well, I'm going
to go ahead and return explicitly 0.
This is another number that the human,
you and I, are never going to see,
but we could have access to it.
And frankly, for course purposes,
check50 can have access to this.
And graphical user interfaces,
when we get to those,
can have access to these values.
So 0, as [? Gred ?] notes,
is just all as well.
But 1 would mean that
something goes wrong.
So let me go ahead and make exit,
which is kind of appropriate,
as we're wrapping up here.
And let me go ahead and do ./exit.
"Missing command-line
argument" is what's displayed.
If I go ahead and say, exit
David, now I see "hello, David."
Or exit Brian, I'll see "exit Brian."
Now, this is not a technique
you'll need to use often,
but you can actually see these
return values if you want.
If I run exit, and I see this error
message, I can very weirdly say,
echo $?, which is a very
admittedly cryptic way of saying,
what was my exit status?
And if you hit Enter, you'll see 1.
By contrast, if I run exit
of David, and I actually
see "hello, David," and I do
echo $?, now I will see 0.
So again, this is not a technique
you and I will use very frequently.
But it's a capability of a program,
and it's a capability of C,
that you do now have access to.
And so in writing
programs moving forward,
what we will often do in labs
and in problem sets and the like
is ask you to return from main
either 0 or 1 or maybe 2 or 3 or 4
based on the problems that might
have gone wrong in your program
that you have detected and
responded to appropriately.
So it's a very effective way of
handling errors in a standard way
so that you know that you are being
proactive about detecting mistakes.
So what kinds of mistakes
might we handle this week?
And what kinds of
problems might we solve?
Well, today was entirely about
deconstructing what a string is.
Last week, it was just a sequence
of text, a chunk of text.
Today, it's now an array of characters.
And we have new syntax in C
for accessing those characters.
We also today have access to more
libraries, more header files,
the documentation, therefore, so
that we can actually solve problems
without writing as much code ourselves.
We can use other people's code
in the form of these libraries.
So one problem we will solve this
coming week by way of problems set 2
is that of readability.
Like, when you're reading a book
or an essay or a paper or anything,
what is it that makes it
like a 3rd-grade reading
level or a 12th-grade reading
level or university reading level?
Well, all of us probably have
an intuitive sense, right?
Like, if it's big font and short
words, it's probably for younger kids.
And if it's really complicated
words with big vocabulary and things
we don't know, maybe it's
meant for university audiences.
But we can quantify this a
little more formulaically,
not necessarily the only way, but
we'll give you a few definitions.
So for instance, here's
a famous sentence--
"Mr. And Mrs. Dursley, of
number four, Privet Drive,
we're proud to say that they were
perfectly normal, thank you very much,"
and so forth.
Well, what is it about this text
that puts Harry Potter at grade seven
reading level?
Well, it probably has to do
with the vocabulary words.
But it probably has to do with the
lengths of the sentences, the amount
of punctuation perhaps, the total number
of characters that you might count up.
You can imagine quantifying it
just based generically on the look
and the aesthetics of the text.
What about this?
"In computational linguistics,
authorship attribution
is the task of predicting the author
of document of unknown authorship.
This task is generally performed by
the analysis of stylometric features--
particular"-- this is
Brian's senior thesis.
So this is not a
seventh-grade reading level.
This was actually rated at grade 16.
So Brian's pretty sophisticated
when it comes to writing theses.
But there too, you could perhaps
glean from the sophistication
of the sentences, the length
thereof, and the words therein--
there's something we could perhaps
quantify so as to apply numbers.
And indeed, that's one way you could
assess the readability of a text
even if you don't have access
to a dictionary with which
to figure out which are the
actual big or small words.
And what about cryptography?
So it's incredibly common
these days and so important
these days for you and I to use
cryptography, not necessarily using
algorithms we ourselves come
up with, but rather using
software, like WhatsApp and Signal
and Telegram and Messenger and others,
that support encryption between you and
the third party or friend or family,
or at least minimally the website
with which you're interacting.
So cryptography is the art of scrambling
information, or hiding information.
And if that information is text, well,
frankly, as of this third week of CS50,
we already have the requisite building
blocks for not only representing text,
but we saw today manipulating it.
Even just uppercasing characters
allows us to start mutating text.
Well, what does it mean
to encrypt information?
Well, it's like our
black box from last week.
You have some input.
You want some output.
The input, we're going to
start calling plaintext.
The message, you want to send
from yourself to someone else.
Ciphertext is the output that you want.
And so in between there,
there's going to be
what we're going to call a cipher.
A cipher is an algorithm
that encrypts or scrambles
its input so as to produce output
that a third party can't understand.
And hopefully, that
cipher, that algorithm,
is a reversible process so that when
you receive the scrambled ciphertext,
you can figure out what it was
that the person sent to you.
But the key to using
cryptography-- pun intended--
is to also have a secret key.
So if you think back to
grade school, maybe you
were flirting with someone
in class, and you sent them
a note on a piece of paper.
Well, hopefully, you didn't just say,
like, I love you, on the piece of paper
and then pass it through
all of your friends,
or let alone the teacher,
to the ultimate recipient.
Maybe you did something
like, an A becomes
a B. A B becomes a C.
A C becomes a D. Like,
you kind of apply an algorithm
to add 1 to all of the letters
so that if the teacher does
intercept it and look at it,
they probably don't have enough care in
the world to figure out what this is.
It's just going to look like nonsense.
But if your friend knows
that you changed A to B, B
to C by adding 1 to every letter,
they could reverse that process
and decrypt it.
So the key, for instance, might
be literally the number 1.
The message literally
might be, "I LOVE YOU."
But what would the
ciphertext be, or the output?
Well, let's consider "I LOVE YOU"
is a string which, as of today,
is an array of characters.
So what use is that?
Well, let's consider exactly that
phrase as though it's an array.
It's an array of characters.
We know from last week, characters
are just integers, decimal integers,
thanks to ASCII, and in turn, Unicode.
So it turns out I, we
already know, is 73.
And if we looked up all the others on a
chart, L is 76, 79, 86, 69, 89, 79, 85.
So we could relatively easily and see--
you might have to check your notes
and check my sample code and so forth--
but relatively easily in C convert "I
LOVE YOU" to the corresponding integers
by just casting, so to
speak, chars to integers.
I could very easily mathematically,
using the plus operator in C,
start to add 1 to every
one of these characters,
thereby encrypting my message.
But I could send my
friend these numbers.
But I might as well make it
a little more user friendly
and cast it back from integers to chars.
So now it would seem that the ciphertext
for "I LOVE YOU," if using a key of 1--
and 1 just means change A to B, not
A to C, just move it by one place--
this is the ciphertext for an
encrypted message of, "I LOVE YOU."
And so the whole process becomes
1 is the input as the key.
"I LOVE YOU" is the
input as the plaintext.
And the output ultimately is
this unpronounceable phrase
that, again, if the teacher
or some friend intercepts,
they probably don't
know what's going on.
And indeed, this is the
essence of cryptography.
The algorithms that protect our emails
and texts and financial information
and health information
is hopefully way more
sophisticated than that
particular algorithm as it is.
But it reduces to the same process--
an input key and an input
text followed by some output,
the so-called ciphertext.
And this has been with us for decades
now in some form, sometimes even
mechanical form.
Back in the day, you could actually
get these little circular devices
that have letters on the alphabet
on one side, other letters
on the alphabet on the other side.
And if you rotate one or
the other, A might line up
with B, B might line up with C.
So you can have even a physical
incarnation of cryptography,
just as was popular in a movie
that seems to play endlessly on TV,
at least here in the US
around Christmas time.
And you might recognize if you've
seen A Christmas Story one such look.
So we'll use just a couple of
minutes of our final moments
together to take a look at this
real-world incarnation of cryptography
that undoubtedly you can
probably see on TV this fall.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- "Be it known to all and sundry
that Ralph Parker is hereby
appointed a member of the Little
Orphan Annie secret circle
and is entitled to all the honors
and benefits occurring thereto."
- "Signed, Little Orphan Annie."
"Countersigned, Pierre Andre," in ink.
Honors and benefits
already at the age of nine.
[RADIO CHATTER]
- (ON RADIO) Attention!
[INAUDIBLE] overboard!
[CLANGING]
- (ON RADIO) Come
[INAUDIBLE] Gone overboard!
- (ON RADIO) [INAUDIBLE]
- Come on, let's get on with it.
I don't need all that jazz
about smugglers and pirates.
[BARKING]
- (ON RADIO) Listen tomorrow
night for the concluding adventure
of the Black Pirate Ship.
Now it's time for Annie's secret message
for you members of the secret circle.
Remember kids, only members
of any secret circle
can decode any secret message.
Remember, Annie is depending on you.
Set your pins to B-2.
Here is the message.
12, 11, 2, 8--
- I am in my first secret meeting.
- (ON RADIO) --25, 14, 11, 18, 16, 23--
- Old Pierre was in great voice tonight.
- (ON RADIO) --12, 23--
- I could tell that tonight's
message was really important
- (ON RADIO) --21, 3, 25.
That's a message from Annie herself.
Remember, don't tell anyone.
[FOOTSTEPS AND PANTING]
- 90 seconds later, I'm in the only
room in the house where a boy of nine
could sit in privacy and decode.
[CHUCKLES] Aha, B. [CHUCKLES] I went
to the next, E. The first word is "be."
S, it was coming easier now.
U. [CHUCKLES] 25, that's R.
- Aw, come on, Ralphie, I gotta go.
- Come on.
- I'll be right down, Ma!
- Gee whiz.
- T, O. "Be sure to."
Be sure to what?
What was Little Orphan
Annie trying to say?
Be sure to what?
- Ralphie, Randy has got to go.
Will you please come out?
- All right, Ma!
I'll be right out!
- I was getting closer now.
The tension was terrible.
What was it?
The fate of the planet
may hang in the balance.
[KNOCKING]
- Ralphie!
Randy's got to go!
- I'll be right out,
for crying out loud!
- [CHUCKLES] Almost there.
My fingers flew.
My mind was a steel trap,
every pore vibrated.
It was almost clear.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
- "Be sure to drink your Ovaltine."
Ovaltine?
A crummy commercial?
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Son of a bi*ch.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right,
that's it for CS50.
We will see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]