[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This CS50 and this is week five.
Recall that last week in week four, we
introduced a few new building blocks,
namely pointers and
spoke in great detail
about how you can now
manipulate a computer's memory
and begin to do things
at a lower level with it.
Well today, we'll sort of use
those basic building blocks
to start creating things called data
structures in the computer's memory.
It turns out that once
you have this ability
to refer to different locations
in the computer's memory,
you can stitch together
your own custom shapes,
your own custom data
structures, as they're called.
And indeed, we'll start
doing that by rolling back
for just a moment to where we first
saw a data structure in week two.
So recall in week two which was
our second week of playing with C,
we introduced you to
the notion of an array.
And an array is just a
contiguous sequence of memory
in which you can store a whole bunch
of integers back to back to back,
or maybe a whole bunch of
chars back to back to back.
And those arrays might have been
represented pictorially like this.
So this would be an array of size 3.
And suppose that this were
an array indeed of integers.
We might have one, two,
three inside of it.
But suppose now-- and here's where we'll
start to bump up against a problem,
but also solve a problem today.
Suppose that you want to add
another number to this array,
but you've only had the forethought
to create an array of size 3.
The catch with arrays in C is that
they're not really easily resizable.
Again, you all know that you have to
decide in advance how big the array is
going to be.
So if you change your mind
later or your program's
running long enough where you
need to store more values in it,
you're in a bind.
Like intuitively, if you wanted to
insert the number 4 into this array,
you would ideally just plop it
right here at the end of the array
and continue about your business.
But the catch with an array is
that that chunk of memory is not--
it doesn't exist in a vacuum.
Recall if we zoom out and look
at all of your computer's memory,
this byte, this byte and a
whole bunch of other bytes
might very well be in
use by other variables
or other aspects of your program.
So for instance for
the sake of discussion,
suppose that the program in question
has one array of size 3 containing
the integers 1, 2 3.
And then suppose that your same program
has a string somewhere in the code
that you've written and that
string is storing hello, world.
Well next to this array
in memory just by chance,
may very well be an H-E-L-L-O
comma space W-O-R-L-D backslash 0.
And there might be free
memory, so to speak.
Memory you could use that's filled with
garbage values and garbage isn't bad.
It just means that you don't know.
You don't really care what
values are or were there.
So there is free space, so to speak.
Each of these Oscars represents
effectively free space
with some garbage value there.
Remnants, maybe, of some execution past.
But the problem here is
that you don't have room
to plop this four right where
you might want to put it.
So what's the solution?
If we have this array of size
3 containing three integers--
1, 2 3-- but it's been painted into a
corner whereby H-E-L-L and so forth are
already immediately next to it, we
can't just put the four there without
sacrificing the H. And that doesn't
really feel like a solution.
So any thoughts on how we
can solve this problem?
Are we completely out of luck?
Can you just not add a number to
an array in a situation like this?
Or is there a solution
perhaps that comes to mind?
Even if you've never programmed
before, if on the screen there--
the lay of the land.
Santiago, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: I would say
that maybe you could
copy the elements in the original
array and create a new array,
but that's one size bigger
or one element bigger.
And then, add that new element.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
That's really good intuition.
After all, there's all
these Oscars on the screen
right now, which again
represent garbage values.
Or in turn, free space.
So I could put 1, 2, 3, 4 up here.
I could put 1, 2, 3, 4 over here.
I could put 1, 2, 3, 4 down here.
So we some flexibility, but
Santiago is exactly right.
Intuitively, all we really
need to do is let's focus only
on four of the available spots.
A new array of size four,
if you will, which initially
has these four garbage values.
But that's OK.
Because as Santiago also
notes, it suffices now
to just copy the old array--
1, 2, 3-- into the new array.
And heck, maybe we can now even free
the memory from the original array,
much like we could if we used malloc.
And that leaves us then, of
course, with just an array of size
4 with that fourth garbage value.
But now, we do have room for,
like the number 4 itself.
So it would seem that there is a
solution to this problem that doesn't
violate the definition of an array.
Again, the only definition
of an array really
is that the memory must be contiguous.
You can't just plop the 4
anywhere in the computer's memory.
It has to become right
after your existing memory
if this whole thing,
this whole structure,
is indeed going to still be an array.
But I worry that might
have cost us a bit of time.
And in fact, let me go ahead
and open up on the screen here
in just a moment a question that
you're all welcome to buzz in for.
What would be the running time
of inserting into an array?
Let me go ahead and reveal
the poll question here.
Feel free to go to the usual URL.
Which Brian, if you wouldn't mind
copying and pasting as usual.
What do you think the running time
is of inserting into an array?
Inserting into an array.
Recall in the past, we talked
about arrays in terms of searching.
But today, this is the
first time we're really
talking about inserting into them.
And if we take a look at the results
coming in, it looks like 80% of you
feel that it's linear
time, big O of n, whereby
it might take as many as n steps
to actually insert into an array.
5% of you propose n log n.
7% of you, n squared.
And then, 2% and 5% respectively
for the other values as well.
So this is kind of an
interesting mix because when
we talked about arrays in the past
and we talked about searching,
recall that we typically
achieve big O of log n.
That's really good.
Unfortunately if we have to
do with Santiago proposed
and actually copy all of the elements
from the old array into the new array,
it's going to take us as many
as n steps because we have
to copy each of the original elements--
1, 2, 3-- over into the new array,
which is going to be of size n plus 1.
So it's on the order
of n steps in total.
So the running time then of
inserting into an array, in terms
of an upper bound at least, is
going to be indeed big O of n
because you've got a copy potentially
all of those elements over.
But perhaps, we might feel
differently if we consider a lower
bound on the running time of insert.
What might the lower bound of
insert be when it comes to an array?
Again, omega notation
is what we can use here.
How many steps maybe in
the best case might it
take me to insert a value into an array?
We won't do a poll for this one.
Brian, why don't we go ahead
and call on a hand for this.
What's a lower bound on
the running time of insert?
Ryan, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: Well, the
best case scenario would
be if there's only one
element in the array.
So you would just have
a one or it would just
be one element right into the array.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so
if you've got an array--
and let me emphasize
that's already empty--
whereby you have room for
the new element, then indeed.
Omega of 1, constant time, is
all you need so long as you
have space available in the array.
And it doesn't matter
how large the array is.
Maybe it's a size 4, but you've
only put one number in it.
That's OK because you can immediately
put the new number in place.
Recall that array support random access.
You can use the square
bracket notation and just
jump to any location in so-called
constant time in just one step.
So if your array is of sufficient
size and it's not full, then yes.
The lower bound on the
insertion into an array
is going to be constant
time, omega of 1.
But as we saw in Santiago's
situation whereby
you have an array that's
already filled with elements
and you want to add
another, well in that case,
then upper bound is indeed
going to be big O of n
because you have to do the additional
labor of copying the values over
from one to the other.
Now those of you have programmed
before, maybe you've use Java.
You might be familiar
with the phrase vector.
A vector is like an array that can
be resized, can grow and shrink.
That's not what arrays in C. Arrays in
C are just contiguous blocks of memory
with values back to back to back.
But once you decide on
their size, that is it.
You're going to have to resize
it, essentially yourself.
They're not going to
automatically grow for you.
So an array was the first and
really the simplest of the data
structures we'll see.
But it's also not nearly
as powerful as what
we can do now that we have
access to a computers memory.
Today, we're going to start to
leverage these things called
pointers, the addresses via which
we can refer to locations in memory.
And we're going to start to stitch
together some fancier data structures--
first, one dimensional in some sense.
Then, two dimensional in some sense-- by
using some very basic building blocks.
Recall these three pieces of
syntax from the past weeks.
Struct, recall, is this
mechanism, this keyword in C,
whereby we can define our
own structures in memory.
We saw one for a person whereby a person
might have both a name and a number
in something like a phone book.
And you've seen the dot
operator The dot operator was
how we go inside of such a structure
and get at dot name or dot number.
The specific variables
inside of the struct.
And then last week, recall
we saw the star operator
whereby the dereference operator,
which colloquially means
go to this particular address.
So just by using these
three ingredients are
we going to be able to now build
up our own custom data structures
that are even fancier than arrays and
can ultimately help us solve problems
more efficiently.
And in fact, this is such a common
technique in programming in C
that these two operators,
the dot and the star,
are often combined into one that
intentionally looks like an arrow.
So we'll see its usage
in just a little bit.
So syntactically today, it's
pretty much building blocks
past but we're going to use these
building blocks now in new ways
to start solving problems differently.
And we'll first do this by way
of something called linked lists.
So for instance, a linked list is going
to be a data structure that solves
some of the problems with an array.
And what's a problem arguably?
Well if it takes big O of n
steps to insert into an array,
frankly that's kind of annoying.
That's kind of expensive.
Because over time if you're writing a
really big program with lots of data--
you're the Googles of the world, the
Twitters of the world-- it's fine
if you want to store all
of your data in a big array
for the sake of efficient searching.
Which recall, was big O of log n if
we use something like binary search
and keep everything sorted.
But it's going to be pretty
painful if every time you
want to add another tweet to the array,
or some other web page to the array.
Depending on what the problem
is that you're solving,
you might potentially--
as Santiago notes--
have to copy all of the contents
of your original smaller array
into a new bigger array just to add more
tweets or more web pages or the like.
So a linked list is going to
be a data structure that's
more dynamic, whereby you
can grow and shrink the data
structure without having to
touch all of the original data
and move it from old location to new.
So what might this look like?
Well let's consider again
our computers memory
and let's propose that I want to
store those same values again.
So like the number one-- and
just for the sake of discussion,
suppose that it's in my computer's
memory at address 0x123.
0x just means it's a hexadecimal number.
1-2-3- is completely arbitrary.
I made it up just for
the sake of discussion.
So let me stipulate that that's
where the number 1 happens
to be in the computer's
memory in this new solution
to the problem of storing lots of data.
Suppose I want to store number 2.
Maybe it's at address 0x456.
And then, suppose I
want to store number 3.
Suppose it's at address 0x789.
So notice deliberately,
these numbers are spread out
in the computer's memory.
Because after all, the problem we
ran into a moment ago with arrays
is that you might have hello, world
or other values from other parts
of your program in the way.
So if I'm proposing
instead that if you want
to store one, and then two,
and then three, that's fine.
Plop them anywhere
you want and you don't
have to worry about where there
is already existing values.
Instead, you can just put these
values where there is room.
The problem, though, is that if you just
start plopping values like one, two,
three anywhere you want
in the computer's memory,
you can no longer very easily
find those values, right?
You might know where
one is, but it no longer
suffices to just look one location
to the right to find the next value
or add two find the
next value after that.
In an array, everything is contiguous.
But if we instead start to
treat the computer's memory
as just a canvas where we can
just draw numbers anywhere
we want, that's fine so
long as we can somehow
help ourselves get from
the first, to the second,
to the third irrespective of
all the other stuff that's
cluttering up the computer's memory.
So in fact, let me propose that
we do this by maybe stealing
a bit more space from the computer.
So rather than use just enough
memory to store one, two, and three,
let me store twice as much information.
In addition to every number that I
actually care about-- one, two, three,
my data--
let me store a little
metadata, so to speak.
The values that I don't
fundamentally care about,
but that are going to help me
keep track of my actual data.
And let me propose
that in this box here,
I literally store the value 0x456.
Again, it's written in hexadecimal,
but that's just the number.
That's the address of
somewhere else in memory.
In this box, let me
propose that I store 0x789.
And in this box, let me arbitrarily
say 0x0, which is just all zero bits.
Now why have I done this?
Even if you've never seen
this structure that's
evolving to be what's
called a linked list,
why have I just done what I've done?
In addition to storing one,
two, and three respectively,
I'm also now storing 0x456 and an
additional chunk of memory and 0x789
and an additional chunk of memory.
But why?
Sofia.
AUDIENCE: So that we know how the
first element relates to the second
or how they're linked together.
DAVID MALAN: That's exactly--
AUDIENCE: --between
the first and second.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So now, I'm using essentially twice as
much space to store each piece of data.
One, two, and three respectively.
But in the second
chunk of space, I'm now
storing a pointer to the next element in
the thing I'll now think of as a list.
So this is 0x456 because
the number two, which
is the next number in the list
I care about, lives at 0x456.
This number is 0x789 because the
next number after that I care about
is at address 0x789.
So it's just a helpful
way now of leaving
myself breadcrumbs so that I can plop
the one, the two, the three anywhere
I want in the computer's memory
wherever there's available space
and still figure out how to get
from one to the other to the other.
And we've actually seen
some of this syntax before.
It turns out that 0x0, which is all
zero bits, that's just the technical--
that's the numeric equivalent
of what we've called null.
N-U-L-L, which we introduced last week,
is a special symbol indicating that
something has gone wrong with
memory or you're out of space.
It's sort of the absence of an address.
C guarantees that if
you use 0x0, AKA null,
that just indicates the absence
of any useful address there.
But you know what?
Again like last week, this is
of getting way into the weeds.
I don't really care about 0x123456789.
So let's just kind of abstract this away
and start thinking about this really
as a list of numbers that
are somehow linked together.
Underneath the hood, the links are
implemented by way of addresses,
or pointers, those low level
numbers like 0x123456789.
But pictorially, it suffices
for us to just start
thinking of this data structure,
hereafter known as a linked list,
as being a collection
of nodes, so to speak--
N-O-D-E-- that are
connected via pointers.
So a node is just a
generic computer science
term that refers to
some kind of structure
that store stuff you care about.
What I care about here is a number and
a pointer to another such structure.
So this is a linked list and each of
these rectangles represents a node.
And in code, we'll implement
those nodes ultimately
by way of that thing
in C called a struct.
But let me pause here
to see first if there
are any questions about the
structure we have built up.
Any questions about this
thing called a linked list
before we see it in some code?
Brian?
BRIAN: Yeah, a question
came in in the chat asking,
isn't this kind of a waste of memory
that we're now using all of these cells
to store addresses too?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
really good observation.
Isn't this kind of a waste
of memory in that we're
storing all of these
addresses in addition
to the numbers 1, 2,
3 that we care about?
Yes, and in fact, that is
exactly the price we are paying,
and this is going to be thematic.
This week, last week and
really every week thereafter,
any time we solve a problem in
CS and programming in particular,
there's always going
to be some price paid.
There's going to be some
cost and really, there's
going to be some trade-off.
So if a moment ago, it was unacceptable
that inserting into an array
is in big O of n because man, that's
going to take so many steps to copy all
of the values from the old
array into the new array,
if that is unacceptable to
you for performance reasons
or whatever the problem is that
you're solving, well, that's fine.
You can solve that problem and
now have much more dynamism
whereby you can plop your
numbers anywhere in memory
without having to move the existing
numbers anywhere else, thereby saving
yourself time, but the price you're
going to pay indeed is more space.
So at that point, it
kind of depends what's
more important to you,
the computer's time,
your human time, or maybe the space or
the cost of the space, the more memory
that you might really need to
literally buy for that computer.
So this is going to be thematic.
This trade-off between space and time
is omnipresent, really, in programming.
Well, let's consider how we might
translate this now into actual code.
Recall that when we
last saw structs in C,
we did something like this to define a
person as having two things associated
with them, a name and a number.
So today, we don't care about
persons and names and numbers.
We care about these things we're
going to start calling nodes,
so let me go ahead and rewind from that.
Erase that and let's instead say
that every node in this structure,
renaming person as
well to node, is going
to have a number, which will
be an int in our case here,
and I've left room for one other
value because we ultimately
need to be able to store
that second piece of data.
That second piece of data
is going to be a pointer.
It's going to be an address
of something, but how might
I express this?
This is going to be
a little less obvious
but we laid the foundation
last week with pointers.
How could I describe
this structure as having
a pointer to another such structure?
Any thoughts on verbally
the syntax to use,
or even if you're not sure of exactly
the incantation, exactly what symbols
we should use to express and
address to another such node?
BRIAN: Someone is suggesting we use
a node * as a pointer to a node.
DAVID MALAN: Node *?
All right.
So * I definitely
remember from last week,
indicating that if you have int
*, this is the address of an int.
If you have char *, this
is the address of a char.
So if all of these arrows really
just represent addresses of nodes,
it stands to reason
that syntax is probably
going to be something akin to node *.
Now I can call this
pointer anything I want.
By convention, I'll call it next.
Because literally,
its purpose in life is
to point to the next node
in the data structure.
And that's going to be in addition to
the int called number that I'll propose
describes the top of that
individual data structure.
But there's a subtle
problem here in C. Recall
that in C, it's kind of a
simplistic language, complicated
though it might often seem, in
that it doesn't understand anything
that it hasn't seen before.
So at the moment, notice
that the very first time
I have mentioned node up
until now was on the very
last line of this snippet of code.
The problem is that by
nature of how typedef works,
the thing called a
node does not actually
exist until the compiler is done
reading that last line of code
and the semicolon, which is
to say that it would actually
be incorrect to use or
refer to quote, unquote
"node" inside of this structure.
Because literally, by
definition of how typedef works,
a node does not exist until, again,
that last line of code and the semicolon
are executed.
Thankfully, there's a workaround.
It's a little weird to look at.
But what you can do in C is this.
You can actually add an additional word
after, literally, the keyword struct.
And we'll keep it simple.
We'll use the exact same word, though
technically that's not necessary.
And now, I'm going to change the inside
of the structure to say this instead.
So it feels a little verbose.
And it feels a little bit of copy paste.
But this is the way it is done in C.
Typedef struct node is essentially
a hint, similar in
spirit to the prototypes
we've talked about for functions
that gives the compiler a clue that,
OK, something called a struct
node is going to exist.
You can then use it inside
of that data structure
and refer to it as struct node *.
It's more of a mouthful this week.
We've not seen multiple words like this.
But it's similar to char *
or int *, like last week.
And I'm going to call
that arbitrarily next.
And down here, the same thing
happens as in the past with persons.
By calling this node at the
very last line of the code, that
just tells the compiler, you know what?
You don't have to refer to it as
struct node all over the place.
You can just call this thing node.
So it's a little verbose in this case.
But all this is done is create
for me, in the computer,
the definition of a node as we
have depicted it pictorially
with that rectangle.
All right, so how can we now translate
this into more useful code, not
just defining what these
structures are, but how
do we begin building up linked lists?
Well, let me propose that a linked
list really begins with just a pointer.
And in fact, here we have, thanks
to the theatre's prop shop,
just kind of a null
pointer, if you will.
I'm going to call this variable "list."
And list is currently
pointing to nothing.
The arrow, we'll say, is just pointing
at the floor, which means it's null.
It's not actually pointing
at anything useful.
Suppose I now want to start
to begin to allocate a linked
list with three numbers, 1, 2, and 3.
Well, how am I going to do this?
Well, at the moment, the only
thing that exists in my program
is going to be this
variable called list.
There's no array in this story.
That was in Week 2.
Today is all about linked lists.
So how do I get myself
a wooden block that
represents 1, another wooden
block that represents 2,
and a third that represents 3?
Well, we need to use our new
friend from last week, malloc.
Recall that malloc allows
you to allocate memory,
as much memory as you might
want, so long as you tell it
the size of that thing.
So frankly, I think what we
could do ultimately today
is use malloc to allocate dynamically
one struct and put the number 1 in it,
another struct put the number 2 on it,
another struct put the number 3 in it.
And then, use these playful arrows
here to actually stitch them together,
having one point to the other.
So thankfully, the prop
shop has wonderfully
created a whole bunch of these for us.
Let me go ahead and malloc a very heavy
node that has room for two values.
And you'll see it has room for
a number and a next pointer.
So the number I'm going
to first install here
is going to be the
number 1, for instance.
And I'm going to leave its pointer
as just pointing at the ground,
indicating that this is a null pointer.
It's not actually
pointing at anything else.
But now that I'm
starting to instantiate,
that is create this list, now I'm
going to do something like this
and say that, all right, my variable
called "list," whose purpose in life
is to keep track of where
this list is in memory,
I'm going to connect one to
the other by actually having
this variable point at this node.
When it comes time, then,
to allocate another node,
I want to insert into this linked list.
Back in the world of arrays, I might
have to allocate a new chunk of memory,
copy this value over
into the new values.
I don't have to do that.
In the world of linked lists, I
just call malloc for a second time
and say, give me another chunk of
memory big enough to fit a node.
Thankfully, from the prop shop,
we have another one of these.
Let me go ahead and
malloc another node here.
At the moment, there's nothing in it.
It's just the placeholder.
So it's garbage values, if you will.
I don't know what's
there until I actually
say that the number shall be number 2.
And then I go over to my linked
list whose variable name is "list,"
and I want to insert this thing.
So I follow the arrow.
I then point the next field of
this node at this node here.
So now I have a linked list of size 2.
There's three things in the picture,
but this is just a simple variable.
This is a pointer that's pointing at
the actual node which, in turn, is
pointing at an actual other node.
Now suppose I want to insert the
number 3 into this linked list.
Recall that malloc is
powerful and that it
takes memory from
wherever it's available,
the so-called "heap" from your computer.
And that means, by definition,
that it might not be contiguous.
The next number might not
actually be here metaphorically
in the computer's memory.
It might be way over there.
So that might indeed happen.
The third time I call malloc
now and allocate a third node,
it might not be available anywhere
in the computer's memory except for,
like, way over here.
And that's fine.
It doesn't have to be contiguous as
it did in the world of our arrays.
I can now put the number 3 in its place.
But if I want to keep a pointer to
that node, so that all of these things
are stitched together, I
can start at the beginning.
I follow the arrows.
And now, if I want to
remember where that one is,
I'm going to have to
connect these things.
And so now, that pointer needs
to point at this block here.
And this visual is very much deliberate.
These nodes can be anywhere
in the computer's memory.
They're not necessarily
going to be contiguous.
The downside of that is that you
cannot rely on binary search,
our friend from Week 0 onward.
Binary search was amazing
in that it's Big O of log n.
You can find stuff way
faster than Big O of n.
That was the whole point
of even the phonebook
example in the very first week.
But the upside of this
approach is that you
don't have to actually keep
allocating and copying more memory
and all of your values any time
you want to resize this thing.
And I'm a little embarrassed to admit
that I'm out of breath for some reason,
just mallocing nodes here.
But the point is using
malloc and building out
the structure does come at some price.
It's exhausting, frankly.
But it's also going to
spread things out in memory.
But you have this dynamism.
And honestly, if you are the
Twitters of the world, the Googles
of the world, where you
have lots and lots of data,
it's going to kill you performance
wise to have to copy all of your data
from one location into
another as Santiago originally
proposed as a solution to the array.
So using these dynamic data
structures, like a linked list, where
you allocate more space
wherever it's available,
and you somehow remember where that
is by stitching [? team ?] things
together, as with these
physical pointers,
is really the state
of the art in how you
can create these more dynamic
structures if it's more important to you
to have that dynamism.
All right, any questions before we
now translate these physical blocks
to some samples of code?
BRIAN: A question came in in the chat.
When in this whole process of linked
lists are we actually using malloc?
And what is malloc being used for?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
So where are we using malloc?
Every time I went off
stage and grabbed one
of these big blocks, that was my acting
out the process of mallocing a node.
So when you call malloc,
that returns to you,
per last week, the address of the
first byte of a chunk of memory.
And if you call malloc of one, that
gives you the address of one byte.
If you call malloc of 100, that
gives you the first address
of 100 bytes that are contiguous.
So each of these nodes, then, represents
the return value, if you will,
of a single call to malloc.
And in fact, perhaps,
Brian, the best way
to answer that question in more
detail is to translate this now
to some actual code.
So let's do that now and then revisit.
So here is, for instance,
a line of code that
represents the beginning
of our story, where we only
had a variable called "list" that
was initialized to nothing initially.
This arrow was not pointing at anything.
And in fact, if it was just
pointing up, down, left,
or right, it would be
considered a garbage value.
This is just memory, which means
there are values inside of it
before I actually put
actual values in it.
So if I don't assign it a value,
who knows what it's pointing to?
But let me go ahead and change the code.
This list variable, by default, has some
garbage value unless I initialize it
to something like null.
So I'll represent that here figuratively
by just pointing at the ground.
That now represents null.
This would be the corresponding
line of code that just
creates for you an empty linked list.
That was the beginning of the story.
Now recall that the next thing
I did was I went off stage
and I called malloc to bring
back one of these big boxes.
That code might instead look like this.
Node *n.
So I could call the variable anything
I want, malloc, size of node.
So size of we might have seen
briefly in that it's just
an operator in C that tells you how
many bytes large any data type is.
So I could do the math and figure out
in my Mac or PC or CS50 IDE just how
many bytes these nodes
are supposed to take up.
Size of just answers
that question for me.
So malloc, again, takes
one argument, the number
of bytes you want to
allocate dynamically,
and it returns to the address
of the first of those bytes.
So if you think of this as one
of my earlier slides in yellow,
it returns to you, like,
the address of the top
left byte of this chunk
of memory, if you will.
And I'm going to go ahead
and assign that to a variable
I'll call n to represent a node.
And its node * because, again,
malloc returns always an address.
And the syntax we saw last
week for storing addresses
is to use this new * syntax here.
So this gave me a block that
initially just had garbage values.
So there was no number in place and who
knows where the arrow was pointing at?
So it looked a little something like
this, if I draw it now on the screen.
List is initialized to null.
It's not pointing at anything right now.
But n, the variable I just
declared, is pointing at a node.
But inside of that
node, or who knows what?
It's garbage values.
Number and next are just garbage values.
Because that's what's there by
default, remnants of the past.
But now, let me propose
that we do this code.
So long as n is not null--
which is something you want to get
into the habit always now of checking,
any time in C, when you call a
function that returns to you a pointer,
you should almost always check
is it null or is it not null.
Because you do not want to try
touching it if it is indeed null.
Because that means there
is no valid address here.
That's the human convention
when using pointers.
But if n does not equal
null, that's a good thing.
That means it's a valid address
somewhere in the computer's memory.
Let me go ahead now and go to that
address, the syntax for which is *n,
just like last week.
And then the operator means go
inside of the structure that's there
and go into the variable inside
of it, called number in this case.
So when I go ahead and
do something like this,
when I have a list that's
initially of size 1,
where this variable is pointing at
the one and only node at the moment,
it's going to have the number 1 in it
as soon as I execute this line of code.
*n means start at the address
embodied here, go to it,
and then put the number,
1 in this case, in place.
But I need to do one
other thing as well.
I want to go ahead, too,
and replace the garbage
value that represents the
next pointer in that structure
and replace it with null.
Null [INAUDIBLE] find that
this is the end of the list.
There's nothing there.
I don't want it to be garbage value.
Because a garbage value
is an arbitrary number
that could be pointing this
way, this way, this way.
Metaphorically, I want to
actually change that to be null
and so I can use the same syntax.
But there's this clever approach now.
I don't have to use star and then dot
over the place, as mentioned earlier.
Star and dot comes with
some syntactic sugar.
You can replace the star and
the parentheses and the dot
that we just saw with an arrow
notation, which means follow the arrow.
And then set this thing
equal to null, which
I'll represent again by just
having the arrow literally points
at the floor for clarity.
So, again, rewinding from
where we started, *n.number,
with the first of those in
parentheses, is the same thing as this.
And the reason that most people prefer
using the arrow notation, so to speak,
is that it really does
capture this physicality.
You start at the address,
you go there, and then
you look at the field,
number or next, respectively.
But it's equivalent to the syntax we saw
a moment ago with the start and the dot
as before.
So after these two steps,
have we initialized
this node to containing the
number 1 and null inside of it.
But what comes next?
What comes next?
Well, at point in the
story, in this code,
I have some other variable
here that's not pictured.
Because we're now transitioning from
the world of woodwork to actual code.
So there's another variable n, which I
might as well be representing myself.
If I am this temporary variable n,
I, too, am pointing at this value.
It's not until I actually execute
this line of code, list = n;,
that I remember where this node
is in the computer's memory.
So n, up until now, has really
just been a temporary variable.
It's a variable that I
can use to actually keep
track of this thing in memory.
But if I want to add this node
ultimately to my linked list,
list started out as null, recall
that this pointer was pointing
at the ground, representing null.
But when I now want to remember that
this linked list has a node in it,
I need to actually execute a line
of code like this, list = null.
All right, what did we next do?
Let's take one more step further.
So at this point in the story,
if I was representing n,
I'm also pointing at the
same block. n is temporary,
so it can eventually go away.
But at this point in the story,
we have a linked list of size 1.
Let's go ahead and take this further.
Suppose now I execute
these lines of code.
And we'll do it a little
faster and all at once so
that you can see it more in context.
The first line of code
is the same as before.
Hey, malloc, give me a
chunk of memory that's
big enough for the size of a node.
And, again, let's use this temporary
variable n to point to that.
And suppose that means that I, if I'm
representing this temporary variable,
I'm pointing at this new
chunk of memory here.
I then check, if n does
not equal null, then
and only then do I go ahead
and install the number
2 as I did physically earlier and do
I initialize the pointer originally
to pointing not at some other node which
doesn't yet exist, but pointing at,
let's just call it the floor,
thereby representing null.
And that's it.
That has now allocated the second node.
But notice, literally, this disconnect.
Just because I've allocated
a new node and put
the number I care about and
initialized its next pointer to null,
that doesn't mean it's
part of the data structure.
The linked list is still missing
a pointer from old to new.
So we need to execute
one other line of code
now so that we can get from this
picture ultimately to the final one.
And here's where we can use the
same kind of syntax as before.
If I start at my list variable, I
follow the arrow as per that code.
And then I update the
next field to point
to n, which is my newly allocated node.
Now, after that final line of code,
do I have a linked list of size 2.
Because I've not only allocated
the node, initialized its two
variables, a number
and next respectively,
I've also chained it together with
the existing node on the linked list.
And let me do this one
even slightly more quickly,
only because it's the same thing, just
so we can see it all together at once.
Now that we have this picture, let's
execute the same kind of code again.
The only difference
in this chunk of code
is that I'm initializing number to 3.
So what has this done for me?
That chunk of code has malloced
a third and final node.
I've initialized the
top to the number 3.
bottom to null, as I'll
represent by just pointing
the arrow at the ground.
There's one final step, then.
If I want to go ahead and insert that
third node into this linked list,
I've got to go ahead now and
not just point it at myself,
me representing, again, the temporary
variable n, I need to now do this.
And this is syntax you won't do often.
We'll see it in an actual
program in just a moment.
But it just speaks to the basic
building blocks we're manipulating.
If I want to go ahead and link the 2
to the 3, I can start here at list.
I can follow the arrow once.
I can follow the arrow again.
And then I can set that
next field equal to n.
Because, again, n is the current address
of that most recently allocated node.
So even though the syntax is getting
a little new, the two arrows I'm using
are literally just like a
code manifestation of just
follow the pointer, follow the pointer,
boom, assign one value to the next.
All right, so at this point in the
story, the picture now looks like this.
So long as I, n, am
still in the picture.
But if I just get rid
of myself, because I'm
a temporary variable, voila,
we've just built up, step by step,
a brand new linked list of size 3.
Seems like a lot of work, but it allows
us to now grow this thing dynamically.
But let me pause here.
Any questions or
confusion on linked lists?
confusions on linked lists?
BRIAN: One question
just came in the chat.
If we're trying to make a list
that's going to be much longer, like,
more than three elements,
wouldn't it get tedius to have,
like, arrow next, arrow
next over and over again?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Really good observation.
And so that's why I said, you
won't usually write it like this.
We'll do it temporarily in a
full-fledged program in just a moment
just to demonstrate it.
But in general, you'll probably
use something like a loop.
And what you'll do is use a temporary
variable that points at this one,
then iterates again,
then iterates again.
And let me stipulate for now that
if you use a loop in the right way,
you can end up writing
just a single arrow by just
keep updating the
variable again and again.
So there is a way to avoid that.
And you do it much more dynamically.
Let me go ahead then and ask
you a question of my own here.
Let me go ahead and ask this one.
If you'd like to buzz
in to this question,
what is the running time
of searching a linked list?
What's the running time of searching
a linked list in Big O notation?
So what's an upper bound,
worst case of searching
a linked list like this one, whether it
has three elements or even many more?
So it looks like, as before,
about 80% of the group
is proposing that it's Big O of n.
And this is actually correct.
Because consider the worst case.
Suppose you're looking
for the number 3, you're
going to have to look at all
three numbers, Big O of n.
If you're looking for
the number 10, you're
going to start here at
the beginning, you're
going to keep looking,
looking, looking, looking.
You're going to get to the end realize,
oh, the number 10 is not even here.
At which point, you've
already looked at n elements.
But here's one of the trade,
again, of linked lists.
With arrays, you could jump to the
end of the list in constant time.
You could just use a
little bit of arithmetic.
You could jump to the middle
elements, or the first element,
all using constant time.
A linked list, unfortunately,
is represented ultimately
by just a single address, the address
that points to the very first node.
And so even though you all on camera
can see this node and this node
and this one as humans
all at once, the computer
can only follow these breadcrumbs.
And so searching a linked list is
going to be Big O of n in that case.
But let me ask a follow up question.
What's the running time of
inserting into a linked list?
So you've got some new number like the
number 4 or 0 or 100 or negative 5,
whatever it may be.
There's going to be a malloc
involved, but that's constant time.
It's just one function call.
But you're going to have
to insert it somewhere.
And here it looks like 68% of
you are proposing Big O of 1,
which is interesting, constant time.
25% of you are proposing Big O of n.
Would anyone be comfortable
chiming in verbally or on the chat
as to why you feel
it's one or the other?
It is indeed one of those answers.
AUDIENCE: It could be O of n.
Because of the fact
that even though you're
using malloc to create
a new node, essentially,
I think all the computer's doing
when you assign it is [? going-- ?]
as you cite those arrows, like we're
going from one arrow to the next
to the next to the next.
And I would think it would be O of n.
DAVID MALAN: It is O of
n as you described it.
But you, too, are making an assumption,
like 25% of other people are making.
You seem to be assuming that if a
new number, suppose it's number 4,
has to go at the end.
Or if it's the number 5,
it has to go at the end.
And I kind of deliberately
set things up that way.
I've happened to maintain them in sorted
order, 1, 2, 3, from left to right.
But up until now, I have
not made the condition
that the linked list
has to be sorted, even
though the examples we've seen
thus far are deliberately that way.
But you know what, if you want to get
fancy and a little more efficient,
and you want to allocate the number
4, and frankly, you don't really
care about keeping the
linked list in sorted order,
well, heck, just pull this
out, put your new node here.
Plug it in here.
Plug the other one back in here.
And just insert the new element
at the beginning of the list.
And for every number
thereafter, malloc as before.
But just keep inserting it here,
inserting it here, inserting it here.
Now it's not going to
take a single step.
Because as I verbalized it,
there's, like, the malloc step.
I have to unplug this.
I have to plug it back in.
So it's like three or four steps total.
But four steps is also constant.
That's big O of 1, because
it's a fixed number of steps.
So if you're able to sacrifice sorted
order when it comes to this list,
you can in constant time
insert, insert, insert, insert.
And the list is going to get longer and
longer, but from the beginning of it
rather than the end.
So that's always a trade off.
If you don't care about sorted order,
and none of your algorithms or code
require that it be sorted, then you
can go ahead and cut that corner
and achieve constant time
insert, which if you're
a Twitter or Google or the
like, maybe that's actually
a net savings and a good thing.
But, again, you sacrifice the
sorted order in that case.
Well, let's go ahead, I think.
And let's translate this
to some actual code.
Let me go ahead here in CS50 IDE.
And let's go ahead and
write a couple of variants
of a program that now actually
do something with numbers
and start to manipulate
things in memory.
So I'm going to go ahead here and
create a program called list.c.
And my first version is
going to be very simplistic.
I'm going to go ahead and include stdio.
Give myself an int main(void).
And then inside of here, let
me go ahead, like we began,
and give myself a list
of integers of size 3.
So this is going to be an
array that's of size 3.
And this array of size 3, I'm
going to go ahead and hard
code some new values into it.
So at the very first location,
I'll put the number 1.
At the second location,
I will put the number 2.
At the third location,
I will put the number 3.
And then, just to demonstrate that
this is working as I think I intend,
I'm going to do a quick for loop.
So for int i get 0, i less than 3, i++.
And then, inside this loop, I'm
going to go ahead and print out %i.
And then I'm going to
print out the value of i.
So now that I've printed out all
of these values in my loop, let
me go ahead and do make list.
Let me go ahead then and
do ./list and hit Enter.
And indeed, I get--
oops, not what I wanted.
So good teachable moment,
not intended, admittedly.
But what have I done wrong here?
My goal is we print out the list.
But somehow, I printed out 0, 1, 2.
And those are indeed not
the numbers in this list.
[? Greg? ?]
AUDIENCE: So you printed i.
You should have printed list of i.
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
So I should have printed the contents
of the array, which is list[i].
So that was just a newbie
mistake by me here.
So let me fix that.
Let me go ahead and recompile
make list, ./list., and voila.
I've now printed the list.
So this is sort of Week 2 stuff, when
we first introduced arrays in Week 2.
But now let me go ahead and transition
now to something more dynamic.
Where I don't have to commit in
advance to creating an array,
I can do this with a dynamically
allocated chunk of memory.
So let me delete everything
I've done inside of main.
And let me go ahead
and give myself this.
Let me go ahead and
declare a list of values
where list is now going to be an
address as per the star operator.
And I'm going to go ahead and malloc--
let's see.
I want space for three integers.
So the simplest way to do this, if
I'm just going to keep it simple,
I can actually do this,
3 times size of int.
So this version of my program
isn't going to use an array per se.
It's going to use malloc.
But it's going to dynamically
allocate that array for me.
And we'll see what the
syntax for this is.
As always now, any
time you use malloc, I
should check whether
list equals equals null.
And if so, you know what?
I'm just going to return 1.
Recall that you can return
0 or 1 or some other value
from main to effectively
quit your program.
I'm going to go ahead and
just return 1 if list is null,
just assuming that something very badly
went wrong, like I'm out of memory
altogether.
But now that I have this chunk
of memory that's of size 3 times
the size of an int, this is actually the
malloc way to give yourself an array.
Up until now, every time we've
created arrays for ourselves,
we've used square bracket notation.
And you all have put a number
inside the square brackets
to give yourself an array of that size.
But frankly, if we have
malloc and the ability
to just ask the computer
for memory, well,
if I want to store three
integers, why don't I ask malloc
for three times the size of an integer?
And the way malloc
works is it's actually
going to return to me a contiguous
chunk of memory of that size,
so that many bytes back to back to back.
And that's a technique that
we'll use in just a moment
when allocating actual nodes.
So at this point in the story, so
long as list does not equal null,
I now have a chunk of memory that's big
enough to fit the size of three ints.
And as before, I can go
ahead and initialize those.
The first element will be 1.
The second element will be 2.
The third element will be 3.
And notice the sort of equivalence
now between using arrays
and using pointers.
C is kind of versatile in
this way and that if you
have a chunk of memory returned to
you by malloc, you can, per last week,
use square bracket notation.
You can use square bracket notation and
treat that chunk of memory as an array.
Because after all, what's an array?
It's a contiguous block of memory and
that is exactly what malloc returns.
If you want to be fancy instead, you
could actually say go to that address
and put the number 1 there.
You could say go to that address
plus 1 and put the next number there.
You could say go to that address plus
2 and put the third number there.
But honestly, this just very
quickly becomes unreadable, at least
to most people.
This is that thing called
pointer arithmetic,
you're doing arithmetic
with pointers, that
is equivalent to using the syntax
that we've used for a while now, which
is to just use the square brackets.
And the nice thing
about square brackets is
that the computer will
figure out for you
how far apart each of those integers
are because it knows the size of an int.
But now, at this point
in the story, things
get interesting and also annoying.
And Santiago, recall, was the one
that helped us solve this earlier.
Suppose I didn't plan ahead.
I only allocated three
integers on line five there.
But now, at line 13,
I'm, like, oh, dammit.
Now I want to add a fourth
integer to the list.
I could obviously just
redo all the code.
But suppose that part of the
story here is to go ahead
and dynamically allocate more memory.
Well, how can I do this?
Well, let me go ahead and allocate
another chunk of memory temporarily.
So I'll call it temp, by convention.
And this time I'm going to go ahead
and allocate 4 times size of int.
Because, again, for the sake
of the story, I messed up
and I want to allocate enough
space now for that original--
I haven't so much messed up.
I have now decided that I want to
add a fourth number to this array.
As always, I should check
if temp equals equals null.
You know what?
I'm going to go ahead and free
the memory I already allocated.
And then I'm just going to
get out of here, return 1.
Something went wrong.
There's nothing to demonstrate.
So I'm going to exit
out of main entirely.
But if malloc did not return null, and
all is well, what am I going to do?
Well, let's first do
what Santiago proposed
when we first began this conversation.
For int i get 0, i less than 3, i++,
let's go ahead and copy into this new,
temporary chunk of memory whatever
is at the original chunk of memory.
So when Santiago proposed
that we copy 1, 2,
3 from the old array into
the new array, here's
how we might do that in code just
using a simple for loop, a la Week 2.
And then let me go ahead now
and add one more value, tmp[3],
which is the fourth location
if you're starting from 0.
I'm going to go ahead and
put the number 4 there.
And now, at this point, I'm
going to go ahead and remember
the fact that tmp is my new list.
So I'm going to go ahead
and free the original list.
And I'm going to update my old
list to point at the new list.
And then lastly, I'm going to go
ahead and use another for loop just
to demonstrate that I think I did this
correctly, this time iterating up to 4
instead of 3.
I'm going to go ahead and print
out with i the contents of list[i].
So let's rewind real quick.
We began the story by allocating
an array of three integers.
But we did it this time dynamically
to demonstrate that malloc just
returns a chunk of memory.
And if you want to treat that chunk of
memory as an array, you absolutely can.
This stuff here, if
list equals equals null,
it's just error checking, just to
make sure that nothing went wrong.
The interesting code resumes here.
I'm putting the numbers 1, 2, and 3
at location 0, 1, and 2 respectively
in that chunk of memory which,
again, I'm treating like an array.
But now at this point in the story,
I've stipulated that, wait a minute,
I want to go ahead and
add a fourth value.
How can I do that?
And let's stipulate that I want to go
back and change the existing program.
Because suppose that for
the sake of discussion,
this is code that's running
at Google or Twitter over time
and it's only after receiving another
tweet that their code realizes,
oh, we need more space.
So how do I do this here?
On line 15, this time I allocate
enough space for four integers.
And I, again, do some error checking.
If tmp equals null, then
something bad happened.
Let's just exit all together.
But if nothing bad happened,
let's take Santiago's suggestion
and translate his English advice into
C. Let's use a for loop from 0 to 3
and copy into this new
temporary chunk of memory
the contents of the
original chunk of memory.
So tmp[i] = list[i].
And then here, which was
the point of this exercise,
let me add my fourth number at tmp[3],
which is the fourth location if you
start counting from 0.
But at this point in the story,
much like my earlier slide,
I have both the 1, 2, 3
in an array of size 3,
and I have 1, 2, 3 duplicated
in the array of size 4.
Let me go ahead and free the original
list and give back to the computer
that original chunk of memory.
Let me then remember,
using my better names
variable, what the address of
this new chunk of memory is.
And then, just to show
off, let me go ahead,
and with another for loop, this
time counting four times, not three,
let me print out all of those values.
Now here's where I'll cross my
fingers, compile my new program.
It does not compile OK.
Because it looks like I have
one too many parentheses there.
So let's recompile the
program with make list--
another error.
So let me scroll up there.
And oh, interesting, so this is a common
mistake, implicitly declaring library
function malloc something something.
So any time you get an
implicitly declaring error,
odds are it means you just did
something simple like this,
you forgot the requisite header file
in which that function is defined.
And indeed, recall from last week,
malloc is in standard lib, as is free.
So now let's do make list.
Cross my fingers again.
Phew.
That time it worked.
./list, voila, 1, 2, 3, 4.
So this is now a completely
literal translation
of all of that code
into a working program
that, again, starts off by
using an array of size 3,
having dynamically allocated it.
And then it resizes it by creating a
new one of size 4, copying old into new,
freeing the old, and then
proceeding as before.
And I've deliberately used malloc
both times here as follows.
If you create an array in C
using square bracket notation,
you have painted yourself into a corner.
You can't use any lines
of code that we have seen
and resize an array that you have
declared using square brackets.
More technically speaking, when
you use the square brackets,
you are statically allocating
the array on the stack.
You're putting it into the
frame of the computer's memory
that belongs to that computer, to that
function's stack frame, per the diagram
last week.
If, however, you use malloc,
our new tool from last week,
and say give me a chunk of
memory, that comes from the heap.
And that you can resize.
That you can give back and take
more of and back and forth.
And in fact, there's even a more simple
way of doing this, relatively speaking.
If you want to reallocate an array,
a chunk of memory, by resizing it,
you don't have to do all of
this, which I did before.
You don't have to use malloc twice.
You can use malloc
once at the beginning.
And then, you can use
a new function that's
actually kind of helpful in
this case, called realloc.
And you can actually do this, realloc
a chunk of memory of size 4 times
size of int.
But specifically, reallocate
the thing called list.
So realloc is very similar to malloc.
But it takes two arguments.
One is the size of the memory you
want, whether bigger or smaller.
But it takes a second argument.
Its very first argument now is
the address of a chunk of memory
that you have already
allocated, as with malloc.
So, again, at the top
of the same program,
recall that I used malloc to give myself
a list that points at a chunk of memory
big enough for three integers.
On line 16, I'm now handing that address
back to realloc, saying, wait a minute,
here is that same address you gave me.
Please now resize it,
reallocate it to be of size 4.
And what the function
does is, if all goes well,
it returns to the address in memory
that it is now of sufficient size.
Otherwise, it returns null
if anything bad happened.
So I'll leave that code alone.
But what I don't have
to do anymore is this.
Realloc actually copies the
old into the new for you.
So, again, coming back to Santiago's
story at the beginning of today,
realloc will not only
give you a bigger chunk
of memory, if you ask for it, by handing
back the address of the memory you
already requested.
And it's going to hand you back the
address of a new chunk of memory
that is big enough to fit
all of those new values.
And it's smart, too.
If there happens to be room at the very
end of the existing chunk of memory,
there's no hello, world, like
we saw on my slide earlier,
then you're actually going to
get back the exact same address.
But the computer's operating
system, Windows, Mac, OS, or Linux,
is going to remember, OK, yes, I know
I gave you three bytes originally.
There happened to be room at
the end of that chunk of memory.
So now I'm going to remember,
instead, that that same address has
room for four integers, or
whatever number you pass in.
So, again, you don't have
to bother copying yourself.
You can let the computer actually
do the reallocation for you.
Any questions, then on malloc, on
realloc, on free, or fundamentally,
on linked lists?
Notice that this isn't yet a list.
This is still an array.
So we still need to take
this program one step further
and actually transition
from this chunk of memory
using arrays to these actual nodes.
But before we do that, any
questions or confusion?
BRIAN: Yeah.
A question came in, why do you not need
to free tmp at the end of the program?
DAVID MALAN: Why do I not need to
free tmp at the end of the program?
Because I'm an idiot and glossed
over that key, important detail.
You absolutely should free not
tmp in this case, but list.
So at this line here, 27, I use my list
variable, which just has a better name,
and I make it equal to tmp so that I
can just refer to it as a bigger list.
But you are quite right.
That was an oversight on my part.
Valgrind would not have liked that.
At the very end of this program,
I should absolutely free list.
However, I don't need
to free tmp, per se,
because I've simply reused the
variable name through that assignment.
Good question and good catch.
Unintended.
Other questions or comments, Brian?
BRIAN: Question came in, why
does the linked list improve
this situation if we can just use
arrays and realloc and malloc to do
all this stuff?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Really good question.
So how have we improved this situation
if we can just use arrays in this way?
Recall that this is
kind of a regression.
What I just did is a regression to
where we started the story, whereby
in any of the versions
of code I just wrote,
I reallocated more space for this array.
Which means that I, manually with
that for loop, or realloc with its own
for loop, had to copy all of
the old values into the new.
So the approach we've taken in
all three versions of this program
that I've written thus far on the
fly, they've all been Big O of n.
When it comes to inserts, they have not
given us the dynamism of a linked list
to just add without that duplication.
And we haven't had the ability yet
to just do an insert, for instance,
at the beginning of the
structure in Big O of 1 time.
So, again, this is the
code translation, really,
of that slower approach
from which we began.
So the ultimate goal now is
going to be to change this code
and give us that dynamism and actually
implement things as a proper linked
list, not just as an array of integers.
But we're about an hour in.
Let's go ahead and take our
first five minute break here.
And when we come back, we'll translate
the nodes themselves to a full program.
All right, we are back.
And recall that we began today by
revisiting arrays and pointing out
that searching is great in
arrays if you keep them sorted.
You get the Big O of log n
that we liked back from Week 0.
But as soon as you want to start
dynamically modifying an array,
it gets very expensive quickly.
It might take you Big
O of n steps to copy
the contents of an old, small
array into a new, bigger array.
And honestly, over time, especially for
real world software with lots of data,
even Big O of n is expensive.
Like, you don't want to be constantly
copying and copying and copying
all of your data around
the computer's memory.
So we can avoid that by
using pointers and, in turn,
stitching together these
structures called linked lists,
albeit at a price of
spending more memory.
But with that additional memory,
that additional cost, comes dynamism.
So that if we want we can
even achieve constant time
when it comes to inserting.
But of course, then we have to
sacrifice things like sortability.
So this came with trade offs.
We've just seen a few
examples of actual C programs
that implement first the old
school array, per Week 0,
where we just hardcode
the array's length.
And unfortunately, we painted
ourselves into a corner,
using the bracket notation alone.
So we deployed instead m which
is more versatile tool that
lets us get as much memory as we want.
And we used that to recreate the
idea of a list implemented as arrays.
But even then, we saw that I
had to copy using a for loop
or we had to copy using,
indirectly, realloc, old into new.
And, again, for these small programs,
you don't even notice the difference.
The programs run like that.
But for large, real world software,
all of that Big O of n time
is going to add up quickly.
So it's best if we can try to avoid
it altogether and achieve dynamism.
So the code via which you can
add to linked list dynamically
is actually part of the challenge
for Problem Set 5 this coming week.
But let's see some of the building
blocks via which we can syntactically
start to allocate nodes and
stitch them together when
we know in advance how many we want.
Which is not going to be
the case for Problem Set 5,
but for now is indeed the case, because
I only want three of these things.
So I'm going to go back
to my program from before.
And I'm going to rewind and
race everything inside of main.
And I'm going to go
ahead and declare myself
a type called struct node initially with
a number inside of it and a struct node
* called next inside of that.
And then I'm going to call this
whole thing quite simply node.
So that's quite similar to
what we did with a person.
But now it's a little fancier in
that I'm giving the structure itself
a temporary name, struct node.
I'm referring to that temporary
name inside of the structure
so that I can have a pointer there, too.
And then I'm renaming what
was person to now node.
Now let's go ahead and actually
use this thing inside of main.
So let me go ahead and
create an empty linked list.
The simplest way to translate the simple
block with which we began today is just
doing node *list;.
Unfortunately, any time
you declare a variable
that does not have an
assigned value, it's garbage.
And garbage is bad in
the world of pointers.
Again, to be clear, if you
create this variable called list
and you do not explicitly
initialize its value
to be something like null
pointing at the ground,
but instead leave it as
a garbage value, it's
the sort of metaphorical
equivalent of this arrow pointing
this way, this way, this other way.
That is to say you might
accidentally, in your own code,
follow this arrow to a
completely bogus place.
And that's the point at which you have
what are called segmentation faults,
as some of you might have experienced
already with Problem Set 4 when you
touch memory that you shouldn't.
So garbage values are bad
ever more so in the context
of pointers for that reason.
So you rarely want to do this.
You almost always want to initialize
the pointer to some known value.
In the absence of an
actual address, we're
going to use null to indicate
that there's nothing there.
But that's deliberate on our part.
Now, suppose I want to insert,
just as I did physically
by lugging the block number 1
onto stage before, let me go ahead
and allocate a node-- we'll
call it n temporarily--
using malloc, this time
asking for the size of a node.
So the story is now changing.
I'm not allocating individual ints.
I'm allocating individual nodes inside
of which is enough room for an integer
and another pointer to a node.
And this size of operator
figures out, from the definition
of this structure up here
above main, how much space
is needed to store an integer
and a pointer to a struct node.
So as always now, I'm
always going to check.
If n equals equals null, I'm
going to get out of this program
immediately, and just return 1.
Because something went wrong, and
there's just not enough memory.
But if all went well, I'm going to
go ahead now and go into that node n.
I'm going to go into its number
field and assign it the value 1.
And I'm going to go into that node n
and go into its next field and, for now,
assign it the value null.
So this is as though I've just allocated
the wooden block with a 1 in it
and I have initialized
its next pointer to null.
Now I'm going to go ahead and update
the list itself to point at that value.
So, again, my variable called
list is the variable via which
I'm representing the whole list.
And now that I have an
actual node to point to,
I'm setting list which, again, is a
pointer, to a node, equal to whatever
n is, the address of an actual node.
So at this point in the story, I
have the small wooden block connected
to the larger block containing 1.
Let's suppose, for the
sake of discussion,
I now want to add the number 2
to this list, this time using
a node as well, not just an integer.
I'm going to go ahead and
allocate n, using malloc,
giving myself the size of another node.
I'm going to again just going
to check if that thing equals
null let me go ahead and free
the list so I don't leak memory.
Then let me go ahead and return 1.
So that's just a quick
sanity check to make
sure I free any memory I've
already allocated before.
But if all goes well, and
that's what I'm hoping for,
I'm going to go ahead and go into this
node n and store in its number field
literally the number 2.
And then now, because this thing--
I'll insert it in sorted order for now--
I'm going to go ahead and
insert this next = NULL.
And if I indeed want to put this
number 2 node after the number 1 node,
I can start at the top of the
list, I can go to the next node.
And inside of its value, I can say n.
So this line of code here starts at
the little block, follows the arrow,
and then updates the next pointer
of that first node, the 1 node,
to instead store the
address of this new node, n.
And then lastly, let's do one more
of these so n = malloc(sizeof(node));
one last time.
Let me go ahead and do my
sanity check one more time.
If n = = NULL something bad happened.
So now I'm going to go ahead and
don't worry about the syntax just yet.
But I'm going to go
ahead and free list next.
And I'm going to go
ahead and free(list);
and then I'm going to
go ahead and return 1.
But more on that another time.
That's just in the corner case
where something bad happened.
But if nothing bad happened, I'm going
to update the number field to be 3.
I'm going to update the
next field to be NULL.
And now I'm going to
update the list next block
next block to equal this new one n.
And then here, after this, I can proceed
to print all of these things if I want.
And in fact, I'll go ahead
and do this with a loop.
The loop is going to look a little
different from before in this case.
But it turns out we can use for
loops pretty powerfully here, too.
But at this point in the
story, my list pointer
is pointing at the 1 node,
which is pointing at the 2
node, which is pointing at the 3 node.
And, again, as someone
observed earlier, it's
not common to use this double
arrow notation in this case.
I bet I could actually use a
loop to iterate over these things
one at a time.
And we can see this here
when it's time to print.
Let me go ahead and do this for.
And instead of using i, because there
really aren't any numbers in question.
This is no longer an array, so I can't
use square bracket notation or pointer
arithmetic.
I need to use pointers.
So this might feel a
little weird at first.
But there's nothing stopping me
with a for loop from doing this.
Give me a temporary pointer
to a node called tmp
and initialize it to be whatever
is at the beginning of the list.
Keep doing the following so
long as tmp does not equal NULL.
And on each iteration of this loop,
don't do something like i++ which,
again, is not relevant now.
But go ahead and update
my temporary pointer
to be whatever the value of the
temporary pointer's next field is.
So this looks crazy cryptic
most likely, especially
if you're new to pointers as of
last week, as most of you are.
But it's the same idea
is a typical for loop.
You initialize some variable
before the semicolon.
You check some condition
after the first semicolon.
And you perform an update of that
variable after the second semicolon.
In this case, they're
not integers, though.
Instead, I'm saying give myself a
temporary pointer to the beginning
of the list, like my finger pointing
at, or if you prefer, the foam finger
pointing at some node in the list.
Go ahead and call that
temporary variable tmp.
And now do the following.
So long as tmp is not null,
that is, so long as it's
pointing at an actual legitimate
wooden block, what do I want to do?
Let me go ahead and print out,
using printf and %i as always,
whatever value is in the number
field of that node there.
And that's it.
With this simple for loop,
relatively simple for loop,
I can essentially point at
the very first node in my list
and keep updating it to the next
field, updating it to the next field,
updating it to the next field.
And I keep doing this until
my finger sort of walks off
the end of the list of
wooden blocks, thereby
pointing at null, 0x0, at
which point the loop stops
and there's nothing more to print.
So in answer to that
question earlier, do we
need to use this double arrow notation?
Short answer, no, this is kind
of the secret ingredient here.
This syntax inside of the for loop
takes whatever you're pointing at,
follows one arrow, and then
updates the temporary variable now
to point at that structure instead.
So this is kind of the equivalent in
the world of pointers and linked lists
of doing i++.
But it's not as simple as i++.
You can't just look one byte
to the right or to the left.
Instead, you have to follow
an arrow, follow an arrow.
But by reassigning this temporary
variable to wherever you just followed,
it's a way of following
each of these orange arrows
as we did physically a moment ago.
After this, I should, for good measure,
go ahead and free the whole list.
And let me just offer up a common
way of freeing a linked list.
I can actually do something like this.
While list != NULL, so while the
whole list itself does not equal null,
go ahead and get a temporary pointer
like this to the next field so I
remember what comes after
the current head of the list.
Free the list node itself.
And then update list to be tmp.
So, again, this probably looks crazy
cryptic and certainly in the coming
days, especially with
Problem Set 5, you'll
work through this kind of logic a
little more logically, a little more
pictorially, perhaps.
But what am I doing here?
First, I'm going to do the following,
so long as my linked list is not null.
And if I've got three
nodes in it, by definition
it's not null from the beginning.
But my goal now is to free all
of the memory I have allocated
from left to right, so to speak.
So how do I do that?
Well, if I've got a wooden
block in front of me,
it's not safe to free
that wooden block yet.
Because that wooden block, recall,
contains the pointer to the next node.
So if I free this
memory prematurely, I've
then stranded all subsequent nodes.
Because they are no longer accessible
once I've told the computer
you can take back this chunk
of memory for the first node.
So this line of code here, on line
52, is just saying temporarily
give me a variable call tmp.
And point it not at the list itself,
the first node, point at the next node.
So it's like using my right hand to
point at the current node, my left hand
to point at the next node, so that I can
then, on line 53, free the list itself,
which should not be taken literally.
List represents the first node in
the linked list, not the whole thing.
So when you say free list, that's,
like, freeing just the current node.
But that's OK.
Even now this memory
has been given back,
I still have my left hand
pointing at every subsequent node
by way of the next one.
So now I can update list to
equal that temporary variable
and just continue this loop.
So it's a way of sort
of Pacman style, like,
gobbling up the entire
linked list from left
to right by freeing the first node, the
second node, the third node, and then
you're done.
But by using a temporary variable
to look one step ahead to make sure
you don't chomp, free
the memory too soon
and, therefore, lose access to
all of those subsequent nodes.
All right, phew.
That was a big program.
But it was meant to be in
succession, starting with an array,
transitioning into a dynamically
allocated array, followed by, finally,
an implementation using
linked list, albeit hardcoded
to support only three nodes.
But in that example, do you see
some sample syntax via which you
can manipulate these kinds of nodes?
Questions or confusion
that I can help address?
BRIAN: Yes.
Someone asked, similar to one
of the examples you did before,
why could we not have just done
malloc three times size of node
to get three nodes and do it that way?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
Could I not just use malloc
and allocate all three at once?
Absolutely.
Yes.
That is completely your prerogative.
I did it a little more
pedantically, one at a time.
But you could absolutely
do it all three at once.
You would then need to use
some pointer arithmetic though,
or you would need to
square bracket notation
to treat that bigger chunk of memory
as essentially an array of nodes,
and then stitch them together.
So I am assuming, for
demonstration purposes,
that even though we have these little
simple examples that demonstrate
the syntax, in a real world system,
you're not going to be inserting 1,
then 2, then 3.
Odds are you're going to be inserting 1.
Some time passes.
Then you want to insert 2,
so you allocate more memory.
Then some more time passes.
Then you want to insert 3.
And so there's gaps in between these
chunks of code in the real world.
Other questions or confusion?
BRIAN: Yeah.
Another question came in.
Why would malloc ever
fail to allocate memory?
DAVID MALAN: Why would malloc ever fail?
It's rarely going to fail, but
if the computer is out of memory.
So essentially, if you're writing
such a memory hungry program
with so many variables, big arrays,
big structures, lots of data,
you may very well run out of memory.
Maybe that's two gigabytes, maybe
it's four gigabytes or more.
But malloc may very
well return null to you.
And so you should always check for it.
In fact, I dare say,
on Macs and PCs, one
of the most common reasons, to
this day, for programs to freeze,
to crash, for your home
computer to reboot,
is truly because someone did
something stupid, like I've
done multiple times now
already today and last week,
by touching memory that
you shouldn't have.
So in Problem Set 4
and now 5, any time you
experience one of those
segmentation faults
whereby your program just
crashes, that is the problem set
version of, like, your
whole Mac or PC crashing,
because someone more
experienced than you
made that same mistake in their code.
Just to reinforce this, let's
take a quick final example
involving linked lists which, again,
are this very one dimensional structure,
left to right.
And then we'll add a second
dimension and see what that buys us.
But we've changed the
numbers around here.
Now we still have our list.
But it's first pointing
at the number two here.
And then the number two is pointing
to some other chunk of memory that's
been malloced way over here.
And this, then, is the number 4.
And this, then, is the number 5.
So we have a linked list of size 3.
But I've deliberately spread the
numbers out this time, 2, 4, 5.
Because suppose that we do want to
insert more numbers into this list,
but in sorted order,
it turns out that we
have to think a little
bit differently when
we're adding nodes not to the
end and not to the beginning,
but in the middle.
Like, when we want to allocate
more nodes in the middle,
there's a bit more work
that actually has to happen.
So how might we go about doing this?
Suppose that we want to allocate,
for instance, the number 1.
And I want to add the number 1.
Well, we could use code like this.
This is the same code as we used before.
We allocate the size of a node.
We check whether it equals
null, we initialize it
with a value we care about, and by
default, we sit next equal to null.
And pictorially, it
might look like this.
It's kind of floating somewhere
in the computer's memory.
I have this temporary variable
n, no longer pictured,
that I'm just pointing at
when I allocate the number 1.
So what does this look like?
This is like having the number
1 maybe somewhere over here.
And I'll just put it in place.
We got lucky, and there was a
chunk of memory right there.
So what do I want to now do?
Well, I want to go
ahead and connect this.
So what I could do, just
intuitively, if 1 should go before 2,
I can unplug this.
And I can plug this into
here, which makes sense.
But there's already a problem.
If I have done nothing
else up until this point,
I have just orphaned
three nodes, 2, 4, and 5.
To orphan a node means
to forget where it is.
And if I don't have another
variable in my code,
or if I'm not acting
out with one of my hands
pointing at the original
beginning of the list,
I have literally orphaned
the rest of the list.
And the technical implication
of that, per last week,
is that now I have a
massive memory leak.
You have just leaked
the size of three nodes
in memory that you can
literally never get back
until you reboot the
computer, for instance,
or the program quits and the operating
system cleans things up for you.
So you don't want to do this.
Order of operations actually matters.
So what I should probably do is this.
When I insert the number
1 first, I should probably
recognize that, well, the one
begins at the beginning of the list.
So what I should really do is point
this arrow also at the same node.
And we'll sort of do it a
little sloppily like that.
But let me stipulate those are
both pointing at the same node.
Now that my new node, AKA n and the
code I showed is pointing at this thing,
now I can do kind of a switcheroo.
Because I'm already pointing
at the final destination there.
And now I can remove this
safely, because this is my list.
This is n.
Therefore, I have
variables pointing to both
and I can go ahead and
insert that correctly.
So long story short, order
of operations matters.
So graphically, if I were to do this as
before, just by saying list equals n,
if this is n, and this is list,
and I adjust this arrow first,
bad things are going to happen.
Indeed, we end up orphaning 2, 4, and
5, thereby leaking a significant amount
of memory potentially.
And leaking any memory,
typically, is bad.
So I don't want to do that.
So let's look at the correct code.
The correct code is
going to be to start at n
and update its next field, this arrow
here, to point at the same thing
as the list was originally pointing at.
And then go ahead and update
the list, such that both of them
are currently pointing in duplicate.
Then update the list to
point to the new node.
So, again, the code's a little
different this time from before.
Because before we kept
adding it to the end,
or I proposed verbally that we
just add it to the beginning.
Here, we're adding it,
indeed, at the beginning.
And so the actual steps, the actual
code, are a little bit different.
Well, let's do one final example,
if we want to allocate 3.
Well, I've got to malloc
another node, the number 3.
Suppose that ends up somewhere
in the computer's memory.
Let's go ahead and plop
this one over here.
So now 3 is in place.
How do I now insert this thing?
Well, similar to before, I'm not
going to want to update this pointer
and go like this and then
plug this guy in over here.
Because now I've
orphaned those two nodes.
So that, again is the wrong step.
When you're inside the middle
of a linked list, any code
that you write to
insert into the middle,
if you care about inserting in sorted
order, this should be updated first.
And odds are I should kind of cheat
and point this at the same thing,
even though there's only one
physical plug at the moment.
So we'll just pretend
that this is working.
There we go.
And now I can go ahead and safely
say that n and the previous node
are already pointing
where they should be.
So now it's safe for
me to unplug this one
and go ahead and update
this final arrow to point
at the new node in the correct location.
So let's see that in code again.
If I go here, I've got graphically
the node 3 kind of floating in space.
I first update its next field to
point also at the 4 in duplicate.
Then, I update the 2 to point to the 3.
The goal being, again, to avoid
any leaking of memory or orphaning
of nodes.
All right , we are about to
leave linked lists behind.
Because as multiple of you
have noted or probably thought,
they're good, but maybe not great.
They're good in that they are
dynamic and I can add to them, as
by inserting at the
beginning if I really want
and don't care about sorted order.
But they're still a good
amount of work to do
if I want to keep them in
sorted order and I insert them
in the middle or the end.
Because that's, like,
Big O of n if I keep
traversing all of these darn arrows.
So we get the dynamism,
but we don't necessarily
get the performance increase.
But we fundamentally have opened
up a whole new world to ourselves.
We can now stitch together
these data structures
in memory using pointers
as our thread, if you will.
We can just use memory as a canvas,
painting on it any values we want.
And we can sort of remember
where all of those values are.
But this is indeed very single,
one dimensional, left to right.
What if we give ourselves
a second dimension?
What if we start thinking
sort of not left to right,
but also left to right, up, down.
So, again, this is
meaningless to the computer.
The computer just thinks of
memory as being byte 0, 1, 2, 3.
But we humans can kind of
think of these data structures
a little more abstractly,
a little more simply.
And we can think about
them in a way familiar,
perhaps, to us in the real world.
Trees, not the ones so much
that grow from the ground,
but if you're familiar
with family trees.
Where you might have a
matriarch or a patriarch
and then sort of descendants
hanging off of them graphically
on a piece of paper, something you
might have made in grade school,
for instance.
We can leverage this
idea of a tree structure
that has a root that kind of
branches and branches and branches
and grows top to bottom.
So, again, more like a family tree
than an actual tree in the soil.
So with trees, it turns
out, this idea of a tree,
we can take some of the lessons
learned from linked lists.
But we can gain back some
of the features of arrays.
And we can do that as follows.
Consider the following
definition of what we're
about to call a binary search tree.
Binary search being a very good
thing from the first, Week 0.
And a tree now being the new idea.
Here's an array from Week
0, Week 1, Week 2, whenever.
And it's of size 7.
And recall that if it's sorted, we
can apply binary search to this array.
And that's great.
Because if we want to
search for a value,
we can start looking in the middle.
Then we can go either left or
right, halfway between each.
And then we can similarly
go left or right.
So binary search on a
sorted array was so powerful
because it was Big O of
log n, we've concluded,
by just having and having and
having the problem again and again,
tearing the phone book in half
again and again and again.
But the problem with
binary search is that it
requires that you use an array
so that you have random access.
You have to be able to index
into the array in constant time
using simple arithmetic, like bracket
0, bracket n minus 1, bracket n minus 1
divided by 2, to get the halfway point.
You have to be able to do
arithmetic on the data structure.
And we've just proposed getting
rid of that random access
by transitioning to a
dynamic data structure
like a linked list instead of an array.
But what if we do this?
What if you and I start thinking not on
one dimension, but on two dimensions?
And what if we alter our
thinking to be like this?
So think of an array, perhaps,
as being a two dimensional
structure that has not only
with or length, but also height.
And so we maintain, it seems,
visually this relationship
between all of these values.
But you know what?
We can stitch all of these
values together using what?
Well, pointers.
Pointers are this new
building block that we can use
to stitch together things in memory.
If the things in memory
are numbers, that's fine.
They're integers.
But if we throw a little more
memory at them, if we use a node,
and we kind of wrap the
integer in a node such
that that node contains not
only numbers but pointers,
we could probably draw
a picture like this, not
unlike a family tree,
where there's a root
node, at the very top in this case,
and then children, so to speak.
Left child and right child, and that
definition repeats again and again.
And it turns out the computer scientists
do use this data structure in order
to have the dynamism
of a linked list, where
you can add more and
more nodes to the tree
by just adding more and
more squares even lower
than the 1, the 3, the 5, and the 7.
And just use more pointers to kind
of stitch them together, to sort of
grow the tree vertically,
down, down, down, if you will.
But a good computer scientist would
recognize that you shouldn't just
put these numbers in random
locations, otherwise,
you're really just wasting your time.
You should use some algorithm.
And notice.
Does anyone notice the
pattern to this tree?
Can anyone verbalize or
textualize in the chat
what pattern is manifest by
these seven nodes in this tree?
They're not randomly ordered.
They're very deliberately ordered
left to right, top to bottom,
in a certain way.
Can anyone put their finger on what
the definition of this thing is?
What is the most important
characteristic besides it
just being drawn like a family tree?
[? Greg? ?]
AUDIENCE: You have put
in the middle of them,
on top of them you have
put the middle number.
For example, between 1
and 3, you have put 2.
Between 5 and 7, you have put 6.
So on top of them, you
have put the middle number.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
There's this pattern
to all of the numbers.
Between 1 and 3 is 2.
Between 5 and 7 is 6.
Between 2 and 6 is 4.
And it doesn't even have to
be the middle number, per se.
I can generalize it a
little bit and comment
that, if you pick any node
in this tree, so to speak,
its left child will be
less than its value,
and its right child's will
be greater than its value.
And we can do that again and again.
So here's 4.
Its left child is 2.
That's less than.
Here's 4.
It's right child to 6.
That's greater than.
We can do this again.
Let's go to 2.
Its left child is 1, which is less.
Its right child is 3, which is more.
6, its left child is 5, which is less.
6, its right child is 7, which is more.
And so this is actually,
if you don't mind
the revisiting recursion from last
week, this is a recursive definition.
This is a recursive data structure.
So it's not only algorithms
or functions that
can be recursive by calling themselves.
A data structure can also be recursive.
After all, what is this thing?
This is a tree, yes.
I'll stipulate.
But it's technically
a tree with two trees.
Right?
This node here, number four,
technically has two children.
And each of those
children is itself a tree.
It's a smaller tree.
But it's the same exact
definition again and again.
And any time we see a
recursive data structure,
it's actually going to be an
opportunity to use recursive code,
which we'll take a look
at in just a moment.
But for now, notice what
we've achieved again,
the dynamism of using pointer
so that we can, if we want,
add more nodes to this
tree, as by stringing them
along the bottom in the correct order.
And yet, we've preserved an
important order for binary search,
AKA, the formal name of this data
structure, binary search tree,
by making sure that left child is
always less, right child is always more.
Because now, we can go about
searching this thing more efficiently.
How?
Well, if I want to search for
the number 3, what do I do?
Well, I start at the
beginning of the tree.
Just like with a linked list, you start
at the beginning of the linked list.
So with the tree, you start with
the root of the tree [? always. ?]
Suppose I want to search for 3.
Well, what do I do?
Well, 3 is obviously less than 4.
So just like in Week 0 where
I tore the phone book in half,
you can now think of this as
chopping down half of the tree.
Because you know 3, if it's
present, is definitely not
going to be anywhere over here, so
we can focus our attention down here.
Here's the number 2.
This is another tree.
It's just a smaller
subtree, if you will.
How do I find the number 3?
Well, I look to the right
because it's greater than.
And boom, I found it.
But by contrast, suppose I were
searching for the number 8.
I would start here.
I would look here.
And then conclude, no, it's not there.
But, again, every time
I search for that 8,
I'm ignoring this half of the tree,
this half of the subtree, and so forth.
So you're going to
achieve, it would seem,
the same kind of power, the same kind
of performance as we saw from Week 0.
So how do we translate
this idea now into code?
We have all the building blocks already.
Let me go ahead and propose
that, instead of the node
we used before for a linked list, which
looked like this, with a number and one
pointer called next--
but, again, we could have called
those things anything-- let's go ahead
and make room for not just a
number, but also two pointers, one
that I'll call left, one
that I'll call right.
Both of those is still a
pointer to a struct node.
So same terminology as before, but
now I have two pointers instead of one
so that one can conceptually point
to the left and point to a smaller
subtree.
One can point to the right
and point to a larger subtree.
So how do we go about implementing
something like binary search?
Well, let's actually see some code.
And this is where recursion
really gets kind of cool.
We kind of forced it when building
[? Maro's ?] pyramid with recursion.
Like, yeah, you can do it.
And yes, the pyramid was, I claimed,
a recursive physical structure
or virtual structure in the game.
But with data structures and pointers,
now recursion really starts to shine.
So let's consider this.
If I declare a function
in C whose purpose in life
is to search a tree for a number,
it's going to, by definition,
search from the root on down.
How do we implement this?
Well, my function, I'll propose,
is going to return a bool.
True or false, the number
is in the tree, yes or no.
It's going to take two arguments,
a pointer to a node, AKA tree.
I could call it root or anything else.
And it's going to take
a number, which is
the number I care about, whether it's
four or six or eight or anything else.
So what's going to be
my first chunk of code?
Well, let me do the best
practice that I keep preaching.
Any time you're dealing with
pointers, check for null
so that your program doesn't freeze
or crash or bad thing happens.
Because who knows?
Maybe you will accidentally
or maybe intentionally
pass this function on null
pointer, because there's no tree.
Maybe you'll screw up.
And that's OK, so long as
your code is self-defensive.
So always check pointers for null.
If so, if the tree is null,
that is, there is no tree there,
obviously, the number is not present.
So you just return false.
So that's one of our
base cases, so to speak.
Else, if the number you're looking for
is less than the tree's own number--
so, again, this arrow notation
means take tree, which is a node *,
so take this pointer.
Go there to the actual node.
And look in its own number field.
If the number you're looking
for from the argument
is less than the number in
the tree's own number field,
well, that means that
you want to go left.
And whereas in the phone book, I
went to the left of the phone book,
here we're going to go
to the left subtree.
But how do I search a subtree?
Here's where it's important that a
tree is a recursive data structure.
A tree is two subtrees with
a new root node, as before.
So I already have code via which
I can search a smaller tree.
So I can just say
search the left subtree,
as expressed here, which means
start at the current node
and go to the left child
and pass in the same number.
The number is not changing.
But the tree is getting smaller.
I've effectively, in code,
chopped the tree in half.
And I'm ignoring the right half.
And I'm returning
whatever that answer is.
Otherwise, if the number
I care about is greater
than the number in the
current node, do the opposite.
Search the right subtree,
passing in the same number.
So, again, just like
with the phone book,
it kept getting smaller and smaller?
Here I keep searching a
smaller and smaller subtree.
Because I keep chopping off
branches left or right as
I go from top to bottom.
There's one final case.
And let me toss this out to the group.
There's a fourth case.
Verbally or textually, what else should
I be checking for and doing here?
I've left room for one final case.
BRIAN: A few people are suggesting
if the tree itself is the number.
DAVID MALAN: If the tree itself
contains the number, yeah.
So if the number in
the tree equals equals
the number I'm looking for, go ahead
and, only in this case, return true.
And so this is where the
code, again, gets kind of--
recursion, rather, gets
a little mind-bending.
I only have false up here, true here.
But not in either of these middle two
branches, no pun intended, if you will.
But that's OK.
Because my code is designed in such a
way that if I search the left subtree
and there's nothing there, like,
literally I'm at the leaf of the tree,
so to speak, then it's
going to return false.
So that's fine.
That's, like, if I
search for the number 8.
It's not even in the tree.
I'm only going to realize that
once I fall off the end of the tree
and see, oops, null.
I'll just return false.
But if I ever see the number
along the way, I will return true.
And these two inner calls to search,
these two recursive calls to search,
are just kind of like passing the buck.
Instead of answering
true or false themselves,
they're returning whatever the
answer to a smaller question
is by searching the left or
right tree instead respectively.
So, again, this is
where recursion starts
to get not really forced or even
necessarily really as forced,
but really as appropriate.
When your data is itself recursive,
then recursion in as a coding technique
really rather shines.
So if ultimately, we have-- oh,
[? an ?] minor optimization.
As we might have noted
in Week 0 with Scratch,
we, of course, don't need to explicitly
check if the number is equal.
We can get rid of that last condition
and just assume that if it's not null
and it's not to the left
and it's not to the right,
we must be standing right on top of it.
And so we just return true there.
Well, let me summarize the picture here.
This is now a two
dimensional data structure.
And it's sort of better than a linked
list in that now it's two dimensions.
I gain back binary search,
which is amazing, so
long as I keep my data in sorted order
per this binary search tree definition.
But I've surely paid a price.
Right?
Nothing is absolutely better than
anything else in our story thus far.
So what is the downside of a tree?
What price have I secretly
or not so secretly paid here,
while preaching the upsides of trees?
And, again, the answer is often in
this context sort of space, or time,
or developer time, or money, or some
resource, personal, or physical,
or real world.
Yeah.
How about over to [INAUDIBLE]?
AUDIENCE: So I think that inserting
is no longer constant time.
And I guess we need more memory.
You need memory to [? sort ?] two
pointers instead of one this time.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
It seems insertion is
no longer constant time.
Because if I need to preserve sorted
order, I can't just put it at the top.
I can't just keep pushing
everything else down
because things might get out of order.
In that case, it would [? seem. ?] Or
rather, even if I maintain the order,
it might kind of get
very long and stringy.
If I add, for instance,
another number, another number,
and I keep jamming it
at the top, I probably
need to kind of keep things
balanced, if you will.
And yeah, the bigger point,
too, is that immediately I'm
using twice as many pointers.
So now my node is getting
even bigger than these things.
I now have room for not
only a number and a pointer,
but another pointer, which is, of
course, going to cost me more space.
Again, so a trade off there.
And let's go ahead and
ask the group here,
when it comes to insertion, why
don't we consider for a moment what
the running time of insertion might
be when inserting into a binary search
tree.
If you'd like to pull up the
URL as always, let me go ahead
and present this one.
What's the running time of
inserting into a binary search tree?
So if you want to insert
the number 0 into that tree,
if you want to insert the number
8, or anything in between or bigger
or smaller, what are the answers here?
So not quite as big of a
victory for the tallest bar.
About 60% of you think log n.
And the good instincts
there, frankly, are so
that is going to be the right answer.
And that's kind of the right instinct.
Anytime you have binary search, odds are
you're talking something logarithmic.
But we've also seen divide and
conquer and merge sort with n log n,
so not unreasonable that about
10% of you think that, too.
n squared would actually be bad.
So n squared is, like, the worst
of the times we've seen thus far.
And that would suggest that a tree
is even worse than a linked list,
is even worse than an array.
And thankfully, we're not at that point.
But it's indeed log n, based
on certain assumptions.
So why is that?
So if we consider the
tree from a moment ago,
it looked a little something like this.
And what is involved in
inserting into a tree?
Well, suppose I want
to insert the number 8.
Well, I start here.
And it obviously belongs to
the right because 8 is bigger.
I go here.
It belongs to the right
because 8 is bigger.
I go here.
It belongs to the right,
because 8 is bigger.
And so a new node is going to
be created somewhere down here.
And even though it doesn't fit on the
screen, I could absolutely call malloc.
I could update a couple of pointers.
And boom, we've added an
eighth node to the tree.
So if it took me that many steps,
starting at the root, 1, 2, 3,
how do I generalize this
into Big O notation?
Well, a binary search tree, if you lay
it out nice and prettily like this,
nice and balanced if you will, the
height of that binary search tree,
it turns out, is going to be log of n.
If n is the number of total nodes,
7 or 8 now in the story, then
log base 2 of n is going to
be the height of the tree.
So if you take n nodes, n
numbers, and you kind of
balance them in this nice sorted way,
the total height is going to be log n.
So what is the running time of insert?
Well, the running time of
insert is equivalent to how many
steps does it take you to
find the location into which
the new number belongs?
Well, that's 1, 2, 3.
And as it turns out, log
base 2 of 8 is indeed 3.
So the math actually works
out perfectly in this case.
Sometimes, there might be
a little rounding error.
But in general it's going
to indeed be Big O of log n.
But what if we get a little sloppy?
What if we get a little
sloppy and we start
inserting nodes that are giving
us a bit of bad luck, if you will?
So for instance, suppose
that I go ahead-- and let
me do something on the fly here.
Suppose that I go ahead and
insert the number 1, the number 2,
and the number 3 such that
this is what logically happens.
This adheres to the definition
of a binary search tree.
If this is the roots, it's 1.
It has no left subtree, and
that's not strictly a problem,
because there's nothing violating
the definition of a search tree here.
There's just nothing there.
2 is in the right place.
3 is in the right place.
So this, too, technically
is a binary search tree.
But it's a bit of a corner case,
a perverse case, if you will,
where the way you inserted things ended
up in the binary search tree actually
resembling more of a what, would you
say, if you want to chime in the chat?
And Brian, if you might want to relay?
BRIAN: A few people are saying
it looks like a linked list.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So even though I've drawn
it sort of top down,
so in the sort of
second dimension, that's
really just an artist's rendition.
This tree is a binary search tree.
But it's kind of sort
of also a linked list.
And so even the most
well-intentioned data
structures, given unfortunate inputs
or some bad luck or some bad design,
could devolve into a different
data structure just by chance.
So there's a way to solve this
though, even with these values.
When I insert 1, 2, 3, I could
allow for this perverse situation
where it just gets long and stringy, at
which point everything is Big O of n.
It's just a linked list.
It just happens to be drawn
diagonally instead of left right.
But does anyone see a
solution intuitively?
Not in terms of code,
no formal language,
but there is a solution here to make
sure that this tree with 1, 2, 3
does not get long and
stringy in the first place.
What might you do instead to solve this?
BRIAN: A few people in
the chat are suggesting
you should make 2 the new root
node at the top of the tree.
DAVID MALAN: So if I instead make 2
the new root node, let me go ahead
and mock this up real quickly.
And in a moment, I'll reveal what
I think you've just verbalized.
What if instead, I make sure
that when inserting these nodes
I don't naively just keep going to
the right, to the right, to the right?
I exercise some judgment.
And if I notice, maybe, that
my data structure, my tree
is getting kind of long
and stringy, maybe I
should kind of rotate it around,
using that second dimension for real
so that I change what the root is.
And we won't go through
the code for doing this.
But it turns out this is the solution.
That is exactly the right intuition.
If you take a higher level
class on data structures
and algorithms specifically
in computer science,
you'll study trees like AVL
trees, or red, black trees,
which are different types
of tree data structures.
They kind of have built into them the
algorithms for kind of shifting things
as needed to make sure that as you
insert, or maybe as you delete,
you constantly rebalance the tree.
And long story short, doing so
might cost you a little extra time.
But if you've got a lot of data, keeping
that thing balanced and logarithmic
in height, so to speak, and not long
and stringy in the linear in height,
it's probably, depending on your
application, going to save you
quite a bit of time overall.
So we might say that insert into
a balanced binary search tree
is indeed Big O of log n.
But that is conditional on you making
sure that you keep it balanced.
And that's going to be more
code than we'll go into today,
but indeed, a possible design decision.
All right, any questions then on
now trees and binary search trees,
in particular?
We started with arrays a few weeks ago.
We've now got linked lists, which
are good, better, but not great.
To trees, which seemed maybe to be great
but, again, it's always a trade off.
They're costing us more space.
But I bet we can continue to
stitch some of these ideas
together for other structures still.
Brian, anything outstanding?
BRIAN: Yeah.
One question came in as to why
it's a problem if you have,
like, the 1, and the 2, and the 3 all
in just one sequence on the right side?
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, a
really good question.
Why is it a problem?
Maybe it isn't.
If you don't have a very
large data set and you
don't have many values in the
structure, honestly, who cares?
If it's three elements,
definitely don't care.
If it's 10 elements, if it's 1,000,
heck, if your computer is fast enough,
there might be a million
elements, and it's not a big deal.
But if it's two million
elements or a billion elements,
then it totally depends, again, on
what is the business you're building?
What is the application you're writing?
How big is your data?
How fast or how slow is your computer?
It might very well matter ultimately.
And indeed, when we've seen some
of our algorithms a couple of weeks
ago, when we compared bubble sort
and selection sort and merge sort,
even though those were in a
different category of running times,
n log n and n squared, just
recall the appreciable difference.
Log of n in the context of
searching is way better than n.
So if your data structure is devolving
into something long and stringy,
recall that's, like, searching a
phone book a thousand total pages.
But binary search and not
letting it get long and stringy
gives you, like, 10
steps instead of 1,000
steps in order to
search those same pages.
So, again, even in Week 0 we
saw the appreciable difference
between these different
categories of running times.
All right, well, let's
see if we can't maybe
take some of the best of both worlds.
Thus far, again, we've seen arrays.
We've seen linked lists.
We've seen trees.
What if we kind of get a little
Frankenstein here and mash things
together and take sort of the
best features of these things
and build up something grander.
In fact, I feel like the Holy
Grail of a data structure
would be something for which cert
and insertion aren't n, Big O of n,
aren't Big O of log n.
But wouldn't it be amazing
if there's a data structure
out there where the running time
is like constant time, Big O of 1.
That's the Holy Grail.
If you can cleverly lay out your
computer's memory in such a way
that if you want to search for or
insert a value, boom, you're done.
Boom, you're done, and none of this
linear or logarithmic running time.
So let's see if we
can't pursue that goal.
Let me propose that we introduce
this topic called hash tables.
Hash table is another
data structure that's
essentially an array of linked lists.
So, again, it's this
Frankenstein monster,
whereby we've combined arrays
ultimately with linked list.
Let's see how this is done.
Let me propose that we first
start with an array of size 26.
And I'm going to start drawing my
arrays vertically, just because it
sort of works out better pictorially.
But, again, these are all
artist's renditions, anyway.
Even though we always draw arrays left
to right, that's completely arbitrary.
So I'm going to start, for now,
drawing my array top to bottom.
And suppose that the data
structure I care about now
is going to be even more
interesting the numbers.
Suppose I want to store things like
names, like dictionaries, or names
like contacts in your phone.
If you want to keep track
of all the people you know,
it would be great if it doesn't
take linear time or logarithmic time
to find people.
Instead, constant time would
seem to be even better.
So here's an array,
for instance, size 26.
And I proposed that deliberately.
In English, there's 26
letters, A through Z. So
let's consider location
0 is A. Location 25 is Z.
And if I now go and start inserting
all of my friends into my new phone,
into the contacts application,
where might I put them?
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and think of each of
these elements as, again, 0 through 25,
or really A through Z.
And let me, upon inserting a new
friend or contact into my phone,
let me put them into a location that has
some relationship with the name itself.
Let's not just start putting
them at the very beginning.
Let's not necessarily put
them alphabetically per se.
Let's actually put them at a specific
location in this array, not just top
to bottom, but at a specific entry.
So suppose the first person I want
to add to my contacts is Albus.
Well, I'm going to propose that
because Albus starts with an A,
he is going to go into the A location,
so the very first entry in this array.
Suppose I next want to add Zacharias.
Well, his name starts with Z. So he's
going to go in the very last location.
So, again, I'm jumping around.
I went from 0 to 25.
But it's an array, and I can
do that in constant time.
You can randomly index to any
element using square brackets.
So this is both constant time.
I don't have to just put
him right after Albus.
I can put him wherever I want.
Suppose the third person is Hermione.
Well, I'm going to put
her at location H. Why?
Because I can do the math,
and I can figure out H. OK,
I can just jump immediately to
that letter of the alphabet.
And in turn, thanks to ASCII
and doing a bit of arithmetic,
I convert that to a number as well.
So she ends up at 0,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
because H ends up mapping to the
eighth character, or location 7.
All right.
Who else?
All these other people
end up in my address book.
And so they're all spread out.
I don't have as many as 26 friends.
So there's some gaps in the data there.
But I fit everyone here.
But there might be a problem.
And you can perhaps see this coming.
Thus far, I've kind of gotten lucky.
And I've only know people whose names
are-- uniquely start with a letter.
But as soon as I meet someone at
school and I add them to my contacts,
well, now Harry, for instance,
has to go in the same location.
Now this is a problem if I want
to store both Hermione and Harry,
because their names both start with H.
But, again if it's an array,
it's absolutely a deal breaker.
At that point, all things break down.
Because I could, yes, grow the array.
But if I grow the array,
then it's size 27.
And then it's, like, how do I know what
number is what letter at that point?
It just devolves into a complete mess.
But if I borrow the idea
of a linked list, what if I
make my array an array of linked lists?
So yes, even though
there's this collision
where both Hermione and Harry belong
at the same location in the array,
that's fine.
In the event this happens, I'm just
going to kind of stitch them together
into a linked list from left to right.
So it's not ideal.
Because now it takes me two steps
to get to Harry instead of 1,
using simple arithmetic and
square bracket notation.
But heck, at least I can still
fit him in my address book.
So a bit of a trade off,
but feels reasonable.
Well, someone else, Hagrid--
all right, it's not ideal
that now it takes me
three steps to get to
Hagrid in my address book.
But three is way better than
not having him in there at all.
So, again, we see a manifestation
of a trade off here, too.
But we've solved the problem.
And a hash table is, indeed,
exactly this data structure.
It is an array of linked lists, at
least it can be implemented as such.
And it is predicated on introducing
the notion of a hash function.
This is actually something we'll
see in other contexts before long.
But a hash function is going to allow
us to map not only Hermione, Harry,
and Hagrid, but also Ron and
Remus, Severus and Sirius
to their respective
locations deterministically.
That is, there's no
randomness involved here.
Every time I look at
these people's names,
I'm going to figure out the
location at which they belong
and that location is
never going to change.
So how do I do this?
Well, it turns out we can think
back to problem solving itself
and what functions are.
So this is problem
solving as we defined it.
This is also a function in any
language that takes inputs and outputs.
A hash function is going to
be sort of a secret sauce
inside of this black box for now.
And so what is a hash function?
Well, a hash function is literally
a function, either mathematically
or in programming, that takes as
input some string, in this case,
like Hermione or Harry,
and it returns some output.
And the output of a hash
function is usually a number.
In this case, the number I want
is going to be between 0 and 25.
So in order to implement
this notion of a hash table,
not just pictorially on the
screen, but in actual code,
I'm literally going to have to write
a function that takes a string,
or if you will, char*, as input and
returns an int between 0 and 25 so that
I know how to convert Hermione or Harry
or Hagrid to the number 7 in this case.
So what does this hash function do?
It takes as input something
like Albus and it outputs 0.
It takes someone like
Zacharias, and it outputs 25.
And you can probably
see the pattern here.
The code I would write in order to
implement something like this is
probably going to look at
the user's input, that char*.
And it's going to look at
the first character, which
is A or Z, respectively, for these two.
And it's then going to
do a little bit of math
and subtract off, like, 65 or whatnot.
And it's going to get me
a number between 0 and 25,
just like with Caesar or some of
our past manipulations of strings.
So from here, we can now take this
building block, though, and perhaps
solve our problems a
little more effectively.
Like, I don't love the fact
that even though, yes, I've
made room for Harry, and
Hermione, and Hagrid,
and now Luna, and Lily, and Lucius, and
Lavender, some of these linked lists
are getting a little long.
And there's another
term you can use here.
These are kind of like
chains, if you will,
because they look like chain link
fences or little links in a chain.
These are chains or linked lists.
But some of them are
starting to get long.
And it's a little stupid that I'm trying
to achieve constant time, Big O of 1,
but technically, even though some of
the names literally take one step,
some of them are taking
two or three or four steps.
So it's starting to devolve.
So what would be an optimization here?
If you start to get uncomfortable
because you're so popular
and you've got so many names in
your contacts that looking up
the H's, looking up the L's is
taking more time than the others,
what could we do to improve the
situation and still use a hash table,
still use a hash function?
But what would maybe
the logical solution
be when you have too
many collisions, you
have too many names
colliding with one another?
How could we improve our performance
and get at locations, again,
closer to one step, not
two, not three, not four?
So literally one step, because
that's our Holy Grail here.
BRIAN: A few people have suggested
you should look at more than just
the first letter.
Like, you could look at the
second letter, for example.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Nice.
So if looking at one
letter of the person's name
is obviously insufficient.
Because a whole bunch of us have
names that start with H or A
or Z or the like, well, why
don't we look at two letters
and therefore decrease
the probability that we're
going to have these collisions?
So let me go ahead and restructure this.
And focusing on the Hermione,
Harry, and Hagrid problem,
why don't we go ahead and take our array
in the hash table, the vertical thing
here, and let's think of it as maybe
not just being H at that location.
But what if we think of
that location specifically
as being HA, and then HB, HC, HD,
HE, HF, all the way down to HZ.
And then IA, IB, IC,
and so forth, so we now
enumerate all possible pairs
of letters from AA to ZZ?
But this would seem to
spread things out, right?
Because now Hermione goes in
the HE location in the array.
Now Harry goes in the HA.
And now Hag-- oh, dammit.
Like, Hagrid still goes
in the same location.
So what would maybe be a better fix?
Again, this isn't horrible, like
two steps is not a big deal,
especially on fast computers.
But, again, with large enough
data sets, and if we're
no longer talking about people
in your contacts, but maybe
all the people in the world who have
Google accounts, or Twitter accounts,
and the like, where you want to
search this information quickly,
you're going to have a lot of people
whose names start with H and A
and Z and everything else.
It would be nice to
spread them out further.
So what could we do?
Well, instead of using
the first two letters,
frankly I think the logical extension of
this is to use the first three letters.
So maybe this is the HAA bucket.
This is the HAB, HAC, HAD, HAE, dot,
dot, dot, all the way down to HZZ,
and then IAA.
But now when we hash our
three friends, Hermione
goes in the HER bucket so to
speak, the elements of the array.
Harry, HAR, goes in that bucket.
And Hagrid now gets his own bucket,
HAG, as would everyone else.
So it seems to have solved
this specific problem.
You could still imagine, and I have
to think harder and probably Google
to see if there's other Harry Potter
names that start with HAG or HAR
or HER to find another collision.
Because you could imagine
using four letters instead.
But what price are we paying?
Like, I'm solving this
problem again and again.
And I'm getting myself
literally faster look up time,
because it's giving me one step.
I can mathematically
figure out by just doing
a bit of ASCII math, what
the number of the index
is that I should jump to in
this bigger and bigger array.
But what price am I paying?
Brian, any thoughts you'd like to relay?
BRIAN: Yeah.
A few people are saying it's
going to take a lot of memory.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
My God, like, this is taking
a huge amount of memory now.
Previously, how much memory did it take?
Well, let me pull up a little
calculator here and do some quick math.
So if we had originally 26 buckets, so
to speak, elements in the array, that,
of course, isn't that bad.
That feels pretty reasonable, 26 slots.
But the downside was
that the chains might
get kind of long, three names,
four names, maybe even more.
But if we have AA through ZZ, instead
of A through Z, that's 26 times 26,
that's 676 buckets.
Doesn't sound like a huge deal,
though that's bigger than most things
we've done in memory thus
far, not a huge deal.
But if we have three, that's 26
possibilities times 26 times 26,
for AAA through ZZZ.
Now we have 17,576 buckets in my array.
And the problem isn't so much
that we're using that memory.
Because honestly, if you
need the memory, use it.
That's fine.
Just throw hardware at the problem.
Buy and upgrade more memory.
But the problem is that
I probably don't know
that many people whose
names start with HAA or AZZ
or any number of these combinations
of letters of the alphabet.
A lot of those buckets
are going to be empty.
But it doesn't matter if they're empty.
If you want an array and you want
random access, they have to be present
so that your arithmetic
works out, per Week 2,
where you just use
square bracket notation
and jump to any of the locations
in memory that you care about.
So finding that trade off, or finding
the inflection point with those trade
offs, is kind of an art
and/or a science, figuring out
for your particular data, your
particular application, which
is more important, time or space or
some happy medium in between the two.
And with Problem Set 5,
as you'll see, you'll
actually have to figure
out this balance in part
by trying to minimize,
ultimately, your own use of memory
and your own use of computers' time.
But let me point
something out, actually.
This notion of hash
table, which up until now,
definitely the most sophisticated
data structure that we've looked at,
it's kind of familiar to
you in some way already.
These are probably larger than the
playing cards you have at home.
But if you've ever played
with a deck of cards,
and the cards start out randomly,
odds are you've, at some point,
needed to sort them for
one game or another.
Sometimes you need to
shuffle them entirely.
If you want to be a little
neat, you might sort them,
not just by number, but also by suit.
So hearts and spades and clubs and
diamonds into separate categories.
So honestly, I have this literally
here just for the sake of the metaphor.
We have four buckets here.
And we've gone ahead and labeled
them in advance with spade there.
So that's one bucket.
Here we have diamond shape here.
And here we have--
[GRUNTING]
--here we have hearts
here and then clubs here.
So if you've ever
sorted a deck of cards,
odds are you haven't really
thought about this very hard.
Because it's not that interesting.
You probably mindlessly start
laying them out and sorting them
by suits and then maybe by number.
But if you've done that, you
have hashed values before.
If you take a look at the
first card and you see,
that, oh, it's the ace of diamonds.
You know, yes, you might care ultimately
that it's a diamond, that it's an ace.
But for now, I'm just going to put it,
for instance, into the diamond bucket.
Here's the two of diamonds here.
I'm going to put that
into the diamond bucket.
Here's the ace of clubs.
So I'm going to put that over here.
And you can just progressively
hash one card after the other.
And, indeed, hashing really just means
to look at some input and produce,
in this case, some numeric output
that outputs the like bucket 0, 1, 2,
or 3 based on some
characteristic of that input,
whether it's actually the suit
on the card like I'm doing here,
or maybe it's based on the
letter of the alphabet here.
And why am I doing this?
Right?
I'm not going to do the whole thing.
Because 52 steps is going to take a
while and get boring quickly, if not
already.
But why am I doing this?
Because odds are you've
probably done this.
Not with the drama of actual buckets,
you've probably just kind of laid them
out in front of you.
But why have you done that, if that's
indeed something you have done?
Yeah.
Over to Sophia?
AUDIENCE: There's a possibility that
we could actually get to things faster,
like, if we know what bucket it is.
We might be able to even search
things for, like, 0, 1, or less.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Something like that.
You start to gain these
optimizations, right?
At least, as a human, honestly, I
can process four smaller problems
just much easier than one
bigger problem, that's size 52.
I can solve four 13 card problems
a little faster, especially
if I'm looking for a particular card.
Now I can find it among
13 cards instead of 52.
So there's just kind of
an optimization here.
So you might take as input these cards,
hash them into a particular bucket,
and then proceed to solve
the smaller problem.
Now that's not what a hash
table itself is all about.
A hash table is about storing
information, but storing information
so as to get to it more quickly.
So to Sophia's point, if indeed she just
wants to find like the ace of diamonds,
she now only has to look through
a 13 sized problem, a linked
list of size 13, if you will, instead
of an array or a linked list of size 52.
So a hash table allows you to
bucketize your inputs, if you will,
colloquially, and get
access to data more quickly.
Not necessarily in time one,
in one step, it might be two.
It might be four.
It might be 13 steps.
But it's generally
fewer steps than if you
were doing something purely
linearly, or even logarithmically.
Ideally, you're trying to pick
your hash function in such a way
that you minimize the number of elements
that collide by using not A through Z,
but AA through ZZ and so forth.
So let me go ahead here
and ask a question.
What, then, is the
running time when it comes
to this data structure of a hash table?
If you want to go ahead and search
in a hash table, once all of the data
is in there, once all of
my contacts are there,
how many steps does your phone have to
take, given n contacts in your phone,
to find Hermione or
Hagrid or anyone else?
So I see, again, 80% of you are
saying constant time, Big O of 1.
And, again, constant time might mean
one step, two steps, four steps,
but some fixed number,
not dependent on n.
18% of you or so are saying linear time.
And I have to admit, the
20% of you or so that
said linear time are technically,
asymptotically, mathematically correct.
And here we begin to see sort of a
distinction between the real world
and academia.
So the academic here, or rather the real
world here, the real world programmer
would say, just like Sophia did,
obviously, a bucket with 13 cards in it
is strictly better than one
bigger bucket with 52 cards.
That is just faster.
It's literally four times
as fast to find or to flip
through those 13 cards instead of 52.
That is objectively faster.
But the academic would say yes, but
asymptotically-- and asymptotically
is just a fancy way of saying
as n gets really large,
the sort of wave of the hand that I
keep describing, asymptotically taking
13 steps is technically big O of n.
Why?
Well, in the case of the cards here,
it's technically n divided by 4.
Yes, it's 13.
But if there's n cards total,
technically, the size of this bucket
is going to end up being m divided by 4.
And what did we talk about when
we talked about Big O and omega?
Well, you throw away
the lower order terms.
You get rid of the constants,
like the divide by 4,
or the plus something else.
So we get rid of that.
And it's technically a
hash table searching.
It is still in Big O of n.
But here, again, we see a
contrast between the real world
and the theoretical world.
Like, yes, if you want to
get into an academic debate,
yes, it's still technically
the same as a linked
list or an array, at which point
you might as well just search
the thing left to right linearly,
whether it's an array or a linked list.
But come on.
Like, if you actually hash
these values in advance,
and spread them out into
4, or 26, or 576 buckets,
that is actually going to be faster
when it comes to wall clock time.
So when you literally look
at the clock on the wall,
less time will pass taking
Sophia's approach than taking
an array or linked list approach.
So here, those of you who
said Big O of n are correct.
But when it comes to the
real world programming,
honestly, if it's faster
than actual n steps,
that may very well be a net positive.
And so perhaps we should be focusing
more on practice and less, sometimes,
on the theory of these things.
And indeed that's going
to be the challenge.
The Problem Set 5 to
which I keep alluding
is going to challenge
you to implement one
of these data structures, a hash
table, with 100,000 plus English words.
We're going to, in a nutshell,
give you a big text file containing
one English word per line.
And among your goals is going to be to
load all of those 140,000 plus words
into your computer's
memory using a hash table.
Now if you are simplistic
about it, and you
use a hash table with
26 buckets, A through Z,
you're going to have
a lot of collisions.
If there's 140,000 plus English
words, there's a lot of words in there
that start with A, or B, or
Z, or anything in between.
If you maybe then go with AA
through ZZ, maybe that's better,
or AAA through ZZZ, maybe that's better.
But at some point, you're
going to start to use
too much memory for your own good.
And one of the challenges,
optionally, of Problem Set 5,
is going to be to playfully
challenge your classmates whereby,
if you opt into this, you can
run a command that will put you
on the big board which will show on
the course's website exactly how much
or how little RAM or memory
you're using, and how little
or how much time your
code is taking to run.
And so we just put aside the sort of
academic waves of the hand saying,
well, yes, all of your
code is Big O of n.
But n divided by 4, Sophia's approach,
is way better in practice than n
itself.
And we'll begin to tease
apart the dichotomy
between theory here and practice.
But these aren't the only ways
to lay things out in memory.
And we wanted to show you just a
few other ideas that come out now
that we have all of
these building blocks.
One of which is the data structure
that we're going to call a trie.
Trie is actually short
for the word retrieval,
even though it's not
quite pronounced the same.
It's also known as a prefix tree.
And it's a different type
of tree that is typically
used to store words, or other
more sophisticated pieces of data
instead of just numbers alone.
So a trie is actually a
tree made up of arrays.
So you can kind of see a pattern here.
A hash table was an
array of linked lists.
A trie is a tree, each of
whose nodes is an array.
So at some point, computer scientists
started getting a little creative
and started just, like,
literally smashing together
different data structures to see what
they could come up with, it seems.
And so a trie begins to look like this.
But it has this amazing property
that's better than anything in theory
we've seen before.
Here is one node in a try.
And it's a node in the sense that this
would be like a rectangle or square.
But inside of that node is literally
an array of size 26 in this case.
And each of those locations or buckets,
if you will represent A through Z.
And what we're going to do is any
time we insert a word, like a name,
like Harry, or Hagrid, or
Hermione, or anyone else,
we are going to walk through the letters
of their name, like, H-A-G-R-I-D,
and we are going to follow a series
of pointers from one node to another
as follows.
So for instance, if this is A through
Z, or 0 through 25, here is location H.
So if the goal at the moment is to
insert the first of our contacts,
for instance, Harry, I'm
going to start by looking
at the first node, the root of the
tree, looking up the H location.
And I'm going to kind of make
mental note that Harry starts there,
the H in Harry starts there.
Then if I want to insert
the A in Harry, I'm
going to go ahead and add a new
node, representing 26 letters.
But I'm going to keep track of
the fact that, OK, A is here.
So now I'm going to
have another pointer--
oh, I'm sorry-- not Harry, Hagrid first,
H-A-G-R-I-D. So what have I just done?
A trie, again, is a tree, each
of whose nodes is an array.
And each of those arrays is an
array of pointers to other nodes.
So, again, we're really just
mashing up everything together here.
But it's the same
building blocks as before.
Each node in this tree, top to bottom,
is an array of pointers to other nodes.
And so, if I wanted to check
if Hagrid is in my contacts,
I literally start at the first
node, and I follow the H pointer.
I then follow the A pointer.
I then follow the G pointer,
the R pointer, the I pointer.
And then I check at the D pointer.
Is there a Boolean value inside of that
structure-- more on that another time,
perhaps--
that just says, yes or no, there
is someone named H-A-G-R-I-D
in my contacts.
Notice there's no other
letters noted at the moment.
And there's no other green boxes.
Green just denotes a Boolean
value for our purposes now.
So that means there's no one whose name
is H-A-G-R-I-A, or R-I-B, or R-I-C.
It's only H-A-G-R-I-D that
exists in my contacts.
But notice what happens next.
Now if I go ahead and
insert Harry, notice
that Harry and Hagrid share the H,
the A, and then this third node.
But then Harry needs to
follow a different pointer
to store the R and the Y.
And notice the green there.
It's sort of a checkmark in the data
structure, a Boolean value, that's
saying yes.
I have someone in my
context named H-A-R-R-Y.
And then, if we add Hermione, she shares
the H, and then also the second node.
But Hermione requires some
new nodes all together.
But notice this key property, the
reason for this sort of complexity,
because this is probably the weirdest
structure we've seen thus far,
is that even if I have a
billion names in my phone book,
how many steps literally does
it take me to find Hagrid?
Someone?
Feel free to chime in the text,
the chat window if you like?
Even if I have a billion
names in my contacts,
how many steps does it take
for me to look up and check
if Hagrid is among them?
BRIAN: People are saying six.
DAVID MALAN: Six, H-A-G-R-I-D. If I
have 2 billion names, 4 billion names,
how many steps does it take?
6, and this is what we mean by
constant time, constant time at least
in the length of the humans'
names in the data structure.
So what does this mean?
No matter how many names
you cram into a trie data
structure, the number
of other names does not
impact how many steps it takes for me
to find Harry or Hagrid or Hermione
or anyone else.
It is only dependent on
the length of their name.
And here's where we can
get a little academic.
If you assume that there's a
finite number of characters
in any human, real or imaginary's name,
maybe it's 20, or 100, or whatever.
It's more than 6, but it's
probably fewer than hundreds.
And then you can assume
that that's constant.
So it might be Big O
of, like, 200 characters
for someone with a super long name.
But that's constant.
And so technically a try
gives you that Holy Grail
of look up times and
insertion times of Big O of 1.
Because it is not dependent
on n, which is the number
of other names in the data structure.
It is dependent only on the length
of the name you're inputting.
And if you assume that all names
in the world are reasonably linked,
less than some finite value,
like 6, or 200, or whatever
it is, then you can call that.
And it technically is Big O of 1.
That is constant time.
So here is the goal of this whole day,
like, trying to get to constant time.
Because constant time
is better than, it would
seem, linear time, or logarithmic
time, or anything else we've seen.
But-- but-- but-- again,
there's always a trade off.
What price have we just
paid if you see it?
Why are tries not necessarily all that?
There's still a catch.
Daniel?
AUDIENCE: For example, if let's say you
have two people in your contact list.
One person was named Daniel and
one person was named Danielle.
And you know that
Daniel is in your list.
So the L would have this
Boolean operator of true.
But then, how would you get to
Danielle, if your L was an operator
and it didn't point to
another L for Danielle?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question,
a corner case, if you will.
What if someone's name is a
substring of another person's name?
So Daniel, D-A-N-I-E-L, and I
think you're saying Danielle,
D-A-N-I-E-L-L-E. So the second
name is a little longer.
Let me stipulate that we can solve that.
I have not shown code that represents
each of the nodes in this tree.
Let me propose that we could
continue having arrows even below.
So if we were to have
Daniel in this tree,
we could also have
Danielle by just having
a couple of more nodes below Daniel and
just having another green checkmark.
So it is solvable in
code, even though it's not
obvious from the graphical
representation, but absolutely
a corner case.
But thankfully, it is solvable in tries.
What might another downside
be, though, of a trie?
Like, you do get Big O of 1 time.
You can solve the
Daniel-Danielle problem.
But there's still a price being paid.
Any thoughts?
Yeah.
How about over to Ethan,
if I'm saying it right?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
I'm Ethan.
DAVID MALAN: Ethan.
AUDIENCE: I think it's because it
would just take a lot of memory
to house all of that.
And that could take a lot of time.
It could slow down the system.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
Yeah.
You can kind of see it
from my picture alone.
We only added three names
to this data structure.
But my God, like, there's
dozens, maybe 100 plus pointers
pictured here, even though
they might all be null.
Right?
If the absence of an arrow here suggests
that they're null, 0x0, but even
storing null, 0x0, is 8 0 bits.
So this is not lacking
for actual memory usage,
we're just not using
it very efficiently.
We have spent a huge
number of bits, or bytes,
or however you want to measure it.
Because look, even with the H's,
I'm using one pointer out of 26.
25 pointers are probably
initialized to null,
which means I'm wasting 25 pointers.
And you can imagine the lower
and lower you get in this tree,
the less likely there is to be a name
that even starts with H-A-G-R-I-D.
Daniel came up with a good
example with Danielle.
But that's not going to often happen.
Certainly, the lower
you get in this tree.
So as Ethan says, you're
wasting a huge amount of memory.
So yes, you're gaining constant time
look ups, but my God, at what price?
You might be using megabytes,
gigabytes of storage space.
Because, again, the most
important property of an array
is that it's all contiguous.
And therefore, you have random access.
But if you have to have
every node containing
an array of size 26
or anything else, you
have to spend the memory
over and over again.
So there, too, is a trade off.
While this might be
theoretically ideal, theory
does not necessarily mean practice.
And sometimes, designing something
that is textbook less efficient,
might actually be more
efficient in the real world.
And in Problem Set 5, in
your own spellchecker,
when you build up this
dictionary that we then
use to spell check very
large corpuses of text,
will you begin to experience some of
those real world trade offs yourself.
Well, we wanted to end today
with a look at what else
you can do with these
kinds of data structures,
just to give you a taste of
where else you can go with this
and what other kinds of
problems you can solve.
Again, thus far, we've looked
at arrays, which are really
the simplest of data structures.
And they're not even structures per se.
It's just contiguous blocks of memory.
We then introduced
linked lists, of course,
where you have this one
dimensional data structure that
allows you to stitch together nodes and
memory, giving you dynamic allocation.
And if you want deallocation, inserting
and deleting nodes if you want,
then we had trees, which kind of
gives us the best of both worlds,
arrays and linked lists.
But we have to spend more
space and use more pointers.
Then, of course, hash tables
kind of merged together
two of those ideas, arrays
and the linked lists.
And that starts to work well.
And indeed, that's what you'll
experiment with your own spellchecker.
But then, of course, there's
tries, which at first glance
seem better, but not without
great cost, as Ethan says.
So it turns out, with all of those
building blocks at your disposal,
you can actually use them as
lower level implementation details
to solve higher level problems.
And this is what are known as abstract
data structures, or abstract data
types.
An abstract data structure
is kind of a mental structure
that you can imagine, implementing
some real world problem,
typically, that's implemented
with some other data structure.
So you're sort of writing
code at this level.
But you're thinking about what you've
built ultimately at this level.
And that's abstraction, taking
lower level implementation
details, simplifying them for
the sake of discussion or problem
solving higher up.
So what's one such data structure?
A queue is a very common
abstract data structure.
What is a queue?
Well, those of you who
grew up, say, in Britain
call a line outside of a store a queue.
And that's, indeed,
where it gets its name.
A queue is a data structure
that has certain properties.
So if you're standing outside
of a store or a restaurant,
in healthier times, waiting to get
in, you're generally in a queue.
But there's an important
property of a queue.
At least, if you live
in a fair society, you'd
like to think that if you
are the first one in line,
you are the first one
to get out of line.
First in, first out.
It would be kind of obnoxious
if you're first in line
and then they start letting people
in who are behind you in that queue.
So a queue, if it's
implemented correctly,
has a property known as
FIFO, first in, first out.
And we humans would think of
that as just a fair property.
And a queue generally has two
operations associated with it at least,
enqueue and dequeue.
Those are just conventions.
You could call it add and remove,
or insert, delete, whatever.
But enqueue and dequeue are sort
of the more common ones to say.
So enqueuing means you
walk up to the store
and you get in line,
because you have to wait.
Dequeue means they're ready
to serve you or have you.
And so you get out of line.
That's dequeue.
And again, FIFO is just
a fancy acronym that
describes a key property of that,
which is that it's first in, first out.
So how could you implement a queue then?
Well, what's interesting about that
data structure is that it's abstract.
Right?
It's more of an idea than
an actual thing in code.
You want to implement some
kind of fair queuing system.
And so you think of it as a queue.
But frankly, if we're going to
translate that example to code,
you could imagine using
an array of persons.
That could implement a queue.
You could use a linked list of persons.
Frankly, either of those
would actually work.
Underneath the hood is the lower
level implementation details.
But what would be a problem,
if we translate this real world
analogy like queuing up outside
of a store to get in, into code
and you used an array?
What would a downside
be of using an array
to represent a queue, in general, even
though we're making a bit of a leap
from real world to code suddenly?
But there's probably a downside.
What might a downside be of using
an array to implement a queue, Ryan?
AUDIENCE: If you're using
an array, you can't really
just take out the existing values.
Because if you were thinking
about doing this in a line,
you would have to take out the first
person, take out the second person.
But you can't really dynamically
sort of change the memory after that.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Yeah.
That's a really good point.
Think about a line.
Suppose that there's a line that can
fit 10 people outside the Apple store.
Because Apple's pretty good right now
during the health crisis of letting
people in only so many at a time.
So suppose they have room for
10 people, six feet apart.
That's actually a pretty apt
analogy, this year more than ever.
But as Ryan says, if you want to dequeue
someone, then the first person in line
is going to go into the store.
And then the second person,
you're going to dequeue them.
They go into the store.
The problem with an
array, it would seem,
is that now you have essentially empty
spaces at the beginning of the line.
But you still don't have room at
the end of the line for new people.
Now there's an obvious
real world solution there.
You just say, hey, everyone, would
you mind taking a few steps forward?
But that's inefficient.
Not so much in the human world,
you've got to get into the store.
But in code, that's copying of values.
You have to move, like, eight values
two places over if two people were just
let into the store.
So now your dequeue
operation is Big O of n.
And that doesn't feel quite ideal.
And we can do better than
that if we're a little
clever with some local
variables and such.
But that would be one
challenge of a queue,
certainly, is just how well we
could implement it using an array.
So you might imagine, too,
an array is limited, too.
Because it would kind of be obnoxious
if you get to the Apple store.
There's already 10 people in line.
And they don't let you get in line.
They say, sorry, we're all full for
today, when they're obviously not.
Because eventually there'll
be more room in the queue.
A linked list would allow you to
keep appending more and more people.
And even if the line outside
the store gets crazy long,
at least the linked list
allows you to service
all of the customers who
are showing up over time.
An array of fixed size
would make that harder.
And, again, you could
allocate a bigger array.
But then you're going to have
to ask all the customers, hey,
could everyone come over here?
No.
Go back over there.
I mean, you're constantly moving humans,
or values and memory, back and forth.
So that is only to say that
to implement this real world
notion of a queue, which is very
commonly used even in the computer
world to represent certain ideas, for
instance, the printer queue, when you
send something to the printer,
especially on a campus or in a company,
there's a queue.
And ideally, the first
person who printed
is the first one who gets
their printouts thereafter.
Queues are also used in software.
But there's other abstract data
types out there besides queues.
One of them is called a stack.
So a stack is a data
structure that can also
be implemented underneath the hood
using arrays or linked lists or,
heck, maybe something else.
But stacks have a different property.
It's last in, first out.
Last in, first out.
So if you think about the
trays in the cafeteria,
in healthier times when everyone was
on campus using trays from a cafeteria,
you'll recall, of course, that
trays tend to get stacked like this.
And the last tray to go on top of the
stack is the first one to come out.
If you go to a clothing
store, your own closet,
if you don't hang things on
hangers or put them in drawers,
but kind of stack them, like
here, like all of these sweaters,
this is a stack of sweaters.
And how do I get at a sweater I want?
Well, the easiest way to do
it is with last in, first out.
So I constantly take the black
sweater, the black sweater.
But if I've stored all of
my sweaters in this stack,
you may never get to the
sort of lower level ones,
like the red or the blue sweater
because, again, of this data structure.
So LIFO, last in, first out,
is in fact, the property
used to characterize stacks.
And stacks are useful or not useful,
depending on the real world context.
But even within computing,
we'll see applications over time
where stacks indeed come into play.
And those two operations that those
things support are generally called
push and pop.
It's the same thing as add or remove or
insert or delete, but the terms of art
are generally push and pop, where this
is me popping a value off of the stack.
This is me pushing a
value onto the stack.
But, again, it's last in, first
out, otherwise known as LIFO.
And then there's this
other data structure
that actually has a very real world
analog, known as a dictionary.
A dictionary is an
abstract data type, which
means you can implement it with arrays,
or linked lists, or hash tables,
or tries, or whatever
else, an abstract data type
that allows you to
associate keys with values.
And the best analog here is
indeed in the real world.
What is a dictionary, like
an old school dictionary
that's actually printed
on paper in book form?
What is inside that book?
A whole bunch of keys, a whole bunch of
boldfaced words, like apple and banana
and so forth, each of which have
definitions, otherwise known as values.
And they're often
alphabetized to make it easier
for you to find things so that you
can look things up more quickly.
But a dictionary is an abstract data
type that associates keys with values.
And you look up the values
by way of their keys,
just like you look up a word's
definition by way of the word itself.
And dictionaries are actually
kind of all around us, too.
You don't think of them
in these terms, probably.
But if you've ever been to Sweet
Green, for instance, in New Haven
or in Cambridge or elsewhere,
this is a salad place
where nowadays, especially, you can
order in advance online or on an app
and then go into the store and
pick up your food from a shelf.
But the shelf, the way they do it
here in Cambridge and in other cities,
is they actually have letters of the
alphabet on the shelves, A, B, C, D, E,
F, all the way through Z. The idea being
that if I go in to pick up my salad,
it's probably on the D section,
if Brian goes in to pick up his,
it's in the B section, and so forth.
Now here, too, you can
imagine perverse corner cases
where this data structure,
this dictionary whereby
letters of the alphabet map to
values, which are people's salad,
is not necessarily fail proof.
Can you think of a
perverse corner case where
Sweet Green's very wonderful,
methodical system actually breaks down?
Can you think of a limitation here,
even if you've never been to Sweet Green
or never eaten a salad, what
could break down with this system
if going into a store and picking
something up based on your name?
Any thoughts?
BRIAN: A few people say
there might be a problem
if two people have the same name.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
If two people have the same names,
you start to stack things up.
So literally, Sweet Green will start
stacking one salad on top of the other.
So there is actually an
interesting incarnation
of one data type being built on
top of yet another data type.
So, again, all of these are sort of
like custom Scratch pieces, if you will,
that we're constantly sort
of reassembling into more
interesting and powerful ideas.
But at some point, if there's
a lot of B names, or D names,
or any letter of the alphabet, I surely
see a finite height to this shelf.
So it's kind of as though Sweet Green
has implemented their dictionary
using stacks with arrays.
Because arrays are fixed size.
So there's surely only so many
inches of space here vertically.
So you can see a real world limitation.
So what does Sweet Green
do if that happens?
They probably just kind of cheat
and put the D's in the C section,
or the D's in the E section.
Like, who really cares
in the real world?
Your eyes are probably going
to skim left and right.
But algorithmically, that
is slowing things down.
And in the worst case, if you're
really late to pick up your salad,
or if Sweet Green is
really popular and there's
a huge number of salads on the
shelf, your name might be Albus,
but your salad might end up
way over here in the Z section
if they're just out of room.
And so that, too, is a
valid algorithmic decision,
to just make room somewhere else.
But, again, trade offs
between time and space.
And so we thought we'd end on a
note, thanks to some friends of ours
at another institution who made
a wonderful visualization that
distinguished these notions
of stacks versus queues.
Stack and, again, a queue are
these abstract data types that
can be implemented in different ways.
They have different properties, each
of them respectively FIFO or LIFO.
And here, for instance, is a
final look in our final moments
together here today about how these
ideas manifest themselves, perhaps
in the real world, not unlike
this stack of sweaters here.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
- Once upon a time, there
was a guy named Jack.
When it came to making friends,
Jack did not have the knack.
So Jack went to talk to the
most popular guy he knew.
He went up to Lou and
asked, "What do I do?"
Lou saw that his friend
was really distressed.
"Well," Lou began, "just
look how you're dressed.
Don't you have any clothes
with a different look?"
"Yes," said Jack.
"I sure do.
Come to my house, and
I'll show them to you."
So they went off to Jack's.
And Jack showed Lou the box
where he kept all his shirts
and his pants and his socks.
Lou said, "I see you have
all your clothes in a pile.
Why don't you wear some
others once in a While?"
Jack said, "Well, when I
remove clothes and socks,
I wash them and put
them away in the box.
Then comes the next
morning, and up I hop.
I go to the box and get
my clothes off the top."
Lou quickly realized
the problem with Jack.
He kept clothes, CDS,
and books in the stack.
When he reached for
something to read or to wear,
he chose top book or underwear.
Then, when he was done, he
would put it right back.
Back it would go, on top of the stack.
"I know the solution!"
said a triumphant Lou.
"You need to learn to
start using a queue."
Lou took Jack's clothes
and hung them in a closet.
And when he had emptied
the box, he just tossed it.
Then he said, "Now, Jack, at the end of
the day, put your clothes on the left
when you put them away.
Then tomorrow morning when
you see the sunshine, get
your clothes from the right,
from the end of the line.
Don't you see?" said
Lou, "it will be so nice.
You'll wear everything once
before you wear something twice."
And with everything in queues
in his closet and shelf,
Jack started to feel quite
sure of himself, all thanks
to Lou and his wonderful queue.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
That's it for CS50.
We will see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]