[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this is week 6.
And this is, again, one of those
rare days where in just a bit of time
you'll be able to say that
you learned a new language.
And that language today is going
to be this language called Python.
And we'd thought we'd
begin by introducing Python
by way of some more familiar friends.
So this, of course, is where we
began the course back in week 0
when we introduced Scratch,
a simple program that
quite simply says "hello, world."
And then very quickly,
things escalated and became
a lot more cryptic, a lot more
arcane, and we introduced C and syntax
like this, which of course
do the exact same thing,
just printing out "hello, world" on
the screen, but with the requirement
that you understand and you
include all of this various syntax.
So today, all of this complexity,
all of the syntax from C,
suddenly begins to melt
away, such that we're
left with this new
language called Python
that's going to achieve the exact same
goal simply with this line of code
here.
Which is to say that Python
tends to be more accessible,
it tends to be a little easier.
But that's because it's built on
this tradition of having started,
as humans years ago, building
these low-level languages like C,
realizing what features are missing,
what some of the pain points are,
and then layering on top of those older
languages new ideas, new features,
and in turn new languages.
So there are dozens, hundreds really,
of programming languages out there.
But there's always a subset of them that
tend to be very popular, very in vogue
at any given time.
Python is among those
very popular languages.
And it's the third of our languages
that we'll look at, indeed,
at this point in the term.
So let's go ahead and introduce
some of the syntax of Python,
really by way of comparison with
what we've seen in the past.
Because no matter how new
some of today's topics are,
they should all be familiar in the sense
that we're going to see loops again,
conditions, variables,
functions, return values.
There's pretty much just going
to be a translation of features
past to now features present.
So this of course, in
the world of Scratch,
was just one puzzle piece or a
function, whose purpose in life
is to say "hello, world" on the screen.
In week 1, we translated this
to the more cryptic syntax here,
key details being that it's printf,
that you have the quote, the string,
"hello, world," you have this backslash
n to represent a new line character.
And then of course, this kind of
statement has to end with a semicolon.
The equivalent line of code
today on out in this language
called Python is going
to be quite simply this.
So it looks similar, certainly, but
it's now print instead of printf.
We still have the double quotes, but
gone are the backslash n as well as
the semicolon.
So if you've been kicking yourself
all too frequently for forgetting
stupid things like the semicolons,
Python will now be your friend.
Well, let's take a
look at another example
here, how we might go about
getting user input as well.
Well, here notice that we have
a puzzle piece called Ask.
And it says, ask "What's
your name?" and wait.
And the next puzzle piece said,
whatever the human had typed in,
precede it with the word "hello."
In C we saw code like
this-- string_answer
equals get_string "what's your name?"
and then printing out
with printf, "hello %s,"
plugging in one value for the other.
In Python, some of this complexity
is about to melt away, too.
And in Python, we're going to
see a little something like this.
So no longer present is the
mention of the type of variable.
No longer present is the
semicolon at the end.
And no longer present is the %s and
that additional argument to print.
So in fact, let's go ahead and
see these things in action.
I'm going to go ahead and go over
to CS50 IDE here for just a moment.
And within CS50 IDE, I'm
going to go ahead and write
my very first Python program.
And to do that, I'm going to go ahead
and create a file that we'll initially
called hello.py.
Much like in the world of C, Python
programs have a standard file extension
being .py instead of .c.
And I'm just going to do what I
proposed was the simplest translation.
I'm just going to go ahead
and say print, "hello, world."
I'm going to save my file.
And then I'm going to go
down to my terminal window.
And in the past, of course,
we would have used make,
and then we would have
done ./hello or the like.
But today, I'm quite simply going to run
a command that itself is called Python.
I'm going to pass in the
name of the file I just
created as its command line argument.
And voila, hitting Enter, there is
my very first program in Python.
So that's pretty powerful.
Let's go ahead and create the second
program that I proposed a moment ago.
Instead of just printing
out "hello, world"
the whole time, I'm also
going to go ahead this time
and give myself a variable
that I'll call answer.
I'm going to go ahead now
and get input from the user.
And I'm going to go ahead and
use the familiar get_string
that we did see in C.
I'm going to go ahead and ask,
"What's your name" question mark.
I'm not going to bother
with a semicolon.
But down here, I'm going to go ahead
and say print "hello," comma, and then
a space inside of the quotes.
And instead of doing something like %s,
I'm actually going to go ahead and just
do a plus operator, and then
literally the word "answer."
But the catch is that this
isn't going to work just yet.
This isn't going to work just yet,
because get_string, it turns out,
just like it doesn't come with C,
it also doesn't come with Python.
So I need to do one
thing that's going to be
a little bit different from the past.
Instead of hash including something,
I'm going to literally say
from cs50 import get_string.
So in the world of C,
recall that we included
cs50.h, which had declarations for
functions like get_string and get_int
and so forth.
In the world of Python, we're going to
show you something similar in spirit,
but the syntax is just
a little different.
We're going to say from cs50, which is
our Python library that we the staff
wrote, import, that is,
include a function specifically
called get_string.
And now any errors that I might
have seen a moment ago on the screen
have disappeared.
If I go ahead and save this file and now
do python space hello.py and hit Enter,
now I can go ahead and type in my actual
name, and voila, I see "hello," comma,
"David."
So let's tease apart what's
different about this code
and consider what more
we can do after this.
So again, notice-- on line 3,
there's no mention of string anymore.
If I want a variable, I just
go ahead and give myself
a variable called answer.
The function is still called get_string,
and it still takes an argument just
like the C version, but the line
no longer ends with a semicolon.
On my final line of code here, print
is now indeed print instead of printf.
And then this is new syntax.
But in some sense, it's going to
be a lot more straightforward.
Instead of having to think in advance
where I want the %s and my placeholder,
this plus operator seems to
be doing something for me.
And let me go ahead and ask
a question of the group here.
What does that plus
operator seem to be doing?
Because it's not addition
in the arithmetic sense.
We're not like adding numbers together.
But the plus is clearly doing something
that gives us a visual result.
Any thoughts from Peter?
What's this plus doing?
AUDIENCE: It's concatenating strings.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it's
concatenating strings,
which is the term of art to describe
the joining of one string and the other.
So it's quite like, therefore,
Scratch's own Join block.
We now have a literal
translation of that Join block,
which we didn't have in C. In C we
had to use printf, we had to use %s.
Python is going to be a little
more user friendly, such
that if you want to join
two strings like "hello,"
comma, space, and the
contents of that variable,
we can just use this
plus operator instead.
And the last thing that we
had to do was, of course,
import this library
so that we have access
to the get_string function itself.
Well, let's go ahead and take a
tour of just some other features
of Python and then dive in primarily
to a lot of hands-on examples today.
So recall that in the
example we just saw,
we had this first line of code,
which gets a string from the user,
stores it in a variable called answer.
We had this second line of
code, which as Peter notes,
concatenated two values together.
But it turns out, even though this is
definitely more convenient than in C
in that you can just take an
existing string and another
and join them together without having
to use format strings or the like,
well, it turns out there's
another way, there's frankly many
ways in languages like Python
to achieve the same result.
And I'm going to go ahead and propose
that we now change this line here
to this funky syntax.
So definitely ugly at
first glance, and that's
partly because this is a
relatively new feature of Python.
But notice that in Python can we use
these curly braces, so curly braces
that we have used in C, to plug in
an actual value of a variable here.
So instead of %s, Python's print
function uses these curly braces that
essentially say, plug in a value here.
But there's one oddity here.
You can't just start putting curly
braces and variable names into strings,
that is quoted strings in Python.
You also have to tell the language that
what follows is a formatted string.
So this is perhaps the
weirdest thing we've seen yet.
But when you do have a
pair of double quotes
like I have here, prefixing
it with an f will actually
tell the computer to format
the contents of that string,
plugging in values between those
currently braces, as opposed to
literally printing those
curly braces themselves.
So let me go ahead and transition to
my actual code here and try this out.
Instead of using the concatenation
operator as Peter described it,
this plus operator, let
me literally go ahead
and say, "hello, answer," initially.
So this is probably not going
to be the right approach,
because if I rerun this
program, python of hello.py,
it's going to ask me what's my name.
I'm going to type in
"David," and it's going
to ignore me altogether, because I
literally hardcoded "hello, answer."
But it's also not going to
be quite right to just start
putting that in curly braces, because
if I again run this program, python
of hello.py, and type in
my name, now it's going
to say "hello, squiggly brace answer."
So here is just a subtle
change where I have
to tell Python that this type of string
between the double quotes is in fact
a formatted string.
And now if I rerun python of
hello.py and type in "David,"
I now get "hello, David."
So it's marginally more convenient
than C, because, again, you
don't have to have a placeholder
here, a placeholder here, and then
a comma separated list
of additional arguments.
So it's just a more
succinct way, if you will,
to actually introduce more values
into a string that you want to create.
These are called format
strings, or for short f-strings.
And it's a new feature that we now
have in our toolkit when programming
with this new language called Python.
Well, let's take a look at a few
other translation of puzzle pieces
to see, and then turn
to Python and then start
building some programs of our own.
So here in Scratch, this was an
example early on of a variable
called counter, initializing it to 0.
In C, in week 1, we started translating
that to code like this-- int counter
equals 0 semicolon.
And that gave us a variable of
type int whose initial value was 0.
In Python, the code is
going to be similar--
similar, but it's going to
be a little simpler still.
Notice that I don't have to in Python
mention the type of variable I want.
It will infer from context what it is.
And I also don't have to
have the semicolon there.
So counter equals 0 in Python is going
to give you a variable called counter.
And because you're assigning
it the value 0, Python itself
the language will infer
that, oh, you must
mean this to be an int or an integer.
What else did we see in Scratch?
Change counter by 1.
So this was a way of increasing
the value of a variable by 1.
In C, we had a few different
ways to implement this.
We could say counter
equals counter plus 1.
It's kind of pedantic, it's kind
of long and tedious to type.
So instead, we had some
shorthand notation that
allowed us to do it this way instead.
In C, we were able to do
counter plus equals 1,
and that was going to
achieve the same result.
Well, in Python we actually have
a couple of approaches as well.
We can, much like in C,
say it explicitly like this
but just omit the semicolon.
So counter equals counter plus 1.
The logic in Python is
exactly the same as in C.
And as for this shorthand notation,
this also exists in Python, again
without the semicolon.
The one thing that does not exist in
Python at this point in the story is
that fancy counter++ syntax, or i++,
that syntactic sugar that made it even
more succinct to just
increment a variable,
unfortunately does not exist in Python.
But you can do counter plus equals 1,
or whatever your variable happens to be.
Well, what else did we
see in Scratch and then C?
recall this.
We introduced, of course,
conditions pretty early on.
And those conditions
use Boolean expressions
to decide whether to do this, or
this other thing, or something else
altogether.
In C, we converted this to
what looked kind of similar.
Indeed, the curly braces kind
of hug the printf line, just
like the yellow condition here
hugs the purple Say block.
And we had parentheses around the
Boolean expression, like x less than y.
We again used printf
inside of the curly braces
which had double quotes, a backslash
n for a new line, and a semicolon.
Python, nicely enough, is going
to be sort of identical in spirit
but simpler syntactically.
What Python is going to look
like henceforth is just this.
So the parentheses around
the x less than y go away.
The curly braces go away.
The new line goes away.
And the semicolon goes away.
And here you see just a tiny example
of evolution of humans programming
languages.
If you and I have been frustrated
for some time about all
the stupid semicolons and curly
braces all over the place,
it makes it harder, in some
sense, for your code to read,
let alone being correct, humans
decided when inventing new languages
that, you know what, why
don't we just say what we mean
and not worry as much about all
of this syntactic complexity?
Let's keep things simpler.
And indeed, that's what we see
here, is one example in Python.
But there's a key detail.
If any of you have
been in the habit, when
writing code in C, of being
a little sloppy when it comes
to your indentation, and
maybe style50 is constantly
yelling at you to add spaces, add
spaces, or remove spaces or lines,
well, in Python it is now necessary
to indent your code correctly.
In C, of course, we, CS50 and
a lot of the world in general
recommend that you indent your code
by 4 spaces, typically, or one tab.
In the context of
Python, you must do so.
If you accidentally omit these spaces
just to the left of the print statement
here, your Python code is
not going to run at all.
The Python program just won't work.
So no more sloppiness.
Python is going to impose this on you.
But the upside is you don't have to
bother including the curly braces.
What about a more complicated
condition where there's
two paths you can follow, if or else?
Well, in this case in C, we translated
it pretty straightforwardly like this.
Again, parentheses up here, curly
braces here and here, backslash n,
backslash n, and semicolon.
You can perhaps guess
in Python that this
is going to get a little
more compact, because boom,
now we don't need the
parentheses anymore.
We do we need to indent, but
we don't need the curly braces.
We don't need the new line, and
we don't need the semicolon.
So we're sort of shedding features
that can be taken now for granted.
What about this example in Scratch when
we had a three-way fork in the road,
if, else, if, else?
Well, in Python-- or rather in C, we
would have translated this like this.
And there's not much going on there.
But it's pretty substantive number
of lines of code, some 12 lines,
just to achieve this simple idea.
In Python, notice what's
going to go away here
is, again those parentheses, again those
curly braces, again the backslash n,
and the semicolon.
There's only one oddity here.
There's only one oddity.
What looks wrong or weird to you?
Maybe, what looks like a typo to you?
And I promise I haven't screwed up here.
Maybe elsewhere, but not here.
Andrew?
AUDIENCE: I would say the elif instead
of else if is different syntactically.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So whereas in C we would literally say
else if, in Python, humans years ago,
decided, heck, why say else if and waste
all of that time typing that out if you
can more succinctly say "elif"
as one word, E-L-I-F. So indeed,
this is correct syntax here.
And you can have more of those.
You can have four forks in the road,
five, six, any number thereafter.
But the syntax is indeed
a little different.
But it's a little tighter, right?
There's less syntactic distraction
when you glance at this code.
You don't have to ignore as
many semicolons and curly
braces and the like.
Python tends to just be a
little cleaner syntactically.
And indeed, that's
characteristic of a lot of more
recent, more modern languages like it.
All right, let's take a look at a few
other blocks in Scratch and in turn C.
In Scratch, when we wanted to do
something again and again as a loop,
perhaps forever, we would
literally use the Forever block.
In C, we could implement
this in a few different ways.
And we proposed quite simply this one--
while true print out "hello, world,"
again and again and again.
And because the Boolean
expression never changes,
it's going to indeed execute forever.
So Python is actually
pretty similar, but there
are a couple of subtle differences.
So ingrain in your mind
what this looks like here.
We have true in parentheses, the curly
braces, the new line, the semicolon.
A lot of that's about to
go away, but they're still
going to be a slight difference.
Notice that we're indenting,
as I keep emphasizing.
We no longer have the new line or the
semicolon or the currently braces,
but True--
and it turns out, False--
now must be capitalized.
So whereas in C it was lowercase
false, lowercase true, in Python
it's going to be capitalized
False, capitalized True.
Why?
Just because.
But there is one other detail that's
important to note, both with our loops
here, as well as with our conditions.
Just as before, if I rewind
to our most recent condition,
notice that even though we've
gotten rid of the curly braces
and we've gotten rid of
the parentheses, we now
have introduced these colons, which
are necessary after this expression,
this expression, and this
one, to make clear to Python
that the lines of code that
follow indented underneath
are indeed relevant to
that if, elif, or else.
And we see that same feature again
here in the context of a loop.
We saw other loops, of course.
In Scratch, when we
wanted to do something
a finite number of times like 3, we
would repeat the following three times.
In C, we had a few different
approaches to this.
And all of them, I dare
say, were very mechanical.
Like, if you want to do something
three times, the onus in C
is on you to declare a variable,
keep track of how many times
you've counted already,
increment the thing.
Like, there's a lot of moving parts.
And so in C, one approach
looked like this.
We declare a variable
called i equals 0--
but we could call it anything we wan--
we have a while block here that's
asking a Boolean expression again
and again, is i less than 0--
is i less than 3?
And then inside of the loop,
we printed out "hello, world."
And using C's syntactic
sugar, the plus plus notation,
we kept adding 1 to i,
add 1 to i, add 1 to i,
until we implicitly
break out of the loop
because it's, of course,
no longer less than 3.
So in Python, similar in spirit, but
again, some of that clutter goes away.
i equals 0 is all we need say
to give ourselves a variable.
While i less than 3 is all we need
to say there but with a colon.
Then inside of that, indented
properly, we print out "hello, world."
And-- we can't do the plus
plus, so minor disappointment--
but i plus equals 1 increments i.
So this would be one way of implementing
in Python the exact same thing a loop
that executes three times.
But we saw other
approaches, of course, in C,
and there's other approaches
possible in Python as well.
You might recall in C that we
saw this approach, the for loop.
And odds are you've been
reaching for the for loop
pretty frequently, because even
though it looks a little more cryptic,
you can pack more features
into that one line of code
in between those
semicolons, if you will.
So same exact logic, it just
prints out this "hello, world"
three times using a for loop instead.
In Python, things start to
get a little elegant here now.
It's a little weird at first glance,
but it's definitely more succinct.
If you want to do something three
times, it turns out in Python
you can use a more succinct
syntax for the for loop-- for i
in, and then in square
brackets a list of values.
So just as we used in the past square
brackets in a few different places
to connote arrays and indexing into
arrays, in the world of Python whenever
you surround a bunch of values that
themselves have commas in between them,
and you encapsulate them
all using square brackets,
that's what we're going
to call in Python a list.
And it's very similar
in spirit to an array,
but we'll call it in the
context of Python a list.
And so what this line of code says is,
for i in 0, 1, 2-- what does that mean?
This is a for loop in Python that
says, give me a variable called i.
And on the first iteration of
this loop set i equal to 0.
On the second iteration of
this loop set i equal to 1.
And on the last iteration of this
loop, set i equal to 2 for me.
It just does all of that for you.
Now, at the end of the
day it actually doesn't
matter what i is per se, because
I'm not printing the value of i.
And that's totally fine.
Odds are you've used for loops where
you did something again and again,
like printing "hello, world,"
even though you didn't print out
the value of i.
So technically, I could have put
any 3 things in the square brackets
if I want.
But the convention would be just
enumerate, just like in C, 0, 1, 2,
just like a computer
scientist counting from 0.
But this could break down pretty easily.
This could become very
ugly very quickly.
Does anyone see a problem
with for loops in Python
if you have to put in between those
square brackets the list of values
that you want to iterate over?
Noah?
AUDIENCE: If you want to do,
for example, a thing 50 times,
you'd have to write out
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
My God, it would start
to look hideous quickly.
And it's funny you mention
50, because in preparing
this demonstration for lecture
today, I went back to week 0,
when actually the analog in week 0
was to indeed print out "hello, world"
50 times.
And I thought to
myself, damn it, this is
going to look atrocious
now, because I literally
have to put inside of square
brackets 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9, all the way to 49, as Noah says,
which would just look atrocious.
Like, surely there's
got to be a better way.
And there is.
While this might be compelling
for very short values,
there's a simpler way
in Python when you want
to do something some number of times.
We can replace this list
of three values with this,
a function called range that takes an
input, which is the number of things
that you want to return.
And essentially, what range will
do for you passed an input like 3,
it will automatically generate for you
a list of three values, 0, 1, and 2.
And then Python will iterate
over those three values for you.
So to Noah's concern a moment ago,
if I now want to iterate 50 times,
I just change the 3
to a 50, I don't have
to create this crazy mess of a manually
typed out list of 0 through 49,
which, of course, would not be a very
well designed a program, it would seem,
just because of the length of it and
the opportunity to mess up and the like.
So in Python, this is perhaps now,
if you will, the most Pythonic way
to do something some number of times.
And indeed, this is a term of
art in the Python community.
Long story short, technical
people, programmers,
they tend to be pretty
religious in some sense
when it comes to the "right
way" of doing things.
And indeed, within the
world of Python programming,
a lot of Python programmers
do have both opinions
but also standardized recommendations
that dictate how you "should"
write Python code.
And tricks like this are
what are considered Pythonic.
You are doing something Pythonically
if you're doing it the quote, unquote
"right way," which doesn't
mean right in the absolute,
it means right in the sense
that most other people, rather,
agree with you in this sense.
All right.
Let's see a few final features
of Python before we now start
to build some of our own features.
In C, recall, we had this
whole list of data types.
And there are more, and you
can create your own, of course.
But the primitives that
we looked at initially
were these-- bool, char, double,
float, int, long, string, and so forth.
In Python, even though
I haven't needed them,
because I can give myself a
variable like a string or an int,
just by giving it a name
like counter or i or answer,
and then assigning it
a value, and Python
infers from what you're assigning
it what data type it should be,
Python does have data types.
It's just what's known
in the programming
world as a loosely typed language.
In the world of C, C is a
strongly typed language,
where, not only do types exist,
you must use them explicitly.
In the world of Python,
you have what's called
a loosely typed language,
in which types exist,
but you can often infer them implicitly.
The burden is not on you
the programmer to specify
those data types incessantly.
Let the computer figure it out for you.
So this is our list from C.
This now is going to be our analogous
list in the world of Python.
We're going to have bool
still, True and False,
but capital T, capital F.
We're going to have floats,
which are real numbers
with decimal points.
We're going to have ints, which of
course are numbers like negative 1,
0, and 1, and so forth.
And then not strings per
se, but "stirs", S-T-R.
And where is in the world of C, there
was technically no "string type"--
that was a feature offered by the
cs50 library, which just made more
accessible the idea of a char star--
recall that C has strings.
And they're called strings, but
there's no data type called string.
The way you give yourself
a string, of course, in C
is to declare something as a char star.
And in cs50's library, we
just gave that char star
a synonym, a nickname, an
alias, called "string."
In Python, there are actual--
there is an actual
data type for strings.
And for short, it's called S-T-R.
All right.
So with that said, what
other features do we
have from Python that we can use here?
Well, there's other
data types as well in
Python that are actually going
to prove super useful as we begin
to develop more
sophisticated programs and do
even cooler things with the language.
We've seen range already.
Strictly speaking, this is a
data type of sorts within Python
that gives you back a range
of values, by default 0 on up,
based on the input you provide.
List, I keep mentioning verbally.
A list is a proper data type in Python
that's similar in spirit to arrays.
But whereas in arrays--
recall, we've spent great
emphasis over the past few weeks
noting that arrays are a fixed size.
You have to decide in advance how
big that array is going to be.
And like last week, if you
decide, oops, I need more memory,
you have to dynamically
allocate more space for it,
copy values over, and then
free up the old memory.
Like, there's so much jumping
through hoops, so to speak,
when you want to use arrays in C if you
want to grow them or even shrink them.
Python and other higher-level languages
like it do all of that for you.
So a list is like an array that
automatically resizes itself,
bigger and smaller.
That feature now you get for free
in the language, so to speak.
You don't have to implement it yourself.
Python has what are called tuples.
In the context of like
math, or GPS, you might
have x- and y-coordinates, or
latitude and longitude coordinates,
so like comma separated values.
Tuples are one way of
implementing those in Python.
Dict, or dictionaries.
So Python has dictionaries that
allow you to store keys and values.
Or literally in our human world, if
you have a human dictionary here,
for instance for English, much
like a dictionary in physical form,
lets you store words and their
definitions, a dictionary in Python,
more generally, lets you
store any keys and any values.
You can associate one
thing with another.
And we'll see that this is a wonderfully
useful and versatile data structure.
And then lastly for
today's purposes, there's
these things called sets
which, if you recall from math,
a set is a collection of values, like
a, b, c or 1, 2, 3, without duplicates.
But Python manages that for you.
You can add items to a set, you
can remove items from a set.
Python will make sure that
there are no duplicates for you,
and it will manage all of
the memory for you as well.
So what we have in the way of functions,
meanwhile, is a few familiar friends.
Recall that in C we used the
cs50 library to get chars,
doubles, floats, ints,
longs, and strings.
In Python, thankfully, we don't have to
worry about doubles or longs anymore.
More on that in a bit.
But the cs50 library for Python, which
you saw me import a few minutes ago,
does give you a function
called get_float.
It does give you a
function called get_int,
it does give you a
function called get_string,
that, at least for this
week's purposes, are just
going to make your life easier.
These two are training wheels
that we will very quickly take off
so that you're only using
native Python code ultimately,
and not CS50'S own library.
But for the sake of transitioning
this week from C to Python,
you'll find that these will just
make your life easier before we relax
and take those away, too.
So in C, to use the library
you had to include cs50.h.
In Python, again you're
going to go ahead and import
cs50, or more explicitly, the specific
function that you might want to import.
So it turns out there's
different ways to import things.
They ultimately achieve
essentially the same goal.
You can, with lines
like this, explicitly
import one function at a time, like
I did earlier using get_string,
or you can import the
whole library all at once
by just saying more
succinctly, import cs50.
It's going to affect the syntax
we have to use hereafter,
but you'll see multiple ways of doing
this in our examples here on out.
You can also simplify
this a bit, and you
can import a comma separated list of
functions from a library like ours.
And this is a convention we'll
see quite frequently as well.
Because if we start using popular
third-party libraries written
by other programmers on the
internet, they will very commonly
give us lots of functions
that we ourselves can use,
and we will be able to import
those one after the other,
by just specifying
them here in this way.
All right.
Let me pause here just to see if
there's any questions on Python syntax.
Like, that's essentially it for
our crash course in Python syntax.
We're now going to start building things
and explore what the features of Python
are and what some of the nuances
are, and really the power of Python.
But first, any questions on syntax?
We've seen loops, conditions, variables.
Olivia, question or comment.
AUDIENCE: In a for loop, if you want
to increment by something besides 1,
but you don't want to explicitly type
out the list, how would you do that?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
So if you wanted to use a for loop
and iterate over a range of values,
but you wanted that range to be 0,
2, 4, 6, 8, instead of 0, 1, 2, 3,
let me go ahead and go back to
that slide from a moment ago.
And I can actually
change this on the fly.
Let me go into that slide,
which was right here.
And what I can do, actually, is specify
another value, which might be this.
If I change the input to range to
be not one value but two values,
that's going to be a
clue to the computer
that it should count a
total of three values,
but it should increment 2 at a time
instead of the default, which is 1.
And there's even other
capabilities there, too.
You don't have to start counting at 0.
You can adjust that as well, which
is to say that with Python, you're
going to find a lot more
features come with the language,
and even more powerfully, the
functions that you can write
and the functions that
you can use in Python
also can take different
numbers of arguments.
Sometimes it's 0, sometimes
it's 1, sometimes it's 2.
But it's ultimately often up to you.
Good catch.
Other questions?
AUDIENCE: Will we see sequences
primarily in the for loops?
Or are there other applications
where they're very useful?
DAVID MALAN: Sequences in what sense?
In the sense of ranges or
lists or something else?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, in terms
of ranges, specifically.
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
Will we use them in other contexts?
Generally speaking, it's pretty rare.
I mean, I'm racking my brain
now as to other use cases
that I have used range for.
And I'm sure I could
come up with something.
But I think hands down, the most common
case is in the context of iteration,
as in a for loop.
And I'll think on that to
see other applications.
But any time you want to
generate a long list of values
that follow some pattern, whether
it's 0, 1, 2, or as Olivia points out,
a range of values with
gaps, range will allow
you to avoid having to
hardcode it entirely.
And you can actually write your own
generator function, so to speak,
a function that returns whatever
pattern of values that you want.
Other questions or confusion?
Anything on your end, Brian,
from the chat or beyond?
BRIAN: Looks like all the
questions are answered here.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
Well, let's go ahead now and
do something more interesting
than hello, world.
Because after all, this is where
programming really gets fun,
really gets powerful,
when you and I no longer
have to implement those low-level
implementation details, when
you had to implement memory
management for your hash table,
or memory management for a linked
list, or copying values in an array.
We've spent the past several
weeks focusing really
on some low-level primitives
that are useful to understand,
but they're not fun to write.
And I concede that they might not
be fun to write in problem set form.
And they're certainly not going to be
fun to write for the rest of your life,
every time you want to just
write code to solve some problem.
But again, that's where
libraries come in.
And now, this is where
other languages come in.
It turns out that Python is
a much better, a much easier
language to use for solving
certain types of problems,
among them some of the problems we have
been solving in past problems sets.
So in fact, let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead
and grab a file here--
give me one moment--
called bridge.bmp, which you might
recall from a past problem set.
This is the beautiful Weeks bridge down
by the Charles River in Cambridge, Mass
by Harvard.
And this is a very clear photograph
taken by one of CS50's team members.
And in recent weeks, of
course, you wrote code
to do all sorts of mutations of this
image, among them blurring the image.
And blur, I dare say, was not
the easiest problem to solve.
You had to look up, down, left,
and right, sort of average
all of those pixels.
You had to understand how an image
is represented one pixel at a time.
So there's a lot of low-level minutia
there, when at the end of the day,
all you want to do is
just blur an image.
So whereas in past weeks we sort of
had to think at and write at this lower
level, now with Python
it turns out we're
going to have the ability to think
at a higher level of abstraction
and write far less code for ourselves.
So let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to use my Mac for
this instead of CS50 IDE,
so I can open the images more quickly.
This is to say that, even
though we'll continue
using CS50 IDE for Python
and for other languages
over the remainder of the course, you
can also install the requisite software
on a Mac, on a PC, sometimes
even kind of sort of a phone
today, to use Python and sort of see,
in other languages, on your own devices.
But again, we tend to
CS50 IDE during the class
so as to have a standard
environment that just works.
So I'm going to go
ahead and write, though,
on my computer a program
called blur.py, py, of course,
being the file extension
for Python programs.
So my program looks a
little different now.
I've got this black and
blue and white window.
But this is just a text editor
on my own personal Mac here.
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I need to have some
functionality related to images
in order to blur an image.
So I'm going to go ahead and
import from a PIL library,
a Pillow library, so to
speak, a special feature
called Image and a special
feature called ImageFilter.
That is to say, these are
essentially two functions
that someone else smarter than me when
it comes to image manipulation wrote,
they made their code freely available
on the internet free and open source,
which means anyone can use
the code, and I am allowed now
to import it into my program, because
I before class downloaded and installed
it beforehand.
Now I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to give myself
a variable called before.
And I'm going to call
Image.open on bridge.bmp.
So again, even though we've never seen
this before, never used this before,
you can kind of glean
syntactically what's going on.
I've got a variable on
the left called before.
I've got a function on the
right called Image.open,
and I'm passing in the name bridge.bmp.
So it sounds like this is kind
of like fopen in the world of C.
Now notice, this dot is kind
of serving a new role here.
In the past, we've used the
operator only for structs in C,
when we want to go into a person
object, or into a node object,
and we want to go inside of it
and access some variable therein.
Well, it turns out in Python, you have
things similar in spirit to structs
in C. But instead of containing only
variables or data, like name and number
like we did for the person
struct a few weeks back,
in Python you can have
inside of a structure
not only data, that is
variables, you can also
have functions inside of structures.
And that starts to open up
all sorts of possibilities
in terms of features available to you.
So it seems that I've got this Image
object, this Image struct that I've,
again, imported from someone else.
Inside of it is an open
function that expects
as input the name of a file to open.
So we'll see this syntax increasingly
over the course of today's examples.
Let me give myself a
second variable, after.
Let me go ahead now and
assign to this variable called
after the results of calling that
before image's filter function,
passing in ImageFilter.BoxBlur of 1.
Now, this is a little
cryptic, and we're not
going to spend time on this
particular syntax, because odds are,
in life you're not going to have
that many opportunities to want
to blur an image for which you're
going to run and write code.
But for today's purposes, notice
that inside of my before variable,
because I assigned it the return
value of this new feature,
it has inside of it not just data
but also functions, one of them
now called filter.
And this filter function takes as input
the return value of some other function
called that, long story short,
will blur my image using
a box of a 1-pixel radius.
So just like your own code,
if you implemented blur in C,
this code is going to tell my code
to look up, down, left, and right
and blur the pixels by taking
the average around them.
And that's kind of it.
After that I'm going to do after.save.
And I'm going to save this as out.bmp.
I just want to create a
new file called out.bmp.
And if I've made no
mistakes, let me go ahead now
and run python of blur.py and hit Enter.
No error messages, so
that's usually a good thing.
If I type ls now, notice
that I've got bridge.bmp,
which I already opened, blur.py,
which I just wrote, and out.bmp.
And if I go ahead and open out.bmp,
let's go ahead and take a look.
Here's before, here's after.
Huh.
Before, after.
Now, over the internet
it probably doesn't
look that blurred, though on my
Mac right here a few inches away,
it definitely looks blurred.
But let's do it a little
more compellingly.
How about, instead of looking one
pixel up, down, left, and right,
why don't we look 10 pixels at a time?
So we really blur it by looking
at more values and averaging more.
Let me go ahead now and
run python of blur.py.
Now let me go ahead and reopen.
And now you see before and after.
Before and after.
So what is this to say?
Well, here is, what, problem set 4 in
four lines of code blurring an image.
So pretty cool, pretty powerful.
By standing on the shoulders of
others and using their libraries can
we do other things quite quickly.
Notice what I can also do here,
too, is solve a more recent problem.
Let me go over to a different
directory, where I have in advance--
and you can download these files
off of the course's website--
a few files that we wrote before class.
One is called speller.py.
So long story short, speller.py
is a translation from C
into Python the code for speller.c.
Recall that that was part of the
distribution code for problem set 5,
and in speller.c, we translated
it now to speller.py.
And in dictionaries and in
texts, we see the same files,
as in problem set 5, two different
sized dictionaries and a whole bunch
of short and long texts.
What hasn't been created yet is the
equivalent of a dictionary.c, a.k.a.
now, dictionary.py.
So let me go ahead and implement
my spell checker in Python.
Let me go ahead and create a file
called dictionary.py, as is again,
the convention.
And let's go ahead.
We have to implement
four functions, right?
We have to implement check,
load, size, and unload.
But I probably need like a global
variable here to store my dictionary.
And this is where you all implemented
your hash table with a pointer,
and then linked lists, and arrays,
and all of that, a lot of complexity.
You know what, I'm just going to go
ahead and give myself a variable called
words and declare it as a set.
So recall that a set is
just a collection of values
that handles duplicates for you.
And frankly, that's all I really need.
I need to be able to store all
of the words in a dictionary
and just throw them into a set, so
that there's no duplicate values
and I can just check, is one
word in the set or is it not.
Well, let's go ahead now and
load words into that set.
I'm going to go ahead and
define a function called load
that takes the name of a file to open.
And here is some
admittedly some new syntax.
So thus far, we've only typed
code into the file itself.
In fact, the most striking
difference thus far,
dare say, about Python versus
C, is that I have never
once even written a main function.
And that, too, is a feature of Python.
If you want to write
a program, you don't
have to bother writing your default
code in a function called main.
Just start writing your code.
And that's how we were
able to get hello, world
down from this many lines of
code in C to one line in Python.
We didn't even need to have main.
But if I want to define my own
functions, it turns out in Python,
you use the key word def for define,
then you put the name of the function ,
and then in parentheses, like in C,
you put the names of the variables
or parameters that you
want the function to take.
You don't have to specify
data types, though.
And again, we don't use curly
braces, we're instead using a colon.
So this says, hey, Python, give
me a function called load that
takes an argument called dictionary.
And what should this function do?
Well, the purpose of the
load function in speller
was to load each word
from the dictionary
and somehow put it into your hash table.
I'm going to go ahead and do the same--
read each word from the dictionary
and put it into this so-called
set, my variable called words.
So I'm going to go ahead and open the
file, which I can do with this function
here.
In Python, you don't use fopen.
You just use a function called open.
And I'm going to sign the return value
of open to a variable called file.
But I could call that anything I want.
This is where Python gets really cool.
Recall that reading
the lines from Python--
from the file in C was
kind of arduous, right?
You had to use fread
or some other function
in order to read
character after character
after character, one line at a time.
Well, here in Python,
you know what, if I
want to iterate over all
the lines in the file,
we'll just say for line in file.
This is going to automatically
give me a for loop that
assigns the variable line to each
successive line in the file for me.
It will figure out where
all of those lines are.
What do I want to do with each line?
Well, I want to go ahead and add
to my set of words that line.
Insofar as each word--
each line represents a word, I just
want to add to my global variable words
that line.
And that's not quite
right, because what's
at the end of every line in my file?
Every line in my file by definition
has a backslash n, right?
That is why all of the
words in the big dictionary
we gave you are one per line.
So how do you get rid of the
new line at the end of a string?
Well, in C, my God, we would have
to use malloc to make a copy,
and then move all of the characters
over, and then shorten it a little bit
by getting rid of the backslash n.
Uh-uh.
In Python, if you want to strip off
the new line at the end of a string,
just do rstrip.
To strip characters means by
default to strip off white space.
White space includes the space bar,
the tab character, and backslash n.
And so if you want to take
each line and throw away
the trailing new line at the end of
it, you can simply say line.rstrip.
And this is where strings
again in Python are powerful.
Because they are their own data
type, they have inside of them,
not only all of the characters composing
the string, but also functions,
like rstrip which strips
from the end of the line
any white space that might be there.
You know what, after
this I think I'm done.
I'm just going to go
ahead and close the file,
and I'm going to go
ahead and return True.
So that's it.
That's the load function in Python.
Open the dictionary, for
each line in the file
add it to your global variable,
close the file, return True.
I mean, I'm pretty sure that my code is
probably several lines, and certainly
many hours, shorter than
your code might have
been for implementing that as well.
Well, what about checking?
Maybe the complexity is just elsewhere.
Well, let me go ahead
and define a function
called check that takes a specific
word as input as its argument.
And then I'm just going to check if
that given word is in my set of words.
Well, it turns out in
C you would probably
have to use a for loop or
a while loop, and you'd
have to iterate over
the whole list of words
that you've loaded using binary
search or linear search or the like.
Ugh, I'm so past that at
this point so many weeks in.
I'm just going to say, if word in words,
go ahead and return True, else return
False.
And that now is my
implementation of check.
Now, it's a little buggy.
And I will fix this.
Does anyone spot the bug?
Even if you've never seen Python before,
but having spent hours implementing
your own version of check, is there
some step I'm missing logically?
There is a bug here.
Does anyone spot what I'm
not doing that you probably
did do when checking if a given
word is in fact in the dictionary?
BRIAN: A couple of people are
commenting on case sensitivity.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, case sensitivity.
So odds are, in your
implementation in C you probably
forced the word to all uppercase,
or you forced it to all lowercase.
Totally doable, but you probably had
to do it like character for character.
You might have had to copy the
input using malloc, or putting it
into an array character
for character, then
using a toupper or tolower to capitalize
or lowercase each individual letter.
Ugh, like, that would take
forever, as indeed it might have.
So you know what, if you want to
take a given word and lowercase it,
just say word.lower.
And Python will take care of
all of those steps of iterating
over every character, changing each
one to lowercase, and returning to you
the new result. And indeed,
this now, I would think,
is consistent with what you
did in your example as well.
Well, how about size?
Well, in size recall
that you had to define
a function that doesn't take any
inputs but returns the number of words
in the set of words.
And I'm going to go ahead
here-- and actually, I
got my invitation slightly off here.
Let me fix this real fast.
If you want to return the
size of your dictionary,
or really the number
of words in your set,
you can just return the length
of that global variable words.
Done.
And lastly, if you want
to unload the dictionary,
let me go ahead and unload things.
Doesn't take input as well.
Honestly, because I've not
done any equivalent of malloc,
I've not done any
memory management-- why?
You don't have to in Python--
I can literally just return True in all
cases, because my code is undoubtedly
correct, because I didn't have to bother
with pointers and addresses and memory
management.
So all of the stress that might have
been induced over the past few weeks
as you understood the lower level
details of memory management now
go away, not because it's not
happening underneath the hood,
but because Python is doing it for you.
And I did spot one bug here actually.
Notice I kind of relapsed
into C code here.
What I should have said here
is it's actually file.close.
So here when I close the file in load,
I actually have to call file.close,
because now that function close is
associated with that variable for me.
So again, there is memory
management happening.
Malloc and free or realloc are
all happening sort of for you
underneath the hood.
But what Python the
language is doing for
you now is managing all of that for you.
That's what you get by using a
so-called higher-level language instead
of a lower-level language.
You get more features,
and in turn in this case,
you get all of those problems
taken care of for you,
so that you and I can focus
on building our spell checker,
so you and I can focus on
building our Instagram filters,
not on allocating memory, copying
strings, uppercase and things, which
honestly, while it might have been
fun and very gratifying the first time
you got those things working,
programming would very quickly become
the most tedious thing in
the world if any time you
want to write a program you have to
think and write code at that low level.
All right.
Let me go ahead and really cross my
fingers that I didn't screw up here,
and go ahead and run this code.
So I'm going to go ahead and
run python of speller.py--
which, admittedly, I wrote in advance,
because just like the distribution
code in speller, we wrote speller.c for
you, we wrote speller.py in advance.
But we won't look at
the internals of that.
I'm going to go ahead
and test this on, how
about something big like Shakespeare.
And I'm going to cross my fingers here.
And so far so good.
The words are kind of flying by.
I'm going to assume they're correct.
Hopefully we'll get to the output.
And it looks like, yeah, I think
I see some familiar numbers here.
I've got 143,091 words.
And then down here, the total time
involved was just under 1 second.
So that's pretty darn fast.
And to be clear, I'm using
my Mac instead of the IDE,
so my numbers might be a little
different than in the cloud, but 0.9
seconds.
But you know what, out of curiosity, let
me open up a different tab real quick,
and let me go ahead and make
speller from problem set 5.
So I brought in advance our own
implementation of speller, the staff
solution, written in C in
dictionary.c and speller.c,
and I've just compiled it with make.
And let me go ahead and run ./speller
using the same text on Shakespeare.
So again, I just ran
the Python version, now
I want to run the C version
using the staff's implementation.
All right.
Wow.
All right, it flew by way
faster, kind of twice as fast.
And notice, even though the numbers are
the same up above, the times are not.
My C version took 0.52
seconds, so half a second.
My Python version took
0.9, or roughly 1 second.
So it would seem that my C version is
faster, my Python version is slower.
Why might that be?
Because I'm kind of disappointed
if we just spent all this time
preaching the virtues of
Python, and yet here we
are writing worse code, in some sense.
Santiago?
AUDIENCE: Could it be because
C, even though it's low level,
it explicitly tells the
computer what to do,
and so that makes it a little
faster, whilst in Python it all
happens like underneath the
hood, as you were saying,
so that could make it a little slower.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
In Python, you have a
general-purpose solution
to the problem of memory
management, and capitalization,
and all of these other
features, that we ourselves
have to implement ourselves in C. Python
has general-purpose implementations
of all of those.
But there's a price you pay by using
someone else's code to implement
all of those things for you.
And you pay an even greater price
by using the type of language
that Python is in a sense.
So there's been this
other salient difference
between using C and using Python.
When I wrote C code, I would
compile my code from source code
into machine code.
And recall that machine code
are 0's and 1's understood
by the computer's brain, the so-called
CPU, or Central Processing Unit.
We always had to compile our code
every time we changed the source code.
And then we did like
./hello to run the program.
But every demo thus far in Python,
I haven't used make or clang.
I have used not ./hello, but rather
python space the name of the program.
And why is that?
Well, it turns out that Python
is often implemented as what
we describe with an interpreter.
So Python is not only a language
like we've been writing,
it's also a program unto itself.
The Python program I keep running
is an identically named program
that understands the Python language.
And what's happening, though, is that
by using an interpreter, so to speak,
to run my programs you're
incurring some amount of overhead.
You're paying a performance price.
Why?
Well, computers, recall from
week 0, at the end of the day,
only understand 0's and 1's.
That's what makes them tick.
But I have not outputted
any 0's and 1's.
I the human have only
been writing Python.
So there needs to be some kind of
translation between my Python code,
in this English-like syntax, into
what the computer itself understands.
And if you're not going to go
through the effort of compiling
your code every time you
make a change, but instead
you're just going to run your
code through an interpreter,
as is the norm in the
Python world, you're
going to pay a price, because someone
had to implement a translator for you.
And in fact, there's formal
terminology for this.
In the world of Python
we have, for instance,
a picture that looks more like this.
Whereas in the world of C, we would
actually take our source code as input
and output, first
machine code is output,
and then run the machine code,
in the world of Python thus far,
I'm writing source code, and
then I'm immediately running it.
I'm not compiling it into
0's and 1's in advance.
I'm trusting that there's a program,
coincidentally called Python,
whose purpose in life is to
translate that code for me
into something the
computer does understand.
And what does that actually
mean in real terms?
Well, it means that if
I were to think back
to an algorithm like this, which
probably cryptic to many of you,
though not all, might
be a Spanish algorithm
for searching a phone book for someone.
And suppose that I don't
speak Spanish at all.
I might, ideally, compile this
program, this algorithm, into something
I do understand by using a compiler
that translates Spanish to English.
Like voila, this English version, much
better reading and understanding this,
I can execute this
algorithm pretty fast,
because I'm pretty good at English.
But if you only give me the
Spanish version, the source code,
and you require that I translate
it or interpret it line by line,
honestly that's really
going to slow me down,
because it's like me having to
go take like a Spanish dictionary
and look up every word--
"Recoge guia telefonica."
All right, well, what's "recoge"?
I have to look that up.
What's "guia", what's "telefonica"?
Oh, OK.
Pick up phone book.
Got that.
Step one.
What's step two?
"Abre a la mitad de guia telefonica."
So "open to the middle"--
well, wait, I don't know that.
Spoiler.
What does that mean, "abre"?
All right, let me look that up.
And it means "open."
"A la mitad," that
means "to the middle."
"De guia telefonica,"
"of the phone book."
Oh, that means "open to the
middle of the phone book."
So I'm struggling to go back
and forth here, clearly.
But it's clearly a slower process.
And if I keep going, "Ve la
pagina," "Look at the page,"
looking up, translating
every line, it's undoubtedly
going to slow down the process.
And so that's effectively
what's happening for us
when we run these Python programs.
There is a translator, a man
in the middle, so to speak,
that's looking at your source
code and reading it top to bottom,
left to right, and essentially
translating each line respectively
into the corresponding code
that the computer understands.
So the upside of this
is that, thankfully, we
don't have to run make or clang.
We don't have to compile
our code anymore.
Like, how many people
here have made a change
to an earlier pset in C, forgotten
to save the file but you rerun the--
sorry, you forgot to recompile
the file, and you rerun it,
and the program
obviously has not changed
because you haven't actually,
not only saved but recompiled it?
So that stupid, annoying
human step is gone.
In the world of Python, if you change
your file, go ahead and just rerun it,
reinterpret it.
You can save that step.
But the price you're going to
pay is a little bit of overhead.
And indeed, we see that here
in terms of my Python version
taking roughly 1 second
to spellcheck Shakespeare,
and my C version taking
only one half of a second.
So here, too, I promised in past
weeks this theme of trade-offs.
This is so prevalent in the world
of computer science and programming,
and frankly in the real world.
Any time you make some
improvement or gain some benefit,
odds are you are paying some price.
Maybe it's time, maybe it's space,
maybe it's money, maybe it's complexity,
maybe it's anything else.
There's this perpetual
trade-off of resources.
And being a good
programmer, ultimately, is
about finding those inflection
points and knowing ultimately
what tools to use for the trade.
All right, let's go ahead
here, take a 5-minute break.
And when we come back, we'll
look at other features of Python,
we'll end ultimately today with
some really powerful capabilities.
Back in five.
All right.
We are back.
And first, a retraction if I may.
Brian kindly pointed out that my answer
to Olivia and Noah's follow-up question
unfortunately missed the mark, as I
was doing things on the fly instead
of reading the documentation.
So let me recall for
us this example here,
wherein we had the range
function returning three values.
So that code correct, that
gives us the values 0, 1, and 2.
But what I think Olivia asked was
that if you wanted to skip values,
and for instance do every two
digits, how do we do that?
And I unfortunately screwed
up the syntax for that,
providing only two inputs
to range instead of three,
as would be needed here.
So for instance, suppose
that we wanted to print out
all of the numbers between
0 and 100, inclusive,
but skipping every other-- so,
0, 2, 4, 6, 8, so all the even
numbers on up through 100.
We would actually want to do
something like this instead.
We would say, for i in range
of 0 comma 101 comma 2.
Why is that?
Well, we'll pull up the
documentation in just a moment,
but 0 is where you
want to start counting.
The second value, 101, is where
you want to stop counting.
But it is by definition
exclusive, so we have
to go 1 past the value we care about.
And then the 2, the third
argument, is how many
numbers do you want to increment at
a time, from 0 to 2 to 4 to 6 to 8,
on up through 100.
So how could I have
figured this out in advance
rather than embarrassing myself now?
Well, it turns out there is
official documentation for Python.
And we'll always link this to you.
And here there is this
search box at the very top.
And you can see that during
the break I was searching
for the documentation for range.
And sure enough, if I search for the
range documentation, at first glance
it might seem kind of
overwhelming, because there's
a lot of mentions of something
like range in the documentation.
Fortunately, the first result
here is the one we want.
And if I click on that, you'll
see some documentation that's
a little cryptic at first glance.
But what's interesting
about this is that range
comes in two different flavors.
And even though I keep
calling it a function,
technically it's what's called a class.
But more on that another time.
It behaves for our
purposes as a function.
Notice that there's two lines here.
And they're similar but different.
The first one specifies
that this range function
can take one input, the stop value.
So at what value do you
want to stop counting?
So before, when we did range of 3,
it stands to reason that by default,
if you start counting at 0
and you stop at 3, that will
get you to use i equals 0, 1, and 2.
But there's another flavor
of the range function, which
is not the one that I proposed exists.
There's another that takes in
potentially three arguments, here
or technically two.
But it works in the following way.
When you see syntax like this
in Python's documentation,
this means that the
alternate form of range
takes an argument called start,
followed by an argument called stop,
followed by, optionally, a
third argument called step.
And I know as the reader it's optional,
because it's in square brackets here.
So nothing to do with lists or
arrays or anything like this.
This is just human documentation.
Anytime you see things
in square brackets,
that tends to imply to the human
reader that this is optional.
So what does that mean?
Well, notice that there
is no flavor of range that
lets me specify a stop and a step, which
I thought there was a moment ago when
answering Olivia and Noah.
But rather, there is
this three-input version.
So if I specify I want
to start at 0, I want
to stop at 101, which is just
past the 100 I care about,
and then provide an
optional step of 2, this
will give me a program
ultimately that will print out
all of those even numbers.
So let me do this.
First let me go into a program here.
I'll call it count.py.
And I'm going to go ahead and start
at 0, go up to but not through 101,
stepping 2 at a time.
And this time I'm going to print out i.
And here, too, another
handy feature of Python--
no more %s, and also no more %i.
If you want to print out the
value of a variable called i,
just say print, open
paren, i, close paren.
You don't need another
format string as in C.
Let me go ahead now and run
python of count.py, Enter.
And it scrolled by really fast.
But notice that it stopped
at 100, and if I scroll
to the beginning it started at 0.
So my apologies.
Mea culpa for messing that up earlier.
But what a wonderful opportunity to
introduce the official documentation
for Python, which will
soon become your friend,
cryptic though it might
feel at first glance.
All right.
Let's go ahead then and
revisit one other program
that we started with earlier.
And that program was again this
relatively simple Hello program
that we left off in this state.
We were using the get_string function
from the CS50 library in Python.
We had a variable called answer
that was getting the return
value of that version of get_string.
And we were printing out
"hello," comma, so-and-so.
And we were using that new
cryptic feature, but handy,
known as a format string or an f-string,
which just means replace whatever's
in curly braces with the actual value.
So let's start to now take
off the training wheels
that we just put on only an hour ago.
Let's get rid of the CS50 library.
How can we actually get
input in Python without using
a library from someone like CS50?
Well, get_string no longer exists.
But thankfully there is another function
we can use called, quite simply, input.
Input is a function that, quite similar
to get_string in both C and Python,
prompts the user with a phrase, like
this one here, "What's your name?";
waits for them to type in a value;
and as soon as they hit Enter,
it returns whatever the
human has typed in for you.
So if I go ahead now and rerun
this program, python of hello.py,
after getting rid of the CS50 library
and using input instead of get_string,
what's my name?
David.
"Hello," comma, "David."
So already there now,
this is raw, native Python
code completely unrelated
to anything CS50 specific.
But now let's go ahead, and let's
keep using the CS50 library initially,
because we'll see that very quickly
are there advantages of using it,
because we do a lot of
error checking for you.
But we'll eventually take those
training wheels off entirely as well.
But notice, indeed, how
relatively simple it is to do so.
Let me go ahead and open up a
program that we wrote in advance.
And I'm going to go ahead and grab this.
This is available, as always,
on the course's website.
And I'm going to go ahead and
open a file called addition0.c,
which we've actually seen before.
And I'm going to go ahead
and do this fancy thing here
where, in just a moment, I'm
going to split my window so
that I can see two files at a time.
And over here I'm going to create a new
file, and I'll call this addition.py.
So that is to say, I'm just going
to rearrange my IDE temporarily
today so that we can see one
language on the left, C, and then
corresponding language
on the right in Python.
And again, you can download
all these examples online
if you'd like to follow
along on your own.
So if I'm translating this program on
the left to this program on the right,
let's first recall what the
program on the left actually did.
This was a program that prompts the
user for x, prompts the user for y,
and quite simply performs
addition on the two.
So this is week 1 stuff,
way back when now.
Well, let's go ahead and translate this.
I will use the get_int
function from the CS50 library,
because it's going to make my
life a little easier for now.
I'm going to say from
cs50 import get_int.
I'm going to then go ahead and
get an int from the user using
get_int and prompting them for x.
I'm going to then go ahead and get an
int from the user prompting them for y.
I'm going to then finally go ahead
and, let's say, print out x plus y.
And let me go ahead down here
and run python of addition.py.
I'm now being prompted for x, let's type
in 1, y, let's type in 2, and voila,
3 is my program here.
So pretty straightforward.
Fewer lines of code, because one,
I don't have these unnecessary
includes like stdio.h.
I don't have any of the curly braces.
To be fair, I don't have
any of the comments.
So let me write comments.
In Python, it's going to
be a different symbol.
"Prompt user for x" should be prefixed
with a hash symbol now instead of a //.
I'll go ahead and prompt user for y, and
then, how about here, perform addition.
But even still, it's pretty tight.
It's only 10 lines of code with
some of those comments there.
All right, well, what might I do
that's a little bit different?
Well, let's take off
the training wheels.
Let's take off the training wheels
and get rid of the CS50 library
again and get input here.
Well, if I go ahead and get
input here, get input here,
assigning the values to x and y
respectively, I'm going to go ahead now
and run python of addition.py.
x will be 1 again, y will be 2 again,
and the answer, of course, is--
12.
Well, that's wrong.
What's going on?
How did I screw up such
a simple program already?
Albeit in a new language for me, Python.
What did I do here?
Yeah, Ben?
AUDIENCE: Because it's really
taking it in as two strings,
so it's just putting
them next to each other
as opposed to doing
the actual math on it.
It's not reading it as in int.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
So input, this function
that comes with Python,
really is analogous
to Cs50's get_string.
No matter what the
human types, it's going
to come back as keyboard input
characters, or ASCII characters,
or Unicode characters from weeks past.
Even if they look like
numbers, they're not
going to be treated as numbers, a.k.a.,
integers, unless we coerce them so.
Now remember in C, we had this ability
to cast values from one to another.
Casting meant to convert
one data type to another.
And we were allowed to do that for
chars to ints or ints to chars,
but you could not do it for strings
to ints, or from ints to strings.
For that we needed special functions.
And some of you might have
used atoi, ASCII to int,
which was a function that actually looks
at all of the characters in an ASCII
string and converts it to
the corresponding integer.
In Python, frankly,
it's a little simpler.
We can just cast it from
one thing to another.
So I'm going to go ahead and
cast the return value of input
as using this, int.
And I'm going to do the same for y,
passing the return value of input there
to convert what looks
like a string to what's--
what looks like an int to
what's actually an int.
And now let me go ahead and perform the
additions again, python of addition.py.
And notice this time,
hopefully to Ben's point,
it's not going to concatenate
two strings, as we saw
is the default behavior of plus when
you have two strings left and right.
Hopefully now it will do a do
addition on x equals 1, y equals 2.
And voila, now we're back in business.
However, what if I'm not the
most cooperative or sharp user,
and I type in "cat" for x?
Now some crazy stuff starts to happen.
So notice we've triggered
our very first error when
it comes to running a program
whereby my program won't even
run in the first place.
And notice I'm getting some
somewhat cryptic syntax here--
traceback, most recent call
last, file addition.py line 2.
All right, that's at least familiar.
I screwed up somewhere on line 2.
It's showing me the line of code here.
And it's saying "ValueError-- invalid
literal for int with base 10, cat."
That's a very cryptic
way of saying I just
have tried to cast something that's
not an integer to an integer.
And so this is why we use
things like the CS50 library.
It's actually kind of annoying
to write all of the code
that checks and makes sure did the user
type in a number and only a number,
and not "cat" or "dog" or
some other cryptic string.
We ourselves now would have to
implement that kind of error checking
if we don't want to
use the CS50 library.
So there, trade-off.
Maybe you feel more comfortable
writing all of the code yourself.
You don't want to use some random
person on the internet's library,
whether it's CS50's or someone else's,
even if it's free and open source.
You want to write it yourself.
OK, fine.
If you want to write
it yourself, now I've
got to add a bunch more
lines of code to check,
did the human type in a decimal digit
one after the other, or did they
type in other ASCII characters?
So again, trade-off between
using libraries are not.
Generally, the answer is going to
be use a common library to do--
to solve these kinds of problems.
Well, let's go ahead and change
the program a little bit.
Let me go ahead and open a new
file called division.py just
to do a bit of division here.
And let me go ahead on the
right-hand side and copy
paste what we did before, but
just change to division here.
Let me go ahead and divide x by y.
And I keep typing in 1 for x, 2 for y.
In a moment I'm going to run
python of division.py and type
in 1 for x and 2 for y.
But before I hit Enter, if this were a
program in C, what would the answer be?
Feel free to just respond
in the chat if you'd like.
If this were a program in
C, and I'm dividing x by y,
what would I have gotten in week
1 and every week since, Brian?
BRIAN: The consensus looks like 0.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah,
because of truncation.
If 1 divided by 2, of course,
is 1/2, or 0.5, 0.5 is a float.
But if I'm dealing with integers,
even though it's implicitly
integers thus far, and now
explicitly now that I've casted them,
I would seem to throw away
the 0.5 and just get back 0.
But let me go ahead and run python of
division.py and putting x equals 1,
y equals 2.
And voila, wow, one of the most annoying
features, or lack of features in C,
seems to have been--
seems to have been solved in Python
by division doing what you want.
And if you divide one
integer by another in Python,
it turns out one of the other
features of today's language
is that it does what
you the programmer would
expect, without having to get into
the weeds, of the nuances of floats
and ints.
Just does the quote, unquote
"right thing" instead.
Well, let me go ahead and open up
another program here, also from week 1.
This one was called conditions.c.
And this one-- give me one moment
to open this up on the left--
this one here was a program
whose purpose in life
was to get an int from the user
called x, get another called y.
And then it just did this-- if x
less than y, print out as much.
Else if x greater than y, print
out as much, and so forth.
Let's go ahead and
translate this program
into the corresponding Python code using
some of the syntax we've seen already.
I'm going to go ahead and
save this as conditions.py.
And I think I'm going
to go ahead and keep
using the library, the
CS50 library, so that I
don't have to worry about
those kinds of errors
when casting bad input to another.
So from cs50 import get_int.
And let me go ahead and now get an
int from the user, calling it x.
Let's go ahead and get an int
from the user, calling it y.
And I won't bother typing comments
this time, just for time's sake.
And now let me ask the question.
In C, I would have
done if x less than y.
Python's a little more terse.
If x less than y suffices,
but with a colon.
Under that, I'm going to go ahead
and say print "x is less than y."
Elif-- this is the weird one--
x is greater than y, go ahead and
print out "x is greater than y."
And then else, also with a colon,
print out "x is equal to y."
And I think that's just about it.
I'm going to go ahead down here
and run python of conditions.py.
I'll type in 1, I'll type in
2, and indeed x is less than y.
I'll run it again,
this time with 2 and 1.
X is greater than y.
And let me run it again with 1 and 1.
X is equal to y.
So that seems to have worked.
And let me point out one other thing.
I mentioned earlier that you have
this other shorthand syntax where
you can just say import the CS50 library
if you don't want to bother typing out
individual function names.
That's totally fine.
But notice that the IDE is
yelling at me at lines 3 and 4
that get_int is no longer recognized.
That's because Python
supports this feature,
when using other people's libraries,
that it can namespace them for you.
That is to say, you can't refer
to get_int anymore directly.
You have to more explicitly say,
call the get_int function that's
inside of the CS50 library.
And so again, using our
familiar dot operator,
means go inside of that CS50
library, just like a C struct,
and call the function
called get_int therein.
So I can now go ahead and rerun
this, python of conditions.py,
typing in 1 and 1, and voila,
the code is now working again.
So which is better?
It depends.
I mean, if it's sort of more
readable to just write get_int
all over the place, that's going to
save you a lot of keystrokes-- you don't
have to keep typing cs50 dot, cs50 dot.
If, though, you're writing
a pretty big program,
and maybe you're using two different
libraries that both implement
a function called
get_int, you want to be
able to distinguish one from the other.
So you might want to just import
the libraries by their name,
and then prefix the function
calls, as I've done here,
which is known as namespacing.
Namespacing means that you can have
two identically named variables
or functions existing in
two different namespaces.
They don't collide, so
long as they are inside
of the CS50 library or some
other library's name instead.
Let me do one other thing
with conditions here.
Let me go ahead and open up
another file from week 1.
This one was agree.c.
And this program prompted the user
to input whether or not they agree.
And we checked a little curiously
that first week using equals
equals quote, unquote "Y" or lowercase
"y," or quote, unquote capital "N"
or lowercase "n."
Well, how do we go about
converting this one?
Let me go ahead and give
myself a new file over here.
I'll call it agree.py in this case.
And it turns out we can solve
this one in a few different ways.
Let me go ahead and start off
by importing from CS50 get_int,
just because it's-- oh, no, get_string,
rather, because it's convenient.
Let me go ahead and get the
user's input via get_string
and ask them the same question, "Do
you agree," question mark with a space.
Then let me check.
If s equals equals quote, unquote "Y"
or s equals equals lowercase "y," then
I'm going to go ahead
and print out "Agreed."
Else-- oh, no, elif s
equals equals capital "N"
or s equals equals lowercase "n," let
me go ahead and print out here quote,
unquote, "Not agreed."
And I think that should do it.
But something's weird here.
There's a few differences.
What strikes you as different from C?
What muscle memory might
you have to break now
when using conditions with
multiple Boolean expressions
combined in this way?
And there's another subtlety.
There's at least two salient
differences between C and Python
with just this example alone.
Any thoughts in chat or [INAUDIBLE]?
Ryan?
AUDIENCE: I was going
to say, for this one,
instead of using the symbols
for the logical operators,
you can just type the text directly.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
We can literally just
type the English word "or"
if we want to express a logical or.
So in C, recall on the left, we
would have done this vertical bar
thing, which is fine.
You get used to it.
But it's not very readable,
at least in any English sense.
Python took the approach
of using more frequently
actual English or English-like words
that actually do read left to right.
And indeed, a theme is emerging here.
When you read Python code,
it is closer to English
than C is, because you don't
trip over as much punctuation.
Each line of Python code
tends to read a little more
like an English phrase
or an English sentence.
And there's one other subtlety here.
On the left back in week 1, I
took care to use single quotes
around the Ys and the Ns.
This week I'm using double quotes.
But to be honest, it
actually doesn't matter.
I can alternatively use single quotes
everywhere, so long as I'm consistent.
But in Python there is
no fundamental difference
between double quotes and single
quotes, so long as you are consistent.
The reason being, when we looked at
the data types that existed between C
and now Python, absent from the
list of Python data types was char.
In Python there is no such
thing as an individual char.
Everything that's
character-based is a string.
Even if it's just one character
long, everything is a string.
Downside is we don't have
quite as fine grained control.
Upside is we get a lot more features
with those string structures,
as we've already seen with,
for instance, doing something
like uppercase with those as well.
Well, let me go ahead and--
I think I can simplify this.
For instance, suppose I wanted to
tolerate something like not just "Y"
or "y," in uppercase or lowercase.
Suppose I wanted to also tolerate "Yes"
in uppercase or lowercase as well.
Well, you could imagine just
starting to add to the code
or s equals equals "Yes,"
or s equals equals "yes."
But wait a minute, what if the
user is being a little sloppy?
And what if I want to actually say
like, well, what if they're yelling?
Or s equals equals "YES" in all caps.
And there's a few other
permutations as well.
Like, this is quickly
devolving into quite the mess.
But if at the end of the day you really
just want to detect "Y" or the word
"Yes," irrespective of capitalization,
I bet we can be pretty clever in Python
here.
What if I go ahead and say, if s
is in quote, unquote "y" or "yes"--
in fact, I can borrow
an idea from earlier,
whereby I can use the square
bracket notation to give me
a list, which again, is like an
array, but it will automatically grow
or shrink as you need it.
You don't have to decide
in advance how big it is.
This preposition here, in,
is a new keyword in Python
that will literally answer
that question for me.
And we've used it before earlier.
When I implemented speller, I said if
the word is in my set of words, return
True.
So if s in this list, I'll
get back True or False
based on the answer to that question.
But again, it's not tolerating case.
But no big deal--
dot lower, now I can say, is
the lowercase version of s,
no matter what the human typed
in, in this list of two values?
That means now the user
can type in all caps,
in alternating caps, and one capitalized
letter, or any other permutation
whatsoever.
All right.
So that, then, is our conditions.
Let me pause here to see
if there's any questions.
Any questions or confusion
that we can clear up?
With syntax, with conditions,
Boolean variable--
Boolean values?
BRIAN: So a question came up.
So in Python we are allowed to
use the equals equals syntax
to compare two strings?
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
So another really good catch.
In Python, there are no pointers.
Underneath the hood,
there are still addresses.
Like, your memory hasn't gone anywhere.
But underneath the hood, all, of that
is now managed for you by the language
itself.
So if you want to conceptually
compare one string against another,
just as I did here now on line 7,
you can indeed use equals equals,
and Python will do the quote,
unquote "right thing" for you.
You don't need to regress
into using strcmp instead.
Just for clarity, let me
go ahead and update this.
If s.lower in quote,
unquote "n" or comma "no,"
we can achieve the same result
there by doing the same technique.
Well, let me go ahead and
open up another example
that you might recall we did
a progression of examples
to make it good, better, and
then best, this one involving
just a cat meowing in some form.
So let me go ahead and
open up from week 1
an example that was called meow0,
relatively straightforward, that
simply did this.
It simply meowed three times.
So suffice it to say now, in
Python, it's pretty trivial
to do something three times like this.
I'm going to go ahead
and call this meow.py.
And of course, I can just do
something like print "meow."
And I can just copy paste that.
But of course, the whole point
of this example back in week 1
was not to devolve into just copy paste.
Surely there's a better way.
And we've seen a better way this time.
If we wanted to change
this into a for loop in C,
we could have done something like
for int i get 0, i less than 3, i++.
Then in some curly
braces we could have done
printf of "meow," new line, semicolon.
So that was the next version
of our meow code in C.
But in Python, of course,
it's a little more succinct.
I can just do for i in range
3 print quote, unquote "meow."
So very similar in spirit to
our hello, world of before.
But again, we don't have to
include any libraries for this.
We don't need to have a main function.
We don't need any of those curly
braces or semicolon or the like.
We can just dive in and
focus on the code itself.
But recall that we also, last
time, evolved the meow program
into having our own helper
function, our own function that
actually allowed us to create an
abstraction on top of meowing.
And that was in our third
version, a.k.a., meow2.
Let me go ahead and open
up this version in a tab.
And notice that this version starts
to get a little involved, because one,
we needed a prototype at
the top, because I now
have meow function at the
bottom whose purpose in life
was just to print "meow,"
but to abstract that away
as a new helper function.
And then I had this code
here with a for loop inside.
Well, in Python it's going to work
out to be a little simpler here, too.
If I want to do something three
times, for i in range of 3
go ahead and call meow.
Now of course, meow doesn't yet exist.
So I can solve that problem.
We've seen earlier, albeit
quickly, in speller that I
can define my own functions like meow.
There's no more void,
because if you don't
want to have arguments in a
function, just don't put them there.
There's no return value
specified in Python.
They're implicit instead.
So it suffices to do this.
And now I can just print out "meow."
So here now, I have a program
that iterates three times,
calling meow each time, and
meow is defined down below.
Let me go ahead and run
this, python of meow.py.
Huh.
Traceback, most recent call last.
There's a problem on line 2 of
meow.py because of NameError-- name
"meow" is not defined.
Now, the language being used there by
Python is a little different from C's.
It's frankly a little
more human friendly.
But what just happened?
What problem has arisen that I yet
haven't tripped over until now?
Even if you've never
programmed in Python before,
and even if you haven't run help50
yet, what might be the issue there?
Ginny?
AUDIENCE: It's that the function is not
found when we are trying to call it,
because it's described below
when we are calling it.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: There is no prototype.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, there's no prototype.
And it turns out in Python, there
isn't a notion of prototypes.
So unfortunately, the
solution we saw in week 1
is not to just copy and
paste the first line up above
and end it with a semicolon.
That's just not a thing.
I could do this.
I could just move my meow
function to the top of the file,
thereby defining the function
first, and then using it last.
And that would actually solve
the problem, "meow meow meow."
That, of course, doesn't
really help us long term,
because you could probably imagine a
situation where this function wants
to call this function, but
this function calls this one,
and you just can't really neatly
order them in some safe way.
And it's just not going to
be as maintainable, right?
Recall that one of the values of putting
main at the top of our C programs
was that any reasonable person
who wants to understand your code
is probably going to start
reading top to bottom.
They're not going to want to have
to scroll through all of your code
looking for the actual main code.
So it turns out in Python, even
though you don't need a main function,
it's actually common to
define one nonetheless.
It's going to be implemented
with something like this.
And I'm just going to indent
my code below that there.
So now I've defined main.
But I haven't executed any code yet.
On line 6, I've now defined meow,
but I haven't executed any code yet.
And I mean that literally.
If I run python of
meow now and hit Enter,
I would hope to see "meow
meow meow," but I see nothing.
And this is a little weird.
But Python is doing literally
what I told it to do.
I told it to define a
function called main,
and I told it to define
a function called meow.
What I never told it to do is to
call either of those functions.
So the simplest fix here-- it's a little
different from C and a little weird--
is just call main is your
very last thought in the file.
So define main up at the top, just where
most programmers would expect it to be,
but call it all the way at the bottom.
And let me go ahead and
now and run my program.
And now voila, "meow meow meow" is
back, because I've defined main,
I've defined meow, and
now I am calling main.
Now, as an aside, you will very
often see in various documentation
and tutorials online a much more
cryptic incantation than this,
which will have you typing out this.
This achieves the same goal,
but it's not strictly necessary
for our purposes.
This line of code, if you see it in
any online references, or examples,
or books, or sections or
the like, it is necessary
only when you're
implementing, essentially,
your own libraries-- like
your own CS50 library,
or your own image blurring
library or the like.
It's not necessary when we're just
writing individual programs of our own.
So I'm going to go ahead and keep mine
simple and literally just call main.
And let me just wave my hand at why
you'd need that syntax otherwise
in this context.
But let me go ahead and
modify this one last time.
Because recall that in C, the
last version of my program
had me running meow
and passing it input.
Because I defined meow as
taking an input like n,
and then doing something like for
int i get 0, i less than n, i++,
and then inside of my curly
braces did I print meow,
so that now I have a helper function
that I've invented that takes one
input, an int called n.
And it loops that many times and
prints out meow that many times.
And now I have a real nice abstraction,
and that now my program is distilled,
it's just meow three times.
And it doesn't matter
how I implemented meow.
I can do the same thing in Python.
I can go ahead and say that
meow takes an argument called n.
I don't have to bother
specifying its type.
I can now say for i in range of n, and
I can print "meow" that many times.
And now I can get rid of my loop in
main and just say "meow" three times.
And so same functionality.
If I run this a final
time, "meow meow meow,"
but now I'm kind of designing my
code in a more sophisticated way
by actually giving myself now some
of my own actual helper functions.
All right, any questions,
then, on this progression?
Now, we're not really
seeing new Python syntax.
We're now just seeing a translation
of some actual past C programs
into Python to show
really the equivalence.
All right.
Well, let's go ahead, then,
and open another version
from week 1 of a program
called positive.c,
which was an opportunity back then, not
only to define our own helper function
called get_positive_int,
but it also introduced us
to the familiar do while loop.
And unfortunately, we're going
to take that away from you now.
Python does not have a do while loop.
But it's, of course, a very useful
thing to be able to do something
while a condition is true.
After all, pretty much any time
we've gotten user input in the class,
we've used do while, so that we prompt
them at least once and then optionally
again and again and again,
until they cooperate.
So let me go ahead and
implement this in Python
now in a file called positive.py,
and go ahead here in positive.py,
and translate this thing as follows.
Let me go ahead and from
cs50 import get_int.
Let me go ahead and define
a function called main.
So now I'm just going to
start to get into this habit.
I'm going to go ahead and give
myself a variable called i
and call get_positive_int.
And then I'm just going to
go ahead and print out i,
keeping it nice and simple.
Now I have to implement
get_positive_int.
It doesn't need to take any input, so
I'm not going to give it any arguments.
And now I have to do to do while thing.
So the Pythonic way to do this
in Python is almost always
to deliberately induce an infinite loop.
And the idea being, if you want
to do something again and again,
just start doing it forever
and then break out of the loop
when you are ready to.
So what do I want to do
forever in this function?
Well, I want to go ahead
and get an int and prompt
the human for a positive integer.
And then I want to go ahead on
the next line and ask a question.
Well, if n is greater than 0,
thereby making it positive, break.
And the last line of code here
is going to be to return n.
So notice in C on the left,
I did this do whole thing.
I had to declare n outside
of the do while loop,
because it had to be outside
the curly braces to be in scope.
But in Python here,
notice what I'm doing here
is actually a little bit different.
And did I screw up?
Oh, yes, I did screw up.
OK.
If ask the actual question,
if n greater than 0.
So what did I do actually differently
here on the right-hand side?
Well, notice, I deliberately
induced this infinite loop
on line 10, which just means,
do the following forever.
I then ask the user for a variable
n with get_int, and then I check,
is n greater than 0?
If so, break out of the loop.
How do I break out of the loop?
Well, notice that the indentation
here has been very consistent.
So when I break out of the
loop, that puts me back
in line with the original
indentation which is now on line 14.
Notice that the return lines up with
the while loop, which means it's
the first line of code
that's outside of that loop.
In the past, we would have had
very explicit curly braces.
Now we rely only on indentation
that then lets me return n.
So what are some of
the differences here?
One, the do while loop
is completely gone.
But two, scope is no longer an issue.
It turns out in Python that the
moment you declare a variable,
it exists until the
end of that function.
You don't have to worry about the nuance
of declaring a variable first like we
did in C up here and then
returning it down below.
The moment we execute this
line of code 11 here, n
suddenly exists for the entirety
of the remainder of that function.
So even though we declared it
inside of the loop, so to speak,
as per the indentation, it is still
accessible to the return statement
here at the end of the program.
All right.
Let me pause there and see if
there's any questions or confusion
on getting user input, doing the
equivalent, logically, of do while,
but doing it now in
this more Pythonic way.
Peter?
AUDIENCE: In Python, are variables
accessible across functions or no?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
No.
So if you declare a variable
inside of a function,
it is scoped, so to
speak, to that function.
It is not available elsewhere.
You would have to return it
and pass it as output to input.
Or you would have to define it, for
instance, as a global variable instead.
All right.
Well, what else, then,
might we translate?
Well, recall from our
earlier endeavors in week 1,
we played around with
these examples from Mario.
And for instance, we wanted to
print something out in Python--
in C that mimics the notion of
these pyramids, or these coins,
or these little bricks on the screen.
Well, here let me go ahead and
open up a new file called mario.py.
And I'm going to transition away from
always showing the before and after
and now just start to focus
more on the Python code.
But you can always look back if you
wanted the corresponding C versions.
How do I go about printing out
three bricks like this vertically?
Well, in Python I might
say something like,
for i in range of 3, quite simply,
as we've done a few times already,
and just go ahead and print out a hash.
I don't need to worry about the new
line, because you get it for free,
so to speak.
But I'm going to go ahead now
and run python of mario.py.
And voila, there's my very simple
ASCII version of this Mario structure.
But what if I want to
do the coins instead?
What if I want to do this horizontal
coins that appear in these four bricks
and print out a version of that?
Well, how might I do that?
Well, let me go ahead
and change this to be--
instead in my code for i in range of
4, so I can print four of these things.
Let me go ahead and print out a
question mark and then run this.
So let me run mario.py.
And voila-- damn.
Like, not what I wanted.
And so here is that trade-off.
You might have been
kind of excited, so far
as it's possible to be excited
about code, that, oh, my God,
you don't need to do the stupid
new line characters anymore.
But what if you don't want it?
Now we've kind of found a downside of
getting those new lines automatically.
Well, it turns out if we read the
documentation for the print function
in Python, it, too, can
take multiple arguments.
And what's powerful
about Python, too, is
that it supports not just
positional arguments,
where you just do a comma separated list
of multiple arguments to a function.
Python supports what are
called named arguments, whereby
if a function, especially one
that's super powerful like print,
takes multiple inputs, like this one,
this other one, and this other thing.
Each of those inputs can have names.
And you, the user of that
function, can specify the name.
And it turns out that print in Python
supports an argument called "end."
And you can explicitly say what value
you want to give to that parameter
by mentioning its name.
And here I'm going to literally do this.
I'm going to tell the
print function that I
want the value of "end," a parameter,
an argument to it, to be quote, unquote.
The reason for that is that
if I read the documentation,
the default is actually this.
If you read the documentation, it
will tell you print's default value
for its end argument is backslash n.
This, too, is a feature
that C did not have.
C did not have optional arguments.
They're either there or they're not.
Rather, they either have to be
there, or they cannot be there.
Python supports optional arguments
that even have default values.
And so in this case, the default
value of this, per the documentation,
is that end is quote,
unquote backslash n, which
is why every line ends with that value.
If you want to change
that to be nothing,
the so-called empty string, you
change it to quote, unquote.
So let me go ahead and run
this now, and voila, closer.
It's a little stupid looking,
because now my cursor ended up--
my prompt ended up on the same line.
So maybe after this line, let me just
go ahead and print nothing, that is,
a new line.
And now if I run mario.py, voila,
now I get the effect I want.
And if you want to see
what's really going on here,
I can do something stupid like "HELLO."
And now I can end every print with
"HELLO," "HELLO," "HELLO," "HELLO."
Not that you would do that,
but that's all it means.
It's ending every call to
print with that expression.
But the correct version, of course,
is just to blank it out in this way.
But here's something
that's kind of cool.
And this is where if
you're kind of a geek,
life starts to get
really interesting fast.
I can actually change my Python code
to print out these four question
marks in the sky to be quite simply
print quote, unquote question
mark times 4.
And now if I rerun this
program, boom, done.
And here's where, again, you're getting
a lot of features in the language
where you don't have
to think about loops,
you don't have to think
about a lot of syntax.
If you want to take a question
mark and do it four times,
you can literally use
the star operator, which
has been overloaded to support not
only multiplication with numbers
but also automatic concatenation, if
you will, with strings in this way.
So let me go ahead and do
one final version for mario.
Recall that the last
thing we built with mario
looked a little something like this.
Let me go ahead and change my mario
code now to be for i in range of 3,
because this is a 3 by 3
grid of bricks, let's say.
And let's go ahead and
now, inside of this loop,
do another nested loop where
I do three columns as well.
And in here, I want to print
out a single hash at a time.
But I don't want to
print out a new line.
I only want to print
out a new line here.
So it turns out that essentially,
because Python gives you
the backslash n's automatically,
essentially any logic
you wrote in the past
now needs to be reversed.
If you ever printed a new line, now
you don't want to print a new line.
And if you ever didn't print a new
line, now you do, in some sense.
So let me go ahead and--
not make, wrong language--
python of mario.py.
And voila, my 3 by 3 grid.
So this is to say that in
Python, we can nest loops, just
like we did in C. I can use
multiple variable names, like i
and j being conventional.
There's no curly braces,
there's no semicolons.
But again, the logic, the
ideas are still the same.
It just takes a little bit of
time to get used to, for instance,
some of the new syntax.
You'll recall that in C, we ran into a
problem pretty early on with integers.
And let me create a
program here called int.py.
And let me initialize a
variable called i to 1.
And let me go ahead and do this forever.
Let me do this forever.
Instead of a while True block.
Let me print out whatever i is.
And then let me go ahead and just
add 1 to i on each iteration.
Let me go ahead and run this program.
And let me increase the size of my
window for now and just run this thing.
Whoops, that was mario.
Let me run this thing, python of int.py.
And you'll see that it's
counting up to infinity.
And honestly, this is
going to take a while.
You know what's faster than counting
by 1/ maybe multiplying by 2.
So let me go ahead and
multiply by 2 instead.
To kill the program, just
like in C I used Control-C.
And that's why I see keyboard interrupt.
It respected my wanting
to cancel the program.
Let me rerun this now and
just count really big.
And even though the internet's
being a little slow,
which is why it's a little shaky,
that's a really big number already
if I keep doubling i.
What would have happened
already at this point
if I were using C to
implement this program?
If in C I declared a variable
called i, and it was an int,
and I kept doubling it,
again and again and again
and again and again, literally forever?
Any thoughts?
Yeah.
What would have happened in C. Joy?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I think
it would have crashed.
DAVID MALAN: It would have crashed?
Why?
AUDIENCE: Because it would
be taking much memory.
DAVID MALAN: Good thought.
So it wouldn't crash per se.
Something would go wrong.
It wouldn't crash.
Because it's still an
int, and in C at least,
it would still be taking up on a
typical computer 32 bits or 4 bytes.
But honestly, the program probably
would have started printing 0
by now, or even negative numbers.
Because recall, one of
the limitations of C
is that integers are a finite size--
only 32 bits or 4 bytes.
Which means if you keep
going from 1, 2, 4 8, 16,
a million, 2 million,
4 million, 8 million,
and so forth, eventually you're
going to get into the billions.
And as soon as you cross the 2 billion
threshold or maybe the 4 billion
threshold, if using signed or unsigned
numbers, it's going to get too big.
You're going to have integer overflow.
But in the world of Python, integer
overflow, not a thing anymore.
In the world of Python,
your numbers will
get as big as you need them to get.
They will automatically
address this problem for you.
Unfortunately, floating point
imprecision, still a thing.
So I only divided 1 by 2 earlier.
But if I continue to divide other values
and I looked at enough decimal points,
we would still suffer, unfortunately,
from floating point imprecision.
However, in the world of Python,
like in Java and other languages,
there are libraries,
scientific libraries
that allow you to use as
much precision as you need,
or at least as much memory
as your computer has.
So those problems, too, have been
better solved in more modern languages
than in something out
of the box like C code.
But just by multiplying that number
again and again was I able, then,
to demonstrate much larger numbers
than we ever saw in weeks past.
Well, let me go ahead and
do another program here,
this one called scores.py.
That's going to be an
example of really keeping
track of scores, which was an example
we did early on in week 2 of the class.
And in Python, I'm going
to go ahead and give myself
a list of scores like this--
72, 73, and 33--
again, sort of a playful
reference to our ASCII numbers.
But in this context,
they're quiz scores-- so
two OK quiz scores, and
one kind of low quiz score,
assuming these things
are out of like 100.
But notice the syntax I'm using.
Square brackets in
Python give me a list.
I don't have to decide
in advance how big it is.
It's not an array per se,
but it's similar in spirit.
But it will automatically
grow or shrink.
And the syntax is even simpler.
Suppose I want to average
these scores in Python.
I could do something like this.
I could print out that the average
of these scores is, for instance--
and then I could do something like this.
I could do the sum of scores
divided by the length of scores.
And some of this is actually
kind of new already.
It turns out in Python that there is sum
function that will take a list as input
and return to you the
sum of those items.
And we've seen already
there's a len function, L-E-N
that tells you the length of a list.
So if I add up all my scores and then
divide by the total number of scores,
that should give me by
definition my average.
So python of scores.py, voila--
whoops, what did I do here?
Ah, I screwed up.
So unintended, admittedly, but
let me try to save myself here.
So what just happened?
Well, this error message
is a little cryptic.
It says, "TypeError-- can only
concatenate str, not float, to str."
long.
Story short, Python
in this case does not
like the fact that I'm trying to
take a string, average, on the left
and concatenate to it
a float on the right.
So there's a couple of
ways I can solve this.
And we saw the fundamental
solution earlier.
If this expression here
that I've highlighted
is by definition mathematically a
float, but I want it to become a string,
I can just tell Python,
convert that float to a string.
So much like there's the itoa
function that some of you discovered,
which is the opposite
of the atoi function,
I can take in Python,
in this case a float,
and convert it to a string equivalent.
So now if I run python of scores.py,
voila, my average is 59.333333.
And you already see
a bit of imprecision.
There's some rounding error at the end
there that is not a perfect one third.
But there's another way I could do this.
And it's a little uglier.
But I could use one of those f-strings.
I could, say, go ahead
and plug in a value
here and just print
out the user's average.
So it turns out that inside
of these curly braces,
you don't have to print just variables.
You can actually put
entire coding expressions.
And I would encourage you not to
paste crazy long lines of code,
because it's going to very
quickly get unreadable.
At that point you probably
should use a variable.
But here I can go ahead and
run python of scores.py.
And voila-- I screwed up again.
Also not intentional,
but I can fix this.
Yeah, I'm missing the f at the beginning
to make this a formatted string.
And now if I rerun it,
voila, same exact answer.
So again, I have multiple approaches.
There's a third one here.
I could do something-- and actually,
I don't need the str in that context,
because now if it's
inside of a format string,
Python will presume that I want to
automatically convert it to a string.
So that's nice.
Or I can just factor this
out, and I can say something
like this-- give me a variable called
average, assign it equal to that math,
and then print out the average.
So again, just like in C, so many
different ways to solve the problem.
And which one is best
depends really on what
might be most readable, most
maintainable, or easiest to do.
Let me go ahead and add
some scores dynamically now.
Instead of hardcoding
my three scores, let
me ask myself for my scores
over the course of the semester.
From cs50 let me get_int, just
so I can get some numbers easily.
Let me give myself an empty list
of scores, the syntax for which
is just open bracket, close bracket,
so nothing inside of it initially.
And now let me go ahead and do this.
Let me get myself three scores--
maybe it's the end of the term now.
For i in range of 3, let me go
ahead and append to the scores array
whatever the return value
of get_int is like this.
Now, this, too, I could
do in a bunch of ways.
Let me get rid of this here.
Whoops.
Nope, we'll leave that there.
This I could do in a bunch of ways.
But notice what I'm doing.
I'm getting int, and I'm
passing the return value of int
to a new function called append.
It turns out that lists,
the square brackets,
once you've defined them
in a variable like scores,
they, too, have functions
built into them.
So I can do scores.append in
order to add a number to the list.
So now let me go ahead and
run this, python of scores.py.
Let me manually type in
my 72, my 73, and my 33.
And voila, same exact answer.
But think about how much
of a pain this would
have been in C, if you
had to either decide
in advance the size of the
array, or not decide in advance
and use malloc and realloc to
keep growing and shrinking it.
Python, using this
append function, which
comes inside of that
list variable, handles
all of this automatically for us.
All right.
So that, too, is a
whole bunch of features.
Any questions, though,
that I can answer here?
Any questions?
No?
Yeah, over to Santiago.
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
I had a question about--
so even if append reduces the
amount of code you have to write,
does it underneath the hood
just do exactly what we
were doing in C, which is like, malloc
and realloc, or something like that?
Is that all-- is that
happening inside Python?
DAVID MALAN: It is.
Yeah, that's exactly what
you're getting for free,
so to speak, with the language.
All of that malloc stuff,
realloc stuff, maybe it's
implemented with an array
underneath the hood,
like in the actual computer's memory.
Maybe it's a linked list
like we saw last week.
But all of that is happening for you.
But that, again, is one of the
reasons why the code ultimately
runs a little slower, because you have
someone else's code in between you
and the CPU in your computer
doing a bit of that work for you.
Sophia?
AUDIENCE: Are there
efficiency differences
in between the ways that we print,
of utilizing the f formatting
or the other forms that we've used?
DAVID MALAN: You don't have to be--
if I'm understanding correctly,
there are some fancy features of it.
For instance, there
is syntax you can use
to specify how many
decimal points you want
to print after a floating point value.
But it's no longer all of
the %i, %s, %f, and so forth.
They're slightly different syntax,
but fortunately less of it,
since you don't have to worry
as much about those conventions.
Other questions or confusion?
No?
All right.
Well, let me go ahead and
do one other example that
might be familiar from some weeks past.
Let me go ahead and whip up a
quick example of uppercasing, just
to tie together one of
our earlier examples
that we saw more
organically, or lowercasing.
In this case, a file
called uppercase.py.
Let me go ahead, and from the
CS50 library, let me go ahead
and import get_string.
And then once I have this, let me go
ahead and get a string from the user
and ask them for,
"Before," for instance.
And then let me go ahead
and do the following.
Let me go ahead and print
out "After," the goal being I
want to uppercase this
whole string for the user.
And I'm going to keep
this all on the same line.
So again, I want a program
that's going to print "Before,"
ask the human for some
input, and then after,
show the capitalized
version of the whole string.
So how can I do this?
Well, we've seen one way already.
I can do literally,
for instance, s.upper.
And let me go ahead and save this.
And now run python of uppercase.py.
Let me type in "hi" in
lowercase, and boom, now
I get back the uppercase version.
But if you want, you can actually
manipulate individual characters
as well.
Let me go ahead and a little
more pedantically do this.
For c in s, print c.
Now, this isn't quite what I want
yet, but it's a stepping stone.
Notice now if I type
in "hi" in lowercase,
I see "h," "i," exclamation
point, all still lowercase.
So I haven't done anything interesting.
But you know what, let me
get rid of the new line,
just so it all stays on the same
line, because that was kind of ugly.
Let me do it again.
OK, a little better.
Let me actually add a new line
at the very end of the program
to move my cursor to the new line.
Let's do it once more, "hi."
OK, I'm not uppercasing anything.
But if I change c to c.upper,
I can do that as expected.
And let me run it again, "hi," and boom.
Now I have another working program.
But the new feature now is,
notice this coolness on line 5.
If you want to iterate
over a string's characters,
you don't need to initialize i to 0
and then use square bracket notation
like you did in C. You just say, for c
in s, or for x and y, whatever it is.
For can also be used to iterate over
the individual characters in a string,
as you might want to
do when doing something
like cryptography or the like.
So we don't have to just uppercase
the whole string all at once.
We can still gain access
to our individual values.
And there's other things you can do in
Python as well that we could do in C.
Let me go ahead and create a
program here called argv.py,
for argument vector, which, recall,
was the name of the input to main
that allows you to access
command line arguments.
Now today, we have seen that
you can have a main function
but you don't need to,
but it's conventional.
It's not required anymore.
And so we haven't seen argc
or argv yet, but that's
because they're elsewhere in Python.
If you want to access command
line arguments in Python,
it turns out that you can
import a module called argv.
And this is a little new, but it follows
the same pattern as the CS50's library.
I'm going to import from the System
library a feature called argv.
So this just means that it
comes with Python, but to use it
you have to import it explicitly.
And now I'm going to do this.
If the length of argv
equals 2, then I'm going
to go ahead and print out, just
like we did a few weeks ago,
"hello," and then argv bracket 1.
Somewhat cryptic, but I'll
come back to this in a moment.
Else, I'm going to go ahead and print
out a default of "hello, world."
So we did this some
weeks ago, in week 2,
whereby we ran a program that if the
user typed their name at the prompt,
it would say "hello,
David" or "hello, Brian."
If they didn't, it would
just say "hello, world."
So to be clear, if I run this thing
and run it without any command line
arguments, I just see "hello, world."
If I run it again, though, and
type my name in and hit Enter,
now I see "hello, David."
So how is that working?
Well, this first line of
code gives me access to argv,
which is now tucked away in
the sys library, if you will,
the sys package, so to speak.
But it works the same way.
There's no argc, but no problem.
If argv is a list of command
line arguments, which it is,
len, L-E-N, will tell me the length of
that list, which is equivalent to argc.
So I can reconstruct the same
idea from my version in C.
And here, then, I have a format
string that prints out "hello," comma,
and then whatever's in curly braces.
And argv is a list.
And just like in C,
which had arrays, a list
is just an array that can
dynamically grow and shrink for you.
You can still use square bracket
notation to get at, in this case,
the second thing the human typed.
So let me change this
just for clarity to be 0.
And if I rerun this
now and type in David,
it says weirdly, "hello, argv.py."
So what you don't see
is the word "Python."
Python is the interpreter, but that's
not part of your program's execution
per se.
argv 0 is going to be the name of
the Python program you're running,
and argv 1 is going to be the first
word thereafter, and so forth.
So we still have access
to that feature, but now
we can convert it now to Python.
And in fact, if I want to print
out all the command line arguments,
I can just more simply do this--
for arg in argv, go ahead and print arg.
So very succinct, if not
obvious at first glance.
Now let me go ahead
and type in something
like "David Malan," two words.
Enter, you now see everything printed
or typed after the program's name,
and so forth.
So here, too, notice how neatly we
can iterate over a list in Python.
There's no i, there's no
square brackets necessarily.
You can just say, for arg in argv, just
like a moment ago I said for c in s.
Pretty much the Python
for loop is smart enough
to figure out what it is
you want it to iterate over,
whether it's a string or a list.
And my God, it's just so much
more fun or pleasant to program
now, when you don't have to worry
about all the stupid mechanics
of incrementing, and plus
plus, and semicolons, and all
of that syntactical mess.
All right, let me pause here to
see if there's any questions.
I know we're going through
some of these examples quickly,
but they're really just
translations again.
And for upcoming problems
and problems sets
will you be able to more methodically
compare before and after as well.
Anything at all on your end, Brian?
BRIAN: Nothing here.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So let's look at some of
our final past examples.
And then we'll reserve some
time at the end of today
to look at some even
more powerful things
that we can do because now
of languages like Python.
Let me go ahead and create a program,
this time called exit.py, exit.py.
And this program's
purpose in life, it's just
going to demonstrate exit statuses.
Recall that eventually
in C, we introduced
the notion of returning 0, or returning
1, or any other value from main.
We do have that ability
now in Python, too,
that you'll start to see
in more larger programs.
Here, too, I'm going
to go ahead and import
sys, the whole thing this time, just
to show a different way of doing this.
I'm going to say, if
the length of sys.argv
does not equal 2, let me go
ahead and yell at the user,
"Missing command-line arguments."
And then after this, I'm going
to go ahead and do sys.exit 1.
Otherwise, I'm going to go ahead and
print out a formatted string that
says "hello," comma arg v bracket
1, with sys now in front of it
for reasons I'll explain in a moment.
And then at the end, I'm going to go
ahead and by default print sys.exit 0.
All right.
So what is going on here?
One, because I'm now using
sys for two different things,
I decided not to import
argv specifically,
but just to import the whole library.
But because I did that, I can't
just write the word "argv" anywhere.
I now have to prefix it with the name
of the package or library that it's in.
So that's why I started
doing sys.argv, sys.argv.
But I'm also using another feature of
the sys library, which gives me access
to an exit function, which is the
equivalent to returning from main.
So this is a bit of a dichotomy.
In C, you had to return 0 or 1,
or some other integer from main.
In Python, you instead call sys.exit
with the same kinds of numbers.
So a little bit different syntactically,
but it's the same fundamental idea.
What's the purpose of this program?
Well, if I run this
thing, its purpose is just
to make me type in one word and only
one word after my program's name.
So notice, if I just
run python of exit.py,
it's yelling at me, "Missing
command-line argument."
If I run it instead with my name after
that, now it says "hello, David."
So stupid program.
It's only meant to demonstrate how
you can now return different values
or really return
prematurely from a program,
because you're no longer in main.
You can't return per se, but you
can now in Python exit as needed.
So that's the comparable line there.
All right, any questions,
then, on exit statuses?
Again, we're just kind of churning
through the list of features
we saw in C, even if they don't
come to you super naturally--
pun not intended-- but rather, there
are analogs here in the Python world.
No?
All right.
Well, recall that after that
we started focusing really
in the class on algorithms.
And that's when the
size of our data sets
and our-- the efficiency of our
code started to really matter.
Let me go ahead and write
a program called numbers.py
that, for instance, contains
an import at the top for sys,
because I'll need that in a moment.
And then it gives me--
and let me give myself an array of
numbers, like 4, 6, 8, 2, 7, 5, 0.
And you might recall that those were
the numbers behind the doors in week 3.
And suppose that I want to
search for the number 0.
Well, in C, to implement linear
search you would use a for loop
and a variable like i, and
check all of the locations.
Python is way simpler.
If 0 in numbers, go ahead
and print out "Found."
And then I'll go ahead and
else print out "Not found."
And that's it.
So let me go ahead now and
do python of numbers.py.
Hopefully I will see [INAUDIBLE]
found, because it's in fact there.
So that's it.
Linear search is just a prepositional
phrase, if 0 in numbers,
gives you the answer True
or False that you want.
So there is our linear search.
What if I want to do it for names?
Well, let me go ahead and give myself
a second file, similar in spirit,
called names.py.
Let me again import--
and actually, if I really want
to be identical to our C version,
let me go ahead and exit with 0
here, and let me exit with 1 here.
But strictly speaking,
that's not necessary.
That just happens to be what I
did when we did this in C instead.
In names, let me go ahead
and do something similar.
Let me give myself a names list
with a whole bunch of names--
"Bill," and "Charlie," and "Fred," and
"George," and "Ginny," and "Percy,"
and lastly "Ron," all
the way at the end.
And then let me just check if "Ron"
is in that list using linear search.
If "Ron" in names, go ahead
and print out "Found."
Else, go ahead and
print out "Not found."
And I won't bother printing out
or exiting with 0 or 1 this time.
But let me go ahead and
run python of names--
whoops, python of names.
And voila, we found "Ron."
And notice, I'm not cheating.
I don't think I've screwed up.
If I go ahead and say "Ronald," if
that was in fact his formal name,
now I search for "Ron," not found.
It's looking, indeed,
for an exact match.
So that's pretty cool, that
we can distill something
like that pretty readily.
Well, recall that a little bit ago,
I proposed that Python has other data
types as well, among which are these
things called dictionaries or dicts,
D-I-C-T, which represent a collection
of key-value pairs similar in spirit
to a dictionary.
Like, the Spanish dictionary has Spanish
keys and English values converting one
to the other, this
English dictionary has
English words and English definitions.
But the same idea-- a
collection of keys and values.
Using one, you can find the other.
Well, let's go ahead and translate
this into Python in a program
called phonebook.py,
and implements something
like our C phone book a
while back, which, recall,
in C, we used a couple of arrays
initially, then we scratched that,
and we used an array of structs instead.
Now let's use a dictionary, which
is a more general-purpose data
structure, as follows.
Let me go ahead here and
from cs50 import get_string.
Then let me go ahead and give
myself a dictionary of people.
And the syntax here
is a little different,
but I'm going to go ahead and
preemptively use curly braces.
They are back for the
purposes of dictionaries.
And then here's how you
define key-value pairs.
One key is going to be "Brian."
And his value is going
to be "+1-617-495-1000."
That's his number.
And then I'll be one of
the other keys from now
We'll keep it a very small
phone book or dictionary.
Mine will be "+1-949-468-2750."
And that's it.
So the curly braces can
technically be on different lines.
I could move this up here,
I could get rid of this.
But there are certain style
conventions in Python.
The point, though, here is that a
dictionary is defined with curly braces
at the beginning and end; the keys
and values are separated by colons;
and the key-value pairs
are separated by commas.
So that's why it's conventional
to write it the way I did.
It's just a little
more obvious that this
is a dictionary with two keys,
each of which has a value.
It's just associating left
with right, so to speak.
Now, what does this mean?
Suppose I want to search
for someone's name.
Well, let me go ahead and give myself a
name variable called get_string, asking
the human for a name.
And let me implement my own virtual
phone book, much like the Contacts app
on your phone.
Let me go ahead and then
say, once I have the name,
if name in people, that's great.
If I found the name in
people, let me go ahead
and print out that the number for
that person is people bracket name.
And this is where dictionaries
are going to get really powerful.
Let me run it first and then explain.
Python of phonebook.py, Enter--
whoops, python of phonebook.py.
Let me search for Brian's number.
Boom, there's Brian's number.
Let me go ahead and run
it with David's name.
Boom, there's that number.
Let me go ahead and run it
with, say, Montague's name.
Don't have his phone number just yet.
He's unlisted, as would be
anyone else that I type in.
So what has gone on here?
Well, at the top I'm declaring
this new variable called people.
And it's a dictionary, a set of
key-value pairs left and right.
Then I'm just getting a string from
the user using get_string as before.
And then this is powerful, too.
This is essentially, on line 9,
searching the whole dictionary
for the given name.
And it's returning to me down here the
name associated with that-- or, sorry,
the number associated
with that person's name.
And let me make this more
clear by factoring this out.
Let me give myself a variable
called number and then more
explicitly print out
that variable's name.
Here's what's different today.
"If name in people" in here,
what this does is Python
searches all of the keys for that name.
It doesn't search values.
When you say if name in a given
dictionary, like people is,
it searches only the keys.
If you've then found the
key, I know definitively
that "David" or "Brian"
are in the dictionary.
And notice this.
It's just like in C's arrays syntax.
You can now use square
bracket notation to index
into a dictionary using a
word like "David" or "Brian,"
and get back a value
like our phone number.
In C, and thus far even
in Python, whenever
we've seen square bracket notation, it
would only be typically for numbers,
because arrays or lists
have indices, numbers
that addresses the first
location, middle, and last,
and so forth, everything in between.
But what's powerful about
dictionaries is that they're otherwise
known as associative arrays.
A dictionary is a collection
of key-value pairs.
And if you want to look
up a key, you simply
use square bracket
notation, just like we used
to use square brackets for numbers.
And because Python is a
pretty fancy language,
it handles the searching for you.
And even better, it does
not use linear search.
When searching a dictionary,
it aspires to give you
constant time by using what we
called last week a hash table.
Dictionaries are typically implemented
underneath the hood using something
like a hash table.
And recall that, even
though it was really
a goal of achieving constant time,
if you choose a really good hash
function and a really--
the right size array to hash into,
you can come close to constant time.
So again, among the features
of a dictionary in Python
are that it gives you
very high performance.
It's not linear search.
And in fact, set-- recall that when
we began playing with Python earlier,
and I re-implemented
speller using, what,
10 or 20 lines of code
max instead of the many
more that you might have written
for pset 5, speller used a set.
And a set is just a
collection of values.
Long story short, it's similar
in spirit to a dictionary
in that it, too, underneath
the hood uses a hash table
to get you answers quickly.
So if you think back to what that
speller example was from earlier
on today, when I had a line of code
that just said words equals set,
that one line of code was
implementing pretty much the entirety
of your spell checker.
All of those pointers, all of those
hash tables and chains and linked lists
are distilled into
just one line of code.
You get that with the language itself.
All right.
Any questions, then, on dictionaries?
They will recur, and they tend to be
one of the most useful data structures,
because this ability to just associate
something with something else
is just a wonderful way, it
turns out, to organize your data.
Any questions here?
Yeah, Sophia?
AUDIENCE: Is there only
a set hash function
that Python has defined
for these dictionaries,
or can we change the
hash function in any way?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
It comes with a hash
function for you, and Python
figures all of that out for you.
So that's the kind of detail that
you should leave to the library,
because someone else has
spent all of the time thinking
about how to dynamically adapt the
data structure, move things around as
needed, so that you no longer
need to stress to the degree
you might have when
implementing speller yourself.
And it turns out, other
things get easy, too.
This is not a commonly
needed feature, necessarily,
but it is something we can do.
And let me go ahead and write
a quick program called swap.py.
Recall that in swap.c a couple of
weeks ago, we gave x a value of 1,
y a variable-- a value of 2,
and then I printed out something
like "x is x, y is y."
But this week I'm using format
strings just to print that out.
Then I did something like swap x, y,
and I just kind of hoped for the best,
and then I printed out
those values again.
Well it turns out in Python,
because you don't have pointers
and you don't have addresses
per se that you have access to,
you can't resort to the
solution like last week
and pass these variables
around by reference,
so to speak, by their address.
That's just not possible.
Why is that a thing?
Well, it would seem to be
taking a feature away from you,
but honestly, if this past week was any
indication, including the week prior,
pointers are hard.
And segmentation faults are frequent.
And getting all of that stuff
right is difficult. And at worst,
your programs can be compromised,
because someone can access memory that
they shouldn't.
So Python takes that feature away.
Java also takes that feature
away from programmers
to protect you against yourself
from screwing up, like you may have
and should have in some number
of times this past week.
But it turns out, in Python there
are solutions to these problems.
And if you want to swap
x and y, that's fine.
Swap x and y.
And so now if I run python of
swap on this program, voila, boom,
it's distilled into one other line.
So even though they take something away
from us that you can do a lot of damage
with or make a lot of mistakes
with, we can nonetheless
hand you back a more powerful
feature with this one liner for swap.
And notice that it's x comma y on
the left, but y comma x on the right.
And that has the effect
of doing what Brian
did with the glasses of liquid
of doing the switcheroo,
even without a temporary
variable explicitly there,
though some magic is
happening underneath the hood.
Well, let's go ahead and implement a
couple of final programs from week 4
and then introduce a few
of our own here in week 6.
Let me go ahead and
implement another phone book
that this one's a
little more persistent.
Let me go ahead here and open-- create
a file here called phonebook.csv.
And let me go ahead and
name this name comma number.
So CSV file, recall, is like
a very simple spreadsheet.
And we're going to go ahead and just
create that so I have it nearby.
And then I'm going to create a new
file called phonebook.py that's
initially empty.
And this time I'm going to do this.
I'm going to import from cs50 the
get_string function as before.
But I'm also going to import a
library called the CSV library.
It turns out, Python comes with a whole
lot of functionality related to CSV
files to make your life easier and
make it easier to do things with CSVs.
Among the things I might
want to do is this.
Let me go ahead and open up that
file, phonebook.csv, in append mode,
similar to fopen two weeks ago.
And let me go ahead and assign
that to a variable called file.
Then let me go ahead and just
get a name from the user.
So let me use get_string to get
someone's name, "Name" here.
Then let me go ahead and
get-- use get_string again
to get someone's number
here, so using "Number."
And then lastly-- and
this is the new code--
let me save that name
and number to a file.
And recall from pset 4 that saving
files and writing bytes out to files
is pretty involved.
Like, it probably took you a while
to implement recover, or blur,
any of those filters that
involved creating new files.
Turns out the CSV library
makes this pretty easy.
Let me go ahead and give
myself what's called a writer.
And I'm going to give myself the return
value of calling csv.writer of file.
So what is this doing?
File, again, represents the
file I'm trying to open.
csv.writer is some function
that comes with the CSV library.
And it expects as input a file
that you've already opened.
And it kind of wraps that file
with some fancier functionality
that's going to make it way
easier for me the programmer
to write to that file.
What am I going to do?
I'm going to use that writer variable
to write a row that specifically
contains a name and a number.
And I'm using a list,
because if you think
of a spreadsheet with columns and
rows, a list is kind of the right idea.
Each of the cells from left to
right is kind of like a list.
A row is like a list.
So I'm going to deliberately
use a list here.
And then lastly, I'm going to close the
file, just as I've done in the past.
So it's a little cryptic here.
But again, get_string--
get_string is old now.
This is old now.
So the only things that are
new are importing the CSV.
I'm opening this file in append
mode, similar to what I did in C.
And then these lines here involve
wrapping the file with the CSV
functionality, writing a row
to this file with writerow,
and then closing it.
So let me go ahead and try this now.
Let me open up a phonebook.csv,
which for now only
contains these headers which I
created manually a moment ago.
And let me go ahead and run
this, python of phonebook.py.
Let me go ahead and add Brian.
And Brian will be
+1-617-495-1000, Enter.
And now let me go to
my CSV file over here.
Dammit, I screwed up.
Pretend I didn't hit Enter there.
Now it works.
Let me go ahead now and
do this again by input--
I should have hit Enter when
I created the file manually,
but I screwed up on creating it.
So let me wave my hand at that and
convince you that I did this correctly
in code by adding myself,
David, +1-949-468-2750, Enter.
Let me go back to my CSV file.
And voila, now it's formatted
correctly, because I did--
writerow includes a line for me.
And notice, too, if I download this
file-- let me download phonebook.csv
like I did in a past week.
Let me download this to my own Mac.
Let me open this CSV file.
And whether you have Apple Numbers
installed or Microsoft Excel,
you'll open something
that looks like this.
And voila, I've dynamically
created, using Python code now,
my own sort of CSV file.
And it turns out there's a way to
tighten this up just a little bit.
Not a big deal to do it the
way I did, but it turns out
that you can also open and close
files a little differently.
You can do this.
With file-- with, rather,
with open as file.
Then I can indent all of this here,
and I can get rid of my close line.
So not a big deal to do it the
way I did with open and close,
but the way I've done this
here is a little more Pythonic.
This "with" keyword, which is not
something analogous to anything
we've seen in C, the with
keyword, when you open a file,
it will automatically close
it for you eventually.
So you might see that in some online
references or other materials.
But again, it just does
that for you automatically.
Well, let's go ahead and do this.
I like the fact that we
can now manipulate CSV.
And it turns out that if
you've ever used Google Forms--
that's a very popular way of
collecting data from users.
In fact, let me go ahead and
go to a URL which is going
to show you a form like this here.
Brian, if you wouldn't mind typing
that into the chat, go to that you URL,
cs50.ly.hogwarts.
And if everyone wouldn't
mind just playing along,
just tell us what house you wish
you were assigned to by the Sorting
Hat in the world of Hogwarts.
What house would you be in?
Now, if you've used Google
Forms before, you'll
recall that you can see these results,
certainly in the Google Form itself--
and already 122 of you have buzzed in.
And we could see a distribution
and a graph and so forth.
But what I want is not the
distribution pictorially there.
I'm going to go ahead and
open up a spreadsheet.
And so if you've never used Google
Forms before, you can click a button,
and then you can get a list
of all of the responses
that are coming in live right now.
And by default, Google keeps
track of the timestamp,
when the form was submitted, and
what house was actually used.
So I'm going to go
ahead now and do this.
Let me go ahead and download
that in another tab.
Give me just a moment to
do it on this screen here.
I'm going to go ahead and
download that CSV file onto my Mac
locally, by going to
File, Download, CSV.
That's going to put it
into my Downloads folder.
And then I'm going to go ahead
and upload this into my IDE
by just dragging and dropping.
Whoops, I have to open the file browser.
I'm going to do this by
dragging and dropping the file.
All right.
Now I have that file there.
And let me go ahead now and
make sure the file's there.
I have this file called
"Sorting Hat Responses--
Form Responses 1," and so forth.
Well, let me go ahead and write a
program now that manipulates this data,
much like you might if
running a student group that's
collecting data in a Google Form, or
you're just collecting information
in general and have it in CSV format.
How might you now tally
up all of the results,
especially if Google
weren't just telling
you graphically what the results were?
Well, let me go ahead and write
a program called hogwarts,
which was not something that we've
seen ever before in C. Let me go ahead
and import this CSV library.
Let me give myself
initially a dictionary
called houses that contains
a whole bunch of keys,
like "Gryffindor" with
initial count of 0;
"Hufflepuff" with an initial count of 0;
"Ravenclaw" with an initial count of 0;
and also, "Slytherin" with
an initial count of 0.
So notice, in a dictionary,
or dict in Python,
the keys and values don't need
to be strings and strings.
It can certainly be strings and numbers.
Because I'm going to use this
dictionary ultimately to keep
count of all of the votes
for one house or another.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and open up
with open the Sorting Hat File--
Form Responses 1.csv"-- long filename,
but that's the default from Google--
as file.
So I'm going to use my one liner
instead of having to open and close.
I'm going to give myself this time a
reader, which we did not see before.
CSV library has a reader
function that allows
me to read a CSV file automatically.
I'm going to go ahead
and skip the first row.
Next is a function that
just skips the first row,
because recall that that one is
just timestamp and house, which
I do want to ignore.
I want the real data from you all.
And here's what's cool
about CSVs in Python.
I can-- if I want to iterate over all of
the rows that are in that spreadsheet,
I can do for row in reader.
And now, let me go ahead and get at,
for instance, the house in question.
So the house in a given row is going
to be the row's first entry, 0 indexed.
So what is going on here?
Well, let me go back to the
Google spreadsheet a moment ago.
And in the Google spreadsheet,
there's two columns.
And the way the CSV reader works is
it returns to you one row at a time--
and that's conceptually
pretty straightforward.
It maps perfectly to the
idea of a spreadsheet.
But each row is returned to you as a
list, a list in this case of size 2.
So row bracket 0 would give me
a given timestamp, row bracket
1 would give me a given house name.
So that's why here in the IDE, I'm going
ahead and declaring a variable called
house, and I'm assigning it
equal to row bracket 1, because I
don't care about the timestamp.
We all just did this
roughly at the same time.
But now that I have the house, I can
now index into the dictionary, just
like in C you could index
into an array using a number.
But in a dictionary, I can use strings.
So I'm going to go ahead and say,
go into the houses dictionary, which
I defined up above, and go to
the house key, and go ahead
and increment it by 1.
And that's it.
At this point, I have opened the CSV
file and read it using the library.
In this loop, I'm iterating over
every row in the spreadsheet
that you all created by filling
out that form again and again.
I'm just using a variable
to get at whatever's
in the second column, otherwise
known as row bracket 1,
because row bracket 0
would be the timestamp.
And then I'm going into
the dictionary called
houses, which we defined up here.
I'm indexing into it just like an
array, but it's a list in this case,
using its house name, which
looks up the appropriate key.
And then plus equals 1 has the
effect of incrementing its value.
So it's a nice way of going into
the dictionary and incrementing.
Go in and increment.
So now let's go ahead at the very end
here and just print out the result.
"For house in houses" is the
fancy way to iterate over
all of the keys in a dictionary, go
ahead and print out a formatted string
as follows.
Let me print out the house name followed
by a colon followed by the houses
dictionary, indexing into it with house.
So again, cryptic.
We'll come back to this in a second.
Python of hogwarts.
Let me cross my fingers
that I didn't screw this up.
And I did.
The IDE knew before I did.
All right.
Now let me hope that I didn't
screw this up-- and dammit.
All right.
The file is called something
slightly different.
Google's name must have changed,
sorry, versus when I practiced.
Let me copy this.
So close.
Sorting hat responses.
Ah, it has parentheses which I forgot.
All right.
Now let me cross my fingers,
rerun the program, dammit.
OK, no such file or--
oh, I forgot the csv, dot csv.
OK.
Now cross fingers and--
oh, thank God.
OK so Gryffindor, not surprisingly,
the most popular house.
Hufflepuff at 40, Ravenclaw at 71,
Slytherin-- oh, beat out Hufflepuff.
Very interesting for
whatever sociological reason.
But here we have a program
now that analyzed the CSV.
Now, we happened to do it
with silly Harry Potter data.
But again, imagine collecting
any data you want from users,
downloading it as a CSV to
your Mac or PC or your IDE,
then writing code that analyzes
that data however you want.
I did a very simple summation,
but you could certainly
imagine doing something
fancier than that,
like doing summations or
averages, standard deviations.
All of that functionality
could we get as well.
All right, any questions on
dictionaries before we now
offer up some of the most
powerful features we've yet
seen in a programming language?
Anything at all on your end, Brian?
BRIAN: No hands raised here.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
Well, let me go ahead now, and
I'm going to transition actually
to my Mac where I have in
advance pre-installed Python,
just so that I can do things locally.
It will make things a little faster.
I don't have to worry about
internet speeds and the like.
And this is indeed the case, that
on your own Mac, your own PC,
you can download and install
the Python interpreter,
run it on your own Mac and PC.
However, I would recommend
you continue using this IDE,
certainly for problem sets' sake
until the end of the semester,
maybe transitioning to your
Mac or PC for final projects
only, only because what I
did this weekend was spent--
waste a huge amount of time just
getting stupid libraries to work
on my own Mac, which is
often easier said than done,
just because when programmers are
writing code that's supposed to work
on every possible Mac and PC in the
world, you and I and everyone else
have slightly different version
numbers, different software install,
different incompatibilities.
So those kinds of headaches very quickly
arise when you're doing things locally.
So let me encourage you to wait
until terms end with final projects,
perhaps, to move off
of the IDE and do what
I'm about to now do, just because
you'll be able to see these demos more
clearly here.
I'm going to go ahead,
and on my own Mac,
I'm going to go ahead and create
a program called speech.py.
In advance, I've installed a library
that supports speech synthesis.
And if I want access
to that functionality,
it suffices to import pyttsx3, which is
the name of that person's open source
free library that I downloaded and
installed on my Mac in advance.
I read the documentation.
I literally never used
this before this past week.
And I found that I can declare a
variable called engine, for instance.
I can then call pyttsx3.init
to initialize the library.
Why?
That's just because of how
the programmer designed it.
You have to initialize it first.
I then can use that engine to say things
like, say, "hello," comma "world."
Then after that, I should run
the engine and wait for it
to finish before my own program quits.
All right.
Let me go ahead now and close that, and
run python of speech.py on my own Mac
here.
COMPUTER VOICE: Hello, world.
DAVID MALAN: Interesting.
So it said what I typed in.
And indeed, I can probably make
this even more interesting.
Let me go ahead and say
something like this.
Let me open up speech.py again
and add some functionality.
I won't use the CS50 library, but I
will use maybe the input function.
Let me go ahead and say name gets input,
"What's your name," question mark.
And then let me go ahead
and say, not "hello, world,"
but let me use an f-string--
which doesn't have to
be used in print, you
can use it in any function
that takes a string.
Let me go ahead and say
"hello" to that name.
All right.
Let me go ahead and run
python speech.py again.
Oops.
Let me go ahead and run
python of speech.py again.
What's my name?
David.
COMPUTER VOICE: Hello, David.
DAVID MALAN: Weird choice of inflection,
but indeed it synthesized it.
Let's try Brian.
COMPUTER VOICE: Hello, Brian.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So we could probably
tinker with the settings
to make the voice sound
a little more natural.
But that's pretty cool.
Well, let me go into some code I
wrote in advance this time using
a different library, this one related
to faces and facial detection.
Certainly very much in vogue
when it comes to social media
these days, with Facebook and other
websites automatically tagging you,
very concerning increasingly with state
governments and federal governments
and law enforcement using facial
detection to find people in a crowd.
And let me go ahead and open
up a file here, for instance,
a little more benignly, like a
whole bunch of people in an office.
So here is a photograph of
some people in an office.
And there's a lot of faces there.
But there's a lot of boxes of paper and
other distractions besides those faces.
But let me go ahead and look at,
quickly, a program called detect.py.
Most of this file is comments,
just so that if you want at home
you can follow along
and see what it does.
But let me just highlight
a few salient lines.
Here is that Pillow
library again, where I'm
accessing image related functionality
from a pre-installed Python function.
And this one's just kind of amazing.
If you want to use facial
recognition technology,
just import face_recognition.
That is a library you can
import that will give you access
to that kind of power.
Down here now, I only knew how to figure
this out by reading some documentation,
but you access the library called
face_recognition.load_image_file,
which is a function
that does what it means.
I'm opening up office.jpg.
And then scrolling down here to the
white code, which is the actual code--
all of the blue is comments, recall--
this line of code here is
all that's required in Python
to use the face recognition library,
find all of the face locations
in a given image, and store them
in a list called face_locations.
This line of code here
is just a Python loop
that iterates over every face
in the faces that were detected.
And then these several lines
of code here, long story short,
just crop out individual faces and
create a new image with the found
faces.
So without getting too much into the
details of the library, which are not
that intellectually interesting, the
features are interesting to us for now,
let me run python of detect.py.
Let me give my Mac a few
seconds here to do its thing.
And voila, if I zoom in here
we see Phyllis, and Jim,
and Roy, and pretty much
every other face that
was detected in that photograph, cropped
out as, indeed, an individual face.
So if you've ever noticed
a little square on yourself
in Facebook when uploading a photo,
this is exactly the kind of code
that Facebook and others are using on
their servers in order to execute that.
Well, you know what, how about this?
In the same office
photo, you know, there's
one person that always
seems to stand out.
No one really likes him.
And that's Toby.
What if we had a mug shot of Toby
in a separate file like this?
Can we find Toby in a crowd
among these people in the office?
Well, we can.
Let me go ahead now and run a
program called recognize.py,
which you're welcome to look at online.
It's similar lines of code,
It's not terribly many,
that is going to do some thinking.
It's opening up both the
office JPEG and this one.
And notice what just
happened, if I zoom in,
wonderfully, Toby is the only one
with a big green box around his face,
having indeed been recognized.
So again, I'll just glance at the code.
This time, if I open up recognize.py,
it's a few more lines of code.
But again, I'm importing face
recognition and some other things.
I'm loading toby.jpg.
And I'm loading office.jpg.
And then there's some more code
here that's looking for Toby,
looking for Toby, and then drawing
a big green box around the face that
is ultimately found.
So again, at the end of
the day, it's just loops.
It's just functions.
It's just variables.
But now the functions are
pretty darn fancy and powerful,
because again, they're taking advantage
of all of these other features
that we ourselves have
implemented in a language like C,
or have now seen glimpses of
within the world of Python.
Well, let's do another one.
Let me go ahead and open
up real quickly a program
that will allow me to create one of
these 2D barcodes, a so-called QR code.
Let me go ahead and create a file called
qr.py And in this file, let me go ahead
and do this.
Import the operating
system library, for reasons
we'll soon see, and let me
import the QR code library, which
will do all of the hard work for me.
Let me go ahead and create
an image called qr--
that's assigned the
value of qrcode making.
And let me paste in this URL of
one of the course's lecture videos,
for instance.
And then let me go ahead and save
this image as qr.png, Portable Network
Graphic, as indeed a PNG,
a very popular file format
for photos and other things.
And then let me actually
open this thing up.
Open up system-- actually,
nope, that's fine.
Let me keep it simple.
We don't need the os library.
Nope, we do.
Let's go ahead and open
it up with "open qr.png."
So three lines of code--
make a QR code with that URL, save
it as qr.png, and open the file.
Three lines of code.
Let me go ahead and run python of qr.py.
Voila, it was pretty fast.
If you would like to take out
your own iPhone or Android phone,
turn on the camera if
your phone supports this,
and scan this 3D barcode by awkwardly
just pointing your phone at the lecture
as we speak, it should open up YouTube
for you, hopefully, and with such is--
I apologize to those-- yes, thank you
for showing me what you're not seeing.
I apologize for doing that yet again.
Never gets old.
But all we've done is embed in a
two-dimensional format, details
of which we won't go
into in class, a URL,
which suggests that you can store
anything inside of these 2D barcodes,
and if you decode them with
something like your camera can
the software running on your phones
these days decode these things for you.
Well, let me do something else, this
time involving another sense, this one
listening.
Let me go into a file called listen.py.
And let me go ahead and
do something very simple.
Let me go ahead and get a user's
input in a variable called word
by using the input function.
Say something.
And then let me just send it all to
lowercase, just to keep things simple.
And now let me do this.
Once I get the user's words,
let me go ahead and say,
if the word "hello" is in their words,
go ahead and print out "Hello to you
too!"
So if they say hello, I
want to say hello back.
Elif, "how are you" in words, then let
me go ahead and print out something
like, "I am well,
thanks," as the computer.
Elif "goodbye" in words, then let me
go ahead and say something reasonable
like "Goodbye to you too."
And then lastly, else let
me go ahead and print out
just something like "Huh?"
Unrecognized.
So if you will, here is the beginnings
of an artificial intelligence, an AI--
a program that's going to somehow
interact with me the human typing
in phrases to this thing.
So if I did it correctly, let me go
ahead and run python of listen.py.
I did not do something correctly.
Oh, not "is," "in."
OK, sorry.
Let me go ahead and run
python of listen.py.
Say something.
I'll say "hello."
Oh, Hello to you too.
What a nice friendly program.
Let me ask it how it is,
"how are you," question mark.
It seems to detect that.
Let me go ahead and say,
"ok goodbye for now."
And it detects that, too, because
"goodbye" is in the phrase
that the user typed in.
But if I say something like,
"hey there," it's not recognized.
So pretty cool.
We can use very simple string
comparisons using the in preposition
to detect things.
But I bet-- you know, I bet
if we use the right library,
we can really make this
more powerful, too.
Let me go ahead, and just like
I imported facial recognition,
let me import speech recognition in
Python, which is yet another library
that I pre-installed.
Let me go ahead and now
do this, recognizer equals
speech_recognition.Recognizer.
And this is just creating a
variable called recognizer
by my having followed literally the
documentation for using this library.
Then let me go ahead and do this,
also from the documentation,
with speech_recognition.Microphone
as source.
So this is opening up my
microphone in some sense,
again just following the documentation.
Let me go ahead and say
"Say something" to the user.
And then after that, let
me go ahead and declare
a variable called audio, set it equal
to the recognizer's listen function,
passing in my microphone as the source.
And now down here, let me go ahead
and say print out "You said,"
and below that I will print
out recognizer.recognize,
is the hardest part today so far
for some reason, google audio.
All right.
So what's going on?
This line of code--
these lines of code here
are opening up a connection
to my microphone on my Mac.
It's then using the speech recognition
library to listen to my microphone,
and storing the audio from my
microphone in a variable called audio.
These lines of code down
here are literally printing,
"You said," and then it's passing to
the, the google.com, the file of audio
that I just recorded on my
microphone, and it's printing out
whatever comes back from Google.
So let's see what comes
out, again, crossing
my fingers that I didn't mess up.
Python of listen.
Hello, world.
Hoo.
How are you?
It's a pretty good speech recognition.
It's using the cloud, so to speak.
It's passing it up to Google.
But now let's make
things a little fancier
and actually respond to the human.
So let me go back into here and
add back some of the previous logic
and say something like this.
If "hello" in words, then go
ahead and print out, like before,
"Hello to you too."
Elif "how are you" in the words
that have come back from Google,
go ahead and print out
"I am well, thanks!"
And down here if I said
"goodbye" in words,
then go ahead and print
out "Goodbye to you too!"
Else if nothing comes back that I
recognize, let's just print out "Huh?"
So if I did this right, let's now go
ahead and let's do python of listen.py.
Hello, there.
Oh, dammit.
OK, standby.
Da-da-da.
Oh, sorry.
Let me do a find and replace.
I called the variable
"words" instead of "audio."
And I just executed a fancy
command to replace it everywhere.
So "audio" is what I
meant to say this time.
Now, let's go ahead and run
this, python of listen.py.
Hello, world.
Dammit.
AudioData is not iterable.
This is a bug.
Give me one second to
double check my notes.
Very sorry to disappoint.
The audio in-- oh, I did--
sorry.
I did it right the first
time but the wrong way.
Let me change my variable back to words.
OK.
What I forgot to do was
call one line of code here
that's literally sitting in front of me.
I need to convert the recognizer's
return value, recognize_google audio.
I need to store the return value
of passing the audio to Google
and storing the resulting text here.
And so I have re-stored,
using the words variable here.
All right now let me go ahead
and run python of listen.py.
Hello, there.
Very nice.
How are you today?
Cool.
OK, goodbye.
All right.
So there we have an even more
compelling artificial intelligence.
Granted, it's not that intelligent, it's
just looking for preordained strings.
But I bet we can do something even more.
And in fact, let me go ahead and step
inside, and see if a colleague of mine
can't help do something in real time.
On a big fancy PC here
in the theater, we
are running some other
Python program on a CPU
that's fast enough to
do this in real time.
And we've connected one
of our cameras to that PC,
so that what you're about to see is
the result of one of our cameras being
wired into this PC, running that
camera's input into Python software
running on that PC.
And we have trained the PC,
using this Python software,
to recognize certain images in the past.
And let's see if we
can't do this as well.
Brian, would you mind
putting me on screen 1?
And Rongxin, do you want to go
ahead and load up our first guest?
I think we are live.
So again, you see my mouth moving
in lock step with Einstein here.
His lips are matching mine.
His head movements are moving--
matching mine.
We can even be inquisitive.
If my eyebrows go up, move
my mouth this way, this way.
And you can see that the
Python program in real time
is mapping my facial movements
onto someone else's face, of course
otherwise known as a deep fake.
Rongxin, could we try out
Brian's photo instead?
Here now we have Brian who
similarly is matching big smile.
Gets a little fake at some point.
But again, if we pre-rendered all
of this instead of doing it live,
the PC could probably
do an even better job.
How about could, we invite Harvard
president Larry Bacow to join us,
Rongxin?
This is CS50, Harvard
University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
How about President Peter
Salovey from Yale, Rongxin?
This is CS50, Yale
University's introduction
to the intellectual
enterprises of computer science
and the art of programming.
Now at this point, the
real-world implications of this
should be getting increasingly clear.
While it's all fun and games to do this
on Instagram, in TikTok and the like,
using various mobile
applications these days,
which are essentially
doing the same thing--
and you can see the image
doesn't quite keep up
with me if I start moving a
little too quickly right now--
this is very real-world implications
in the world of politics, government,
business, and really just the
real world more generally,
because I'm essentially putting in
someone else's mouth my own words.
And while it's clear that these
examples thus far aren't really that
compelling-- if I
start to move too much,
you see that things start
to get out of sync--
just imagine that if we
wait one year, our computers
are going to be twice as fast with
even more memory and the like.
Software is only getting
better and more powerful,
the libraries and the artificial
intelligence is getting more trained.
And so among the themes for
the coming weeks of the class
is not just how to do some
things with technology
and how to write code, but frankly
asking the much bigger, more
important picture question of should
you do certain things with technology,
and should you actually write such code.
We did ask President Salovey and
President Bacow for their permission
in advance to spoof them in this way.
But we thought we would
more playfully end
with just a couple of other
examples that you perhaps
see on Instagram, TikTok, and the like.
Rongxin, could we invite
Pam to join us first?
And how about a certain Jim?
All right.
That's it for CS50 and Python today.
We'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]