[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this is week 3.
And you'll recall that last week, we
equipped you with a lot more tools
by which to solve problems-- not
only problems that we had proposed,
but problems in your own
code, that is to say bugs.
And recall that those tools involve
command line tools like help50
for help with cryptic error messages
that the compiler might spit out;
style50 which, gives
you a bit of feedback
on the stylization of your
code, the aesthetics thereof;
check50, which checks the correctness
of your code against the specifications
in a given problem set
or lab; printf, which
is a function that it exists in
some form in almost any programming
language that you might
ultimately learn, and this
is simply a way of printing out anything
you might want from the computer's
memory onto the screen.
Then perhaps the most
powerful of these tools
was debug50, which was
this interactive debugger.
And even though this command debug50
is a little specific to CS50,
what it triggers to happen,
that little side window
where you can see the
stack of functions that you
might have called
during some break point,
and you can see the local variables that
you might have defined at some point
during the execution
of your code, that's
a very common conventional feature of
any debugger with most any language.
And then lastly, recall there was
this ddb, duck debugger, which
of course, takes this physical form, if
you happen to have a rubber duck lying
around with whom you can talk.
But I'm so pleased to
say that if you lack
that currently while at home, CS50's
own Kareem and Brenda and Sophie
have wonderfully added, if
you haven't noticed already,
that same virtual duck to CS50 IDE.
So if you click in the top
corner, you can actually
begin to have a chat of
sorts with the rubber duck.
And while this is a certainly more
playful incarnation of that same idea,
we really can't emphasize
enough the value
of talking through problems when you're
experiencing them in code with someone
else or with something else.
This particular duck, not all
that large of a vocabulary,
but it's not so much what the
other person says but what you say
and what you hear yourself
saying that is undoubtedly
the most valuable part of the process.
So our thanks to Kareem and
Brenda and Sophie on that.
Recall last week, 2, that we
took a look underneath the hood,
literally in some sense, at the
computer's memory in your laptop
or desktop or phone.
And then we decided to
think about this more
artistically as just a grid of bytes.
So within that chip, there's
a whole bunch of bits.
And if you look at eight of them at a
time, there's a whole bunch of bytes.
And it stands to reason
that we could think
of this as the first byte, the
second byte, the third byte,
and so forth, and sort of
chop this up pictorially
into just a whole sequence of
bytes in the computer's memory.
And recall that if we zoom in on that
and focus on just one continuous block
of memory, otherwise
known as an "array,"
we can do things within this array like
storing a bunch of different values.
So recall last week, we
started by defining a little--
goofily, multiple variables that
were almost identically names,
like scores1, scores2, scores3.
And then we began to clean up the design
of our code by introducing an array,
so we can have just one variable
called scores, that is of size 3
and has room for multiple values.
So today, we'll continue to leverage
this feature of many programming
languages-- being able to
store things continuously,
back to back to back to
back, in a computer's memory,
because this very simple layout, this
very simple feature of the language,
is going to open up all
sorts of powerful features.
And in fact, we can even
revisit some of the problems
we tried to solve way back in week 0.
But there is a catch with arrays.
And we didn't really
emphasize this much last week.
And that's because, even
though you and I can
glance at this picture on the screen
and see immediately that, oh, there's
seven boxes on the screen, there
are seven locations in which you
can store values, you and I can sort of
have this bird's eye view of everything
and just see what's inside
that entire array all at once.
But computers, recall, are much
more methodical, more algorithmic,
if you will.
And so a computer, as
powerful as they are,
can technically only look at one
location in an array at a time.
So whereas you and I can
glance at this and sort of
take it all in at once a computer
just can't glance at its memory
and take in all at once
all of the values therein,
it has to do so more methodically, for
instance, from left to right, maybe
right to left, maybe middle onward.
But it has to be an algorithm.
And so today we'll formalize that notion
and really kind of hide the fact that
this array cannot be seen all at once,
you can only look at one location
in an array at a given time.
And this is going to have
very real implications.
For instance, if we consider
that very first problem
in the very first week where we tried
to find my phone number in a phone book,
the very naive approach was to start
at the beginning and search from left
to right.
And we tried a couple
of variants thereafter.
But the problem, quite
simply, is that of searching.
And this is a term of
art in computer science,
super common, certainly for
you and I as users on Google
and the like to search
for things all day long.
And so certainly searching well,
designing a search algorithm well,
is certainly a compelling feature
of so many of today's tools
that you and I use.
So if we think of this
really as a problem to solve,
we've got some input, which, for
instance, might be an array of numbers,
or maybe an array of web
pages in the case of Google.
And the goal is to get some output.
So if the input to the problem is
an array of values, the output,
hopefully, is going to be something
as simple, really, as a bool--
yes or no.
Is the value you're
looking for discoverable?
Can you search for and find that
value, yes or no, true or false?
Now, within this black box, recall,
is going to be some algorithm.
And that's where today we'll
spend most of our time.
Indeed, we won't really introduce
that many more features of C.
We won't introduce that much more code.
We'll focus again on ideas, just
taking for granted now that you
have some more tools in your toolkit.
Beyond loops and conditions
and Boolean expressions,
we now have this other
tool known as arrays.
But let's first introduce some other
terms of art, some jargon if you will,
related to what we'll call running time.
So we've alluded to this a few times.
When we're thinking about just
how good or bad an algorithm is,
we describe how long it takes to run.
That is its running time.
The running time of an
algorithm is how long it takes--
how many steps it takes, how many
seconds it takes, how many iterations
it takes.
It doesn't really matter
what your unit of measure is.
Maybe it's time, maybe it's
iterations or something else.
But running time just refers to
how long does an algorithm take.
And there are ways that we can think
about this a little more formally.
And we kind of did this
already in the first week,
but we didn't give it this
name, this italicized O,
this capital O on the screen, is
otherwise known as Big O notation.
And computer scientists
and some mathematicians
will very frequently use,
literally, this symbol
to describe the running
times of algorithms,
or mathematically like a function.
So recall this picture, in fact.
When we were searching that phone book,
we did it sort of good, better, best.
We did it linearly-- that is,
searching one page at a time,
we did it twice as fast by
doing two pages at a time--
and then we did it logarithmically
by dividing and conquering,
in half and half and half.
And at the time, I proposed
that if we think of a phone book
as having n pages, where n is just a
number in computer science vernacular,
we might describe the running
time, or the number of steps
involved for that first algorithm, as
being maybe in the worst case n steps.
If the person you're looking
for in a phone book maybe
alphabetically has the last
name starting with Z in English,
well, the Z might be all the way
at the end of the phone book.
So at the worst case, you
might be taking n steps
to find someone like
myself in that phone book.
The second algorithm,
though, was twice as fast,
because we went two pages at a time.
So we might describe its
running time as n divided by 2.
And then the third algorithm, where we
divided the problem in half and half
and half, literally throwing half
of the problem away again and again,
was logarithmic-- technically log
base 2 of n, which, again, is just
a mathematical formula that
refers to halving something again
and again and again.
And you start with, of course,
n pages in that scenario.
Well, it turns out that a
computer scientist would actually
wave their hands at some of
these mathematical details.
Indeed, we're not going to
get into the habit of writing
very precise mathematical formulas.
What we're instead going
to do is try to get
a sense of the order on which
the running time of an algorithm
is, just roughly how fast
or how slow it is, but still
using some symbology
like n as a placeholder.
And so a computer scientist would
describe the running time of all three
of those algorithms from week 0 as
being big O of n, or big O of n/2,
or big O of log base 2 of n.
So "big O" just means "on the order of."
It's sort of a wave of the hand.
Maybe it's n minus 1, maybe it's
n plus 1, maybe it's even 2n.
But it's on the order of
n or these other values.
But in fact, too,
notice that this chart,
there's something kind of curious. ,
Like these first two algorithms from
week 0 kind of pictorially
look pretty much the same.
Like undoubtedly, the yellow
line is a little lower
and therefore a little better and
a little faster than the red line.
But they have the same shape.
And in fact, I bet if we zoomed
way out, these two straight lines
would pretty much look identical.
If you change your axis to be
big enough and tall enough,
these would start to blur together.
But clearly, the green line
is fundamentally different.
And so this speaks to a
computer scientist's tendency
to not really quibble
over these details.
Like, yes, the second
algorithm in week 0 was better.
Yes, this yellow line is better.
But, eh, let's just call both of
those algorithms running times
on the order of n.
That is to say, a computer scientist
tends to throw away constant factors,
like the 1/2 or the divided by 2.
And they tend to focus only
on the dominant factor,
like which value in that mathematical
expression is going to grow the most,
grow the fastest.
And n divided by 2n it's
going to dominate over time.
The bigger the phone book
gets, the more pages you have.
It's really n that's going to matter
less so than that divided by 2.
And same thing over here.
If you're familiar with and
remember your logarithms,
we don't really have to even care
about the base of that logarithm.
Yes, it's base 2, but eh, we
can just multiply that logarithm
by some other number to convert
it to any base we want--
base 10, base 3, base 7, anything.
So let's just say it's
on the order of log n.
So this is good, because
it means we're not really
going to waste time getting
really into the weeds
mathematically when we talk about
the efficiency of algorithms.
It suffices to describe things really in
terms of the variable, n in this case,
if you will, that dominates over time.
And indeed, let's zoom out.
If I zoom out on this
picture, boom, you begin
to see that, yeah, these are really
starting to look almost identical.
And if we kept zooming out, you
would see that they're essentially
one in the same.
But the green one stands out, so
that's indeed on the order of log of n
as opposed to n itself.
So here's a little cheat sheet.
It turns out that
within computer science,
and within the analysis
of algorithms, we're
going to tend to see some
common formulas like this.
So we've just seen on the order of n.
We've seen on the order of log n.
It turns out that the very
common two is going to be n times
log n, maybe even n squared,
and then even big O of 1.
And the last of those just
means that an algorithm
takes, wonderfully, one step--
or maybe two steps, maybe even 10
steps, but a constant number of steps.
So that's sort of the best case
scenario, at least among these options.
Whereas, n squared is going
to start to take a long time.
It's going to start to
feel slow, because if you
take any value of n
and square it, that's
going to imply more and more steps.
So just a bit of jargon,
then, to start off today,
whereby we now have
this sort of vocabulary
with which to describe the running times
of an algorithm in terms of this Big O
notation.
But there's one other notation.
And just as big O
refers to an upper bound
on running times, like
how many steps maximally,
how much time maximally
might an algorithm take,
this omega notation
refers to the opposite.
What's a lower bound on the
running time of an algorithm?
And we don't need another
picture or other formulas.
We can reuse the same one.
So this cheat sheet
here just proposes that,
when describing the efficiency
or inefficiency of an algorithm
and you want to come
up with a lower bound--
like minimally, how many
steps does my algorithm take--
we can use the same
mathematical formulas,
but we can note that with
omega instead of big O.
So again, looks fancy,
but it really just refers
to a wave of the hand trying to sort of
ballpark exactly what the running time
is of an algorithm.
And thankfully, we've seen
a few algorithms already,
including in that week 0, and now we're
going to give it a more formal name.
Linear search is what we
did with that phone book
first off by searching
it page by page by page,
looking for my phone number
in that particular example.
And so the difference today
is that, unlike us humans, who
can look down at a phone book page and
see a whole bunch of names and numbers
at once, unlike a human who can look
at an array on the board a moment ago
and sort of see everything
at once, we need
to be more methodical,
more deliberate today so
that we can translate week 0's
ideas now, not into even pseudocode,
but actual C code.
And so wonderfully, here at
the American Repertory Theater
as we are on Harvard's
campus this semester,
we've been collaborating
with the whole team
here who are much more artistically
inclined than certainly I
could be on my own here.
And we have these seven
wonderful doors that
were previously used in various
theatrical shows that took place here
in this theater.
And we've even collaborated
with the theater's prop shop,
who in back have wonderfully
manufactured some delightful numbers
and brought them to life.
Which is to say that, behind each
of these seven doors is a number.
And this is going to be an opportunity
now to really hammer home the point
that when we want to search
for some number in an array,
it's pretty equivalent to having to
search for a number, in this case,
behind an otherwise closed door.
You and I can't just look
at all of these doors
now and figure out where a number is.
We have to be more methodical.
We have to start searching
these doors, maybe
from left to right, maybe from right
to left, maybe from the middle on out.
But we need to come up with an algorithm
and ultimately translate that to code.
So for instance, suppose I were
to search for the number 0.
How could we go about searching,
methodically, these seven wooden doors
for the number 0?
Let me take a suggestion
from the audience.
What approach might you take?
What first step would you propose I
take here on my own with these doors?
Any recommendations?
How do I begin to find
myself the number 0?
Florence, what do you propose?
AUDIENCE: I would propose starting form
the left, since 0 is a smaller number.
DAVID MALAN: OK, good.
And hang in there for
with me for just a moment.
Let me go ahead and started on the
left edge as Florence proposes.
Go ahead and open the door,
and hopefully, voila--
no.
It's a number 4.
So it's not a 0.
So Florence, what would
you propose I do next?
AUDIENCE: I'd probably start
in the middle somewhere,
if, like, in case, I don't
know, it's going down by 1.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So maybe it's going down.
So let me go ahead and try that.
So you propose middle, I could
go over here, and voila--
nope.
That's the number 2.
And I wonder, where else should I look.
Let me-- I'm a little curious.
I'm a little nervous that
I ignored these doors.
So Florence, if you don't mind,
let's go ahead and look here and--
no, that's the number 6, it seems.
Let's go ahead and check
in here, the number 8.
So they're kind of going up and down.
So Florence, how might I finish
searching for this number?
What remains to be done, would you say?
AUDIENCE: Probably start
from the right now.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So I could start from the right
now, and maybe just go over here.
And voila-- and there it is.
So we found the number 0.
So let me ask Florence,
what was your algorithm?
How did you go about so successfully
finding the number 0 for us?
AUDIENCE: I guess I initially tried
starting, like, by going down by 1.
So like, if the number
was not at the left,
then going to the center, which
is, like, halfway in between
and then going to [INAUDIBLE].
I don't know.
DAVID MALAN: And playfully, how did that
work out for you, going to the middle?
Better or worse, no different?
AUDIENCE: I mean, I guess
maybe it helped a little bit
to then go all the way to the right.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Yeah, we might have
gleaned some information.
But let's go ahead and take a look
at all of the doors for a moment.
There's that 4 and the 6 again.
Here is that 8 again.
Over in the middle we have the 2 again.
Over here we have a
7 for the first time.
Over here we have a 5.
And then of course, we have a 0.
And if you took all of that in,
honestly, Florence, you and I,
we couldn't really have done any better.
Because these door-- these
numbers, it turns out,
are just randomly arranged
behind these doors.
So it wasn't bad at all that
you kind of hopped around.
Although, the downside
is if you hop around,
you and I as humans can pretty easily
remember where we've been before.
But if you think about how we
would translate that to code,
I feel like we're starting to
accumulate a bunch of variables
maybe, because you have
to keep track of that.
So frankly, maybe the
simplest solution-- whoops--
maybe the simplest solution would
have been where we started in week 0,
where we just take a very simple
if naive approach of starting
with our array, this time of size
7, behind which are some numbers.
And if you don't know
anything about those numbers,
honestly the best you can do is just
that same linear search from week 0,
and just check, one at a time, the
values behind each of these doors
and just hope that
eventually you will find it.
So this is already sort of
taking a lot of time, right?
If I do this linear search
approach like I did in week 0,
I'm potentially going to have to
search behind all of those doors.
I'm going to have to search
behind all of those doors.
So let's consider a little more formally
exactly how I could at least implement
that algorithm.
Because I could take the
approach that Florence
proposed, and just kind of
jumping around and maybe using
a bit of intuition.
But again, that's not
really an algorithm.
We really need to do
something more step by step.
And in the meantime, let's go ahead,
Joe, and let's close the curtain
and see if we can't clean those up
with another problem in a moment,
while we consider now linear
search and the analysis thereof.
So with linear search,
I would propose that we
could implement it in pseudocode
first, if you will, like this.
For i from 0 to n minus 1--
we'll see where we're going with this--
if the number is behind the i-th door,
return true, otherwise at
the very end return false.
So it's a relatively simple
translation into pseudocode,
much like we did with the
phone book some time ago.
And why, though, these values?
Because I'm now starting to express
myself a little more like C,
even though it's still pseudocode.
So for i from 0 to n minus 1.
So computer scientists tend
to start counting from 0.
If there's n doors, or 7 doors in this
case, you want to go from 0 on up to 6,
or from 0 on up to n minus 1.
So this is just a very common way of
setting yourself up with a for loop,
maybe in C, maybe in
pseudocode in this case, that
just gets you from left to right,
algorithmically step by step.
If a condition, number
is behind the i-th door--
i-th just being a
colloquial way of saying,
what is behind the door at location i--
go ahead and return true.
I have found myself the number I
want, for instance, the number 0.
And then notice that this return
false is not part of an else,
because I don't want to abort this
algorithm prematurely and abort simply
because a number is not
behind the current door.
I essentially want to wait all the
way to the end of the algorithm,
after I've checked all n doors,
and if I have still not found
the number I care about, then and
only then am I going to return false.
So a very common
programming mistake might
be to nest this internally and think
about things in terms of ifs and elses.
But you don't need to have an else.
This is kind of a catchall
here at the very end.
But now let's consider, if this is the
pseudocode for linear search, just what
is the efficiency of linear search?
What is the efficiency of
linear search, which is to say,
how well-designed is this algorithm?
We put or gave ourselves
a framework a moment ago,
Big O notation, which is an upper
bound, which we can think of for now
as meaning like a worst case.
In the worst case, how many steps
might it take me to find the number 0--
or any number for that matter--
among n doors?
Is it big O of n squared, big
O of n times log n, big O of n,
big O of log n, or big O of
one, which, again, just means
a constant fixed number of steps?
Brian, could we go ahead
and pull up this question?
Let me go ahead and pull
it up on my screen as well.
If you go to our usual URL to
propose what you think an upper bound
is on the running time of linear search.
OK.
Indeed, if we consider now the
running time of linear search,
it's going to be big O of n.
Why is that?
So in the worst case, the
number I'm looking for,
0, might very well be at
the end of that list, which
is going to be on the order of n steps,
or in this case precisely n steps.
So that's one way to think about this.
Well, now let me ask
a follow-up question.
Proposing instead that we consider
omega notation, which is a lower bound
on the running time of an algorithm--
Brian, could we go ahead
and ask this question next?
At that same URL, we'll
see a question asking now
for the possible answers
for the running time--
for a lower bound on the
running time of linear search.
So let's go ahead and take
a look at this one here.
And in just a moment, we'll
see as the responses come in,
about 75-plus percent
of you are proposing
that it's actually omega of 1.
So omega is a lower bound.
1 refers to constant time.
And why is that?
Let me just take a quick
answer on this point.
Among the 75% of you who said one
step, or a constant number of steps,
why is that?
How do you think about this
lower bound on running time?
How about from Keith?
Why omega of 1?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you can just open it and
be lucky and find it in the first door.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So it really speaks to just that.
You might just get lucky, and
the number you're looking for
might be at the very first door.
So the lower bound, in the best
case, if you will, of this algorithm,
linear search might very well be
omega of 1 for exactly that reason--
that you have-- get
lucky and the element
might be there at the beginning.
So that's pretty good.
You really can't do
any better than that.
So we this range now of a lower bound
from omega of 1 on up to big O of n
being an upper bound on the
running time of linear search.
But of course, we have this
other algorithm in our toolkit.
And recall from week 0 that we
looked at binary search-- although,
not necessarily by name.
It was that divide-and-conquer third
algorithm, where we took the phone book
and split it in half
and half and half again.
Now, while I fumbled there, Joe kindly
has given us a new set of doors.
If Joe, you could go ahead and
reveal our seven doors again,
behind which we still have some numbers.
But I think this time, I'm
going to be a little better off.
Cue Joe and the doors behind.
There we go.
So we have our same seven doors.
But behind those doors now is a
different arrangement of numbers.
And suppose this time, I want
to find myself the number 6.
So the number 6-- we'll
change the problem slightly--
but I'm going to give you one
other ingredient this time,
which is going to be
key to this working.
Why were Florence and I able to do
no better than linear search before?
Why were Florence and
I able to do no better
than randomly searching even last time?
What was it about the array
of numbers, or the array
of doors, that did not allow me
previously to use binary search?
Iris, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: Because we didn't know
the numbers are sorted or not.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
We didn't know if the
numbers were sorted or not.
And indeed, barring that
detail, Florence and I
really couldn't have done any
better than, say, linear search.
So this time, though, Joe has
kindly sorted some numbers
behind these doors for us.
And so if I want to
search for the number 6,
now I can begin to use a
bit of that information.
So you know what, I'm going to start
just like we did with the phone book
and start roughly in the middle.
And voila, number 5.
All right.
So we're pretty close,
we're pretty close.
But the thing about
binary search, recall,
is that this is now useful information.
If the numbers are sorted behind these
doors all, of the doors to the left
should presumably be lower than 5,
and all of the doors to the right
should presumably be larger than 5.
Now, I might kind of cut a corner
here and be like, well, if this is 5,
6 is probably right
next door, literally.
But again, algorithmically,
how might we do this?
We don't want to necessarily
consider these special cases.
So more generally, it looks like
I now have an array of size 3.
So let me go ahead and apply that
same algorithm, voila, to the middle.
Now I have the number 7.
And now it's becoming pretty clear
that if the number 6 is present,
it's probably behind this door.
And indeed, if I now look at my
remaining array of size 1, and voila,
in the middle there is that number 6.
So this time, I only had to open up
three doors instead of all seven,
potentially, or maybe all six doors
to find my way to that number,
because I was given this
additional ingredient of all
of those numbers being sorted.
So it would seem, then,
that you can apply
the better, more efficient, better
designed algorithm, now known
as binary search, if only someone like
Joe would sort the numbers for you
in advance.
So let's consider now a
little more algorithmically
how we might implement this.
So with binary search, let
me propose this pseudocode.
If the number is behind the middle
door, return true-- we found it.
So if we got lucky,
then we might very well
have found the number 6
behind the middle door,
and we would have been done.
But that didn't happen.
And in the general case
that probably won't happen.
So if the number is less than
that behind the middle door, then
just like with the phone book,
I'm going to go to the left,
and I'm going to search the left half
of the remaining doors in the array.
Else if the number is greater
than that behind the middle door,
then like the phone book I'm
going to go ahead and search
the right half of the phone book.
But there might still be
one final case potentially,
whereby if there's no doors left at
all, or no doors in the first place,
I should at least have this one special
case where I do say return false.
For instance, if 6, for whatever
reason, weren't be among those doors
and I were searching
for it, I still need
to be able to handle that situation
where I can say definitively
return false if I'm left with
no further doors to search.
So here, then, might be the pseudocode
for this algorithm a bit more formally.
Now let's consider the analysis thereof.
Before, where we left off,
linear search was big O of n.
Linear search was big O of n.
This time let's consider where binary
search actually falls into place
by asking a different question.
I'm going to go ahead and go
back and ask this question now--
what's an upper bound on the
running time of binary search?
An upper bound on the running
time of binary search--
and go ahead and buzz in, if
you'd like, similarly to before.
What's an upper bound on the
running time of binary search?
And you can see here answers are
getting pretty dominant around log n.
And indeed, that jives with
exactly what we did in week 0.
The correct answer is indeed
log of n, because that's
going to be the maximum
number of times that you
can take a list or an
array of a given size
and split it in half and
half and half, until you
find the number you're
looking for, or ultimately you
don't find that number at all.
Meanwhile, if we consider now not just
the upper bound on this algorithm--
so in the worst case, binary
search takes big O of log n--
now let's consider a
related question which
is, what's a lower bound on the
running time of this same algorithm?
What's a lower bound
on the running time?
I'll go ahead and pluck
this one off myself
and go back to some of
the suggestions thus far.
In the best case, maybe,
too, you do get lucky,
and the number you're looking
for, 6 or some other number,
is smack dab in the middle of the array.
And so maybe indeed you can
get away with just one step.
And indeed, a lower bound on binary
search now might very well just
be an omega of 1, because in that
best case you just get lucky,
and it's right where you happen to
start, in this case in the middle.
So we seem to have a range there.
But strictly speaking, it would
seem that binary search is better.
Binary search is better
than linear search,
because as n gets big, big, big,
you can really feel that difference.
In fact, recall from week 0 we played
a little bit with these light bulbs.
And right now, all 64 of
these light bulbs are on.
And let's consider for a moment,
just to put this into perspective,
how long it would take to
use linear search to find
one light bulb among these 64.
And recall that in the worst case,
maybe the light bulb, or the number
that we're looking for, is
way down there at the end,
but we don't know in advance.
And so Sumner, if you wouldn't
mind executing linear search
on these light bulbs, let's just
get a feel for the efficiency
or inefficiency of this algorithm.
Linear search in light bulb form.
So you'll notice that
one light bulb at a time
is going out, implying that I've
searched that door, searched that door,
searched that door.
But we've only gone
through 10 or so bulbs,
and we've got another 50-plus to go.
And you can see that if we look
inside of these doors one per second,
or turn off these light bulbs one per
second, it's going to take a long time.
In fact, it doesn't seem worthwhile
to even wait until the very end.
So Sumner, if you wouldn't mind,
let's bring all the lights back up,
and let's try once more another
algorithm, this one binary search, just
to get, again, a feel of what the
running time is of an algorithm,
like binary search that
runs in logarithmic time.
So in just a moment, we'll go
ahead and execute binary search
on these light bulbs, the idea being
that there's one bulb we care about.
Let's see how fast we can get
down to just one bulb out of 64.
So Sumner, on your marks, get set, go.
And we're done just a few steps later.
And then have this sole light bulb.
That was so much faster.
And in fact, we did this
deliberately one iteration at a time.
The algorithm that we just executed
with Sumner's and Matt's help,
algorithmically was operating at
what's called 1 hertz, 1 hertz.
And if you're unfamiliar with hertz,
it's just one something per second.
It's very often used in physics or
just in discussions of electricity
more generally.
And indeed, in this case if
you're doing one thing per second,
that first algorithm, linear search,
might have taken us like 64 seconds
to get all the way to
that final light bulb.
But that second algorithm
was logarithmic.
And so by going from 64 to
32 to 16 to 8 to 4 to 2 to 1,
we get to the final result much
faster, even going at the same pace.
So in fact, if you think
of your computer's CPU,
CPUs are also measured in hertz--
H-E-R-T-Z. Probably
measured in gigahertz,
which is billions of hertz per second.
So your CPU, the brain of your
computer, If it's 1 gigahertz,
that means it can literally
do 1 billion things at a time.
And here we have this sort of simpler
setup of just light bulbs doing
one thing per second.
Your computer can do 1 billion of
these kinds of operations at once.
So just imagine, therefore,
how much these savings tend
to add up over time if you can take big
bites out of these problems at once,
as opposed to doing
things like we did in week
0, just one single step at a time.
All right.
Well, let's now go ahead and
start to translate this to code.
We have enough tools in our
toolkit in C that I think,
based on our discussion
of arrays last week,
we can now actually start to build
something in code on our own.
So I'm going to go ahead and create
a file here in just a moment,
in CS50 IDE, called,
for instance, numbers.c.
Let me go ahead and translate this
to a file in C code called numbers.c.
The goal at hand is just to
implement linear search in code,
just so that we're no longer
waving our hands at the pseudocode
but doing things a
little more concretely.
So I'm going to go ahead
and include cs50.h.
I'm going to go ahead
and include stdio.h.
And I'm going to start with
no command line arguments,
like we left off last week,
but just with main void.
And I'm going to go ahead and
give myself an array of numbers,
seven numbers, just like the doors.
And I'm going to go ahead
and say int numbers.
And then this is a little trick
that we didn't see last week,
but it's handy for
creating an array when
you know in advance what
numbers you want, which I do,
because I'm going to mimic the doors
that Joe kindly set up for us here, I'm
going to go ahead and say give me an
array that is equal to 4, 6, 8, 2, 7,
5, 0.
And this is the feature
we didn't see last week.
If you know in advance the numbers
that you want to assign to an array,
you actually don't have to bother
specifying the size of the array
explicitly.
The compiler can figure that
out intelligently for you.
But you can use these
curly braces with commas
inside to enumerate from
left to right the values
that you want to put into that array.
So after this line 6 has
executed in my computer,
I'm going to be left with
an array called numbers,
inside of which are
seven integers listed
from left to right in the computer's
memory, so to speak, in this way.
Now, what do I want to
do with these numbers?
Well, let's implement linear search.
Linear search, as we
latched on to earlier,
is a searching from left to right
or equivalently right to left--
but convention tends
to go left to right.
So I'm going to do a standard for loop.
For int i gets 0, i is less than--
I'm going to keep it simple
for now and hardcode this,
but we could clean this up if we
want, and I'm going to do i++ on each
iteration.
So I'm pretty sure that my line
8 will induce a for loop that
iterates eight total times.
And what question do I want
to ask on each iteration?
Well, if the numbers array
at location i equals equals--
for instance, the number I
was searching for initially,
let's go ahead and search for 0--
then what do I want to do?
Let me go ahead and print out
something arbitrary but useful,
like "Found," quote,
unquote, so the human knows.
And then let me go ahead, and just
for good measure, let me go ahead
and return 0.
And we'll come back to
that in just a moment.
But at the end of this program, I'm also
going to do this-- printf "Not found"
with a backslash n.
And then I'm going to
go ahead and return 1.
But before we tease
apart those returns, just
consider the code in the aggregate.
Here's my entire main function.
And on line 6, to recap,
I initialized the array,
just as we did at the very beginning,
with a seemingly random list of numbers
behind the doors.
Then on line 8, I'm going to
iterate with this for loop
seven total times,
incrementing i in each turn.
And then line 10, just like I was
opening the doors one at a time,
I'm going to check if the
i-th number in this array
equals equals the number I care
about, 0, with that first demo.
I'm going to print "Found."
Otherwise-- not else,
per se-- but otherwise,
if I go through this entire loop,
checking if, if, if, if, if, and I
never actually find 0, I'm going to
have this catchall at the end that just
says no matter what, if you
reach line 16, print "Not found,"
and then return 1.
Now, this is a bit of a subtlety.
But could someone remind us
what's going on with the return 0
on line 13 and the return 1 on line 17?
Why 0 in 1, and why
am I returning at all?
What problem is this solving for me?
Even though most of
our programs thus far,
we haven't bothered too much with this.
Demi, is it?
What do you think?
AUDIENCE: It's Demi,
but basically, return 0
is like it was executed
correctly, or it found it,
and it kind of exits that
loop saying that it was found.
And then return 1 is like the
return false, and it exits as well.
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
And "exit" really is the operative word.
In main, when you are done--
ready to quit the program,
as we've done with the word
"quit" in some of our pseudocode in the
past, you can literally return a value.
And recall at the end of last
week, we introduced the fact
that main always returns an int.
You and I have ignored that
for at least a week or two,
but sometimes it's useful
to return an explicit value,
whether it's for autograding
purposes, whether it's
for automated testing of
your code in the real world,
or just so it's a signal to the
user that something indeed went
Wrong.
So you can return a value from main.
And as Demi proposed,
0 means "all is well."
And it's a little
counter-intuitive, because
thus far true tends to be a good thing.
But in this case, 0 is a good thing.
All is well.
It's success.
And if you return any other
value, for instance 1,
that indicates that
something went wrong.
So the reason I'm printing out, after
the word "Found" I'm returning 0,
is so that effectively the
program exits at that point.
I don't want to keep going
again and again if I already
found the number I care about.
And down here, this one admittedly
isn't strictly necessary,
because if I hit line 16
and maybe deleted line 17,
the program's going to end anyway.
But there wouldn't be
that so-called exit status
that we discussed last
week briefly, whereby
you can kind of signal to the
computer whether something
was successful or unsuccessful.
And the reason that 0 is a good thing
and 1 or any other number is not,
consider how many things can go
wrong in programs that you write
or that companies in
the real world write
when you get those error
messages, sometimes
with those cryptic error codes.
There are hundreds,
thousands of problems
that might happen in a computer
program that could be that many error
codes that you see on
the screen, reasons
explaining why the program
crashed or froze or the like.
But 0 is sort of special in that it's
just one value that the world has
decided means "success."
So there's only one way to get
your program right, in a sense,
but there's so many millions of
ways in which things can go wrong.
And that's why humans have adopted
that particular convention.
All right.
But let's consider now not just numbers,
but let's make things more interesting.
Besides the doors,
suppose that we actually
had people's names behind them.
Well, let's go ahead and
write a program this time
that not only searches for numbers,
but instead searches for names.
So I'm going to go ahead and create
a different file here called names.c.
And I'm going to start
a little similarly.
I'm going to include cs50.h at the top,
I'm going to include stdio at the top.
But I'm also this time
going to include string.h,
which we introduced
briefly last week, so
that we have access to strlen for
getting the length of a string,
and, it turns out, some other functions.
Let me go ahead and declare
int main void as usual.
And then inside here, I
need some arbitrary names.
So let's come up with seven names here.
And here, too, I can declare
an array just as I did before.
But it doesn't have to store only ints.
It can store strings instead.
So I've changed the data
type from int to string,
and I've changed the variable
name from numbers to names.
And I can still use this
new curly brace notation,
and I can give myself a name like Bill,
and maybe Charlie, and maybe Fred,
and maybe George, and maybe Ginny,
and maybe Percy, and lastly,
maybe a name like Ron.
And it just barely fits on my screen.
So with that said, I now
have this array of names.
And beyond there being a
perhaps obvious pattern to them,
there's a second less obvious, or
maybe obvious, pattern to them.
How would you describe the list of
names I arbitrarily just came up with?
What's a useful characteristic of them?
What do you notice about these names?
And there's at least two right
answers to this question, I think.
What do you notice about these names?
Jack?
AUDIENCE: They're in alphabetical order.
DAVID MALAN: Yes.
So beyond being the names of the
Weasley children in Harry Potter,
they're also in alphabetical order.
And that's the more salient detail.
For our purposes, I've
had the forethought
this time to sort
these names in advance.
And if I've sorted these
names, that means implicitly
I can use a better algorithm
than linear search.
I can use, for instance,
our old binary search.
But let's go ahead first and
just search them naively for now.
Let's still apply linear
search, because, you know,
what we haven't yet done is necessarily
compare strings against one another.
We've done a lot of comparisons
of numbers like integers.
But what about names?
So let me go ahead and do this.
So for int i gets 0, just like
before, i less than 7, i++--
and I'm doing this only because I
know in advance there are seven names.
I think we could probably
improve the design of this code,
too, by having a variable or
a constant storing that value.
But I'm going to keep it simple and
focus only on the new details for now.
And it turns out, for reasons we'll
explore in more detail next week,
it is not sufficient to do what we
did before and do something like this
if I'm searching for "Ron."
It turns out that in C, you can't use
equals equals to compare two strings.
You can for an int, you can for a char.
And we've done both
of those in the past.
But there's a subtlety that we'll dive
into in more detail next week that
means you can't actually do this.
And this is curious, because
if you have prior programming
experience in languages like Python
or the like, you can do this.
So in C you can't, but
we'll see next time why.
But for now, it turns out
that C can solve this problem,
and historically the way you
do this is with a function.
So inside of the string.h
header file, there
is not only a declaration for strlen,
the length of a string like last week.
There's another function called strcmp.
And "stir compare,"
for short, S-T-R-C-M-P,
allows me to pass in two strings, one
string that I want to compare against
another string.
So it's not quite the same syntax.
Indeed, it's a little harder to read.
It's not quite as
simple as equals equals.
But strcmp, if we read
the documentation for it,
will tell us that this
compares two strings.
And it returns one of
three possible values.
If those two strings are equal, that is,
identically the same letter for letter,
then this function is going
to return 0, it turns out.
If the first string is supposed
to come before the second string
alphabetically, in some
sense, then this function
is going to return a negative value.
If the first string is supposed to come
after the second string alphabetically,
if you will, then it's going
to return a positive value.
So there's three possible outcomes--
either equal to 0, or less than 0,
or greater than 0.
But you'll notice, and in fact, if you
look at the documentation some time,
it doesn't specify what value less
than 0 or what value greater than 0.
You have to just check for any
negative value or any positive value.
And I also told a bit of
a white lie a moment ago.
This does not check
things alphabetically,
even though it coincidentally
does sometimes.
Actually compares strings in
what's called ASCII order,
or ASCIIbetically which is kind
of a goofy way of describing
this function looks at every character
in the two strings, from left to right,
it checks the ASCII values of them,
and then it compares those ASCII values
character by character.
And if the ASCII value
is less than the other,
then it returns a negative
value or vice versa.
So if you have, for instance, the
letter A, capital A in the string,
that gets converted first to 65.
And then if you have an A in
the other string capitalized,
it, too, gets compared to
65, and those would be equal.
But of course, all of these names
have more than one character,
so this ASCII order, or
ASCIIbetical, precedes left to right
so that strcmp checks every
character in the names for you.
And it stops when it hits that
terminating null character.
Recall that strings,
underneath the hood,
always end in C with this
backslash 0, or eight 0 bits.
So that's how strcmp knows
when to stop comparing values.
But if I go ahead and find
someone like Ron, let me go ahead
and print out quote, unquote, "Found."
And like before, I'll go ahead
and return, like Demi proposed,
0, just to imply that all is successful.
Otherwise, if we get all the
way to the bottom of my code,
I'm going to print out "Not found"
to tell the story that we did not
find Ron in this array, even
though he does happen to be there,
and I'm going to go ahead and return 1.
So even though I've
hardcoded everything--
to hardcode something in a program
means to type it out explicitly--
you could imagine using a command
line argument like last week
to get user's input.
Who would you like to search for?
You could imagine using get_string
to get user's input and ask them,
who would you like to search for?
But for now, just for demonstration
sake, I've used only Ron's name.
And if I haven't made any typos--
let me go ahead and type in make
names, Enter, so far so good, ./names.
And hopefully, we'll
see, indeed, "Found,"
because "Ron" is very much in
this array of seven siblings.
But the building blocks
that are new here
are, again, the fact that when we
declare an array of some fixed size
we don't strictly need
to put a number here,
and we have this curly
brace notation when we
know the array's contents in advance.
But perhaps lastly and
most powerfully, we
do have this function in C called
strcmp that will allow us to actually
store and compare strings in this way.
So let me pause here
and just ask if there's
any questions about how we translated
these ideas to code for numbers,
and how we translated
these ideas to code for now
names, each time using
linear search, not, binary.
Caleb, question?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So would that program still work if
"Ron," for example, was like all caps,
like if you're trying to search--
like, if the cases are different in
terms of uppercase and lowercase?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
And let me propose an instinct
that's useful to acquire in general--
when in doubt, try it.
So I'm going to do exactly that.
I do happen to know the
answer, but suppose I didn't.
Let me go ahead and change
"Ron" to all caps, just because.
Maybe the human, the
Caps Lock key was on,
and they typed it in a little sloppily.
Let me go ahead and
make no other changes.
Notice that I'm leaving the original
array alone with only a capital R.
Let me remake this program,
make name, ./names.
And voila, he's still, in fact, found.
Stand by.
Oh, OK.
Caleb, you have just helped
me unearth, a bug that
was latent in the previous example.
None of you should
have accepted the fact
that the previous program worked
with "RON," because I didn't
practice literally what I'm preaching.
So Caleb, hold that thought for just
a moment so I can rewind a little bit
and fix my apparent bug.
So "RON" was indeed found.
But he wasn't found
because "RON" was found.
I did something stupid here.
And it's perhaps all the more
pedagogically appropriate
now to highlight that.
So how did this program say "Ron" was
found, even though this time it also
says "RON" was found in all caps?
And you know what, let me
get a little curious here.
Let me go ahead and search
for, not even "Ron."
How about we search
for Ron's mom, "Molly"?
Make names.
All right.
And now, just to reveal that I really
did do something stupid, ./names.
OK, now something's
clearly wrong, right?
I can even search for the father
"Arthur", make names, ./name.
It seems that I wrote you a program
that just literally always says "Found."
So we shouldn't have
accepted this as correct.
Can anyone spot the bug based
on my definition thus far?
Can anyone spot the bug?
In the meantime, this isn't really
a bad time to open up the duck
and say, "Hello, duck.
I am having a problem whereby my
program is always printing Found
even when someone is not in the array.
And I could proceed to
explain my logic to the duck,
but hopefully Sophia can point me at
the solution even faster than the duck.
AUDIENCE: You need to
compare the value that we
received from strcmp with something.
So we need to compare it
with like 0 and make sure
that we receive the
value that they're equal.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So I said the right thing, but I
literally did not do the right thing.
If I want to check for
equality, I literally
need to check the return value
when comparing names bracket i
against "Ron" to equal 0.
Because only in the case when
the return value of strcmp is 0
do I actually have a match.
By contrast, if the function returns
a negative value or the function
returns a positive value,
that means it's not a match.
That means that one name is
supposed to come before the other
or after the other.
But the catch with my shorthand
syntax here, which is not always
an incorrect syntax to use, whenever
you have a Boolean expression inside
of which is a function call like this--
notice that the entirety
of my Boolean expression
is just a call, so to speak, to strcmp.
I'm passing in two inputs, names
bracket i and quote, unquote "Ron."
And therefore, I'm expecting strcmp
to return output, a so-called return
value.
That return value is going to
be negative or positive or 0.
And in fact, to be clear, if
the first name being searched
for is "Bill" and names
bracket i or names bracket 0
is "Bill," "Bill" comma
"Ron" is effectively what
my input is on the first iteration.
"Bill," alphabetically
and ASCIIbetically,
comes before "Ron,"
which means it should
be returning a negative value to me.
And the problem with Boolean expressions
is, as implemented in this context,
is that only 0 is false.
Any other return value is by
definition true or a Yes answer,
whether it's negative 1 or
positive 1, negative 1 million
or positive 1 million--
any non-zero value in a
computer language like C
is considered true,
also known as truthy.
Any value that is 0 is
considered false, but only
that value is considered false.
So really, I was getting lucky at first,
because my program was finding "Bill,"
but I was confusing "Bill" for "Ron."
Then when I did it again for
Caleb and I capitalized "Ron,"
I was getting unlucky,
because suddenly I
knew "RON" capitalized
wasn't in the array,
and yet I'm still saying he's found.
But that's because I didn't practice
what I preach per Sophia's find.
And so if I actually compare
this against 0-- and now, Caleb,
we come full circle to your question--
I rebuild this program with make names,
I now do ./names and search for all
caps "RON," I should now
see, thankfully, "Not found."
So I wish I could say that
was deliberate, but thus
is the common case of bugs.
So here I am 20 years later
making bugs in my code.
So if you run up to a
similar problem this week,
rest assured that it never ends.
But hopefully you won't have
several people watching you
while you do your problem set this week.
All right.
Any questions, then, beyond Caleb's?
So great question, Caleb,
and the answer is no.
It is case sensitive.
So it does not find "Rob"--
"RON."
Any questions here?
Any questions on linear
search using strings?
No?
All right, well, let's go ahead
and do one final example, I think,
with searching.
But let's introduce
just one other feature.
And this one's actually
pretty cool and powerful.
Up until now, we've been using
data types that just come with C
or come from CS50, like int, and
char, and float, and the like.
And you'll see now that
there's actually sometimes
reasons where you or I might want
to create our own custom data types,
our own types that didn't exist
when C itself was invented.
So for instance, suppose that
I wanted to represent not just
a whole bunch of numbers and
not just a whole bunch of names,
but suppose I want to implement
like a full-fledged phone book.
A phone book, of course,
contains both names and numbers.
And suppose I want to combine
these two ideas together.
Wouldn't it be nice if I could
have a data structure that
is a data type that has some
structure to it that can actually
store both at once?
And in fact, wouldn't it be nice
if C had a data type called person,
so that if I want to represent a
person, like in a phone book, who
had both a name and a
number, I can actually
implement that and code by calling
that variable of type person?
Now, of course, the designers
of C did not have the foresight
to create a data type called person.
And, indeed, that would
be a slippery slope
if they had a data type for every
real-world entity you can think of.
But they did give us the
capabilities to do this.
So if a person, in our limited
world here of phone books,
has both a name and a number, we
might think of it as follows--
a name and a number,
both of type string.
But a quick check here.
Why have I now decided,
somewhat presumptuously,
to call phone numbers strings as well?
We've been talking about
ints behind these doors.
We've been searching for ints in code.
But why did I just presume
to propose that we instead
implement a phone book using
strings for names and numbers?
Any thoughts here, Kurt?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
Because we're not doing math on it.
It's like-- a phone number could
be, like, letters for all we care.
And in fact, I mean,
sometimes you see, like,
1-800 Contacts or something like
that, and maybe we want to allow that.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, absolutely.
A phone number, despite its name,
isn't necessarily just a number.
It might be 1-800 Contacts,
which is an English word.
It might have hyphens in it or dashes.
It might have parentheses in it.
It might have a plus
sign for country codes.
There's a lot of characters
that we absolutely
can represent in C using strings that
we couldn't represent in C using int.
And so indeed, even
though in the real world
there are these "numbers" that you and
I talk about once in a while like phone
numbers, maybe in the US Social
Security numbers, credit card numbers,
those aren't necessarily values that
you want to treat as actual integers.
And in fact, those of you
who did the credit problem
and tried to validate
credit card numbers
may very well have run into challenges
by using a long to represent a credit
card number.
It probably in retrospect
might very well
have been easier for you to treat
credit card numbers as strings.
The catch, of course, by
design is that you didn't yet
have strings in your
vocabulary, at least in C yet.
So suppose I want to
create my own custom data
type that encapsulates, if you
will, two different types of values.
A person shall be henceforth
a name and a number.
It turns out that C gives
us this syntax here.
This is the only juicy piece of new
syntax besides those curly braces
a moment ago that we'll
see today in C, typedef.
And as the name rather
succinctly suggests,
this allows you to define a type.
And the type will be a
structure of some sort.
So a data structure in
a programming language
is typically a data type that
has some structure to it.
What do we mean by "structure"?
It typically has one or
more values inside of it.
So using typedef, and in turn
using the struct keyword,
we can create our own
custom types that's
a structure, a composition
of multiple other data types.
So if we want to keep persons together
as their own custom data type,
the syntax is a little cryptic here.
You literally do typedef
struct open curly brace,
then one per line you specify
the data types that you want
and the names that you want
to give to those data types,
for instance name and number.
And then outside of the
closing curly brace,
you literally put the word "person,"
if that's indeed the data type
that you want to invent.
So how can we use this more powerfully?
Well, let's go ahead and do things the
wrong way without this feature first,
so as to motivate its existence.
Let me go ahead and save
this file as phonebook.c.
And let me start, as always,
with includes cs50.h.
And then let me go ahead
and include stdio.h.
And then lastly, let me
also include string.h,
because I know I'm going to be
manipulating some strings in a moment.
Let me go ahead now, and within
my main function, let me go ahead
and give myself initially, for
the first version of this program,
a whole bunch of names.
Specifically, how about
"Brian" comma "David"?
We'll keep it short, just so as to focus
on the ideas and not the actual data
they're in.
Then Brian and I each
have phone numbers.
So let's go ahead and
store them in an array--
numbers equals, again the curly braces
as before, and +1-617-495-1000--
and indeed, there's already motivation,
per Kurt's comment, to use strings,
because we've got a plus and
a couple of dashes in there--
and then my number here.
So we'll do +1-949-468-2750
close curly brace, semicolon.
So I've gone ahead and declared
two arrays, one called names,
one called numbers.
And I'm just going to have
sort of a handshake agreement
that the first name in names corresponds
to the first number in numbers,
the second name in names corresponds
to the second number in numbers.
And you can imagine that working well
so long as you don't make any mistakes,
and you have just the
right number in each.
Now let me go ahead and do int
i equals 0, i less than 2--
I'm going to keep that hardcoded for
now just to do the demonstration.
And then inside of this loop, let me go
ahead and search for my phone number,
for instance, even though
I happen to be at the end.
So if strcmp of names bracket i equals--
rather, comma "David" equals equals 0--
so I'm not going to
make that mistake again.
Let me go ahead inside of this
loop, inside of this condition here.
And I'm going to go ahead and do the
following-- print out that I found,
for instance my number.
And I'm going to plug that in.
So numbers bracket i.
And then as before, I'm going
to go ahead and return 0.
And if none of this works out, and
I happen not to be in this array,
I'll go ahead and print out as
before "Not found" with a semicolon.
And then I'll return 1 arbitrarily.
I can return negative 1, I could
return a million, negative million.
But human convention would typically
have you go from 0 to 1 to 2 to 3
on up, if you have that many
possible error conditions.
All right.
So I essentially have implemented
in C a phone book of sorts.
We did this verbally in week 0.
Now I'm doing it in code.
It's a limited phone book.
It's only got two names and two numbers.
But I could certainly
implement this phone book
by just using two arrays, two
parallel arrays, if you will,
by just using the honor system that
the first element and names lines
up with the first elements
and numbers and so forth.
Now hopefully, if I
don't make any typos,
let me go ahead and make phonebook.
All right.
It compiled OK. ./phonebook, and it
found what seems to be my number there.
So it seems to work correctly, though
I've tried to pull that one over you
before.
But I'm pretty sure this one
actually works correctly.
And so we found my name
and in turn number.
But why is the design of this
code not necessarily the best?
This is starting to get
more subtle, admittedly.
And we've seen that we
can do this differently.
But what rubs you the
wrong way about here?
This is another example of what
we might call "code smell."
Like, something's a little
funky here, like, ah, this
might not be the best solution
long term Nick, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
So what I'm guessing is that--
like, you know how you made the data
frame before the new data structure,
where the two things
were linked together?
In this case, we're
just banking on the fact
that we don't screw something up
and unintentionally unlink them
from the same index.
So they're not intrinsically
linked, which might not be--
DAVID MALAN: That's
exactly the right instinct.
In general, as great as a programmer
as you're maybe aspiring to be,
you're not all that.
And like, you're going to make mistakes.
And the more you can write
code that's self-defensive,
that protects you from yourself,
the better off you're going to be,
the more correct your
code is going to be,
and the more easily you're going to
be able to collaborate successfully,
if you so choose in the real world,
on real-world programming projects,
whether for a research project, a
full-time job, a personal project
or the like.
Generally speaking, you should
not trust yourself or other people
that-- with whom you're
writing code, you
should have as many defense mechanisms
in place exactly along these lines.
So yes, there's nothing wrong
with what I have done in the sense
that this is correct.
But as noted, if you screw up, and
maybe you get an off by one error--
maybe you transpose two
names or two numbers.
I mean, imagine if you've got
dozens of names and numbers,
hundreds of names and
numbers, thousands of them
the odds that you or someone
messes the order up at some point
is just probably going
to be too, too high.
So it would be nice, then, if we could
sort of keep related data together.
This is kind of a hack, to just on the
honor system say, my arrays line up,
I'm just going to make sure
to keep them the same length.
We can do better.
Let's keep related data together and
design this a little more cleanly.
And I can do this by
defining my own type
that I'll call for instance, a person.
So at the top of this
file, before main, I'm
going to go ahead and
typedef a structure, inside
of which are the two types
of data that I care about,
string name and string
number, just as before.
Notice, though, here that what I have
done here is not give myself an array.
I've given myself one
name and one number.
Outside of this curly brace,
I'm going to give this data type
a name, which I could call "person."
I could call it anything
I want, but person
seems pretty reasonable in this case.
And now down here, I'm going to go
ahead and change this code a little bit.
I'm going to go ahead and
give myself an array still,
but this time I'm going to give
myself an array of persons.
And I'm going to call that array,
somewhat playfully, "people,"
because I want to have two persons, two
people, in this program, me and Brian.
Now I want to go ahead
and populate this array.
That is, I want to fill it with values.
And this syntax is a
little new, but it's just
to enable us to actually store
values inside of a structure.
If I want to index into
this array, there's
nothing different from last week.
I do people bracket 0.
That's going to give me the first person
variable inside, so probably where
"Brian" is supposed to go.
The one last piece of
syntax I need is how do I
go inside of that structure,
that person data structure,
and access the person's name?
I literally just do a dot.
So people bracket 0 gives me the
first person in the people array.
And then the dot means, go inside
of it and grab the person variable.
I'm going to go ahead and set that
name equal to quote, unquote "Brian."
The syntax now for his
name is almost identical--
people bracket 0 dot number equals
quote, unquote "+1-617-495-1000"
semicolon.
Meanwhile, if I want to
access a location for myself,
I'm going to go ahead and
put it at location 1, which
is the second location.
Name will be, quote, unquote "David."
And then over here, I'm going to do
people bracket 1 dot number equals
quote, unquote "+1-949-468-2750"
close quote, semicolon.
So it's a bit verbose, admittedly.
But you could imagine, if we just let
our thoughts run ahead of ourselves
here, if you used get_string, could
sort of automatically do this.
If you used command line arguments,
maybe you could populate some of this.
We don't just have to hardcode,
that is, write my name and number
and Brian's into this program.
You can imagine doing
this more dynamically
using some of our techniques, using
get_string and so forth, from week 1.
But for now, it's just
for demonstration's sake.
So now if I want to search this new
array, this new single array of people,
I think my for loop can stay the same.
And I think I can still use strcmp.
But now I need to go inside
of not names but people,
and look for the dot name field.
So data structures have fields
or variables inside of them.
So I'm going to use
the dot notation there,
too, go into the i-th
person in the people array,
and compare that name against, for
instance, quote, unquote "David."
And then if I have found
"David," in this case myself,
go ahead and access the people array
again, but print out using printf
the number.
So again, the dot operator is
the only new piece of syntax
that's letting us go inside of this
new feature known as a data structure.
If I go ahead and make phonebook
again after making those changes,
all is well.
It compiled OK.
And if I run ./phonebook, I now have
hopefully found my number again.
So here is a seemingly
useless exercise, in that all
I really did was re-implement the
same program using more lines of code
and making it more complicated.
But it's now better designed.
Or it's a step toward being
better designed, because now I've
encapsulated all inside of one variable,
for instance, people bracket 0,
people bracket 1, all of the information
we care about with respect to Brian,
or me, or anyone else we
might put into this program.
And indeed, this is how programs,
this is how Googles, of the world,
Facebooks of the world store
lots of information together.
Consider any of your social
media accounts like Instagram,
or Facebook, or Snapchat and the like.
You have multiple pieces
of data associated
with you on all of those
platforms-- not just your username
but also your password,
also your history of posts,
also your friends and
followers and the like.
So there's a lot of information that
these companies, for better for worse,
are collecting on all of us.
And can you imagine if they just had
one big array with all of our usernames,
one big array with all of our passwords,
one big array with all of our friends?
Like, you can imagine
certainly at scale,
that's got to be a bad
design, to just trust
that you're going to get the ordering
of all of these things right.
They don't do that.
They instead write code in some
language that somehow encapsulates
all the information
related to me and Brian
and you inside of some
kind of data structure.
And that's what they put in their
database or some other server
on their back end.
So this encapsulation is a
feature we now have in terms of C.
And it allows us to create our own
data structures that we can then use
in order to keep related data together.
All right, any questions, then,
on data structures, or more
specifically typedef and
struct, the C keywords
with which you can create
your own custom types
that themselves are data structures?
Besley?
AUDIENCE: Hi.
So is it typical to define the new
data structure outside of main, like
in a header?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
Is it typical to define a new
data structure outside of main?
Quite often yes.
In this case, it's immaterial,
because I only have
one function in this program, main.
But as we'll see this week
and next week and onward,
our programs are going to start to get
a little more complicated by nature
of just having more features.
And once you have more features,
you probably have more functions.
And when you have more functions,
you want your data structure
to be available to all
of those functions.
And so we'll begin to see definition
of some of these structures being,
indeed, outside of our own functions.
Peter, over to you.
AUDIENCE: Oh, yeah.
Will we define new classes
in header files later,
or will we keep defining
them outside of main?
DAVID MALAN: Really good question.
Might we define our own types and our
own data structures in header files?
Yes.
Eventually we'll do that, too.
Thus far, you and I have only been using
header files that other people wrote.
We've been using stdio.h, string.h,
that the authors of C created.
You've been using cs50.h
which we the staff wrote.
It turns out, you can also create your
own header files, your own .h files,
inside of which are pieces of code that
you want to share across multiple files
of your own.
We're not quite there yet.
But yes, Peter, that would
be a solution to this problem
by putting it in one central place.
Thiago, over to you.
AUDIENCE: I was--
I was thinking, this course really takes
enough information to solve the sets,
because I feel there
is missing information.
I am a freshman, and I was taking--
I was so concentrating, and I
can't go on, go ahead on the sets.
Is there anything that I'm missing?
DAVID MALAN: It's a
really good question.
And quite fair.
We do move quite quickly, admittedly.
So indeed, recall from week
0 the fire hose metaphor
that I borrowed from
MIT's water fountain.
Indeed, that's very much the case.
There's a lot of new syntax, a
lot of new ideas all at once.
But when it comes to individual
problems in the problem sets,
do realize that you should
take those step by step.
And invariably, they tend to work from
less complicated to more complicated.
And throughout each of the
lectures and each of the examples
that we do, either live
or via the examples that
are premade on the course's
website for your review,
there's always little clues or hints
or examples that you can then do.
And certainly, by way of other
resources like labs and the like,
will you see additional
building blocks as well.
So feel free to reach out
more individually afterword.
Happy to point you at
some of those resources.
In fact, most recently, too, will
you notice on the course's website
what we call "shorts," which
are shorter videos made
by another colleague of mine, CS50's
own Doug Lloyd, which are literally
short videos on very specific topics.
So after today, you'll
see short videos by Doug
with a different perspective on
linear search, on binary search,
and on a number of other
algorithms as well.
Good question.
Sophia, back to you.
AUDIENCE: I was wondering,
with the return values
that we have for different
error cases, would that be--
like, what's an example of
what we would use that for?
Is that for later if there are
like several different cases
and we want to somehow
keep track of them?
DAVID MALAN: Exactly the latter.
So right now, honestly,
it's kind of stupid
that we're even bothering to spend
time returning 0 or returning 1.
Like, we don't really need
to do that, because we're not
using the information.
But what we're trying to
do is lay the foundation
for more complicated programs.
And indeed, this week
and next week and beyond,
as your own programs get a little
longer, and as we, the course,
start providing you with
starter code or distribution
code, that is, lines of code that
the staff and I write that you then
have to build upon, it's going
to be a very useful mechanism
to be able to signal that this went
wrong or this other thing went wrong.
So all we're doing is preparing
for that inevitability,
even if right now it doesn't really
seem to be scratching an itch.
Anthony?
AUDIENCE: I was just going
to ask really quickly,
obviously in this code we have
"Brian" and your name, "David."
And that's two people.
So let's say we had 10
or 20 or even 30 people.
I know it was a question
in the chat, but I just
wanted to clarify for myself, too.
DAVID MALAN: And the "what
if" being what would change?
Or, what was the end of that question?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
What would change in the code?
Or what we do exactly
to address that problem?
DAVID MALAN: Ah, OK.
Good question.
So if we were to have more names, like a
third name or a tenth name or the like,
the only things that we would have to
change in this version of the program
is first, on line 14,
the size of the array.
So if we're going to
have 10 people, we need
to decide in advance that
we're going to have 10 people.
Better still, I could, for instance,
allocate myself a constant up here.
So let me actually go
up here, just like we
did in a previous class, where we did
something like this-- const int NUMBER.
And I'll just initialize this to 10.
And recall that const means constant.
That means this variable can't change.
Int, of course means it's an integer.
The fact that I've capitalized
it is just a human convention
to make a little visually
clear that this is
a constant, just so you don't forget.
But it has no functional role.
And then this, of course, is just
the value to assign to NUMBER.
Then I could go down here on
line 16 and plug in that variable
so that I don't have to
hardcode what people would
call a "magic number,"
which is just a number that
appears seemingly out of nowhere.
Now I've put all of my special
numbers at the top of my file,
or toward the top of my file, and
now I'm using this variable here.
And then what I could do-- and I
alluded to this only verbally before--
I could absolutely start
hardcoding in, for instance,
Montague's name and number, and
Rithvik's and Benedict's, and Cody's
and others.
But honestly, this seems kind of
stupid if you're just hardcoding
all of these names and numbers.
And in a few weeks, we'll
see how you can actually
store all of the same information
in like a spreadsheet,
or what's called a CSV file--
Comma Separated Values-- or even in a
proper database, which the Facebooks
and Googles of the world would use.
But what I could do for
now is something like this.
For int i gets 0, i less than
the number of people, i++.
And maybe I could do
something like this--
people bracket i dot name equals
get_string, "What's the name"
question mark.
And then here I could do people
bracket i dot number equals
get_string, "What's their number?"
And I could ask that question, too.
So now the program's getting
to be a little better designed.
I'm not arbitrarily
hardcoding just me and Brian.
Now it's dynamic.
And technically, the phone book only
supports 10 people at the moment,
but I could make that dynamic, too.
I could also call get_int.
Or, like you did this past week,
use a command line argument
and parameterize the code
so that it can actually
be for 2 people, 10
people-- whatever you want,
the program can dynamically
adapt to it for you.
Other questions?
On structs, on types, or the like?
No?
All right.
So how did we get here?
Recall that we started with
this problem of searching,
whereby we just want to
find someone in the doors.
We just want to find
someone in the array.
We've sort of escalated
things pretty quickly
to finding not just
numbers or names but now
names with numbers in the
form of these data structures.
But to do this efficiently really
requires a smarter algorithm
like binary search.
Up until now, we've only used in C code
linear search, even though, recall,
that we did have at our disposal
the pseudocode for binary search.
But with binary search, we're going
to need the data to be sorted.
And so if you want to get the
speed benefits of searching
more quickly by having sorted
numbers, somehow someone
is going to have to do that for us.
Joe, for instance, sorted behind the
curtain all of these numbers for us.
But what algorithm did he
use is going to open up
a whole can of worms as to how
we can sort numbers efficiently.
And indeed, if you're the
Googles and the Facebooks
and the Instagrams of
the world, with millions,
billions of pieces of
data and users, you surely
want to keep that data
sorted, presumably,
so that you can use
algorithms like binary search
to find information quickly when you're
searching for friends or for content.
But let's go ahead and here
take a five-minute break.
And when we come back, we'll
consider a few algorithms
for sorting that's going to enable us to
do everything we've just now discussed.
See you in five.
All right.
We are back.
So to recap, we have a couple different
algorithms for searching, linear search
and binary search.
Binary search is clearly the winner
from all measures we've seen thus far.
The catch is that the data needs
to be sorted in advanced in order
to apply that algorithm.
So let's just give
ourselves a working model
for what it means to sort something.
Well, as always, if you think of this
as just another problem to be solved,
it's got input and output, and
the goal is to take that input
and produce that output.
Well, what's the input?
It's going to be a whole
bunch of unsorted values.
And the goal, of course,
is to get sorted values.
So the interesting part
of the process is going
to be whatever there is in the middle.
But just to be even more concrete, if
we think now in terms of this unsorted
input as being an array of
input-- because after all,
that's perhaps the most useful
mechanism we've seen thus far,
to pass around a bunch of values at
once using just one variable name--
we might have an array like this, 6 3
8 5 2 7 4 1, which seems to be, indeed,
randomly ordered, that is unsorted.
And we want to turn that into an
equivalent array that's just 1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8.
So eight numbers this
time instead of seven.
But the goal this time is not to
search them, per se, but to sort them.
But before I get ahead
of myself, could someone
push back on this whole
intellectual exercise
we're about to do with
sorting in the first place?
Could someone make an argument
as to why we might not
want to bother using a sorted
array, why we might not
want to bother sorting the elements,
and heck, let's just use linear search
to find some element--
whether it's a number behind
a door, a name in an array.
Like, when might we want to just use
linear search and not bother sorting?
Sophia, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: We could
encounter errors in sorting,
and that might cause errors, like,
unpredictability in terms of,
like, if we can find something.
Versus linear search,
we know we can find it.
DAVID MALAN: OK, quite fair.
I will concede that implementing binary
search, not in pseudocode, which we've
already done, but in code
is actually more difficult,
because you have to deal
with rounding, especially
if you've got a weird number of
doors, like an odd number of doors
versus an even number of doors
or an array of those lengths.
Honestly, you've got to deal
with these corner cases,
like rounding down or rounding
up, because anything time
you divide something by 2, you
might get a fractional value
or you might get a whole number.
So we've got to make some decisions.
So it's totally solvable.
And humans for decades have been writing
code that implements binary search.
It's totally possible.
There's libraries you can use.
But it's definitely more challenging,
and you open yourselves up to risk.
But let me stipulate that that's OK.
I am good enough at this point in
my progression where I'm pretty
sure I can implement it correctly.
So correctness is not my concern.
What else might demotivate me
from sorting an array of elements?
And what might motivate me to,
ah, just use linear search.
It's so simple.
Can anyone propose why?
Olivia, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: If the name of
the game is efficiency,
and you have a small
enough data set, then
you might as well just
search it versus sort
it, which would be an extra expense.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, really well said.
If you've got a
relatively small data set,
and your computer operates at a
billion operations per second,
for instance, my God, who cares if your
code sucks and it's a little bit slow?
Just do it the inefficient way.
Why?
Because it's going to take you maybe
a few minutes to implement the simpler
algorithm like linear search, even
though it's going to take longer
to run, whereas it might take you
tens of minutes, maybe an hour
or so, to not only write
but debug something
like a fancier algorithm, like
binary search, at which point
you might have spent more time writing
the code, the faster code, than you
would have just running the slower code.
And I can speak to this personally.
Back in grad school, some
of the research I was doing
involved analysis of
very large data sets.
And I had to write code in
order to analyze this data.
And I could have spent
hours, days, even,
writing the best designed
algorithm I could to analyze
the data as efficiently as possible.
Or, frankly, I could write the
crappy version of the code,
go to sleep for eight
hours, and my code will just
produce the output I want by morning.
And that is a very real-world,
reasonable trade-off to make.
And indeed, this is going to
be thematic in the weeks that
proceed in the course, where
there's going to be this trade-off.
And quite often, the
trade-off is going to be
time, or complexity, or the amount
of space or memory that you're using.
And part of the art of being
a good computer scientist,
and in turn programmer, is trying
to decide where the line is.
Do you exert more effort upfront to
make a better, faster, more efficient
algorithm, or do you
maybe cut some corners
there so that you can focus your
most precious resource, human time,
on other, more fundamentally
challenging problems?
So we for the course's
problem sets and labs
will always prescribe
what's most important.
But in a few weeks' time,
with one of our problem
sets will you implement
your very own spell checker.
And among the goals
of that spell checker
are going to be to
minimize the amount of time
your code is taking to run, and also to
minimize the amount of space or memory
that your program is
taking while running.
And so we'll begin to appreciate
those trade-offs ever more.
But indeed, it's the case-- and I
really like Olivia's formulation of it--
if your data set is pretty
small, it's probably not worth
writing the fastest, best
designed algorithm as possible.
Just write it the simple
way, the correct way,
and get the answer quickly, and move on.
But that's not going to be the case
for a lot of problems, dare I say,
most problems in life.
If you're building Facebook
or Instagram or Whatsapp,
or any of today's most popular services
that are getting thousands, millions
of new pieces of data at
a time, you can't just
linearly search all of your friends or
connections on LinkedIn efficiently.
You can't just linearly search
the billions of web pages
that Google and Microsoft
index in their search engines.
You've got to be smarter about it.
And undoubtedly, the more
successful your programs are
and your code are, or websites,
your apps, whatever the case may be,
the more important design
does come into play.
So indeed, let's stipulate now that the
goal is not to search these doors once;
the goal is not to search
these light bulbs once;
the goal is not to search the
phone book once, but rather again
and again and again.
And if that's going to be
the case, then we probably
should spend a little more time and
a little more complexity upfront
getting our code, not only
right but also efficient,
so that we can benefit from
that efficiency again and again
and again, over time.
So how might we go about
sorting some numbers.
So in fact, let me see, to
do this, if we can maybe
get a hand from Brian in back.
Brian, do you mind helping with sorting?
BRIAN: Yeah, absolutely.
So I've got eight numbers here right now
that all seem to be in unsorted order.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
And Brian, could you go ahead, and could
you sort these eight numbers for us?
BRIAN: Yeah, I'll put them in order.
So we'll take these and--
um-- and all right.
I think these are now in sorted order.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, indeed.
I agree.
And now let's take some critique
from the audience, some observations.
Would someone mind explaining how
Brian just sorted those eight numbers?
What did Brian just do, step by step,
in order to get to that end result?
The input was unsorted,
the output now is sorted.
So what did he do?
Peter, what did you see happen?
AUDIENCE: He went through
them step by step.
And if they were in increasing
order, he flipped them,
and kept doing it until they were
all in the correct [INAUDIBLE]..
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
He kept step by step kind
of looking for small values
and moving them to the left,
and looking for big values
and moving them to the right,
so effectively selecting
numbers one at a time and
putting it into its right place.
So let's see this is, maybe in more
slow motion, if you will, Brian.
And if you could be a
little more pedantic
and explain exactly what you're doing.
I see you've already reset the numbers
to their original, unsorted order.
Why don't we go ahead and start
a little more methodically?
And could you go ahead and
for us, more slowly this time,
select the smallest value.
Because I do think,
per Peter, it's going
to need to end up at the far left.
BRIAN: Yeah, sure.
So I'm looking at the numbers,
and the 1 is the smallest.
So I now have the smallest value.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So you did that really quickly.
But I feel like you took
the liberty of being
a human who can kind of have this bird's
eye view of everything all at once.
But be a little more
computer-like, if you could.
And if these eight numbers
are technically in an array,
kind of like my seven
doors out here, such
that you can only look at one number at
a time, can you be even more methodical
and deliberate this time in telling
us how you found the smallest
number to put into place?
BRIAN: Sure.
I guess, since the computer can
only look at one number at a time,
I would start at the
left side of this array
and work my way through the right,
looking at each number one at a time.
So I might start with the 6
and say, OK, this right now
is the smallest number
I've looked at so far.
But then I look at the next number, and
it's a 3, and that's smaller than a 6.
So now the 3, that's the
smallest number I found so far.
So I'll remember that and keep looking.
The 8 is bigger than the 3, so I
don't need to worry about that.
The 5 is bigger than the 3.
The 2 is smaller than
the 3, so that now is
the smallest number I've found so far.
But I'm not done yet.
So I'll keep looking.
The 7 is bigger than the 2,
the 4 is bigger than the 2.
But the 1 is smaller than the 2.
So now I've made my way all the
way to the end of the array.
And 1, I can say, is the
smallest number that I found.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So what I'm hearing is you're
doing all of these comparisons,
also similar to what Peter
implied, and you keep checking,
is this smaller, is this
smaller, is this smaller,
and you're keeping track of the
currently smallest number you've seen?
BRIAN: Yeah, that sounds about right.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So you found it.
And I think it belongs at the beginning.
So how do we put this into place now?
BRIAN: Yeah, so I want to
put it at the beginning.
There's not really space for it.
So I could make space for it, just
by shifting these numbers over.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Wait, wait.
But I feel like you're just-- now
you're doubling the amount of work.
I feel like-- don't do all that.
That feels like you're going
to do more steps than we need.
What else could we do here?
BRIAN: OK.
So the other option is, it
needs to go in this spot,
like this first spot in the array.
So I could just put it there.
But if I do that, I'm going to have
to take the 6 which is there right now
and pull the 6 out.
DAVID MALAN: All right,
but I think that's--
BRIAN: So the 1 is in the
right place, but the 6 isn't.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I agree.
But I think that's OK, right?
Because these numbers started randomly,
and so the 6 is in the wrong place
anyway.
I don't think we're making the problem
any worse by just moving it elsewhere.
And indeed, it's a lot faster, I
would think, to just swap two numbers,
move one to the other
and vice versa, then
shift all of those numbers in between.
BRIAN: Yeah.
So I took the 1 out of the
position at the very end
of the array, all the way
on the right-hand side.
So I guess I could take the
6 and just put it there,
because that's where there's an
open space to put the number.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
And it's not exactly in the right
space, but again, it's no worse off.
So I like that.
All right.
But now, the fact that the 1 is
in the right place-- and indeed,
you've illuminated it
to indicate as much--
I feel like we can pretty
much ignore the 1 henceforth
and now just select the
next smallest element.
So can you walk us through that?
BRIAN: Yeah, so I guess I'd
repeat the same process.
I'd start with the 3.
That's the smallest
number I've found so far.
And I keep looking.
The 8 is bigger than the 3,
the 5 is bigger than the 3.
The 2 is smaller than the 3.
So I'll remember that 2.
That's the smallest
thing I've seen so far.
And then I just need to check to see
if there's anything smaller than the 2.
And I look at the 7, the 4, and the 6.
None of those are smaller than the 2.
So the 2, I can say is the next
smallest number for the array.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
And where would you put that then?
BRIAN: That needs to
go in the second spot.
So I need to pull the 3 out.
And I guess I can take the 3 and just
put it into this open spot, where
there's available space.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
And I feel like it's
starting to become clear
that we're inside some kind of
loop, because you pretty much told
the same story again but
with a different number.
Do you mind just continuing
the algorithm to the end
and select the next smallest,
next smallest, next smallest,
and get that sorted?
BRIAN: Sure.
So we got the 8.
5 is smaller than that,
3 is smaller than that.
And then the rest of
the number is 7, 4, 6.
Those are all bigger.
So the 3, that's going to go
into sorted position here.
And I'll take the 8 and swap it.
Now I'm going to look at the 5.
8 and 7 are both bigger.
The 4 is smaller than the
5, but the 6 is bigger.
So the 4, that's the smallest
number I've seen so far.
So the 4, that's going to go into
place, and I'll swap it with the 5.
And now I've got the 8.
The 7 is smaller than the
8, so I'll remember that.
5 is smaller than that.
The 6 is bigger.
So the 5, that's going
to be the next number.
And now I'm left with 7.
8 is bigger, so 7 is still
the smallest I've seen.
But 6 is smaller, so 6 goes next.
And now I'm down to the last two.
And between the last two, the
8 and the 7, the 7 is smaller.
So the 7 is going to go in this spot.
And at this point, I've
only got one number left.
So that number must
be in sorted position.
And now I would say that this
is a sorted array of numbers.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
So it definitely seems to be correct.
It felt a little slow.
But of course, the computer
could do this much faster
than we, using an actual array.
And if you don't mind my
making an observation,
it looks like if we have eight numbers
to begin with, or n more generally,
it looks like you essentially
did n minus 1 comparisons,
because you kept comparing numbers
again-- actually, did n comparisons.
You looked at the first
number, and then you
compared it again and again and again
at all of the other possible values
in order to find the smallest element.
BRIAN: Yeah.
Because for each of the numbers in the
array, I had to do a comparison to see,
is it smaller than the smallest
thing that I've seen so far?
And if it is smaller, than
I needed to remember that.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So in each pass you considered every
number, so a total of n numbers first.
And so you found the number
1 you put it in its place,
and that left you to be clear
with n minus 1 numbers thereafter.
And then after that, n minus 2
numbers, n minus 3 numbers, dot,
dot, dot, all the way
down to one final number.
So I think this is correct.
And I think that's a
pretty deliberate way
of sorting these elements, a little more
deliberately than your first approach,
Brian, which I might describe
as a little more organic.
You kind of did it like--
more like a human, just kind of
eyeballing things and moving things
around.
But if we were to
translate this into code,
recall that we have
to be ever so precise.
And so let me consider altogether how
exactly we might translate what Brian
did ultimately to, again, pseudocode.
So what he did is actually
an algorithm that has a name.
It's called selection sort.
Why?
Well, it's sorting the
elements ultimately.
And it's doing so by having
Brian, or really the computer,
select the smallest elements
again and again and again.
And once you found each
such small element,
you get the added benefit
of just ignoring it.
Indeed, every time
Brian lit up a number,
he didn't need to keep comparing it,
so the amount of work he was doing
was decreasing each iteration--
n numbers, then n minus 1,
then n minus 2, n minus 3, and so forth.
And so we can think about the
running time of this algorithm
as being manifest in
its actual pseudocode.
So how might we define the pseudocode?
Well, let me propose that
we think of it like this--
for i from 0 to n minus 1.
Now, undoubtedly this is
probably the most cryptic
looking line of the three lines
of pseudocode on the screen.
But again, this is
the kind of thing that
should become rote memory over
time, or just instincts with code.
We've seen in C how you
can write a for loop.
For loops typically, by
convention, start counting at 0.
But if you have n elements, you
don't want to count up through n.
You want to count up to n or
equivalently up through n minus 1,
so from 0 to n minus 1.
All right.
Now what do I want to do on the next--
on the first iteration?
Find the smallest item between
the i-th item and the last item.
So this is not quite obvious,
I think, at first glance.
But I do think it's a fair
characterization of what Brian did.
Because if i is initialized to
0, that was like Brian pointing
his left hand at the first number
on the very left of the shelf.
And what he then did was he found the
smallest element between the i-th item,
the first item 0, and the last item.
So that's kind of a very
fancy way of saying,
Brian, find the smallest
elements among all n elements.
Then what he did was swapped the
smallest item with the i-th item.
So he just did that
switcheroo, so as to not have
to waste time shifting everything over.
He instead just made room
for it by swapping it
with the value that
was in its wrong place.
But now in the next iteration of this
loop, consider how a for loop works.
You do an i++ implicitly in pseudocode.
That's what's happening here.
So now i equals 1.
Find the smallest item between
the i-th item, item 1 0 indexed,
and the last item.
So this is a fancy way of saying,
Brian, check all of the n elements
again, except for the
first, because now you're
starting at location 1
instead of location 0.
And now the algorithm proceeds.
So you could write this
code in different ways
in English like
pseudocode, but this seems
to be a reasonable formulation
of exactly that algorithm.
But let's see it a
little more visually now,
without all of the switching around of
the humans moving around the numbers.
Let me go ahead and
use this visualization.
And we'll put a link
on the course's website
if you'd like to play with this as well.
This is just someone's visualization
of an array of numbers.
But this time, rather than represent
the numbers as symbols, decimal digits,
now this person is using
vertical bars, like a bar chart.
And what this means is that a
small bar is like a small number,
and a big bar is a big number.
So the goal here is to these bars, which
equivalently might as well be numbers,
from short bars over to
tall bars, left to right.
And I'm going to go ahead.
And along the top of the here, I
can choose my sorting algorithm.
And the one we just described,
recall, was selection sort.
So let me go ahead and do this.
And notice, it takes a moment,
I think, to wrap your mind
around what's happening here.
But notice that this pink line is going
from left to right, because that's
essentially what Brian was doing.
He was walking back and forth,
back and forth, back and forth
through that shelf of numbers,
looking for the next smallest number,
and he kept putting the smallest number
over on the left where it belongs.
And indeed, that's why
in this visualization
you see the small numbers beginning
to be put into place on the left
as we keep swooping through.
But notice, the colored bar
keeps starting later and later,
more rightward and more rightward, just
like Brian was not retracing his steps.
As soon as he lit up the
numbers, he left them alone.
And voila, all of these
numbers are now sorted.
So that's just a graphical way of
thinking about the same algorithm.
But how efficient or
inefficient was that?
Well, let's see if we can
apply some numbers here.
But there's also ways to do
this a little more intuitively
over time, which we'll do, too.
So if the first time through
the shelf of numbers, he
had eight numbers at his disposal--
he had to look at all eight numbers
in order to decide which
of these is the smallest.
So that's n steps initially.
The next time he did a
pass through the shelf,
he ignored the brightly lit
number 1, because it was already
in place by definition of
what he had already done.
So now he had n minus 1 steps to go.
Then he did another n minus 2 steps,
then n minus 3, n minus 4, n minus 5,
dot, dot, dot, all the way down
to the final step, where he just
had to find and leave
alone the number 8,
because that was the biggest
number, so one single step.
So this is some kind of
series here, mathematically.
You might recall something like this
in, like, the back of your math book
or in high school, or back of
your physics textbook or the like.
It turns out that this actually
sums up to this formula here--
n times n plus 1 divided by 2.
And if that's not familiar, you
don't remember that, no big deal.
Just let me stipulate that the
mathematical formula with which we
began, where we had the series of
n, plus n minus 1, plus n minus 2,
plus n minus 3, dot, dot,
dot, simply sums up ultimately
to the more succinct n
times n plus 1 divided by 2.
This, of course, if we multiply it out,
gives us n squared plus n divided by 2.
And this now, I will
propose, gives us just this--
n squared divided by 2 plus n/2.
So if we really wanted
to be nit-picky, this
is the total number of steps,
or operations, or seconds,
however we want to measure
Brian's running time.
This seems to be the precise
mathematical formula therefore.
But at the beginning of this
week, we considered again,
the sort of Big O notation.
With a wave of the hand, we care
more about the order of magnitude
on which an algorithm operates.
I really don't care about
these divided by 2 and n/2.
Because which of these factors
is going to matter as n gets big?
The bigger the phone book
gets, the more doors we have,
the more light bulbs we have, the
more numbers we have on the shelf,
n is going to keep getting
bigger and bigger and bigger.
And given that, which
is the dominant factor?
Rongxin, if we could call on someone
here, which of these factors,
n squared divided by 2, or n divided
by 2, really matters in the long run
as our problems get bigger and
bigger, as n gets bigger and bigger?
Which of those factors
mathematically dominates?
Anika?
AUDIENCE: Oh, it's Anika, but--
DAVID MALAN: Anika.
AUDIENCE: It would be the-- no problem.
It would be the n squared.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, n squared.
Right.
If you take any number
for n and you square it,
that's going to be bigger,
certainly in the long run,
than just doing n divided by 2.
And so with our Big O notation,
we could describe the running time
of Brian's selection sort implementation
as, ah, it's on the order of n squared.
Yes, I'm ignoring some
numbers, and yes, if we really
wanted to be nit-picky and
count up every single step
that Brian took, yes, it's n
squared divided by 2 plus n/2.
But again, if you think about
the problem over time and n
getting really large, sort of
Facebook-sized, Twitter-sized,
Google-sized, what's really
going to dominate mathematically
is this bigger factor here.
That's what's going to make
the total number of steps way
bigger than just those
smaller order terms.
So in Big O notation,
selection sort would
seem to be on the order of n squared.
So if we consider our
chart from before where
we had the upper bounds on
our searching algorithms,
both linear and binary,
this one, unfortunately,
is at really the tip top of this
particular list of running times.
And there's infinitely many more.
These are just a subset of
the more common formulas
that a computer scientist
might use and think about.
Selection sort is kind
of a top of the list.
And being number one
on this list is bad.
n squared is certainly
much slower than, say,
big O of 1, which, of course,
was constant time or one step.
So I wonder if we could be--
if we could do a little better.
I wonder if we could do a little better.
And Peter actually did say
something else earlier,
which was about like sharing
two numbers and fixing problems.
And if I can kind of
run with that, let me
propose that we, Brian, return to
you for a look at an algorithm that
might be called instead
bubble sort, bubble sort
being a different
algorithm, this one that
tries to fix problems more locally.
So in fact, Brian, if you
look at the numbers that
are in front of you,
which you've kindly reset
to their original, unsorted
location, I feel like this really,
if we focus on just pairs of numbers,
it's just a lot of small numbers.
Like last time, we tried
to solve the big problem
and sorting the whole thing.
What if we just look at pairs of numbers
that are adjacent to one another?
Can we maybe make some little tweaks
and change our algorithm fundamentally?
So for instance, Brian, 6 and 3, what
observation can you make there for us?
BRIAN: Yeah, sure.
So 6 and 3 that's, the first
pair of numbers in the array.
And if I want the array to be
sorted, I want the smaller numbers
to be on the left and the bigger
numbers to be on the right.
So just looking at this pair, I can tell
you that the 6 and 3 or out of order.
The 3 should be on the left, and
the 6 should be on the right.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So let's go ahead and
do that, and go ahead
and fix that by swapping those two.
And just fix a small little problem.
And now let's repeat
this process, right?
Loops seem to be omnipresent
in a lot of our algorithms.
So 6 and 8 is the next such pair.
What you want-- what do
you think about those?
BRIAN: That particular pair seems OK,
because the 6 is smaller and already
on the left side.
So I think I can leave this pair alone.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
How about 8 and 5?
BRIAN: The 8 is bigger than the 5.
So I'm going to swap these two.
The 5 should be on the left of the 8.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
And 8 and 2?
BRIAN: Same thing here, the 8 is bigger.
So the 8 is going to
be swapped with the 2.
DAVID MALAN: All right, 8 and 7.
BRIAN: The 8 is bigger than the 7,
so the 8 I should switch with the 7.
DAVID MALAN: All right 8 and 4?
BRIAN: 8 and 4, same thing,
it's bigger than the 4.
DAVID MALAN: And 8 and 1.
BRIAN: I can do it one last time.
The 8 is bigger than the
1, and I think that's all.
DAVID MALAN: And with a
nice dramatic flourish,
if you step off to the side, voila--
not sorted.
In fact, it doesn't really
look all that much better.
But I do think Brian's
done something smart here.
Brian, can you speak to at least
some of the marginal improvements
that you've made?
BRIAN: Yeah.
So there are some
improvements, at least.
The 1 originally was all the way at the
very end, and it moved back one spot.
And the other improvement, I
think, is that the 8 originally
was way over here on the left
side of the array somewhere.
But because the 8 is
the biggest number, I
kept switching it over and
over again until it made it
all the way to the end.
And so now actually, I think
this 8 is in the correct place.
It's the biggest number, and it
ended up moving its way all the way
to the right side of the array.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
And this is where this algorithm that
we'll see the rest of in just a moment
gets its name, bubble sort--
alludes to the fact that the biggest
numbers start bubbling their way up
to the top of, or the end of,
the list, at the right-hand side
of the shelf as Brian notes.
But notice, as Brian does, too, the
number 1 only moved over one position.
So there's clearly more work to be done.
And that's obvious from the other
numbers being misordered as well.
But we have improved things.
The 8 is in place, and the 1
is closer to being in place.
So how might we proceed next?
Well, Brian, let's continue to solve
some small bite-sized problems.
Let's start at the beginning again.
3 and 6?
BRIAN: Sure.
The 3 and the 6, those seem to be
in order, so I'll leave those alone.
DAVID MALAN: 6 and 5.
BRIAN: 6 and 5 or out of the order,
so I'll go ahead and take the 6
and put it to the right.
DAVID MALAN: 6 and 2.
BRIAN: Those are out of order as
well, so I'll swap the 2 and the 6.
DAVID MALAN: 6 and 7.
BRIAN: 6 and 7 are OK.
They're in order.
DAVID MALAN: 7 and 4.
BRIAN: Those are out of order,
so I'll switch the 4 and the 7.
DAVID MALAN: 7 and 1.
BRIAN: And those two are out of
order as well, so I'll swap those.
And now I think the 7 has made its
way to the sorted position as well.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
So now we're making some progress.
7 has bubbled its way up to the top of
the list, stopping just before the 8,
whereas the 1 has continued its
advance to its correct location.
So I bet, Brian, if we keep
doing this again and again
and again, so long as the
list remains in part unsorted,
I think we'll probably
get to the finish line.
Do you want to take it from
here and sort the rest?
BRIAN: Yeah, sure.
So I just repeat the process again.
The 3 and the 5 are OK.
The 2 and the 5 are out of
order, so I'll swap them.
The 5 and the 6, those
are fine as a pair.
The 6 and the 4, out of order relative
to each other, so I'll switch those.
And the 6 and the 1, those are out
of order as well, so I'll swap those.
And now the 6, that I can say
is in its correct position.
And I'll repeat it again.
The 3 and the 2 are out of
order, so those get switched.
The 3 and the 5 are OK.
The 5 and the 4 are out of
order, so those get switched.
And then the 5 and the 1
need to be switched as well.
So there's the 5 in sorted position.
And now I'm left with these four.
The 2 and the 3 are
OK, the 3 and the 4 OK.
But the 4 and the 1 are out of order.
So those get switched, and now
the four, that's in its place.
The 2 and the 3 are OK, but the 3 and
the 1 are not, so I'll swap those.
And now the 3 goes
into its sorted place.
And then finally, the last pair to
consider is just the 2 and the 1.
Those are out of order, so I'll swap
those, and now the 2 is in place.
And 1 is the only remaining number, so
I can say that that one's in place, too.
And now I think we have a sorted array.
DAVID MALAN: Nice.
So it felt like this was a
fundamentally different approach,
but we still got to the same end point.
So that really now invites the question
as to whether bubbles or it was
better or worse or maybe no different.
But notice, too, that we've solved the
same problem fundamentally differently.
The first time, we took the more
human natural intuition of just,
find the smallest element.
All right, do it again,
do it again, do it again.
This time, we sort of viewed the
problem through a different lens.
And we thought about, it
would seem, what does it
mean for the list to be unsorted?
As Peter noted, it's when
things are out of order.
Like that very basic primitive
where something is out of order
suggests an opportunity to
solve the problem that way.
Just fix all of the tiny
bite-sized problems.
And it would seem that using a
loop, if we repeat that intuition,
is going to pay off eventually
by fixing, fixing, fixing,
fixing all of the little
problems until the big one itself
would seem to go away.
Well, let me return to the visualization
from before, re-randomize the bars--
short bar is small number,
big bar is big number.
And let me go ahead and run
the bubble sort algorithm,
this time with this visualization.
And you'll notice now sweeping from
left to right are two colored bars that
represent the comparison of two adjacent
numbers again and again and again.
And you'll see this time that the
bars are being a little smart,
and they're not going all the
way to the end every time,
just like Brian illuminated
the numbers and stopped
looking at the 8 and the 7 and
the 6 once they were in place.
But he and this visualization do
indeed keep returning to the beginning,
doing another pass, another
pass, and another pass.
So if we think ahead to the
analysis of this algorithm,
it sort of invites us to consider, well,
how many total comparisons are there
this time?
It would seem that the very
first time through the bars,
or equivalently the very first
time through the shelf, Brian
and this visualization did
like n minus 1 comparisons.
So n minus 1 comparisons
from left to right, out
of n elements you can compare
n minus 1 adjacencies.
After that it was n minus
2, n minus 3, n minus 4,
n minus 5, until just two or one
remain, and at that point you're done.
So even though this algorithm
fundamentally took a different approach
and achieved the same goal, it
sorted the elements successfully.
Let's consider how it
was implemented in code
and whether it's actually a
little faster or a little slower.
And let's set one final
bar, in fact, too.
Earlier, we considered only the
upper bound on selection sort,
just so that we have something
to compare this against.
Let's also consider for a
moment what the running time is
of selection sort in terms of a
lower bound-- best case scenario.
With selection sort,
if you have n elements,
and you keep looking for the next
smallest element, again and again
and again, it turns out that selection
sort is not really our friend.
Here's, for instance, the chart of where
we left off in terms of omega notation
before.
Linear search and binary
search could very well
get lucky and take just one step
if you happen to open a door
and, voila, the number you're
looking for is already there.
But with selection sort,
as we've implemented it,
both with Brian and
with the visualization,
unfortunately it's none so
good with the lower bound.
Why?
Well, Brian pretty naively, every
time he searched for a number,
started at the left and went all the
way to the right, started at the left,
went all the way to the right.
To be fair, he did ignore the
numbers that were already in place.
So he didn't keep looking at the
1, he didn't keep looking at the 2
once they were in place.
But he did keep repeating
himself again and again, touching
those numbers multiple times each.
So again, even though you and I, the
humans, could look at those numbers
and be like, obviously there's
the 1, obviously there's
the 2, the obviously
there's the 3, Brian
had to do it much more methodically.
And in fact, even if that list
of numbers were perfectly sorted,
he would have wasted just as much time.
In fact, Brian, if you don't
mind, could you quickly
sort all eight numbers again?
And Brian, if we start
with a sorted list,
this is kind of a nice perversion to
consider, if you will, algorithmically.
When analyzing an
algorithm, sometimes you
want to consider best
cases and worst cases.
And there would seem to be nothing
better than, heck, the list is already
sorted, you got lucky, there's
really no work to be done.
The worst case is the list is
maybe completely backwards,
and that's a huge amount
of work to be done.
Unfortunately, selection sort doesn't
really optimize for that lucky case
where they're already sorted.
So Brian, I see you've resorted the
numbers for us from left to right.
If we were to re-execute
selection sort as before,
how would you go about
finding the smallest number?
BRIAN: So we decided earlier
that, to find the smallest number,
I need to look at all
the numbers from left
to right in the array and each time
check to see if I found something.
smaller.
So I would start with the 1.
That's the smallest
thing I've seen so far.
But I would have to keep
looking, because maybe there's
a 0 or a negative number later on.
I need to check to see if
there's anything smaller.
So I would check, the 2 is
bigger, the 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
They're all bigger.
So it turns out I was right all along.
The 1 was the smallest number,
and it's already in place.
So now that number is in place.
DAVID MALAN: And then to find
the next smallest number,
what would you have done?
BRIAN: I would do the same thing.
2 is the smallest number I found so far.
And then I would look
through all the rest
to see if there's anything
smaller than the 2.
And I would look at 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
Nothing's smaller than the 2.
So I go back to the two and
say, OK, that number must now
be in its sorted position.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
And that story would be the same
for the 3, for the 4, and for the 5.
Like, nowhere in selection
sort pseudocode or actual code
is there any sort of intelligence of,
eh, if the numbers are already sorted,
quit.
Like, there was no opportunity
to short circuit and abort
that algorithm earlier.
Brian would literally
be doing the same work,
whether they're all
sorted from the get-go
or completely unsorted,
and even backwards.
And so selection sort doesn't
really perform very highly.
So now we're hoping
bubble sort, indeed, does.
So toward that end, let's take
a look at some proposed pseudo
code for bubble sort, assuming
that the input is anything.
Whether sorted or
unsorted, the pseudocode
is always going to look like this.
Repeat until sorted.
For i from 0 to n minus 2--
now, what does this mean?
0 to n minus 1 goes from the
first element to the last.
So 0 to n minus 2 goes from the
first element to the second to last.
Why am I doing that?
We'll see in just a moment.
The condition inside of this loop is,
if the i-th and the i plus 1th elements
are out of order, swap them.
So this is me being a little clever.
If you think about all of these
numbers as being in an array
or behind doors, if you
iterate from 0 to n minus 2,
that's like going from the first
door to the second to last door.
But that's good, because my condition
is checking door i and i plus 1.
So if I start at the beginning here,
and I only iterate up to this door,
that's a good thing.
Because when I compared door i
and i plus 1, at the very end
I'm going to compare
door i and i plus 1.
What I don't want to do is
compare this door i against door i
plus 1, which doesn't even exist.
And indeed, that's going to be
an error that probably all of you
make at some point--
going beyond the boundary
of an array, touching memory
that is going one or more
spaces too far in the array,
even though you didn't
allocate memory for it.
So this hedges against that possibility.
So this would seem to be
a pretty smart algorithm.
But as written, it's not actually
as performant as might be ideal.
With bubble sort, suppose the
list were entirely sorted.
Brian, not to make you sort and
resort numbers too many times.
Do you mind giving us a sorted
list one more time real quick?
In a moment, I want to see, if we
consider that same sorted list as
before, this time with bubble sort,
can we do fundamentally better?
I have this code saying,
repeat until sorted.
So how might this change?
So Brian, you've got the
sorted numbers again.
This should be a good case.
But selection sort did not
benefit from this input,
even though we could have gotten lucky.
Bubble sort, what would your
thought process be here?
BRIAN: So the thought
process for bubble sort
was to go through each of
the pairs one at a time
and see if I need to make a
swap for that particular pair.
So I'd look at the 1 and the 2.
Those two are OK, I
don't need to swap them.
The 2 and the 3 are OK.
I don't need to make a swap there.
The 3 and the 4 are OK.
The 4 and the 5 are OK.
Same with the 5 and the 6, and the
6 and the 7, and the 7 and the 8.
So I made my way through
all the entire array,
and I never needed to make any swap,
because every pair that I looked at,
they were already in the correct
order relative to each other.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
And so it would be foolish
and so obvious this time
if Brian literally retraced
those steps and did it
again with n minus 1 elements, and then
did it again with n minus 2 elements.
I mean, if he didn't do any
work, any swaps the first pass,
he's literally wasting
his own time by even
doing another pass or another pass.
And so that's kind of implicit in the
pseudocode, this repeat until sorted.
Even though it doesn't translate
perfectly into a for loop
or a while loop in C, it kind of
says intuitively what he should do--
repeat until sorted.
Brian has already identified
the fact, by nature of him
not having made any swaps,
that this list is sorted.
Therefore, he can just
stop, and this loop does not
have to continue again and again.
We can map this to C-like
code a little more explicitly.
We can by default say, do the
following n minus 1 times.
Because among n elements, you can look
at n minus 1 total pairs from left
to right without going too far.
But notice, I can add an
additional line of code here
which might say, if no swaps, quit
from the algorithm altogether.
So, so long as Brian is
keeping track of how many swaps
he made or didn't make through one
pass, as with a variable called counter
or whatever, he can simply abort
this algorithm early and certainly
then save us some time.
So with that said, let's
consider for just a moment what
the running time of bubble sort
might be in terms of an upper bound,
in the worst case, if you will.
Well, in the case of bubble
sort, notice with the pseudocode
where we're doing
something n minus 1 times,
and inside of that we're doing
something n minus 1 times.
So again, repeat n
minus 1 times literally
says, do the following n minus 1 times.
The for loop here, which is just
a different way in pseudocode
of expressing a similar idea but giving
us a variable this time, for i from 0
to n minus 1--
n minus 2, is a total number
of n minus 1 comparisons.
So this is an n minus 1
thing inside the repeat,
and an n minus 1 outside the repeat.
So I think what that gives me is n
minus 1 things times n minus 1 times.
So now if I just kind of FOIL
this, sort of in high school
or middle school math, n squared
minus 1n minus 1n plus 1.
We can combine like terms,
n squared minus 2n plus 1.
But per our discussion earlier, ugh,
this is really getting into the weeds.
Who cares about the 2n or the 1?
The dominant factor as n gets large is
definitely going to be the n squared.
So it would seem that
bubble sort, if you actually
do out the math and the formulas,
is going to have an upper bound of n
squared, or rather, on the
order of n squared steps.
So in that sense, it is
equivalent to selection sort.
It is no better fundamentally.
It's what we would say ask
asymptotically equivalent.
That is, as n gets really
large, this formula
is, for all intents and purposes,
equivalent to the selection sort
formula, even though
they differed slightly
in terms of their lower order terms.
For all intents and purposes, ah,
they're on the order of n squared both.
But if we consider a
lower bound, perhaps,
even though bubble sort has the
same upper bound running time,
if we consider a lower bound, as with
this smarter code, where Brian might
actually have the wherewithal to notice,
wait a minute, I didn't do any swaps,
I'm just going to exit out of
this looping pretty much early--
not even prematurely
but early, because it
would be fruitless to keep
doing more and more work--
we can then whittle
down this running time.
I think-- not quite as good as omega
of 1, which was constant time--
like, you cannot conclude definitively
that an array is sorted unless you
minimally look at all
of the elements once.
So constant time is completely
naive and unrealistic.
You can't look at one element, or two
or three, and say, yes, this is sorted.
You've got to obviously look at
all of the elements at least once.
So this would seem to suggest that
the omega notation for it, that
is, the lower bound on
bubble sort's running time,
if we're clever and don't retrace our
steps unnecessarily, is in omega of n.
Or technically, it's n
minus 1 steps, right?
Because if you've got n
elements and you compare
these two, these two,
that's n minus 1 total comparisons.
But who cares about the minus 1?
It's on the order of n, or
omega of n notation here.
So to recap, selection sort selects the
next smallest element again and again
and again.
Unfortunately, based on how it's
implemented in pseudocode and actual
code, it's in Big O of n squared.
But it's also an omega
of n squared, which
means it's always going to take the same
amount of time asymptotically, that is,
as n gets large.
Unfortunately, too, bubble sort
is no better, it would seem,
in terms of the upper bound.
It's going to take as many
as n squared steps, too.
But it's at least marginally better
when it comes to using something
like an input that's already sorted.
It can short circuit and not waste time.
But honestly, n squared is bad.
Like, n squared is really
going to add up quickly.
If you've got n squared and n is a
million or n is a billion, I mean,
my God, that's a lot of 0's.
That's a lot of steps in the total
running time of your algorithm.
Can we do better?
And it turns out we can.
And we'll consider one final algorithm
today that does fundamentally better.
Just like in week 0, we sort of latched
onto binary search and again today--
it's just fundamentally better than
linear search by an order of magnitude,
so to speak.
Its picture representation
was fundamentally different.
I think we can do fundamentally better
than bubble sort and selection sort.
And so while both bubble
sort and selection
sort might be the sort of thing
that I was using in grad school
just to rip up the code
quickly and then go to sleep,
it's not going to work well
for very large data sets.
And frankly, it wouldn't
have worked well
if I didn't want to just
sleep through the problem.
Rather, we want to do things as
efficiently as we can from the get go.
And let me propose that
we leverage a technique--
and this is a technique that you
can use in almost any programming
language, C among them--
known as recursion.
And recursion, quite simply, is the
ability for a function to call itself.
Up until now, we have not
seen any examples of this.
We've seen functions
calling other functions.
Main keeps calling printf.
Main has started to call strlen.
Main called strcmp,
compare, earlier today.
But we've never seen main call main.
And people don't do that, so that's
not going to solve the problem.
But we can implement our
own functions and have
our own functions call themselves.
Now, this would seem to be
a bad idea in principle.
If a function calls itself,
my God, where does it end?
It would seem to just
do something forever,
and then something bad probably happens.
And it could.
And that's the danger
of using recursion.
You can screw it up easily.
But it's also a very powerful
technique, because it
allows us to think about
potential solutions
to problems in a very interesting,
and daresay elegant, way.
So we're not only going to be able to
achieve correctness but also better
design, because of better
efficiency, it would seem, here.
So let me propose this.
Recall this code from week 0, which
was the pseudocode for finding someone
in a phone book.
And recall that, among the
features of this pseudocode,
were these lines here,
"Go back to line 3."
And we describe those in week 0
as being representative of loops,
a programming construct that has
something happen again and again.
But you know what, there's a missed
opportunity here in this pseudocode
to use a technique known as recursion.
This implementation is what
we would call iterative.
It is purely loop based.
It tells me literally, go back to
this line, go back to this line,
go back to this line.
There's no calling yourself.
But what if I changed week 0's
pseudocode to be a little more
like this?
Let me go ahead and get rid of, not
just that one line but two lines
in both of those conditions.
And let me quite simply
say, instead of open
to the middle of the left half of
the book and then go back to line 3,
or open to the middle of the right half
of the book and then go back to line 3,
why don't I just more elegantly
say, search left half of book,
search right half of book?
Now, immediately I can
shorten the code a little bit.
But I claim that by just saying search
left half of book and search right
half of book, I claim that
this is enough information
to implement the very same algorithm.
But it's not using a loop per se.
It's going to induce me the
human or me the computer
to do something again and again.
But there's other ways to
do things again and again--
not by way of a for loop, or a
while loop, or a do while loop,
or a repeat block, or a forever block--
you can actually use recursion.
And recursion, again, is this technique
where a function can call itself.
And if we consider, after all,
the pseudocode we are looking at
is the pseudocode for searching.
And on line 7 and 9 now, I am literally
saying, "Search left half of book,"
and "Search right half of book," this
is already, even in pseudocode form,
an example of recursion.
Here I have in 11 lines of
code an algorithm or a function
that searches a phone book.
In lines 7 and 9, I have lines of
code that literally say, search
a phone book, but more specifically,
search half of the phone book.
And that's where recursion
really works its magic.
It would be foolish and incorrect
and completely counterproductive
to just have a function call
itself with the same input,
with the same input, with
the same input, because you'd
have to be kind of crazy
to expect different output
if the input is constantly the same.
But that's not what we did in week 0,
and that's not what we're doing now.
If you use the same function,
or equivalently algorithm,
but change the input to be
smaller and smaller and smaller,
it's probably OK that a
function is calling itself,
so long as you have at least
one line of code in there
that very intelligently
says, if you're out of doors,
if you're out of phone book pages, quit.
You need to have a so-called base case.
You need some line of code that's
going to notice, wait a minute, there's
no more problem to be solved, quit now.
And so how can we map
this to actual code?
Well, let's consider something
very familiar from week 1.
Recall when you reconstructed
one of Mario's pyramids.
It looked a little something like this.
And let's consider that
this is a pyramid of blocks,
of bricks, that's of height 4.
Why 4?
Well, there's 1, then 2, then 3,
then 4 bricks from top to bottom.
So the total height here is 4.
But let me ask the question, a little
naively, how do you go about creating,
or how do you go about
printing a pyramid of height 4?
Well, it turns out that this
simple Mario pyramid, that's
ever more clear if we get rid
of the unnecessary background,
is a recursive structure of some sort.
It's a recursive physical structure.
Why?
Well, notice that this structure,
this brick, this pyramid,
is kind of defined in terms of itself.
Why?
Well, how do you make
a pyramid of height 4?
I would argue, a little obnoxiously,
a little circularly, well,
you create a pyramid
of height 3, and then
you add an additional row of bricks.
All right.
Well, let's continue that logic.
All right, fine.
How do you build a pyramid of height 3?
Well, you sort of smile and say,
well, you build a pyramid of height 2,
and then you add one more layer.
All right, fine.
How do you build a pyramid of height 2?
Well, you build a pyramid of height
1, and then you add one more layer.
Well, how do you build
a pyramid of height 1?
Well, you just put
the stupid brick down.
You have a base case, where
you sort of state the obvious
and just do something once.
You hardcode the logic.
But notice what's kind
of mind bending, or kind
of obnoxious in a human
interaction, like,
you're just defining the
answer in terms of itself.
I keep saying the same thing.
But that's OK, because the pyramid keeps
getting smaller and smaller and smaller
until I can handle
that one special case.
And so we can do this just for fun
with these little cardboard bricks
here, for instance.
If I want to build a pyramid
of height 4, how do I do it?
Well, I can build a pyramid of height 3.
All right, let me go ahead and
build a pyramid of height 3.
How do I build a pyramid of height 3?
All right, well, I build a pyramid
of height 2, and then I add to it.
OK, how do I build a
pyramid of height 2?
Well, you build a pyramid of height 1.
How do I do that?
Well, you just put the brick down.
And so here's where
things kind of bottom out,
and it's no longer a cyclical argument.
You eventually just do some actual work.
But in my mind, I have to remember all
of the instructions you just gave me,
or I gave myself.
I had to build a pyramid of height
4; nope, 3; nope, 2; nope, 1.
Now I'm actually doing that.
So here's a pyramid of height 1.
How do I now build a
pyramid of height 2?
Well, rewind in the story.
To build a pyramid of height 2,
you build a pyramid of height 1,
and then you add one more layer.
So I think to add one more layer,
I essentially need to do this.
All right.
Now I have a pyramid of height 2.
But wait a minute.
The story began with, how do
I build a pyramid of height 3?
Well, you take a pyramid of
height 2, which I have here,
and you add an additional layer.
So I've got to build
this additional layer.
I'm going to go ahead and give myself
the layer, the layer, the layer.
And then I'm going to put the original
pyramid of height to on top of it.
And voila, it's a
pyramid of height 3 now.
Well, how did I get here?
Well, let me keep
rewinding in the story.
The very first question
I asked myself was,
how do you build a pyramid of height 4?
Well, the answer was build
a pyramid of height 3.
Great, that's done.
Then add one additional layer.
And if I had more hands, I could
do this a little more elegantly,
but let me go ahead
and just lay this out.
Here's the new level of height 3.
And now I'm going to go--
of width 4.
Now I'm going to go and put the pyramid
of height 3 on top of it, until voila,
I have this form here
of Mario's pyramid.
So it's a bit cyclical
in that, every time I
asked myself to build a
pyramid of a certain height,
I kind of punted and said, no,
build a pyramid of this height.
No, build a pyramid of this height.
But the magic of that algorithm
was that there was constantly
this, do a little more work, build
a layer, do a little more work,
build a layer.
And it's in that implicit building
of layer after layer after layer
that the pyramid itself, the
end goal, actually emerges.
So you could implement the same thing
with a for loop or a while loop.
And frankly, you did.
It was a slightly different
shape for problem set 1,
but you did the same thing using a loop.
And you kind of had to do it that
way, at least as we prescribed it.
Because with printf, you have to
print from the top of the screen
to the bottom.
Like, we haven't shown you a
technique yet to print a layer
and then go back on top.
So I'm kind of taking some
real-world liberties here
by lifting these things
up and moving them around.
You'd have to be a little
more clever in code.
But the idea is the same.
And so even physical
objects like this can
have some recursive definition to them.
And so we present this
sort of goofy example,
because this notion of recursion is
a fundamental programming technique
that you can leverage
now to solve problems
in a fundamentally different way.
And I think for this, we need one
final visualization of merge sort,
with both Brian's help
and the computer's.
And merge sort is going to be an
algorithm whose pseudocode is, daresay,
the simplest we've seen thus
far, but deceptively simple.
The pseudocode for merge
sort, quite simply, is this--
sort the left half of numbers,
sort the right half of numbers,
merge the sorted halves.
And notice, even at first glance
this feels kind of unfair.
Like, here's an algorithm
for sorting, and yet I'm
literally using the word "sort"
in my algorithm for sorting.
It's like in English if
you're asked to define a word,
and you literally use the
word in the definition.
Like, that rarely flies, because
you're just making a circular argument.
But in code, it's OK, so long as there's
one special step that's doing something
a little differently, and
so long as the problem keeps
getting smaller and smaller.
And indeed it is.
This pseudocode is not saying,
sort the numbers, sort the numbers,
sort of numbers.
No, it's dividing the problem in
half and then solving the other half
as well.
So it's shrinking the
problem on each iteration.
Now, I will disclaim we're going to
need that so-called base case again.
I'm going to have to do
something stupid, but necessary,
and say, if there's
only one number, quit.
It's sorted.
That's the so-called base case.
The recursive case is where
the function calls itself.
But this is, indeed, our third and final
sorting algorithm called merge sort.
And we'll focus here really
on the juiciest pieces,
one, this notion of merging.
So in fact, Brian, can
we come over to you
just so we can define, before we look
at the merge sort algorithm itself,
what do we even mean when
we say merge sorted halves?
So for instance, Brian has on his
shelf here two arrays of size 4.
In the first array on the left
are four integers, 3, 5, 6, 8.
And in the right side, in
another array of size 4,
are four numbers, too, 1, 2, 4, 7.
Both the left is sorted
and the right is sorted.
But now, Brian, I would like you
to merge these sorted halves.
Tell us what that means.
BRIAN: Sure.
So if I have a left half
that sorted from smallest
to largest and a right half that's
also sorted from smallest to largest,
I want to merge them into a new list
that has all of the same numbers
also from smallest to largest.
And I guess where I could
start here is that the smallest
number of the combined array needs
to begin with either the smallest
number of the left half or the
smallest number of the right half.
So on the left the smallest
number is the 3, and on the right
the smallest number is the 1.
Of those two has got to be the
smallest number for the entire array.
And between the 3 and
the 1, the 1 is smaller.
So I would take that 1, and that's going
to be the first number, the smallest
number, of the merged two halves.
And then I guess I would
repeat the process again.
On the left side the
smallest number is the 3.
On the right side the
smallest number is the 2.
And between the 3 and
the 2, 2 is smaller.
So I would take the 2 [INAUDIBLE] and
that's going to be the next number.
So I'm slowly building
up this sorted array that
is the result of combining these two.
Now I'm comparing the 3 on the
left to the 4 on the right.
Between the 3 and the
4, the 3 is smaller.
So I'll take the 3, and we'll
put that one into position.
Now I'm comparing the 5 on the
left with the 4 on the right.
Between the 5 and the
4, the 4 is smaller.
So that one goes into position.
And then now I'm comparing the 5 on
the left with the 7 on the right.
5 is smaller, so the 5 goes next.
Next I'm comparing the 6 on the
left with the 7 on the right.
The 6 is still smaller, so
that one is going to go next.
Now I'm comparing the 8 and the
7, the only two numbers left.
The 7 is the smaller between the two.
So I'll take the 7 and
put that into place.
And now I'm only left
with one number that
hasn't been put into the merging of the
two halves, and that's the number 8.
So that number is going to
take up the final position.
And now I've taken these to halves,
each of which was originally sorted,
and made one complete array that has
all of those numbers in sorted order.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
And consider what we've done.
We've essentially verbally
and physically kind of
defined a helper function, our
own custom function if you will,
whereby Brian has defined what
does it mean to merge two arrays--
specifically merge two sorted arrays.
Because why?
Well, that's a building
block that I think
we're going to want in
this merge sort algorithm.
So just like in actual
C code, you might have
defined a function that
does some small task,
so have we now verbally and physically
defined the notion of merging.
The mind bending part
here is that "Sort left
half of numbers" and "Sort
right half of numbers"
is kind of already implemented.
There's nothing more for
Brian or me to define.
All that remains is for us to execute
this algorithm, focusing especially
on these three
highlighted lines of code.
And let me disclaim that of the
algorithms we've looked at thus far,
odds are this will be the
one that doesn't really
sink in as quickly as the others.
Even if the others might have
taken you a moment, a day,
a week to settle in-- or maybe
you're still not quite there yet,
that's fine--
merge sort is a bit
of a mind bending one,
because it seems to work magically.
But it really just works
more intelligently.
And you'll begin to get more
comfortable with harnessing
these kinds of primitives so that we
can ultimately, indeed, solve problems
more efficiently.
So Brian has kindly put the
numbers again on the top shelf.
And he has put them into their
original, unsorted order,
just like for selection
sort and bubble sort.
And Brian, I'd like to propose now that
we execute this merge sort algorithm.
And if you don't mind, I'll
recite aloud first the few steps.
So here is one array of size
8 with unsorted numbers.
The goal is to these
numbers using merge sort.
And recall that merge sort
essentially is just three steps--
sort left half, sort right
half, merge sorted halves.
So Brian, looking at
those numbers there,
could you go ahead and sort
the left half of numbers?
BRIAN: All right.
So there are eight numbers.
The left half would be these four
numbers, so I will sort those.
Except I'm not really sure how
do I now sort these four numbers.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So granted, we've seen selection
sort, we've seen bubble sort.
But we don't want to regress to
those older, slower algorithms.
Brian, I can kind of be
a little clever here.
Well, I'm giving you
a sorting algorithm.
So now you effectively have a
smaller problem, an array of size 4,
and I'm pretty sure we can use
the same algorithm, merge sort,
by sorting left half,
sorting right half,
and then merging the sorted halves.
So could you go ahead and sort the
left half of these four numbers?
BRIAN: All right.
So I have these four numbers.
I want to sort the left half.
That's these two numbers.
So now I need to figure out
how to sort two numbers.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
Now, us with human intuition might
obviously know what we have to do here.
But again, let's apply the algorithm--
sort left half, sort right half,
merge sorted half.
Brian, could you sort the right
half of this array of size 2?
BRIAN: So I've got the
array of two, so I'll first
sort the left half of the
array of two, which is the 6.
DAVID MALAN: And this is where the
base case in white on the slide
comes into play--
if only one number, quit.
So Brian, I can let you off the hook.
That list of size one with
the number 6 is sorted.
So that's step one of three done.
Brian, could you sort the right
half of that array of size two?
BRIAN: The right half is the number 3.
It's also just one number,
so that one is done.
DAVID MALAN: Good.
So think about where
we are on the story.
We've sorted the left half, and
we've started the right half,
even though it looks like neither Brian
nor I have done any useful work yet.
But now the magic happens.
Brian, you now have
two arrays of size 1.
Could you merge them together?
BRIAN: All right.
So I'm going to merge
these two together.
Between the 6 and the
3, the 3 is smaller.
So that one I'll put there first.
And then I'll take the 6,
and that one goes next.
And now I have a sorted array
of size 2 that is now done.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
And this is where you now need to
start remembering step by step sort
of in your brain as the things pile up.
How did we get to this point?
We started with a list of size 8.
We then looked at the left half,
which was an array of size 4.
We then looked at the left half of
that, which was an array of size 2,
then two arrays of size 1, then
we merged those two sorted halves.
So I think now if I rewind
in that story, Brian,
you need to sort the right half of
the left half of the original numbers.
BRIAN: All right.
So the left half is these four.
The right half of the left half
is going to be these two numbers.
And so now to those two, I guess
I would repeat the process again--
look at the numbers individually.
I would look at the left half
of these two, which is the 8.
That one is done.
And the 5, that one is done as well.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
So step three of three, then, is
merge those two sorted halves.
BRIAN: All right.
So between the 8 and the 5, the 5 is
smaller, so that one will go in first.
And the 8 will go after that.
And now I have a second array of
size 2 that is also now sorted.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
So here's where, again, you have
to rewind in your mind's eye.
We've just now sorted
the left half, and we've
sorted the left half and the
right half of the left half.
So I think the third and final step
at this part of the story is, Brian,
to merge those sorted halves,
each of which now is of size 2.
BRIAN: All right.
I have two arrays of size 2, each of
which is sorted, that I need to merge.
So I'm going to compare the
smallest numbers from each.
I'm going to compare the 3 and the 5.
The 3 is smaller, so that
one will go in first.
Now between these two arrays,
I have a 6 and a 5 to compare.
The 5 is smaller, so
that one will go next.
Between the 6 and the
8, the 6 is smaller.
And I'm left with just the 8.
So if we go back to the original story
of eight numbers that I was sorting,
I think I have now sorted the
left half of the left four numbers
from that original array.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
So if you're playing
along at home, think
about-- you've got all
these thoughts probably kind
of piling up in your mind.
That's indeed supposed to be the case.
And admittedly, it's hard to
keep track of all of that.
So we'll let Brian now
execute this altogether
together doing the same thing
now, by sorting the right half all
the way to completion.
Brian, if you could.
BRIAN: All right.
So the right half, you got four numbers.
I'm going to start by sorting the
left half of the right half, which
is these two numbers here.
To do that, I'll repeat
the same process--
sort the left half of these two
numbers, which is just the 2.
That one's done, it's only one number.
Same thing with the right half.
The 7 is only one number, so it's done.
And now I'll merge the
sorted halves together.
Between the 2 and the 7, the
2 is smaller and then the 7.
So here now is the left half of
the right half, an array of size 2,
that is sorted.
And I'll do the same thing with
the right half of the right half,
starting with the left half, which is 4.
That's done.
The 1 is done.
And now to merge these
two together, I'll
compare them and say the 1 is smaller.
So I'll put the 1 down and then the 4.
So now I have two sorted
arrays, each of size 2,
that I now need to backtrack
and now merge together
to form an array of size 4.
So I'll compare the 2 and the 1.
Between those two, the 1 is smaller.
Then I'll compare the 2 with the 4.
The 2 is smaller.
Then I'll compare the 7 with the 4.
The 4 is smaller.
And then finally, I'll just
take the 7, the last number,
and put that in the final spot.
And so now from the original
array of eight numbers,
I've now sorted the left half,
and I've sorted the right half.
DAVID MALAN: And now that brings us
to our third and very final step.
Could you, Brian, merge
the sorted halves?
BRIAN: Yeah.
And I think this is actually
an example we've seen already.
And what I'm going to do in
order to these two halves
is just take the smaller
number from each half
and compare them again and again.
So between the 3 and the 1, the
1, that's the smallest number.
So that goes into place.
Then between the 3 and
the 2, the 2 is smaller,
so we'll take that and
put that into place.
Now I'm comparing the 3 with the 4.
The 3, that goes next.
Next I'm comparing the 5 with the 4.
4 is smaller, so the 4
goes into place next.
Now I'm comparing the 5 with the 7.
5 is smaller, so that
one goes into place.
And next, comparing the 6 with
the 7, so the 6 is smaller.
That goes next.
And now I'm left with two
numbers, the 8 and the 7.
The 7 is the smaller of the
2, so that one goes next.
And at this point, I only have
one number left, which is the 8.
And so that one's going to
go into its sorted position
at the end of the array.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
So even though it felt like we
weren't really doing anything
at several points in that
story, it all sort of
came together when we started merging
and merging and merging these lists.
And it's not an accident that
Brian was using multiple shelves,
moving the numbers from top
to bottom, to make clear
just how many times he was
effectively dividing that list up.
We started with a list of
eight, and we essentially
took it to two lists of size 4, four
lists of size 2, eight lists of size 1.
And while it wasn't
exactly in that order,
if you rewind and analyze all of the
steps, that's indeed what he did.
He went from 8 to two 4's
to four 2's to eight 1's.
And that's why he moved those numbers
from the top shelf down three times--
from 8's, to 4's, to 2's, to 1'r.
So how many times did
he move the numbers?
He moved them three times total.
And on each of those shelves, how many
numbers did he have to merge together?
On each of those shelves, he
ultimately touched all eight numbers.
He first inserted the smallest
number, then the second smallest, then
the third smallest.
But unlike selection sort, he had
smartly already sorted those halves,
so he was just plucking
them off one at a time.
He wasn't going back and
forth, back and forth.
He was constantly taking from the
beginning of each of those half lists.
So on every shelf, he was
doing, let's say, n steps,
because he was merging in
all n elements of that shelf.
But how many times did he
merge n elements together?
Well, he did that three total times.
But if you think about binary search,
and really the process of divide
and conquer more generally, anytime
you divide something in half and half
and half, as he was doing
from 8's to 4's to 2's to 1's.
That's a logarithm.
That's log base 2.
And indeed, that is wonderfully
the height of this shelf.
If you have eight elements on the
shelf, the number of additional shelves
Brian used, 3, is exactly what you
get by doing the math log base 2 of 8.
Which is to say, Brian
did n things log n times.
And again with a wave of the
hand, computer scientists
don't bother mentioning the
base with Big O notation.
It suffices just to say log n--
Brian did n things log n times.
And so if we consider, then,
the asymptotic complexity
of this algorithm, that is to say
the running time of this algorithm,
in terms of big O notation, notice
that it performs strictly better then
selection sort and bubble sort--
n times log n.
And even, again, if you're a
little rusty on logarithms, log n,
we have seen as of week
0 in binary search,
is definitely faster than n steps.
So n squared is n times n.
n log n is n times log n,
which is indeed mathematically
better then n squared.
As with merge sort, though, if
we consider the lower bound,
notice that bubble sort, yes,
got us as low as omega of n.
Turns out merge sort is a
little bit like selection sort
in that it doesn't optimize itself and
get you out of the algorithm early.
It's always n log n, so it's
lower bound omega of n log n.
And that might not be acceptable.
Sometimes you might
have certain data inputs
where maybe it tends to be sorted
and you don't want to waste time.
So maybe you'd be OK with bubble sort.
But honestly, as n gets
large, the probability
that the input to your sorting algorithm
is just by chance going to be sorted
is probably so, so low
that you're just better
off in the general case using an
algorithm like merge sort that's
n log n always.
We can see this visually
using our bars, too.
And notice, just as Brian
was dividing and conquering
the problem in half and half and
half, and then reconstituting
the array by merging those halves, you
can kind of see that visually here.
There's a lot more going on.
And it's going to seem in a moment
that everything just kind of magically
worked.
But you can see in the faded
purple bars that, indeed, this
is sorting things in halves and
then merging those halves together.
And this visualization
was a little different.
It did not have the
luxury of three shelves.
It just moved top to
bottom, top to bottom.
And honestly, Brian could have
been a little more optimal there.
We wanted to make clear how
many total shelves there were.
But honestly, there's no
reason he couldn't have just
moved the numbers down then back
up, then back down then back up.
And, indeed that's the price
you pay with merge sort.
Even though n log n is better
than n squared, and ergo
merge sort is arguably better than
selection sort and bubble sort,
you pay a price.
And this speaks to the
trade-off I mentioned earlier.
Almost always, when you do
something better in code
or solve a problem more
intelligently, you have paid a price.
Maybe you spent more time as
the human writing the code,
because it was harder and
took more sophistication.
That is a cost.
Maybe you had to use
actually more space.
Brian had to have at least one extra
shelf in order to implement merge sort.
If implementing merge
sort in code and C,
you will need at least a second array to
temporarily put the numbers into as you
merge things back and forth.
If you want to be extravagant,
you can have three separate arrays
or four separate arrays.
But it's suffices, per the graphical
representation of merge sort,
to just use a second array.
Now, that might not seem
like such a big deal.
But implicitly, you need
twice as much space.
And that might be a big deal.
If you've got a million things to
sort, and you now need two arrays,
that's 2 million chunks
of memory that you need.
And maybe that's not tenable.
So there, too, there's
going to be a trade-off.
And maybe while slower, selection
sort of bubble sort, maybe
it's better because it's a
little more efficient with space.
It's going to depend
on what you care about
and what you want to optimize for.
And honestly, money
is sometimes a factor.
In the real world, maybe it's
better to write slightly slower code
so that you don't have to buy twice as
many servers or twice as much memory
for your computer.
It depends there on what
resource is more important--
your time, the computer's time,
your wallet, or some other resource
altogether.
So we'll continue to see
these kinds of trade-offs.
But perhaps the most mind blowing
thing we can do as we wrap up here
is share a few visualizations of how
these algorithms actually compare.
And one last piece of jargon is
this one final Greek symbol, theta.
It turns out that, thanks to
selection sort and merge sort,
we can actually apply one more term
of art here, this theta notation.
Anytime an algorithm has
both the same upper bound
as its lower bound running
time, you can actually
describe it in just one sentence instead
of two in terms of theta notation.
So because selection sort was in
both big O of n squared and omega
of n squared, you can actually just
say, ah, it's in theta of n squared.
It's always n squared either in the
upper bound or in the lower bound.
Same thing for merge sort.
It's in theta of n log n.
We cannot use theta for bubble sort or
for binary search or for linear search,
because they had different
upper and lower bounds.
Well, let me go ahead now and
prepare a final demonstration,
this time using some random inputs.
So you'll see here a video comparing
selection sort, bubble sort,
and merge sort all together.
All three of them
start with random data.
But let's just see what
it means for an algorithm
to be an n squared in the worst case
or in n log n in this case instead.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Selection sort's on the top,
bubble sort's on the bottom,
merge sort's in the middle.
And would you believe it,
merge sort is already done.
[MUSIC INTENSIFIES]
And meanwhile, we have some very
trendy music we can listen to,
which is really just
there to distract us
from the fact at how slow n
squared actually is in practice.
And notice, there's not
that many bars here.
There's maybe like a hundred or so bars.
Like, n is 100.
That's not even a big value.
When we're talking about the
Twitters, the Facebooks, the Googles
of the world, these are trivial sizes.
And yet, my God, we're still waiting
for selection sort and bubble sort
to finish.
And so you can see here that it really
matters when you exercise a little bit
more cleverness, and you leverage
a more efficient algorithm--
and finally, selection sort is
done, bubble sort still taking
a little longer here.
And this is going to
depend on the input.
Sometimes you can get lucky or unlucky.
But I think it's convincing that
merge sort has won in this case.
[MUSIC PLAYING]