[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right, this
is CS50, and this is week four.
And for the past
several weeks, we've had
training wheels of sorts on, while
using this language known as C.
And those training wheels have been
in the form of the CS50 library.
And you use this library, of course,
by selecting and including cs50.h
atop your code.
And then if you think about
how [INAUDIBLE] works,
you've been linking your
code via dash L CS50.
But all of that has been automated
for you up until now, using make.
Today, we'll transition
from last week's focus
on algorithms to a little
more focus on machines
and on the machines we now use to
implement these algorithms all the more
powerfully, as we begin to
take off these training wheels
and look at what's really going on
underneath the hood of your computer.
And as complicated as some
aspects of C have been,
as new is programming
may very well be to you,
realize that there's not all that
much going on underneath the hood
that we need to understand
to now move onward
and start solving far more interesting
and more sophisticated and more
fun problems.
We just need a few
additional building blocks.
And so today, we'll do this,
first, by relearning how to count.
Here, for instance, is what
we'll call the computer's memory.
And we've seen this grid before.
And we can number recall all of the
bytes in your computer's memory.
We might call this byte number 0, 1,
2, 3, 4, all the way up to byte 15,
and so forth.
But it turns out, when talking
about computers' memories,
computers and computer
scientists and programmers
actually don't tend to use decimal.
They definitely don't tend to
use binary at that low level.
Instead, they tend to use,
just for conventional sake,
something called hexadecimal.
Hexadecimal is a different
base system that,
instead of using 10 digits
or 2 digits, uses 16 instead.
And so a computer scientist,
when numbering things
like bytes in a computer memory, would
still do 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
But after that, instead of going
onward with decimal to, say, 10,
11, 12, 13, 14, 15, they
instead, conventionally,
would start using a few
letters of the alphabet.
And so, in hexadecimal, this
different base system base 16,
you start counting at 0 still.
You count up to and through 9.
But when you want to
keep counting higher,
you then go to A, B, C, D, E, and F.
And the upside of this is that, within
hexadecimal-- and that hex implies 16--
you have 16 total individual digits, 0
through 9, and also now, A through F.
So we don't have to introduce second
digits just to count up as high as 16.
We can use individual
digits 0 through F.
And we can keep counting up further
by using multiple hexadecimal digits.
But to get there, let's
introduce this vocabulary.
So in binary, of course,
we use 0's and 1's.
In decimal, of course,
we use 0 through 9's.
And in hexadecimal, to be clear, we're
going to use 0 through F's, otherwise
known as base-16.
And it's just a convention
that we use A through F. We
could have used any other six symbols.
But these are what humans have chosen.
So hexadecimal works quite similarly
to our familiar decimal system.
And it's even familiar to, now, what you
know as the binary system, as follows.
Let's consider a two-digit value
using hexadecimal instead of decimal
and instead of binary.
Well, just like in the world
of decimal, we used base-10,
or in the world of
binary, we used base-2.
We're just going to use, now,
base-16, ergo, hexadecimal.
So this is 16 to the first.
This is 16 to the--
sorry 16 to the 0.
This is 16 to the first.
And of course, if we multiply that
out, it's just the ones column
and now the 16's column.
And so if you want to
count up in hexadecimal,
you still start with 0 as usual, then
01, 02, 03, 04, 05, 06, 07, 08, 09.
And then things get interesting.
Now, you don't go to 01,
because that would be incorrect.
01, in this base system, would be
like 16 times 1 plus 1 times 0.
That's not what we want.
After the number we know is 9, we
now count up to A, B, C, D, E, F.
And now, things get interesting again.
But just like in the decimal system,
when you count up to, like, 99,
you have to start carrying
the 1, same thing here.
If you want to count
past F, you carry the 1.
And so now, to represent one
value greater than F, we use 01,
which looks like 10, but is not 10.
In hexadecimal, it is 01.
16 times 1 gives us 16.
1 times 0 gives us 0.
And of course, that gives us the
decimal number we now know is 16.
So we will no longer introduce
more and more base systems.
But let me stipulate that
just by using these columns
that you learned back in
grade school, presumably,
can you implement any base system now.
It just so happens that
in the world of computers,
and today in the world of
memory, and soon, also files,
it's just going to be
very conventional to be
able to recognize and use hexadecimal.
And in fact, there's a reason
humans like hexadecimal,
or at least some humans.
Computer scientists recall that if we
count up as high as FF, in this case,
we would still do the same math.
So 16 times 15 plus 1 times 15 is
going to give us, really, this,
or of course, 240 plus 15, or 255.
And I did that pretty quickly.
But that's just the sort of
grade school math of multiplying
the column by the value
that's in it, where again,
each of these F's is how we now
express 15 using a single digit.
But recall that we've seen 255 before.
Back when we talked about
binary a few weeks ago,
255 also happened to be the pattern that
we see here, eight 1 bits using binary.
And so the reason that computer
scientists tend to hexadecimal,
is that, you know what, in
eight bits, there's actually
two pairs here, like four on
the left, four on the right.
If we sort of scooch
these things over, it
turns out that because
hexadecimal allows
you to represent 16
possible values, it's
a perfect system for
representing four bits at a time.
After all, if you've got four bits
here, each of which can be a 0 or 1,
that's 2 times 2 times 2 times 2
possible values for each of those,
or 16 total values, which is to
say that in the world of computers,
if you ever want to talk
in units of four bits,
it's wonderfully convenient
to use hexadecimal instead,
only because, conveniently, one
hexadecimal digit happens to be
equivalent to four binary
digits, 0's and 1's.
So 0, 0, 0, 0, all the
way up through 1, 1, 1, 1.
So why do humans do this?
It's just now the human convention
because of that convenience.
Now, some of you may very well
have seen hexadecimal before.
In fact, recall our
discussion in week 0 of RGB,
where we discussed the
representation of colors using
some amount of red, green, and blue.
And at the time, we used this example.
We took our example out of context.
And instead of using
hi as a string of text,
we reinterpreted 72, 73, and
33 as a sequence of colors.
How much red do you want?
How much green do you want?
How much blue do you want?
And that's fine.
It's perfectly fine to think and
express yourself in terms of decimal.
But computer scientists tend not to do
it that way in the context of colors
and in the context of memory.
Instead, they tend to use
something called hexadecimal.
And hexadecimal, here,
would actually just
have you change these values from 72,
73, 33, to the equivalent hexadecimal
representation.
And we won't bother doing the math here.
But let me just stipulate
that 72, 73, 33 in decimal
is the same thing as 48,
49, 21 in hexadecimal.
Now, obviously, if you glance
at these three numbers,
it's not at all obvious if you're
looking at hexadecimal digits
or decimal digits, because they do
use the same subset, 0's through 9's.
And so a convention, too,
in the computing world,
is any time you represent
hexadecimal digits,
you tend to prefix them,
just because, with 0x.
And there's no mathematical
meaning to the 0 or the x.
It's just a prefix you put there
to make clear to the viewer
that these are hexadecimal digits,
even if they might otherwise
look like decimal digits.
So where are we going with this?
Well, those of you who
might have experimented
in the past with making your own
web pages and making them colorful,
or those of you who are artists and
have used programs like Photoshop, odds
are, you've seen these codes before.
In fact, here are a few
screenshots of Photoshop itself.
If you click on a color in Photoshop
and you pull up this window,
you can change the color that
you're drawing on the screen
to be any of the colors of the rainbow.
But more arcanely, if
you look down here,
you can actually see
these hexadecimal codes,
because it's become human
convention over the years
to use hexadecimal to represent
different amounts of red, green,
and blue.
So if you have no red, no green, no
blue, otherwise represented as 000000,
well, that's going to give you
the color we know here as black.
It's sort of the absence of
any wavelengths of light there.
If by contrast, though, you
change all of those six digits
to the highest possible value, which,
again, is F. The range in hexadecimal 0
through F, otherwise in decimal,
being 0 through 15, well,
with FFFFFF, that's a lot of red,
a lot of green, a lot of blue.
And when you combine those
wavelengths of light,
you get the color we see here as white.
And you can imagine, now,
combining different amounts
of red or green or blue.
So for instance, in hexadecimal,
FF0000, is the color we know as red.
00FF00 is the color we know as green.
And finally, 0000FF is the color
we know as blue, because again,
the system that programmers and artists
often but don't always use, is indeed,
this system of RGB for
red, green, and blue.
So we introduced this
here not because you
have to start thinking any
differently, because again,
the mathematical mechanism
is the same as week 0.
But you're going to start seeing
numbers in examples, in programs,
as just appearing in hexadecimal by
convention, as opposed to actually
being interpreted as decimal.
So if we consider, now,
our computer's memory,
we'll now start thinking of
this whole canvas of memory,
all of these bytes inside
of our computer's memory,
as being innumerable as 0,
1, 2, all the way through F.
And then if we keep counting, we can go
to 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18,
19, 1A, 1B, 1C, 1D, and so forth.
And it's fine if it's
not nearly that obvious,
as you look at these things,
what the decimal equivalents are.
That's not a problem.
It's just a different way of thinking
about the locations, in this case,
of a computer's memory, or the
representation of one color or another.
All right, well, let's now use this
as an example of an opportunity,
rather, to consider what's actually
being stored in our computer's memory.
And to be clear, I'll start prefixing
all of these memory addresses,
so to speak, with 0x, just to make
clear that we're now talking, indeed,
in terms of 0's and 1's.
So here's a simple line of code.
Out of context, we would
need to, actually, put this
in main or some other program
to actually do anything with it.
But we've seen this
before many times, now,
where you declare a variable,
for instance, n for number.
Declare it as an int for its type.
And then, perhaps,
even assign it a value.
Well, what's actually going on when we
use this kind of code in our computer?
Well, let's go ahead and whip
this thing up in a actual program.
Let me create a file
called address.c because I
want to start experimenting with some
addresses in the computer's memory.
I'm going to go ahead and
include standard io dot h.
I'm going to give myself int main void.
And down here, I'm going to
go ahead and declare exactly
that variable, int n equals 50.
And then I'm going to go ahead and print
out, with percent i and a backslash 0,
the value of n.
So nothing interesting there,
nothing too complicated.
I'm going to go ahead and make address.
And then I'm going to go ahead
and do dot slash address.
And of course, as per week
one, we should hopefully
see just the number 50.
But today, we're going to give you some
more tools with which you can actually
start poking around
your computer's memory.
But let's first consider
this line of code
in the context of your
computer's hardware.
So if you're writing a program
with a line of code like this,
that n needs to be somewhere
in your computer's memory.
That 50 needs to be put somewhere
So if we, again, consider this
to be just part of our computer's
memory, a few dozen bytes, well,
suppose that that variable, n,
happens to end up down here.
I've deliberately drawn n as taking up
four bytes, four squares, because we
call that an integer, typically, at
least on CS50 IDE and modern systems,
tends to be four bytes.
So I made sure to have it
fill four complete boxes.
And then value might be 50
that's actually stored there.
Well, it turns out that within
your computer's memory, again,
there are these addresses
that are implicitly there.
So even though, yes, we can
refer to this variable, n,
based on the variable
name I gave it in my code,
surely this variable exists at
a specific location in memory.
I don't know offhand where it is.
But let me just propose that maybe
it's at location 0x12345678, just
an arbitrary address.
I have no idea, in
actuality, where it is.
But it certainly does have an address,
because every one of these squares
inside of your computer's memory has an
address, a unique identifier like 0, 1,
2, and so forth.
Maybe the 50 ended up at
memory address 0x12345678.
Well, that's kind of cool about C, is
that we can actually begin to see this,
no pun intended.
So let me go ahead and
modify this program
and introduce a little
bit of new syntax that
will allow us to start poking around
the inside of your computer's memory
so we can actually see
what's going on underneath.
So I'm going to go ahead and change
this program to do this instead.
I'm going to go ahead
and say, you know what?
Don't just print out the value,
n, which, of course, is 50.
Let me see, just out of curiosity,
what is the actual address of n.
And to do that today, we're going to
introduce one new piece of syntax,
which happens to be this here.
There's two new operators, today, in
C. The first is an ampersand, which
does not represent a logical and.
Recall a couple of weeks
ago, we did see that if you
want to combine Boolean expressions,
this and that, you use two ampersands.
It's an unfortunate coincidence
that an ampersand, solo like this,
will mean something different today.
Specifically, this ampersand is
going to be our address of operator.
By simply prefixing any variable name
with an ampersand, we can tell C,
please tell me what address
this variable is stored in.
And this star, not to be
confused with multiplication,
also has another meaning
in today's context.
When you use this
asterisk, you can actually
tell your program to look inside
of a particular memory address.
So the ampersand tells you
what address a variable is at.
The star operator, otherwise
known as the dereference operator,
means, go to the following address.
So they sort of are reverse operations.
One figures out the address.
One goes to the address.
And so let's see this for real here.
Let me go ahead and change my n
in my program here to ampersand n.
So I want to print out, not the
number in n, but the address of n.
And now, how do I print out an address?
Well, it is just a number.
But actually, printf supports a
different format code for addresses.
You can do percent p, for
reasons we'll soon see,
that says to print out the
address of this variable
and interpret it as hexadecimal,
again, by convention.
So I'm going to go ahead
and make address now
after only making two
changes to this file.
Everything seems to compile OK.
Now, I'm going to go
ahead and run address.
And we will see that, in
this particular program,
address.c, for whatever
reason, that variable, n,
ended up at crazy
location 0x7ffd80792f7c.
Now, is that useful?
Not in practice, necessarily.
We're going to make this become
useful by leveraging these addresses.
But the specific address
is not interesting.
I'm glancing at this number.
I have no idea what that
number is in decimal.
I would have to do the math, or
frankly, just Google a converter
and do it for me.
So again, that's not
the interesting part.
The fact that this is in hexadecimal
is just an implementation detail.
It happens to represent the
location of this variable.
And again, we won't want
to do this, necessarily.
But just to be clear that
one of these operators,
the ampersand gets the address.
And the star operator
goes to an address.
We can actually undo the
effects of these things.
For instance, if I print out now, not
ampersand n, but just out of curiosity,
star ampersand n, I can kind of
undo the effects of this operator.
Ampersand n is going to say,
what is the address of n?
Star ampersand n is going
to say, go to that address.
So this is kind of a pointless exercise,
because if I just want what's in n,
I can just, obviously,
print n like we began.
But again, just as an
intellectual exercise,
if I prefix n with the address of
operator, and then use the asterisk
and say, go to that address,
it's the same exact thing
as just printing n itself.
So let me change the format
code back to an integer.
Instead percent p, let me go
ahead and make address now,
seems to compile OK, and run address.
And voila, we're back at the 50.
So as weird as the syntax
today might start to feel,
realize that these operators,
at the end of the day,
are relatively simple in what they do.
And if you understand that one just
kind of undoes the effects of the other,
can we start to build up some pretty
interesting programs with them.
And we're going to do so by
leveraging a special type of variable,
a variable called a pointer.
And there is that p in percent p.
A pointer is a variable that contains
the address of some other value.
So we've seen integers before.
We've seen floats and chars and
strings and other types as well.
Pointers, now, are just a
different type of variable
that store the address of some value.
And you can have pointers to integers,
pointers to chars, pointers to bools,
or any other data type.
A pointer references the
specific type of the value
that it actually is referring to.
So let's see this more concretely.
Let me go back, now, to my program here.
And let me introduce
another variable here.
Instead of immediately printing out
something like n, let me go ahead
and introduce a second variable
that is of type int star.
And this, I will admit, is probably
the most confusing piece of C syntax
that we'll, in general, see,
just because, my god, star is now
used for multiplication, for going
to an address, and also, now,
declaring a variable.
This is, arguably, not
the best design decision.
But it was made decades ago.
So this is what we have.
But if I do int star p equals ampersand
n, now, what I can do down here,
is print out the address of n by
temporarily storing it in a variable.
So I'm not doing anything new just yet.
I'm still declaring
on line 5, an integer
called n, assigning at the value 50.
What's new now on line 6, is that I'm
introducing a new type of variable.
This type of variable
is known as a pointer.
A pointer, again, is just a variable
that stores the address of some value.
And the syntax, admittedly weird, for
declaring a pointer to an integer,
is literally say int, because
that's the type you're pointing to,
star, and then the name of the
variable you want to create.
And I could call this anything, but
I'll call it p to keep it succinct.
And again, on the right
hand side of the equals sign
is the same operator as before.
If you want to figure out what is the
address of n, it's just ampersand n.
And so we can store that address,
now, somewhere longer-term.
Before, I just passed in ampersand
n and printf did it's thing.
Now, I'm temporarily, on line 6,
storing that address in a new variable
called p.
And its type is technically int
star, is what a programmer might say.
So it would be incorrect to
say int p equals ampersand n.
And indeed, our compiler,
Clang, won't like that.
It won't let you compile
the code, most likely.
And so, instead, I do int star p to
make clear that I know what I'm doing.
I am storing the address of an
int, not an integer, per say.
So if I go ahead, now, and save
this, recompile with make address.
And notice, I changed one
line of code 2 earlier.
I went back to percent p to print
a pointer that is an address.
And I'm pointing out the value
of p, no longer the value of n.
If I now run dot slash address,
voila, there's that cryptic address.
And these addresses may
very well change over time.
Depending on what's going
on inside of your program
or other things on the system, these
addresses might be different each time.
And that's to be expected and
not something to be relied on.
But it's clearly some
random cryptic address,
similar to my arbitrary
0x12345678 before.
But now, let's just undo this operation.
Just so we can come full
circle here, let me now propose
how I can print out the value of n.
And let me call on
someone for this if I can.
If my goal, now, on line 7, is no longer
to print the address of n, but to print
n itself using p.
I'm going to go ahead
and change, preemptively,
the format code to percent i.
And a shorthand notation would,
obviously, be just print n.
But suppose I don't
want to print n for this
exercise, how can I now print the value
in n by referring to it by way of p?
What should I literally type
as printf's second argument
to print out the value of n by using
this new variable, p, in some way.
Yeah, let's call on Joshua.
AUDIENCE: I believe, if you
use the ampersand before the p,
it will probably do it.
DAVID MALAN: OK, ampersand p,
let me go ahead and try that.
Let's try ampersand p
to print out this value.
So ampersand p, I'm
going to save the file.
I'm going to do make address and enter.
And it doesn't seem to be the case.
Notice that I'm getting an error.
It's a little cryptic.
Format specifies type int, but the
argument has type int star star,
more on that another time.
So it turns out this was incorrect.
Let's take one other suggestion,
because the ampersand, recall,
gets the address of something.
But p is already an address.
So Joshua, what you
technically proposed,
was get me the address of the address.
And that's not the
direction we want to go.
We want to go to what
is at that address.
Sophia, what do you think?
AUDIENCE: We want to add a percent--
or a star p when we print it.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
So I had a little trouble hearing you.
But I think if we instead use
not the ampersand operator,
but the star operator,
that's going to be,
indeed, the dereference operator,
which essentially means,
go to the value in p.
And if the value in p is an address,
I think, let's try this, make address.
Yep, that compiled OK this time.
Now, if I do dot slash
address, hopefully, I
will now see, indeed, the number 50.
So again, we don't seem to have
made any fundamental progress.
At the end of the day, I'm still
just printing out the value of n.
But we've introduced this new
primitive, this new puzzle piece,
if you will, that allows
you, programmatically,
to figure out the address of
something in the computer's memory
and to actually go to that address.
And we'll soon see exercise more
sophisticated control over it as well.
But let's come back to a
pictorial representation of this
and consider what it is we just did
in the context, now, of this code.
So inside of my main, the two
interesting lines of code,
really, were these two lines first
before we made Sophia's addition
and actually dereferenced p
and printed it out with printf.
But let's consider, for a
moment, what these values now
look like in a computer's memory.
And again, the syntax
is a little cryptic
because we now have a
star and an ampersand.
But again, that just means,
now, we get to start thinking
in terms of the computer's memory.
So for instance, here's a grid
of memory inside of my computer.
And maybe, for instance, the
50 and the n end up down there.
They could end up anywhere, not
even pictured on the screen here.
They end up somewhere in the computer's
memory, for our purposes thus far.
But it technically lives in an address.
And let me simplify the address
just so it's quicker to say.
This 50, now, stored in the
variable n, maybe it actually
lives at address 0x123.
I have no idea where it
is, but we've clearly
seen that it can live in a
seemingly random address like that.
Now, what about p?
p is technically a variable itself.
It's a variable that stores
the address of something else.
But it's still a variable,
which means, when you declare p
with the code earlier, it actually
does take up some bytes of memory
on the screen.
And so let me go ahead and propose that
p happens to end up in memory here.
Now, p is deliberately
drawn to be longer here.
I'm consuming eight
total bytes this time,
because it turns out, on modern
computer systems, including CS50 IDE,
pointers tend to take up eight bytes.
So not one, not four, but eight bytes,
so I've simply drawn it to be bigger.
So what is actually
stored in the variable p?
Well, it turns out that, again, it's
just storing the address of some value.
So if the integer n, which itself
is storing 50, is at location 0x123,
and pointer p is being assigned
that address, it's just like saying,
well, stored in this variable
p, is literally just a number
represented here in
hexadecimal notation, 0x123.
So that's all that's going on
inside the computer's memory
with those two lines of code.
There's nothing fundamentally
new, except the fact
that we have new syntax with which to
refer to these addresses explicitly.
This is n down here.
This is p up here.
And the value of p just
happens to be an address.
Now, I keep saying that these
addresses are a little cryptic.
They're a little arbitrary.
And they are.
And honestly, it is rarely, if ever,
going to be enlightening to know,
as a human, what address this
integer n is actually at.
Who cares if it's at 0x123 or 0x456?
Generally, we don't.
And so computer scientists, when
talking about computers' memory,
tend not to talk at these low level
details, in terms of actual numbers. ,
Instead, they tend to
simplify the picture,
sort of abstract away all of the
other memory, which frankly, is not
relevant to the discussion
thus far, and just
say, you know what, I know
that p is storing an address.
And that address happens
to be that of 50 down here.
But I really don't care, in
my everyday programming life,
what these specific addresses are.
So you know what?
Let's just abstract it away as an arrow.
And again, abstraction is all about
simplifying lower level details
that you may very well need to
understand but you don't necessarily
need to keep thinking about.
You don't need to keep
thinking at this level.
It suffices to think at this level.
So we might as well draw
a pointer, pictorially,
as pointing at some value
and irrespective of what
the actual address is.
And so this is very much
the case in our human world.
We have very similar
conventions whether or not
it might be obvious
at first glance, such
that we may very well be using these
same mechanisms in our everyday lives.
So for instance, if you happen to have
a mailbox out in the street on your home
or down in the basement of Harvard
Science Center when on campus, it
may very well look like something like
this, at least more residentially.
And suppose that this mailbox here
is representing, in this case, p,
in the story.
It's storing a pointer, that is,
the address of something else.
Well, if there's a whole bunch
of other mailboxes on the street,
well, we can put anything
we want in these mailboxes.
We can put postcards,
letters, packages even.
And just as in the real world,
can we do the same in the virtual.
I can store chars or integers or
other things, including addresses.
So for instance, Brian, I think you
have your own mailbox somewhere else.
And Brian, of course, has a mailbox
that itself has a unique address.
So Brian, for instance, what
happens to be the unique address
of the mailbox on your street there?
BRIAN: Yeah, so here is my mailbox.
It's labeled n.
And its address is over here.
The address of my mailbox
appears to be 0x123.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so my
mailbox, too, has an address.
Frankly, again, I don't
really care about it.
So I've not even put
it on the mailbox here.
But if my mailbox represents p,
a pointer, and Brian's mailbox
represents n, an
integer, well, it should
mean that if I look inside
the contents of my pointer
and I see the value 0x123,
that is now my clue,
a breadcrumb of sorts, that can now let
me go look inside of Brian's mailbox.
And Brian, if you wouldn't
mind doing that for us,
what do you have at that address?
BRIAN: And if I look in my
mailbox at address 0x123,
I have the number 50
inside of this mailbox.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, indeed.
So in this case, he happens
to be storing an int.
But it could be anything else.
And again, we don't typically care
about these specific addresses.
Once you understand the metaphor,
really, we can do something silly
and really just think of this
mailbox as storing a value that's
pointing at Brian's mailbox.
It's some kind of direction drawn
there, pictorially as an arrow,
here as a silly foam finger.
Or if you prefer, a foam Yale finger
pointing, instead, at Brian's mailbox,
just as a sort of breadcrumb leading
us to some other value on the screen.
So when we talk today and
beyond about addresses,
that's all we're talking about.
We humans in the real world have
been using addresses for eons, now,
to uniquely identify our homes
or businesses or the like.
Computers do the exact
same thing at a lower level
using their computer's memory.
So let me pause here to see if there
are any questions on pointers, variables
that store addresses, or
on these new operators,
like the ampersand or
the asterisk, which
now has a new meaning today onward.
Nothing yet.
All right, seeing none,
well, let's consider now,
the same story in the context of
a completely different data type.
Thus far, we've played only with ints.
But consider strings.
We've spent a lot of time on
strings, using encryption with them
and solving implementing electoral
algorithms using user's input.
So let's consider a
fundamentally different data
type that stores, not individual
integers, but strings of text instead.
So for instance, in any
program involving a string,
you might have a line of code that
looks like this. string s equals, quote
unquote, "HI!"
in all caps with an exclamation point.
So that may very well be a line
of code that we've seen thus far.
What's actually going on inside
of the computer's memory?
Well, let me propose that when you type
in quote unquote, "HI!" in a computer,
it ends up somewhere in
your computer's memory.
So HI exclamation point, plus, per last
week, a backslash 0-- or two weeks ago,
a backslash 0, which is how a computer
represents the end of that string.
But let's look a little
more carefully at
what is going on
underneath this hood here.
Technically speaking, I could
address those individual characters
we have seen as of week two, by using
bracket notation like s bracket 0,
s bracket 1, s bracket
2, and s bracket 3.
We use the square bracket
notation to treat a string
as though it's an array of characters.
And it is, it was, and it still is.
But it turns out, strings can also be
manipulated by way of their addresses
as well.
And so for instance, maybe
this same exact string, HI,
is stored at memory address 0x123
and then 0x124, 0x125, and 0x126.
Notice that they're
deliberately contiguous
addresses, back to back to back.
And they're only one byte apart,
because each of these chars, of course,
is just one byte in C.
So those numbers are not
important, specifically.
But the fact that they're one
byte apart from each other
is important, because that's
the definition of a string,
and indeed, an array, to have
memory back to back to back.
Now, what exactly, though, is S?
S was the name of the variable I gave a
moment ago to go to that line of code,
string S equals quote unquote, "HI."
well, what is S?
S is a variable that has to go
somewhere in the computer's memory.
And suppose that S is, indeed,
HI with an exclamation point.
And the HI happens to live
at this location here.
You know what you can
think of S as being now,
isn't, at a high level, a
string, but at a lower level,
it's just the address of a string.
More specifically, let's
start thinking about a string
as technically being just the address
of the first character in the string.
Now, that might give
you pause for a moment,
because why the first character?
How are you going to remember that, wait
a minute, this string isn't at and only
at 0x123.
It also continues at
0x124, 0x125, and so forth.
But let me pause and
ask the group here, why
might it very well be
sufficient for a computer
and us programmers to just think
of strings in terms of being
the address of the very first byte.
Like, why is it sufficient,
no matter how long
the string is, even if it's
a whole paragraph of text,
why is it very cleverly sufficient
to think of a string like S
as just being identical to
the address of the first byte?
Ginni, is it?
AUDIENCE: Possibly because it happens
that strings, whenever we are defining
a new string, that is altogether.
Suppose, if I'm writing my name, Ginni,
so it will be G-I-N-N-I altogether.
So it will be sufficient
if something is pointed
towards just first character
of my name, so that I can just
follow up for the first character and
then get all the characters afterwards.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
So all of these basic definitions
we had over the past couple of weeks
now come together.
If a string is just an
array of characters--
and by definition of array,
those characters are back
to back to back, and per
two weeks ago, every string
ends with this conventional
backslash zero or nul character.
All you need to do when
thinking about a string
is just to know where
does the string begin,
because you can use a
four loop or a while loop
or some other heuristic with a
condition and a Boolean expression
to figure out where the string
ends without even knowing,
in advance, its length.
So that is to say, let's
start, for the moment,
thinking of about strings
as being quite simply
that, just the address of the
first character in the string.
And if we then take that as
fact, let's go ahead, now,
and start playing with a program that
doesn't use integers, but instead,
used strings, using
this basic primitive.
So let me go ahead and delete the
code I'd written before, an address.c.
Let me just change it up to be string
equals quote unquote, "HI" semicolon.
And notice, I'm not manually
typing any backslash 0's.
C does that for us automatically.
When you close the quote,
the compiler takes care
of adding that backslash 0 for you.
Now, I'm going to go
ahead on the next line
and go ahead and print out
percent s backslash n comma s,
if I want to print out that string.
Now, this program is not
at all interesting anymore.
Back in week one, we
wrote something like--
OK, yes it is interesting
because I screwed up.
So five errors.
I've written seven lines
of code and five errors.
And let's see what's going on.
As always, always go to
the top, because odds are,
there's just some
confusing cascading effect.
The very first error I see is use
of undeclared identifier string.
Did I mean standard n?
I didn't mean standard n,
string, string, string.
So I could run help 50 as
my frontier, but honestly, I
make this mistake often
enough that I kind of know now
that I forgot to include cs50.h.
And indeed, if I now do this
and recompile make address--
OK, all five errors are gone
just by that one simple change.
And if I run address now, it's just
going to, quite simply, say HI.
But let's now start to
consider what's going
on underneath the hood of this program.
Suppose I am curious and want
to print out what is actually
the address at which this string lives.
Well, it turns out--
let me be clever here.
Let me print out, not a format
code of percent s, but percent p.
Show me this same string as an address.
Let me go ahead and recompile,
make address, seems to compile OK.
Let me run dot slash address.
And again, I'm still printing
s, but I'm asking printf
to present it as though it's a pointer.
And interesting, it's
not the same as before.
But again, that's reasonable
because the memory addresses
aren't going to always be the same.
But it doesn't matter what it is.
But that's kind of interesting.
All this time, any time
you've been using strings,
had you just changed your
percent s to a percent p,
you could have seen where, in
memory, that string actually starts.
It's not functionally
useful to us just yet.
But it's been there this whole time.
And let me go ahead and
do the following now.
Suppose I get a little curious
further, and I do printf.
Let me go ahead and print out another
address followed by a new line.
And let me go ahead and print out
the address of the first character.
So again, this is a little weird to do.
And we wouldn't typically
do this that often.
But again, just to make the point that
these operators give us very simple
answers to questions like, what
is the address of this thing?
If s bracket i, as of week two in CS50,
represented the second character in s,
because 0 index means s bracket 0 is
the first, s bracket 1 is the second.
If I play around with
today's new operator,
this ampersand, I bet I can see the
address of that second character.
And in fact, let me go
ahead and be more explicit.
Let me change this first s to be s
bracket 0 and put an ampersand here.
And let me go ahead, now, and
make this program, make address.
OK, a little funky--
I just missed a semicolon.
So easy fix there.
Let me go ahead and
recompile with make address.
run dot slash address.
And interesting, well, maybe--
interesting to me.
So you see, now, two
addresses, the first of which
is 0x4006a4, which apparently, is the
address of the first character in s.
But notice what's curious
about the next one.
It's almost the same except
the byte is one further away.
And I bet if I do this, not
just for the h and the i,
but also the exclamation
point-- let me do
one more line of almost
identical code, just
to make the point that all
this time it's, indeed,
been the case that all characters in
a string are back to back to back.
And you can now see it in code.
b4, b5, b6, are just one byte apart.
So we see some visual confirmation,
now, that strings are indeed
laid out in memory just like this.
Now, again, this is not a very
useful programmatic exercise
to look at the address
of individual characters.
But again, this is just to
emphasize that underneath the hood,
some relatively simple
operations are being
enabled by way of this new ampersand,
and in turn, star operator.
So let's consider for a
moment what this really looks
like inside the computer's memory.
At a low level, yes, s is
technically an address.
And yes, it's technically the
address of the first byte,
which in the actual
computer, looked different.
But in my slide here, I
just arbitrarily proposed
that it's at 0x123, 0x124, 0x125.
But again, let's not care
about that level of detail.
Let's just kind of wave our hands
and abstract away these addresses
and just now start thinking of s, that
is a string, as technically just being
a pointer.
A pointer.
So it turns out that even though
it's very useful and very common
to think of strings as, obviously,
just being sequences of characters.
And that's been true since week one.
And you can also think
of them as arrays,
back to back sequences of characters.
You can also, it turns
out, starting today,
think of them as just
being pointers, that is,
the address of a character
somewhere in the computer's memory.
And as Ginni notes, because all
of the characters in a string
are, by definition,
back to back to back,
and because, by definition, all
strings end with a backslash 0, that
is literally the smallest and
only amount of information
you need to keep around in a computer
to know where all of your strings are.
Just remember the address
of the very first character
therein, because you can
find your way to the end
by remembering that this backslash
0 is, really, just eight 0
bits, otherwise
represented as backslash 0.
And so we could certainly
have an if condition,
much like we did two weeks
ago when playing around
with the lengths of strings, that
allows us to check for precisely that.
And so when I say we're taking off
some training wheels, here they go.
So up until now, we've been
using, again, the CS50 library,
which gives us, conveniently,
functions like get string and get int
and get float and so forth.
But all this time, the CS50 library,
specifically the file, cs50.h,
had a little bit of a
pedagogical simplification in it.
Recall last week, that you can
define your own custom data types.
Well, it turns out that all this time,
we've been claiming that strings exist
and they're something you
can use in your programs.
And strings do exist in C. They do
exist in Python, in JavaScript, in Java,
and C++, in many, many,
many other languages.
This is not a CS50 term.
But string, technically, does not
exist as a data type in C. It instead,
is more cryptically and more
low-level known as char star.
Char star, now what does that mean?
Well, char star, much like our
int star a few minutes ago,
just represents the address of
a character, much like int star
represents the address of an int.
And if, again, you kind
of agree with me now,
that you can think of strings
as sequences of characters,
or more specifically, arrays of
characters, or more specifically,
as of today, the address of
just the first character,
then it's, indeed, the
case that we now can
apply this new terminology,
today, of pointer,
to our old familiar friends, strings.
String is the same thing as a
synonym, if you will, for char star.
And it's in the CS50 library that
we, essentially, have a line of code
that simplifies or abstracts away char
star, which honestly, no one wants
to think about or struggle with
in the first week of a class,
let alone the first two
or three weeks of a class.
It's a simplification, a custom
data type, that we name string,
just so you don't have to
think about, what is this star?
What is it to the character?
What is it an address of?
But today, we can remove those training
wheels and reveal that, all this time,
you've just been manipulating
characters at specific addresses.
And we've used this kind
of technique before,
abstracting away these
lower level details.
For instance, recall last
week, that we introduced
this notion of a struct, a data type
that you can customize to be your own.
We implemented a better phone
book by wrapping together
a name and a number inside
of a custom data type,
encapsulating them if you will,
inside of something we called person.
And every person we
claimed had a structure
that contains a name and a number.
And by the way of this feature of C,
typedef, we can define a new type.
And the name of that type,
last week, was just person.
So we're using, already, and
we have been sort of secretly
using since the first week of C
in the class, a line of code that
actually looks like this.
And this is, indeed, one of the
lines of code inside of cs50.h.
It says typedef, which
means give me a custom type.
And it creates a synonym
for char star called string.
And it's just a way where we
can hide the funky char star.
We can hide the asterisk, in
particular, which would not
be fun to play with
in the first few days,
but without changing the
definition of what a string is.
So strings exist in C. But there's
no data type called string in C
until you use a library like
CS50's, which makes it exist
by way of that kind of definition.
All right, let me pause
here to see if there's
any questions, then,
about what strings are
or these new ways of
thinking about them.
Any questions about
strings or char stars?
All right, well, if
no questions here, why
don't we go ahead and take
our 5 minute break here first.
And we'll be back in 5
and take another look
at what we can now do
with these new primitives.
All right, we're back.
And we have, now, this ability in code
to get the address of some variable
and also to go to an
address using ampersand
and the asterisk, respectively.
We've thought about strings as
being not only contiguous sequences
of characters, but also arrays.
And then of course, as of
today now, actual addresses,
the address of the first
character and then, from there,
can we find our way,
programmatically, to the end,
thanks to that nul character.
But it turns out there's one other
thing we can do with these addresses
or with pointers more generally.
And that's known as pointer arithmetic.
So anything that's a number,
of course, we can do math on.
And the math is not
going to be complicated,
but it is going to be
powerful for us here.
So I'm going to go back to my
most recent state of address.c.
And let me go ahead, now, and
reiterate that we can print out
the individual characters in a string,
just like we did back in week two,
as by using our square bracket notation.
So I'm getting rid of all evidence
of those addresses for now.
I'm recompiling this
program as make address.
And then I'm going to run
dot slash address now.
And I see HI exclamation
point, one character per line.
But now, consider that there doesn't
need to be a string data type.
In fact, we can take
this training wheel off.
And while it might feel a
little uncomfortable at first,
if I delete this first line altogether,
as I've accidentally omitted anyway
sometimes, I don't need to
keep calling things strings.
I can describe them as strings verbally.
I can think of them as
strings, because string
is a thing in many different
programming languages.
But by default, in C, it
just doesn't exist as a type.
Instead, the type is somewhat
cryptically named, char star.
But again, all that means is
that the star means here's
the address of something.
Char means it's the address of a char.
So char star gives
you a pointer variable
that's going to point to a character.
So now, if s is that, I can
actually treat it the same.
There's no reason I can't keep using
s like a string was back in week two,
using our square bracket notation.
And I can keep printing
out HI exclamation point
using that same square bracket syntax.
But there's one other way I can do this.
If I now know that s is
really just an address,
I can get rid of this
square bracket notation.
And I can actually just do star s,
because recall that star, in addition
to being the new symbol that we use
when declaring a pointer up here,
it's also the same symbol,
confusingly, admittedly,
that we used to go to an address.
So if s is storing an address, which
it is by definition of being a pointer,
star s means go to that address.
And per my picture
earlier, it would seem
to be the case that s is most likely
at an address beginning at 0x123.
It's not going to be the
same in my actual IDE here.
It will be whatever the
computer has ordained.
But it's going to be
the same exact idea.
So let me go ahead and go to star s.
And just for kicks, let me
leave it as just that one line.
So let me go ahead and
rerun this as make address.
All right, and now dot slash address.
I should see, hopefully, a capital
H and only an H. But watch this.
If I know that s, a string, is
technically just an address,
I can actually now do math on it.
And I can go ahead and print out another
character, followed by a new line.
And I can go to, not s,
but how about s plus 1.
So I can do some very simple arithmetic,
if you will, on that pointer.
And let me go ahead
and now recompile this.
So make address, compiles
OK, dot slash address.
And I should see HI.
And if I do one more line of code like
this, printf, percent c, backslash n,
star s plus 2, I can
now go to the character
that is two bytes away
from whatever s is,
which again, is the start of the string.
So now, I've reprinted HI with
the exclamation point character
by character, but not by using
this fancy square bracket
notation, fancy only in the sense that
it was sort of an abstraction for us,
if you will.
I'm instead, manipulating s for what
it really is, which is just an address.
And so here, too, and I've
used this phrase before,
that square bracket notation
that we introduced in week two,
is technically just syntactic sugar.
It's not doing anything
fundamentally different
from these asterisks
and these addresses.
It's just doing it, honestly, in
a much more user-friendly way.
I still prefer, personally, the
square bracket notation from week two.
But it's the same thing as using the
star and doing this math yourself.
So C is just providing us
with this handy feature
of using square brackets that
does all of this so-called pointer
arithmetic for you.
But again, we're going
to this low level just
to emphasize what it is that's going
on ultimately underneath the hood here.
All right, let me pause
here for any questions.
And Brian, please do feel free
to verbalize any on your end.
BRIAN: I see a question that
came in about what would happen
if you tried to print star s plus 3.
DAVID MALAN: So I'm pretty sure that's
going to print out the nul character.
But let's go ahead and
confirm as much here,
percent c backslash n star s plus 3.
All right, I'm getting a
little adventurous here
by looking at things I maybe shouldn't
be looking at, because that's
a low level implementation detail.
But let's see what happens.
It compiles OK, dot slash address.
And it seems to be blank.
Now, maybe that's the nul character.
Honestly, it's not meant to
be a printable character.
It's this special sentinel value
that indicates the end of the string.
But I could do this.
I know from week two
that chars are integers
and integers are chars if I
want to think of them that way.
So let me change only
the very last character
to use the format code percent i.
Let me recompile my code.
Let me go ahead and run address.
And voila, HI exclamation 0.
And there is the all 0 bits represented
here as one single decimal digit thanks
to percent i.
Now, I can get really crazy here.
And why don't we go ahead and
print out not just what characters
are right after this sequence, HI
exclamation point nul character,
why don't we go to-- oh heck, how
about address 1,000 bytes away,
and really get nosy
inside of my computer?
Let me recompile that dot slash address.
OK, nothing really going on over there.
How about 10,000 bytes away?
Let me go ahead and make address.
Let me go ahead and run this
segmentation fault. All, right
that's bad.
And you might be among the fortunate
few who have seen this error before
by touching memory you shouldn't.
And we're going to deliberately
consider this today.
But a segmentation fault, indeed,
means that you have done something
wrong somewhere in your code.
And it tends to mean that you
touched a segment of memory
that you shouldn't have.
And I have no business, honestly,
looking 10,000 bytes away
from the memory that I
know belongs to the string.
That's like arbitrarily looking
anywhere in your computer's memory,
which probably, it seems,
is not a good idea.
But more on that in just a bit.
So let's consider, now,
some of the implications
of these underlying
implementation details
and consider, now, from last week,
why we did a few things the way
we did in the past few weeks, in fact.
So string is just a char star.
And let's, now, consider an example.
Let me zoom out on my memory, just
so I can cram more in at once.
Let's consider an example
where I might want to write
a program that compares two strings.
Let me go ahead and write some new
code here in a new file this time,
called, for instance, compare.c.
My goal with this
program, quite simply, is
going to be to print out the
contents of-- or rather to compare
two strings that the user might input.
I'm going to go ahead
and include cs59.h,
not because I want
string, per say, anymore,
but because I want to use get
string just for convenience.
But we'll take that training
wheel off in a bit, too.
And in this program, I'm
going to go ahead and first
use, not get string yet.
Let me go ahead and keep it
simple and start with get int.
And I'll ask the user for a variable i.
And let me do another one
of these in get int and ask
the user for a value for j.
And then let me go ahead and quite
simply say, if i equals equals j,
then go ahead and print out same else.
Let me go ahead and print out different.
So this is week one stuff, where
I'm using a couple of variables.
I'm using a condition
with two branches, and I'm
using printf to print out whether those
two variables, i and j, are the same.
So let's go ahead and compile this.
All is well.
Run compare, and let me
give it digits 1 and 2.
And indeed, they're different.
And let me go ahead and give it
1 and 1, and they're the same.
So I think, logically, proof
by example, if you will,
this program looks correct.
But let me quickly make it seemingly
uncorrect, by not using integers.
But how about, by using strings instead.
Let me go ahead and
give myself a string.
Although, no, I don't need
that training wheel anymore.
Let's just do char star
s equals get string of s.
But again, even though
I'm calling it char star,
it's still a string
like it was weeks ago.
Let me give myself another string
called t, just to keep the name short.
And s will get--
t will get that value there.
And let me just, very naively
but kind of reasonably,
say if s equals equals t, let's
go ahead and print out same.
And otherwise, let's go ahead
and print out different.
So same exact code, just
different data types, and using
get string instead of get int.
Let me go ahead and make compare,
seems to compile OK, dot slash compare.
Let me go ahead and type in HI!--
woops, HI!.
Let me go ahead and type in HI! again.
And voila, different.
And I forgot my backslash n's, but that
seems to be the least of my problems.
Let me recompile this, make compare,
and now, let me run it again.
How about, let's do a quick test.
David, Brian, these are
definitely different.
OK, good.
So the program seems to work.
How about David, David?
Also different.
Huh, let me try again.
Brian, Brian, also different.
But I'm pretty sure those
strings are the same.
Why might this program be flawed?
What is wrong with
this program right now?
BRIAN: A couple of
people in the chat are
saying that we're not actually
comparing the characters,
we're comparing the addresses.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so that's sort of
the logical conclusion from today's
definition of what a string really is.
If a string is just the
address of its first character,
then if you're literally
doing s equals equals t,
you're comparing those two addresses.
And they are probably
going to be different,
even if I type in the same
thing, because every time we've
called get int or get string, it's
kind of plopped the user's input
somewhere in my computer's memory.
But we now have the tools, honestly,
to answer this or vet this answer
ourselves.
Let me go ahead and
simplify this program.
And let's, just as a quick
sanity check, print out s.
And let's go ahead and print out
t using a new line after each,
just so we can see what the strings are.
So let me go ahead and do this again,
make compare, compiles OK, dot slash
compare.
Let me type in HI, HI.
And they seem to be visually the same.
But recall that, now, I
have this other format code,
such that I can now
start treating strings
as the addresses they technically are.
So let me change percent s
to percent p in both places.
Let me then recompile the program, and
now, rerun compare with both HI and HI
identically typed.
But notice, they've ended up at
slightly different memory locations.
Even though I have coincidentally
typed the same thing, C and my computer
are not going to be so presumptuous as
to use the same bytes for both strings.
That's not going to
give me much flexibility
if I want to change one or the other.
It's going to very simplistically
put one in this chunk of memory
and the other in this chunk of memory.
And indeed, those addresses are
respectively, but arbitrarily,
0x22fe670 and 0x22fe6b0.
So they are spread apart some distance.
But again, it's up to the computer to
decide where to actually put those.
So what's actually going on
inside of the computer's memory?
Well, let's consider if, for instance,
this is s, my pointer, or really,
my string.
But it's just a pointer now.
It's the address of something.
Notice that I've drawn it
as taking up eight squares,
because again, a pointer on
modern systems is eight bytes.
So that's why this thing is so big.
Meanwhile, when I type in something
like HI with the exclamation point,
then it ends up somewhere in memory.
We don't really know
or care where it is.
So let's just arbitrarily say
it happens to end up there
in my computer's memory.
Now, each of those bytes,
of course, has an address.
I don't necessarily know
or care what they are.
But for explanation's sake, let's
just number them again like before,
0x123, 0x124, 0x125, 0x126.
When I then assign s on the left the
value from get string on the right,
get string, what is it going to do?
Well, all of this time since week
one, since you've been using it,
it is, yes, getting a string and handing
it back to you as a return value.
But what does that really mean?
Well, if a string is just an address,
the return value of a function
like get string is to return to, not
the string per se, because that's
kind of a high level concept.
What get string has
always been doing for us
is returning the address
of the string, or more
specifically, the address of the
first character in the string.
And so what is technically stored in
s, to be clear, is that address, 0x123.
It's not returning to the whole string,
the H, the I, the exclamation point.
Rather, it's returning
just one value to you.
It's returning only to you the address
of the first character of that string.
But again, this is all
very good for just s.
What's going on with t?
t is kind of the same story, because
I'm calling get string again.
t is going to get assigned the
address of the first character
of this version of HI.
And let's just arbitrarily say it's
at 0x456, 0x457, 0x458, and 0x459.
And at this point, t is going
to take on the value of 0x456.
And now, at this point, honestly,
we're really getting into the weeds.
Let's just start
abstracting all of this away
and use arrows to point at the values.
And indeed, these arrows
just represent pointers
when we stop caring about
the particular addresses.
So s is really just a
pointer, a variable pointing
at the first character of HI here.
t is just a variable pointing at
the first character of HI there.
And so when you are
comparing two strings
as I was before in the
earlier version of my program,
where I was checking if s equals equals
t, I was, indeed, comparing s and t.
What are s and t?
s and t, respectively,
are 0x123 and 0x456,
or whatever the actual
values happen to be,
which are not going to be
the same because they happen
to point to different chunks of memory.
All right, well who cares?
This is all kind of a nice
intellectual exercise.
But who cares?
Well, how do we solve this problem?
Let's consider what I actually
did in a previous demo.
I sort of preemptively mentioned that
there's this function, string compare,
that allows you to compare two strings.
And I promised that we
would eventually explain
why we use str compare as opposed
to just using the equal equal sign.
Well, to use this function,
I'm going to need to add
in string.h up here per lat time.
But if string compare s t, let
me go ahead and recompile this,
compare dots slash compare.
Now, let me type HI!
and HI! identically.
Now, they still seem to be different.
And dammit, I made the same
stupid mistake as I did last time.
Does anyone know what mistake I
made when comparing two strings?
Somehow I seem to be very
good at making this mistake.
BRIAN: Ibrahim is suggesting
that you add an equal equal zero.
DAVID MALAN: Thank you.
Ibrahim is quite right.
The return value,
recall, of str compare,
is to return 0 if they're the same,
a negative number if one comes
before the other, and a positive
number if one comes after the other,
as in ASCIIbetical order.
So what I should have done,
both last time and this time,
is check for equality with 0.
Let me go ahead and
recompile this program.
OK, good.
Now, let me rerun this program with HI!
twice.
Voila, they're the same.
And just to make sure,
let me do one other check.
Let me do David and Brian, which
should be, indeed, different.
So now, again, I haven't really done
anything different from that last time.
But I'm now thinking about these
strings as being fundamentally just
their addresses.
And so, now, let's make
this actually germane.
Let me go ahead and create
a new file altogether.
And let's, pretty reasonably, try to
copy one string and make changes to it.
So I'm going to go ahead here.
And just for convenience, I'm going
to still use the CS50 library,
not for the string data
type, but just for the
get string function, which we'll see
is more handy than other things--
than other ways of doing things.
And I'm going to go ahead and
include standard io dot h.
include, how about, string.h.
Let me go ahead and do int main void.
And let me go ahead, in this
program, and get myself a string.
But note, we won't
call it string anymore.
We'll just call it char star.
So again, start taking
off that training wheel.
And I'm going to go ahead
and get a string called s.
And then I'm going to
get another string.
But I won't call it that.
I'll call it char star t.
And I want to copy s.
And so you might think, based on week
one, week two, and since, that OK,
if you want to copy a
variable, just do it.
I mean, we've used the
assignment operator
to copy a variable from right
to left for integers, for chars,
and for other data types, perhaps, too.
I'm going to go ahead, now, and make
a change to the original string.
So let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and say, let's
change the first character of t
to be uppercase.
Recall that there's
this function, to upper,
which takes, as input, a character,
like the first character in t,
and returns the uppercase version.
Now, to use to upper, I
need another header file,
which I recall from a couple of
weeks ago now, I need ctype.h.
So let me preemptively go
back and put that there.
And now, let me go ahead
and print these two strings.
Let me go ahead and print out
s as being this percent s.
And let me go ahead and print out the
value of t with percent s as follows.
So again, what I'm doing is I'm
getting a string from the user.
And the only new thing here is char star
today, which is synonymous with string.
On line 10 here, I'm copying
the string from right to left.
And then I'm capitalizing
only the first letter
in the copy, otherwise known as t.
And then I'm just printing both out.
So let me go ahead and
make copy, compiles OK.
Make cop-- dot slash copy.
Let me go ahead and type in hi!
in lowercase, all lowercase,
and then enter.
And voila, huh.
It would seem that I somehow capitalized
both S and T, even though I only
called to upper on T.
Brian, any thoughts
from the group on why I've accidentally
and erroneously capitalized
both somehow?
BRIAN: A couple of people are
saying that t is just an alias of s.
DAVID MALAN: Just an alias of s, that's
a reasonable way of thinking of it,
sure.
And more precisely, any other thoughts
on why this is incorrect somehow?
BRIAN: Peter is now suggesting
that they have the same address.
DAVID MALAN: So yeah, more specifically,
all I've done is copy s into t.
But again, what is s as of today?
It's just an address.
So yes, I have copied s.
But I've copied it literally, which
means copying its address, 0x123,
or whatever it is.
And then on line 12, notice that
I'm changing t by uppercasing it.
But t is at the same address of s.
So really, I'm changing
one in the same string.
So if we think about this in
terms of the computer's memory,
let's consider what I've just done.
Let me clear the computer's memory.
Let me put s down as before.
Let me put hi! down as before,
but all lowercase this time.
And recall that it might be it
addresses 0x123, 124, 125, and 126.
And now, if we consider
that s technically
contains the address of
that first character, 0x123,
and I proceed to create a new variable,
t, and assign t the value of s,
I got to take that statement literally.
I'm literally just putting 0x123 here.
And if we now abstract
away these details just
to make it more clear
visually what's going on,
that's pretty much like
saying that both s and t point
to the same location in memory.
So yes, in that sense, t
is just an alias for s,
which is a reasonable
way of thinking of it.
But really, just t is identical to s.
So when you use the
square bracket notation
to go to the first character
of t, you are equivalently
going to the first character in s.
They are one in the same.
So when I call to upper, I'm calling it
on this character, which of course, is
the one and only h in the story.
And when I print s and
I print t, printf is
following those same
breadcrumbs, if you will,
and ultimately displaying the
same value as having changed.
So we would seem to need
to fundamentally rethink
how we are copying strings.
And let me ask, if this is the wrong way
to copy one string into the other, what
is the right way?
Even if you don't have the functions
in mind or the right vocabulary,
just intuitively, , if we want to copy
a string in the way that a human would
think of copying one into the other,
like a photograph or a photocopy,
how do we want to do this?
Any thoughts, Brian?
BRIAN: Yeah, Sophia suggested we
would want to somehow loop over
the elements in s and put them into t.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, I like that.
So loop over the elements
of s and put them into t.
So it sounds like more work.
But that's, again, what
we're going to have
to do if we want to think of these--
if we want to accept the fact that these
things, s and t, are just addresses,
we're going to now have to go
and follow those breadcrumbs.
So let's go ahead and consider
a variant of this program.
Let me go ahead, here, and change this
such that I'm still getting a string s.
But now, let me go ahead
and propose exactly that,
that we copy the individual characters.
But I need to copy them somewhere.
So I feel like another step in
this process of copying a string
has to be to give myself
some additional memory.
If I have H i exclamation
point in nul character,
I need to, now, somehow take
control of this situation
and tell the computer somehow, in
code, give me four more bytes of memory
so that I have location for t in
which to copy those characters.
So here's a new function today.
If I want to create a string t,
otherwise known today as a char star,
there is a new function we
can use called malloc, which
represents memory allocation.
This is a pretty fancy function that,
fortunately, is pretty simple to use.
It takes, as input, just a number.
How many bytes of memory do you
want to ask the computer for?
So how do I do this?
Well, H i exclamation point backslash
0, I could literally just say four.
But this doesn't feel very dynamic.
I think I can programmatically
implement this a little more elegantly.
Let me go ahead and say,
give me as many bytes
as there are characters in s plus 1.
Plus 1, why am I doing this?
Well, H i exclamation point nul
character, that's technically
what's stored underneath the hood.
But what do you and I think
of the length of Hi! as being?
Well, odds are, in the human
world, it's H i exclamation point.
And who cares about this low
level detail, this nul terminator.
You don't include that in the length
of an English word or any word.
You only think of the actual
characters you can see.
So the length of H, i,
exclamation point 3.
But I do need to cleverly add one more
bite, a fourth, for the nul character,
because I'm going to have
to copy that over as well.
Otherwise, if I don't have
an identical nul character,
t is not going to have
an obvious ending.
So how do I copy, now,
one string into the other?
Well, let me go ahead and take
out our old friend, the for loop,
from week one.
And say, for i equals 0--
how about, actually, n
equals string length of s.
We've done this trick before.
i is less than n, i++.
Let me go ahead and, quite simply,
say t bracket i gets s bracket i.
So this will literally copy, from s,
each of the characters one at a time
into t.
But I need to be a little smarter now.
Even though we almost
always do i less than n,
I'm actually going to very aggressively
say i less than or equal to n.
Why?
Why am I going one step
further than I feel we normally
do when iterating over strings,
and one step further than you
probably did when iterating
over a caesar cipher or a string
in that context?
Brian, any thoughts here?
Why am I going from i less than or equal
to n kind of for the first time here?
BRIAN: Celina is suggesting that we
need to include the nul character.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so if I-- and
now I understand how strings works.
So it's not sufficient to just
copy the H, I, exclamation point.
I need to go one step further, one
more than the length of the string.
And the easiest way to do that
would be less than or equal to n.
Or I could just do a plus 1 there.
Or I can do this any number of ways.
Doesn't matter how you do it.
But I think a less than or equal
to is one reasonable way to do it.
And now, let's go down to the
bottom here and now actually
do this capitalization.
Let's now change the
first character in t
to be the result of calling to
upper on the first character of t.
And then, as before, let's go
ahead and print out whatever s is.
And like before, let's
go ahead and print out
whatever t is and hope now that
only t has been capitalized.
But I do need to make one change now.
It turns out that this
function, malloc, comes
in a file called standard lib dot h.
And again, this is the kind of thing
that you can jot down in notes.
You can always Google
these kinds of things.
Even I forget what header files these
functions are sometimes declared in.
But it happens to be a new one
called standard lib for library
that gives you access to malloc.
So let me go ahead,
now, and make compare.
All right, so far so good.
Dot slash compare-- sorry,
this is not compare.
The old program works fine.
Make copy-- oh my god, seven mistakes.
What'd I do wrong here?
Oh, it looks like I forgot
the type of i and n.
So let me go into my for
loop and add the int.
That was my fault. Let
me make copy again.
OK, all seven errors,
thankfully, went away.
Make copy, let's go ahead and type
in hi! in lower case and hit Enter.
And voila, now I have capitalized
only the copy of s, a.k.a.
t.
And just to be clear, I've
kind of regressed back
to my square bracket notation, honestly,
because it's perfectly acceptable.
It's very readable.
But notice, if I really
want to show off,
I could say something like,
well, go to t's plus i location.
And then do this, which again, I don't
necessarily recommend for readability.
But again, there is this equivalence.
The square bracket notation is the
same thing as pointer arithmetic.
So if you want to go to the address at
t plus whatever i is to offset yourself
one or more bytes, you
can totally do that.
And if I want to be fancy,
I can go down here and say,
go to the first character
in t and capitalize it.
But again, I would argue that even
though, yes, you're very clever
and that you understand pointers
and addresses at this point
if you're writing code like this.
Honestly, it's not
necessarily as readable.
So sticking with week two syntax of
the square bracket notation, totally
reasonable, totally correct, totally
well-designed, and perhaps preferable,
though I should be careful here.
This line of code is a
little bit risky for me
because what if the user just
hits Enter and they don't type hi
or David or Brian.
What if they type nothing except Enter?
In that case, the length
of the string might be 0.
And then I probably shouldn't
capitalizing the first character
in a string that doesn't
really even exist.
So I should probably
have some error checking,
like if, for instance, the string
length of t is at least greater than 0,
then go ahead and safely do that.
But again, this is just one
example of some additional error
checking I can add to the program.
There's actually one more
piece of error checking
I should really do in a
fully correct program,
as you should do in problem sets.
Sometimes things can go wrong.
And if your program is so big,
so fancy, and so memory-hungry
that you're mallocing
lots and lots of memory,
which you won't do in
the program this small,
but over time you might
need more and more memory,
we should also make sure that
t actually has a valid address.
It turns out that
malloc, most of the time,
is going to return to you the
address of a chunk of memory
it has allocated for you.
Just like get string,
it will return to you
the address of the first
byte of the chunk of memory
that it has found space for.
However, sometimes things can go wrong.
Sometimes your computer
can be out of memory.
You've probably seen your Mac or
PC freeze or hang or reboot itself.
That is very often the
result of memory errors.
So we should actually
check something like this.
If t equals equals
this special value nul,
then I'm going to go ahead and
just bail out and return one,
quit, let's get out of the program.
It's not going to work.
This might only happen one
out of a million times.
But it's more correct to check for nul.
Now, unfortunately, the designers
of C kind of used-- or programmers
more generally, use this word,
which is almost the same as N-U-L,
otherwise known as backslash 0.
Unfortunately, this
is a different value.
N-U-L-L represents a nul pointer.
It is a bogus address.
It is the absence of an address.
Technically, its address 0.
It is different from backslash 0.
You use N-U-L-L in the context of
pointers, as we are doing today.
You use backslash 0,
otherwise known verbally,
as an N-U-L, or nul, in
the context of characters.
So backslash 0 is for characters.
N-U-L-L in all caps is for pointers.
And it's just a new symbol
we're introducing today
that comes with this
standard lib dot h file.
All right, so it turns out, honestly,
I don't need to do some of this work.
It turns out that if I want
to copy one string to another,
there is a function for that.
And increasingly, you will not
have to write as many lines of code
as you previously did, because if
you look up in the manual pages
or you've heard about or find online
that there's another function, like one
called strcpy, you can actually,
more simply, do something like this.
So even though I really liked the idea,
and it was correct to use a for loop
to copy all of the characters from s
into t, there's a function for that.
It's called strcpy.
It takes two arguments, the
destination followed by the source.
And it will just handle
all of the looping
for us, all of the copying for
us, including the backslash 0,
so that I can focus on what I
want to do, which in this case,
is actually capitalize things.
So if we consider, now, this example,
in the context of my computer's memory,
we'll see that it's laid
out a little differently.
But there's one more bug
I do want to fix first.
And this is something
we've not had to do yet.
It turns out that any time you
allocate memory with malloc,
you ask the computer for memory,
the onus is on you, the programmer,
to eventually give it back.
And by that, I mean if
you allocate four bytes,
or who knows, four million bytes of
memory for an even bigger program,
you'd better give it back to
the computer, more specifically,
the operating system, be it
Linux or Mac OS or Windows,
so that your computer eventually
doesn't run out of memory.
If all you ever do is ask for
more memory, ask for more memory,
it stands to reason that eventually your
computer will run out, because it only
has a finite amount of memory.
It's got a finite amount
of hardware recall.
So when you're done with memory,
it should be your best practice
to free it afterward as well.
And the opposite of malloc is just
a function called free, which takes,
as its input, whatever
the output of malloc was.
And recall that the output of
malloc, the return value of malloc,
is just the address of the first byte
of memory that it has allocated for you.
So if you ask it for four bytes, like
I did a few lines ago with malloc,
you're going to get back the
address of the first of those bytes.
And it's up to you to remember
how many bytes you asked for.
In the case of free,
all you have to do is
tell free via its input what the
address was that malloc gave you.
So if you stored that address as
I did, in this variable called t,
it suffices when you're done with
that memory just called free t.
And the computer will go about
freeing up that memory for you.
And you might very well
get it back later on.
But at least your computer
won't run out of memory
as quickly, because it can now
reuse that space for something else.
All right, let me go
ahead, then, and propose
that we draw a picture of this--
now new program's memory,
where we copy things.
So recall, this is where we left off
before when comparing two strings.
If this was s and s was pointing to
h, i, exclamation point in lowercase,
this new version of my
code in copy.c, notice,
still gives me another pointer called t.
So that part of the
story hasn't changed.
But I call malloc now.
And malloc is going to return
to me some new chunk of memory.
I don't know in advance where it is.
But malloc's return value
is going to be the address
of the first bite of that memory.
So for instance, 0x456
or whatever it is.
And the subsequent bytes are
going to be increasing by one
byte at a time, 0x457, 0x458, 0x459.
So what is, ultimately, stored in t when
I assign it the return value of malloc?
It's whatever that address is.
Again, I could technically
write 0x456 up here.
But again, we're kind of past that.
That's very 30 minutes ago.
Let's now focus on just the
abstraction that is a pointer.
A pointer is just an arrow
pointing from the variable
to the actual location in memory.
So now, if I go about copying s into
t using strcpy, or more manually,
using my for loop, what happens?
Well, I'm copying the
h over from s into t.
I'm copying the i over from s into t,
the exclamation point from s into t.
And then lastly, the terminating
nul character from s into t.
So the picture is now
fundamentally different.
t is not pointing at the same thing.
It's pointing at its own chunk of
memory that has now, one step at a time,
been duplicating whatever
was at the address s.
And so this is what you and I as
humans would consider, presumably,
to be a proper copy of the program.
Any questions, then, on what we've just
done by introducing malloc and free?
The first of which allocates
memory and gives you
the address of the first byte
of memory that you can now use,
the latter of which hands it back
to your operating system and says,
I'm done with this.
It can now be reused for something
else, some other variable,
maybe, down the road, if
our program were longer.
Brian, any questions or
confusion I can help with?
BRIAN: Someone asked, even
if you're using strcpy
to copy the string instead of copying
the characters one at a time yourself,
do you still need to free the memory?
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
Even if you're using strcpy,
you do need to still use free.
Yes, anytime you use malloc
henceforth, you must use free.
Anytime you use malloc, you must use
free in order to free up that memory.
strcpy is copying the contents of
one chunk of memory to the other.
It is not allocating or
managing that memory for you.
It is just implementing,
essentially, that for loop.
And it's, perhaps, time too, where I
can take off another training wheel
verbally.
It turns out that get string, all
this time, is kind of magical.
One of the things that get
string does from the CS50 library
is it itself uses malloc.
Consider, after all, when we, the
staff, wrote get string years ago,
we have no idea how long your
names are going to be this year.
We have no idea what
sentences you're going
to type, what paragraphs you're going to
type, what text you're going to analyze
for a program like readability.
So we had to implement
get string in such a way
that you can type as few or as
many characters at your keyboard
as you want.
And we will make sure there's
enough memory for that string.
So get string, underneath the hood,
if you look at the code we, the staff,
wrote someday, you'll
see that we use malloc.
And we call malloc in order to get
enough memory to fit that string.
And then, what the CS50
library is also secretly doing,
is it is also calling free for you.
There's, essentially,
a fancy way where you
can write a program that, as soon
as main is about to quit or return
to your blinking prompt,
some special code
we wrote swoops in at that final
moment, frees any of the memory
that we, the library,
allocated so that you
don't run out of memory because of us.
But you all, when
using malloc, will have
to call free, because the library
is not going to do that for you.
And indeed, the goal of today
and next week and beyond
is to stop using the CS50
library, ultimately, altogether.
All right, well let's-- it
would be unfair, I think,
if we introduced all of these fancy
new techniques but don't necessarily
provide you with any sort of tools with
which to determine to chase down bugs
in your new fancy code
or solve problems, now,
that are related to memory.
And thankfully, there
are programs via which
you can chase down memory-related bugs.
This is in addition to
printf, that function,
and help50 and check50 and debug50
and debuggers more generally.
This program-- and it's really the last
of the new tools we'll introduce you
to in C-- is called valgrind.
And this is a program
that exists in CS50 IDE.
But it exists on Macs and
PC's and Linux computers
anywhere, where you can
run it on your own code
to detect if you're doing
anything wrong with memory.
What might you do wrong with memory?
Well, previously, remember, I
triggered that segmentation fault.
I touched memory that I should not.
Valgrind is a tool that
can help you figure out,
where did you touch memory
that you shouldn't have,
so as to focus your own human
attention on whatever lines of code
might be buggy.
Valgrind grant can also detect
if you forget to call free.
If you call malloc one or more
times, but don't call free
a corresponding number
of times, valgrind
is a program that can notice
that and tell you that you have
what's called a memory leak.
And indeed, this is germane
to our own Macs and PCs.
Again, if you've been using
your Mac or PC or sometimes
even your phone for a
long, long time, and maybe
running lots of different programs
at once, lots of browser tabs
open, lots of different
programs open at once,
your Mac or PC might very well
have begun to slow to a crawl.
It might be annoying, if
not impossible to use,
because everything is so darn slow.
That may very well be because one
or more of the programs you're using
has some bug in it whereby a
programmer kept allocating memory
and never got around to calling free.
Maybe it's a bug, maybe
it was deliberate,
they didn't expect you to
have so many windows open.
But valgrind can detect
errors like that.
And honestly, some of
you, if you're like me,
you might very well have 10, 20, 50
different browser tabs open at once,
thinking oh, I'm going to come back to
that someday, even though we never do.
Each of those tabs takes up memory.
Literally, any time you open
a browser tab, think of it,
really, as Chrome or Edge
or Firefox or whatever
you're using, underneath
the hood, they're
probably calling a function
on Mac OS or Windows
like malloc to give you more memory to
contain the contents of that web page
temporarily.
And if you keep opening
more and more browser tabs,
it's like calling
malloc, malloc, malloc.
Eventually, you're going to run out.
And computers can be smart these days.
They can kind of temporarily remove
things from memory to free up space.
This is called virtual memory.
But eventually, something
is going to break.
And it might very well
be your user experience
when things get so slow that you
literally have to quit the program
or maybe even reboot your computer.
So how do we use valgrind?
Well, let me go ahead
and write a short program
that doesn't do anything
useful, but demonstrates
multiple memory-related mistakes.
I'll call this file memory.c.
I'm going to go ahead and
open up the file memory.c
and include at the
top standard io dot h.
And then I'm going to
also, preemptively,
include standard lib dot h, which
recalls where malloc, int main void.
And I'm going to keep this one simple.
I'm going to go ahead and just give
myself a whole bunch of integer.
So this is actually kind of cool.
It turns out that--
well, let's go ahead.
Yeah, I can do this.
Let's go ahead and do this.
Char star s gets malloc.
And let me go ahead and give
myself, how about three of these.
Let me go ahead and allocate
space for three chars.
Or actually, let's give
me four, just like before.
Now, I'm going to go ahead
and say s bracket 0 equals 72.
s bracket 1-- actually,
I'll just do this manually.
Let's do h.
Let's do i.
Let's do our usual exclamation point.
And then just for good
measure, s bracket 3 gets
quote unquote, backslash 0.
This is the very manual
way of actually--
this is the very manual way of
actually building up a string.
But let me introduce a mistake.
Let me accidentally
allocate only three bytes,
even though I clearly need a fourth
for that terminating nul character.
And notice too, the absence of free.
I'm going to, very sloppily,
not bother calling free.
Now, I'm going to go ahead and
compile this program, make memory.
OK, it compiles OK, so that's
good, dot slash memory.
OK, nothing happens,
but that kind of makes
sense because I didn't
tell it to do anything.
Just for kicks, let's print out
that string just like we always do.
Let me now recompile
memory, still compiles.
Let me run dot slash memory.
OK, it seems to work.
So at first glance, you might
be really proud of yourself.
You've written another correct
program, seems to pass check50.
You submit.
You go about your day.
And you're very
disappointed some days later
when you realize, dammit, I did not
get full credit on this because there's
actually a latent bug.
So sometimes, indeed,
there are bugs in your code
that you don't necessarily see
visually, you don't necessarily
experience when running it
yourself, but eventually, there
might be an error when
running it enough times.
Eventually, a computer might notice
that you're doing something wrong.
And thankfully, tools
exist like valgrind,
that can allow you to detect that.
So let me go ahead and just increase
the size of my terminal window here.
And let me go ahead and run
valgrind on dot slash memory.
So it's just like debug50.
Instead of running debug50 and then
dot slash whatever the program is,
you run valgrind dot slash memory.
This one, unfortunately, is
only a command line interface.
There's no graphical user
interface like debug50.
And honestly, it's a
hideous sequence of output.
This should overwhelm
you at first glance.
There's crazy cryptic-ness here.
It's not the best-designed program.
It really was meant for the
most comfortable people.
But there are some useful
tidbits we can take away from it.
As always, let me show
all the way to the top
to the very first line of output.
And I'll draw your attention
to a couple of things
that will start to jump out to you.
And help50 can help you with this.
If you're confused by
valgrind's output, rerun it.
But put help50 at the beginning.
And just like I will do
now verbally, so can help50
help you notice the important
things in this crazy mess of output.
This is worrisome.
Valgrind is noting on this line
here, invalid right of size 1.
And that's on line 10 of memory.c.
So we'll look at that in a moment.
If I scroll down further,
invalid read of size 1.
And that also seems to be on here, it
looks like, on line 11 of memory.c.
And then if I keep scrolling,
keep scrolling, keep scrolling,
I'm not liking this.
3 bytes in 1 blocks are definitely
lost in loss record, whatever that is.
But three bytes in 1
blocks are definitely lost.
And then down here, leak summary,
definitely lost, 3 bytes in 1 blocks.
Incidentally, 1 blocks,
obviously not correct grammar.
This is what happens
when your program doesn't
have an if condition that checks if
the number is 1 or positive or 0.
You could fix this, grammatically,
honestly, with a simple if condition.
They did not when writing
this program years ago.
So there's two or three mistakes here.
One is some kind of
invalid read or write.
And another is this leak.
Well, what is a write?
A write just refers to changing a value.
A read just refers to reading
or using or printing a value.
So let's focus on line 10.
If I scroll back down to my
code and look on line 10,
this was an invalid
write, invalid write.
Well, why is it invalid?
Well, per today's definition,
if you are allocating 3 bytes,
you are welcome to touch the first byte,
the second byte, and the third byte.
But you have no business
touching the fourth byte
if you've only asked for three.
This is like a small scale version of
the very adventurous and inappropriate
poking around I did when I
looked at 10,000 bytes away.
Even looking one byte
away is a potential bug
and can cause a program to crash.
Meanwhile, line 11 is
also problematic, which
is an invalid read, because now,
you're saying go print out this string.
But that string contains
a memory address
that you should not have
touched in the first place.
And the memory leak, the third
problem, stems from the fact
that I didn't free that memory.
So again, it'll take some practice and
experience, some mistakes of your own,
to notice and understand these bugs.
But let me fix the first two like this.
Let me just give myself four bytes.
And let me fix the second
one or the third one,
really, by freeing s at the very end,
because again, any time you use malloc
you must use free.
Let me go ahead and recompile
memory, seems to compile.
Let me rerun it, still
works the same, visually.
But now, let's rerun valgrind on it
and see if there are any errors now,
so valgrind dot slash memory, Enter.
The output's still going
to look pretty cryptic.
But notice all heap blocks were
freed, whatever that means.
No leaks are possible.
It doesn't really get
more explicit than that.
That's a good thing.
And if I scroll up, I see no mention
of those invalid reads or writes.
So starting with this week's
problems and next week's in C,
not only are you going
to want to use tools
like help50 and printf
and debug50 and check50,
but even if you think your code's
right, the output looks right,
you might have a latent bug.
And even when your programs are small,
they might not crash the computer.
They might not cause that segmentation
fault. Eventually, they will.
And you do want to use tools like
this to chase down any such mistakes.
Otherwise, bad things can happen.
And what might happen?
Well, let me go ahead and
reveal an example here
that presents some code
that's a little dangerous.
So here, for instance,
is an example where
I'm declaring at the top of the
function, int star x and int star y.
So what does that mean?
Well, per today's parlance,
this just means give me
a pointer to an integer called x.
Give me a pointer to
an integer called y.
Put another way, give me
a variable called x that I
can store the address of an int in.
Give me a variable called y that I can
store the address of another int in.
But notice what I am not doing
on these first two lines.
I'm not actually assigning
them a value until line 3.
On line 3, even though this is weird--
this is not how we've allocated space
for integers before--
there's no reason that
you can't use malloc
and say, give me enough space
for the size of an integer.
sizeof is new.
It's just an operator in C that
tells you the size of a data type,
like a size of an int.
So maybe you forgot that an int is 4.
And indeed, an int is usually 4,
but not always 4 in all systems.
So size of int just makes sure that it
will always give you the right answer,
whether you're using a modern
computer or an old one.
So this just means, really, allocate
4 bytes to me on a modern system.
And it stores the address
of the first byte in x.
Would someone mind translating
to layman's terms, what
is star x equal 42 doing?
Star, again, is the
dereference operator.
It means go to the address.
And do what?
How would you describe,
with a verbal comment,
what star x equals 42 is doing?
Brian, would you mind
verbalizing any thoughts?
BRIAN: Yeah, so Sophia suggested that at
that address, we are going to place 42.
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
At that address put 42.
Equivalently, go to that address
in x and put the number 42 there.
It's like going to Brian's mailbox
and putting the 42 in his mailbox,
instead of what we previously had
there, which was the number 50.
How about this next fifth
line, star y equals 13?
Brian, could you verbalize someone else?
What does star y equals 13 do for us?
And it's not an accident
that 13 tends to be unlucky.
BRIAN: Peter says, put
13 at the address y.
DAVID MALAN: Good, put
13 at the address in y.
Or put another way, go to the
address in y and put 13 there.
But there's a logical problem here.
What is in y?
If I rewind, I never
actually assign y a value.
I don't initially, and
I don't eventually.
At least with x, even though I didn't
give it a value in declaring it up here
as a variable, I eventually got around
to storing in it the actual address.
Now, just to be really nit picky, I
should probably even, in this program,
check for nul just in
case anything went wrong.
But that's a whole other problem.
It is a more damning problem that
I haven't even given y a value.
And here's where we can reveal
one other detail about a computer.
Thus far, we've been taking for granted
that you and I almost always initialize
our memory.
If we want to give ourselves
a char, an int, a string,
we literally type it
out into the program
itself so that it's
there when we want it.
But if we consider this
picture here, which
is now just a physical incarnation of
some of the contents of your computer's
memory, playfully labeled with
a lot of Oscar the Grouches,
this is because you should never trust
the contents of your computer's memory
if you yourself have
not put something there.
There's a term of art in
programming called garbage values.
If you yourself have not put
a value somewhere in memory,
you should assume, to be safe, that it
is a quote unquote, "garbage value."
It's not a weird value.
It's just a 1, a 2, an
A, a B, a C, you just
don't know what it is, because if
your program is running over time
and you're calling functions
and functions are returning.
You're calling other functions
These values in your computer's
memory are constantly changing,
and your memory gets reused.
When you free memory, that doesn't erase
it or set it all back to 0's or set it
all back to 1's.
It just leaves it alone
so that you can reuse
it, which means over time,
your computer contains remnants
of all of the variables you've ever used
in your program over here, over here,
over there.
And so in a program like this, where
you have not explicitly initialized y
to anything, you should assume
that Oscar the Grouch, so to speak,
is at that location.
It is a garbage value that looks like
an address but is not a valid address.
And so when you say star y equals
13, that means go to that address.
But really, go to that bogus
address and put something there.
And odds are, your
program is going to crash.
You are going to get
a segmentation fault,
because by going to some
arbitrary garbage value address,
it would be like picking up a random
piece of paper with a number on it
and then going to that mailbox.
Why?
It does it belong to you.
If you try to dereference
an uninitialized variable,
your program may very well crash.
And this is, perhaps,
no better-presented
than by some of our friends, Nick
Parlante, a professor at Stanford
University who is breathed life into a
character in claymation known as Binky.
We have just a 2 minute clip from this
that paints the picture of bad things
indeed happening when you touch
memory that you shouldn't.
So hopefully, a helpful reminder as to
what to do and not to do with pointers.
Here we go.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Hey, Binky.
Wake up, it's time for pointer fun.
- What's that?
Learn about pointers?
Oh, goody!
- Well, to get started, I guess we're
going to need a couple pointers.
- OK, this code allocates two
pointers which can point to integers.
- OK, well I see the two pointers.
But they don't seem to
be pointing to anything.
- That's right.
Initially, pointers
don't point to anything.
The things they point
to or called pointees.
And setting them up's a separate step.
- Oh, right, right.
I knew that.
The pointees are separate.
So how do you allocate a pointee?
- OK, well, this code allocates
a new integer pointee.
And this part sets x to point to it.
- Hey, that looks better.
So make it do something.
- OK, I'll dereference the pointer x to
store the number 42 into its pointee.
For this trick, I'll need my
magic wand of dereferencing.
- Your magic wand of dereferencing?
That's great.
- This is what the code looks like.
I'll just set up the number and--
[POP]
- Hey, look, there it goes.
So doing a dereference on x follows
the arrow to access its pointee.
In this case, to store 42 in there.
Hey, try using it to store the number
13 through the other pointer, y.
- OK.
I'll just go over here to y
and get the number 13 set up
and then take the wand of
dereferencing and just--
[HORN] whoa!
- Oh, hey, that didn't work.
Say, Binky, I don't think dereferencing
y is a good idea, because setting up
the pointee is a separate step.
And I don't think we ever did it.
- Hmm, good point.
- Yeah, we allocated the pointer y.
But we never set it
to point to a pointee.
- Hmm, very observant.
- Hey, you're looking good there, Binky.
Can you fix it so that y points
to the same pointee as x?
- Sure, I'll use my magic
wand of pointer assignment.
- Is that going to be
a problem like before?
- No, this doesn't touch the pointees.
It just changes one pointer to
point to the same thing as another.
- Oh, I see.
Now, y points to the same place as x.
So wait, now y is fixed.
It has a pointee.
So you can try the wand of
dereferencing again to send the 13 over.
- Oh, OK.
Here it goes.
[POP]
- Hey, look at that.
Now, dereferencing works on y.
And because the pointers are sharing
that one pointee, they both see the 13.
- Yeah, sharing, whatever.
So are we going to switch places now?
- Oh look, we're out of time.
- But--
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: All right, so
we are not quite out of time.
But let's go ahead and take
our second 5 minute break here.
And when we return, we'll take
a closer look at Oscar and more.
Back in 5.
All right, so I claim that
there's all these garbage
values in your computer's memory.
But how can you see them?
What Binky did was, of course,
try to dereference a garbage value
when bad things happen.
But we can actually see
this with code of our own.
So let me go ahead, quickly, and
whip up a little program here,
just like something we did
in week one or week two,
but without doing it very well.
Let me go ahead and include standard
io dot h as usual, int main void.
And then let me go ahead and
give myself an array of scores.
How about an array of three scores?
And we've done this before where
we collected scores from a user.
But this time, I'm going
to deliberately make
the mistake of not actually
initializing those scores
or even asking the
human for those scores.
I'm just going to blindly go about
iterating from i equals 0 on up to 3.
And on each iteration, I'm just going
to presumptuously print whatever is
at that location in scores bracket i.
So logically, my code is correct
in what it's trying to do,
print out the values in scores.
But notice that I have
deliberately not initialized any
of the 1, 2, 3 scores in that array.
So who knows what's going to be there?
Indeed, it should be
garbage values of some sort
that we couldn't necessarily
predict in advance.
So let me go ahead and make
garbage, since this program
is in a file called garbage.c.
Compiles OK, but when
I now run garbage, we
should see three scores, which are
cryptically negative, 833060864.
Another one is 32765.
And the third just happens to be 0.
So there are those garbage values,
because again, the computer
is not going to initialize
any of those values for you.
Now, there are exceptions.
We have, on occasion,
used a global variable,
a constant that is outside the context
of main and all of my other functions.
Global variables, if
you do not set them,
are conventionally initialized
to 0 or nul for you.
But you should generally not
rely on that kind of behavior.
Your instinct should be to
always initialize values
before thinking of
touching or reading them
as via printf or some other mechanism.
All right, well, let's see how
this understanding, now, of memory,
can lead us to solve problems, but
also encounter new types of problems,
but problems that we can
now hopefully understand.
I'm going to go ahead and
create a new program here.
And recall from last week
that it was very common
for us to want to swap values.
When Brian was doing our sorts for
us, whether it was selection or bubble
sort, there was a lot
of swapping going on.
And yet, we didn't really write
any code for those algorithms.
And that's fine.
But let's consider that very
simple primitive of just
swapping two values, for
instance, swapping two integers.
Let me go ahead and give myself the
start of a program and swap.c here.
I'm going to include standard
io dot h, int main void.
And inside of main, I'm going
to give myself two integers.
Let's just give myself an int called
x and assign it 1, an int called y
and assign it 2.
And then let me go ahead and just
print out what those values are.
I'll just say, literally, x is percent
i comma y is percent i backslash n.
And then I'm going to go ahead and
print out x comma y, respectively.
And then I'm eventually going
to write a function called
swap that swaps x and y.
But let's assume, for
the moment, that exists.
It doesn't, because what
I then want to do right
after that is just reprint the
same thing, x is now percent i,
y is percent i, my presumption
being that the values of x and y
will be swapped.
So how might I swap these two values?
Well, let me go ahead and
implement my own function.
I don't think it needs
to return anything,
so I'm going to say
void is the return type.
I'll call it swap.
It's going to take two
arguments as input.
We'll call it a and b, both integers.
But I could call it anything I want.
But a and b seems reasonable.
And now, I want to go
ahead and swap two values.
Now, Brian was kind of doing this
with his two hands last week.
And that's fine, but we should probably
consider this a little more closely.
In fact, Brian, instead
of numbers, let's
do something a little more real world.
I think you have a couple of
beverages in front of you.
BRIAN: Yeah.
So right here, I have a
red glass and a blue glass,
which I guess we can use to represent
two variables, for instance.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Now, let me suppose--
I wish I'd told you in advance.
I'd actually prefer
that the red liquid be
in the blue glass and the blue
liquid be in the red glass.
So do you mind swapping
those two values,
just like you swapped numbers last week?
BRIAN: Yeah, sure.
So I can just take the two glasses,
and I can switch their places.
DAVID MALAN: OK, wait,
OK, that's not exactly--
you took me too literally.
I think here, if we think of the
glasses, now, as specific locations
in memory, you can't
just physically move
the chips of memory inside of
your computer to swap things.
So I think I literally need
you to move the blue liquid
into the red glass and the
red liquid into the blue glass
so that it's more like
a computer's memory.
BRIAN: OK, I can try to do that.
I'm a little nervous, though,
because I feel like I can't just
pour the blue liquid into the red
glass, because the red liquid's already
in there.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so this
probably doesn't end well,
if he's got to do some kind of
switcheroo between the two glasses.
So any thoughts here?
Like what is the real world solution
to this weird but real problem, where
we want to swap the contents
of these two locations,
just like Brian was swapping the
contents of two memory locations
last week?
Brian, if you have your eye
on the chat in parallel,
might anyone have ideas on how
we could swap these two liquids?
BRIAN: Yeah, a couple of people are
saying that I need a third glass.
DAVID MALAN: All right,
well Brian, do you
happen to have a third glass with
you back there behind back stage?
BRIAN: In fact, I think I do.
So I have a third glass here
that just so happens to be empty.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
And how would you, now, go
about swapping these two things?
BRIAN: All right, so I want to put
the blue liquid inside the red glass.
So the first thing I
need to do, I think,
is just to empty out the red glass
to make space for the blue liquid.
So I'm going to take the
red liquid, and I'm just
going to pour it into this extra glass.
DAVID MALAN: Temporarily though, right?
BRIAN: Temporarily, yeah.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
BRIAN: Just to keep
it to store it there.
And now, I think I can
just pour the blue liquid
into the original red glass,
because now I'm free to do so.
So I'll pour the blue liquid there.
And I think the last thing I need
to do now is, now this blue--
this glass that originally held
the blue liquid is now empty.
So the red liquid, which was inside
of this temporary glass over here,
I can take the red liquid and
just pour it into this glass here.
And now, I didn't swap the
positions of the glasses.
But the liquids have
actually switched places.
Now, the blue liquid is on the left
and the red liquid is on the right.
DAVID MALAN: Awesome.
Yeah, I think that is a
more literal implementation
of what you were doing and
taking for granted last week,
swapping the two values
in two separate locations.
So it seems pretty straightforward.
I just need a little more space.
I need a temporary variable
in code, if you will.
And it seems I need three steps.
I need to pour one out, pour the other
one out, pour the other one back in.
So I think I can translate
that into code here.
Let me go ahead and give
myself a temporary variable,
like a glass, like Brian did.
And I'll call it tmp, T-M-P,
which is pretty conventional when
you want to swap two things in code.
And I'm going to sign it,
temporarily, the value of a.
I'm going to then change the contents
of a to equal whatever the contents of B
are.
And then I'm going to change b to be
whatever the contents of tmp were.
So this feels pretty
reasonable and pretty correct,
because it's just a literal
translation into code,
now, of what Brian
did in the real world.
And I think this will compile.
So let's start there, make swap.
It does-- oh, doesn't compile.
OK, previous implicit declaration,
oh, so many errors, my god.
Implicit declaration of function swap--
wait a minute.
I've seen that before.
I've made this mistake before.
You might have as well.
Anytime you see this, recall it's just
that you're missing your prototype.
Remember that the compiler is
going to take you literally.
And if it doesn't know the word
swap exists when it sees it,
it's not going to compile successfully.
So we need to include my
prototype at the top of my file.
Now, let me try this again, make swap.
OK, that compiles.
Let me go ahead now and run swap
and recall that, in main, what I did
was initialize x to 1, y to 2.
I then print out what
x is and what y is.
I call swap, and then I print
out what x is and y is again.
So I should see 1, 2, and then 2, 1.
So lets hit Enter.
Huh, it does not seem to be working.
Well, let's try it again, just in case--
no, not working.
Well, let me try this.
Let me add some-- printf is my friend.
Let me go ahead and say a is percent i.
b is percent i backslash n, a, b.
So let's print that out.
And let's print that out twice.
So this would be a reasonable
debugging technique.
If you want to know what's going on
underneath the hood, add some printf's.
Let me go ahead and make swap.
That compiles, dot slash swap.
And let's see, a is 1,
b is 2, a is 2, b is 1.
But then x and y are unchanged.
So I feel like my logic is right.
It's switching a and b.
But it's not actually switching x and y.
And I could confirm as much, right?
The more powerful way
to debug this would
be to run debug50, set a break
point, for instance, at line 17,
step through my code, step by step,
stepping into the swap function.
But for now, it seems
clear that swap works.
But main isn't really
seeing those results.
So what's actually going on?
Well, let's consider this real world
incarnation of what my memory is
so I can actually move things around.
And this is all thanks to our friends
in the theater's prop shop in back.
If we think of this as
my computer's memory,
initially, it's all garbage values.
But I can use this as a canvas to
start laying things out in memory.
But calling functions is something
we've taken for granted thus far.
And it turns out, when you call
functions, the computer, by default,
uses this memory in
kind of a standard way.
In fact, let me go ahead and
draw a more pictorial picture.
Let me draw a more literal picture here,
if you will, of the computer's memory
again.
So if this is the computer's memory
and we zoom in on one of the chips,
and we think of the chip as having
a whole bunch of bytes like this.
Let's abstract away the actual hardware
and think of it as we have been.
It's just this big rectangular region
of memory, not unlike all of those Oscar
the Grouches a moment ago.
But by convention, your computer
does not just plop things
in random locations in memory.
It has certain rules of
thumb that it adheres to.
In particular, it treats different
portions of your computer's memory
in different ways.
It uses it in a standard way so
that it's not completely random.
For instance, when you run a program by
doing dot slash something on CS50 IDE
or on Linux more generally, or
you double click an icon on Mac OS
or Windows, that
triggers the computer's--
the program's 0's and 1's stored on
your hard drive to be loaded up here,
to what we'll call machine code,
which again, is the 0's and 1's.
So if you think again,
metaphorically, as your memory
is this rectangular region,
then the machine code,
the 0's and 1's composing your program
are loaded into the top part of memory.
And again, top, bottom, left, right, it
has no fundamental technical meaning.
It's just an artist's rendition.
But it does go into a standard location.
Below that are all of
your global variables.
So are your constants that you
put outside of your functions.
Those are going to end up
just below the machine code,
so again, at the top of
your computer's memory.
Below that is what's called the heap.
And this is a technical term.
And it refers to a big
chunk of memory that malloc
uses to get you some spare memory.
Any time you call malloc, you are given
the address of some chunk of memory
up in this region, below the machine
code, below your global variables.
And it's kind of a big zone.
But the catch is that other parts
of your memory are used differently.
In fact, whereas the heap is
considered to be here on down, somewhat
worrisomely, the stack is
considered to be here on up.
This is to say, when you call
malloc and ask for memory,
that gets allocated up here.
When you call a function,
though, those functions
use what's called stack
space instead of heap space.
So any time you call a function, main
or swap or strlang or string compare
or any of the functions
you've used thus far,
your computer will
automatically store any
of the local variables or parameters
from those functions down here.
Now, this is not
necessarily the best design,
because you can see the
two arrows pointing at one
another is like two trains barreling
down the tracks at one another.
Bad things can eventually happen.
Thankfully, we typically
have enough memory
that these two things don't collide,
but more on that in just a bit.
So again, when you call functions,
memory down here is used.
When you use malloc,
memory up here is used.
Now, for my swap function,
I'm not using malloc.
So I don't think I have
to worry about heap.
And I don't have any global variables.
And I don't really care
about my machine code.
I just need to know that
it's stored somewhere.
But let's consider, then,
what the stack is all about.
The stack, indeed, is
this sort of dynamic place
where memory keeps
getting used and reused.
So for instance, when you call main,
as you might when this swap program is
run, main uses a sliver of memory at
the bottom of this picture, if you will.
So the local variables
in main, like x and y,
end up at this bottom portion of memory.
When you call swap, swap uses a
chunk of memory just above main,
pictorally, in this diagram, such
as variables a and b and temp,
for that matter.
And then, once swap returns and is
done executing, that sliver of memory
essentially goes away.
Now, it doesn't disappear.
Obviously, there's still
physical memory there.
But that's when we get into the
discussion of garbage values again.
They're still like Oscar the
Grouches all over the place.
You just don't know, or at this
point care, what the values are.
But there are values there.
And that's why, a moment ago, when I
printed out that uninitialized score's
array, I did see some bogus
values, because there's still
going to be 0's and 1's there
that are left over from before.
The problem, though, is this.
Let me go over to this physical
incarnation of our memory
and consider this as being our
stack, so it's growing on up.
And in fact, if I want to have two
local variables like I do, x and y,
let's go ahead and think of this
row of memory here as being main,
for instance, here.
And I'm going to go ahead and
replace all these garbage values
with an actual value that I care about.
And the actual values that I care about,
we're going to call x and y, just as
before.
So each of these Oscars
happens to be one byte.
But an int is 4 bytes.
So thankfully, from our
friends in the prop shop,
we have these bigger
integer-sized blocks.
And I'm going to go ahead
and slide this in here.
And we're going to think
of this, in a moment, as x.
And indeed, I'm going to go ahead
and call this x with a marker.
And then I'm going to go ahead and
give myself another integer, a size 4,
and put it down here.
And we're going to think of this as y.
And recall, what do I
initialize these values to?
Well, the value 1,
initially, and the value 2.
But then I called the swap function.
And the swap function has
two arguments, a and b.
And those, by design, become copies of
x and y, because I passed in x comma y.
And I defined swap as taking a comma b.
So I think what I need to
do, physically here, is now
think of this second row of memory as
now belonging to the swap function,
not to main.
And inside of this second
row of memory, I'll
think of this as belonging to swap.
And within the swap row, I'm going
to have another integer of size 4.
And we're going to call this
one a, as down there, a.
And then I'm going to have
another chunk of size 4.
And we're going to call this b.
And again, because those are just
the arguments, x comma y, otherwise
now known as a comma b, I copy
1 and 2 into those values.
But swap has a third variable.
Brian proposed a temporary variable.
So I'm going to go ahead and
give myself four more bytes,
thereby getting rid of whatever
the garbage value's there
and actually setting it
to an integer call tmp.
So I'm going to go ahead and
call this thing tmp, T-M-P.
And what did I do first?
I set tmp equals to a.
So tmp equals to a.
So if a is 1, tmp is 1.
Then what did I do?
I then did a equals b.
So b is 2.
a is 2 as well.
And then lastly, what did I do?
I did b gets tmp.
So I have to go ahead and change
this to be whatever the value of tmp
is, which is now the number 1.
So you can see that
swap is correct insofar
as it is swapping the values of a and b.
But the moment swap
returns, these return
to being thought of as garbage values.
Main is still in the middle of running.
Swap is no longer running.
But these values stay there.
So those are garbage values.
We happen to know what they are,
but they're no longer valid,
because when I go to print out x and y
for the second time, what are x and y?
They're still the same.
And so this is to say, when you
actually write code that takes arguments
and you pass arguments from
one function to another,
those arguments are copied
from one function to another.
And indeed, x and y are
copied into a and b.
So your code may very well look correct
in that it's swopping correctly.
But it's only swapping correctly
in the context of swap,
not touching the original values.
So what I think we need
to do, fundamentally,
is reimplement swap in
such a way that we actually
change the values of x and y.
But how can we do this?
Brian, if we could call in someone here.
How could I conceptually change
my implementation of swap
so that it somehow empowers me to change
x and y, not change copies of x and y?
What could I pass into swap, Brian?
BRIAN: Igor is suggesting
that we use pointers instead.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so perhaps
the leading question here today.
But pointers would seem
to give us a solution.
If pointers are
essentially like a treasure
map to a specific address in your
computer's memory, what I should really
do from main to swap is pass
in not x and y literally,
but why don't I pass in the
address of x and the address of y,
so that swap can now
go to those addresses
and actually do the sort of swap
that Brian enacted in person.
So give the function a sort of map to
those values, pointers to those values,
and then go to those values.
So how might I do this?
Well, the code has to be
a little different now.
When I call swap this time,
what I really need to do
is pass in the addresses
of these two variables.
So I don't necessarily know
what those addresses are.
But for the sake of
the story, we can just
assume that this address,
for instance, is like, 0x123.
And then four bytes away from
that might be 0x127, for instance.
But again, it doesn't
really matter what it is.
But they do have addresses, x and y.
So a pointer recall
tends to be pretty big.
So we needed to get out
a bigger piece of wood,
eight bytes that represents a pointer.
And I actually need to use a
bit more memory in swap now.
If I now declare a to
be, not an integer,
but a pointer to an int,
that is a int star variable,
I could call this thing a now.
And I could store, in it,
the address of x, like 0x123.
If I then change the
definition of b to be
not an integer, but a
pointer to an integer,
that is another int star, which
happens to be eight bytes.
I'm going to use a little more
memory for this thing, but that's OK.
And its name is going to be b now.
And it's going to contain 0x127.
I still need a temporary variable.
I still need a temporary
variable, but that's fine.
I just need four bytes for
that, because the variable
itself just needs to store an int, like
Brian temporarily stored it in a glass.
So I just need an additional four
bytes, like before, for that.
And now, let's just consider the logic.
Here's main.
And swap is now using these 3--
2 and 1/2 rows of memory.
And that's fine.
It's growing upward as I proposed.
X is at address 0x123.
y is at address 0x127.
Therefore, a and b, I propose
conceptually, like Igor proposed,
store the addresses of
a, x and y, respectively.
And now my code, I
think, needs to say this.
Go and store, in the variable
tmp, whatever is at the address a.
So you can kind of think of this
as being an arrow down here.
Follow the arrow, OK.
What is at address 0x123?
The number 1.
So we put one in tmp, just like before.
Then what do we do?
Well, now, I'm going to go ahead
and change, not the value of a,
but I'm going to change what
is at the location in a to be
whatever is at the location in b, which
is an arrow pointing down here, 0x127.
So I'm going to change
this 1, now, to be a 2.
And the third and final
step, recall, is for me, now,
to go, not to b, but to go where b
points to, which happens to be y,
and change that to be the value of
tmp, which of course, is up here.
And at this point in the story,
it's still just three lines of code.
They're different
types of lines of code.
It's three lines of code.
But when swap is done executing,
notice what we've done.
We have successfully
swapped x and y by letting
swap go to those addresses as
opposed to just naively getting
copies of the values therein.
Now, even though this code is
going to look a little cryptic,
it's, frankly, just an application
of the logic we've seen thus far.
I'm going to go ahead and go
back to my old buggy version.
And I'm going to change
the definition of swap
to say that it doesn't take
two integers, a and b, but two
pointers to integers a and b.
And the way you declare a pointer
recall is the type of variable
you point at followed by a
star and then the name of it.
And we haven't seen it,
admittedly, in the context
of a function taking parameters yet.
But it's quite simply that.
I added the stars.
Down here, I need to say,
store in tmp, whatever is at a.
How do I express go to a?
Just add a star here.
How do I express go to a
and put whatever is at b?
I add stars there.
How do I say, go to b and
store whatever is at tmp?
I add one star there.
So tmp is just a simple integer.
It's just an empty glass like Brian had.
There's nothing fancy there.
So we don't need stars around tmp.
But I do, now, need to
change how I'm using a and b,
because now they are addresses
that I actually want to go to.
There's no need for the address
of operator in this context.
But up here, I'm going
to need to make a change.
I do need to change
the prototype to match.
So that's just a copy paste.
But I bet you can imagine
what, lastly, needs to change.
When calling swap, I don't want to
pass in naively x and y, because again,
they're going to get copied.
I want to pass in the address
of x and the address of y,
so that swap now has
sort of special access
to the contents of those
locations in memory
so that it actually can
make some changes therein.
And that, indeed, if I now recompile
this program, make swap, and I do
dot swap and cross my fingers, voila.
Now, I have successfully
swapped lines of code.
So last week, if you
were wondering, perhaps,
why we didn't show you how
to do swap, we could have.
And we didn't need a special function.
You don't necessarily need pointers
if we did all of this in main.
But I'm trying to introduce an
abstraction, this function that
does swap just like Brian
swapped those glasses for us.
And to pass values from
one function to another,
you do need to understand what's
going on in your computer's memory
so that you can actually pass
in little breadcrumbs again,
treasure maps to those locations and
memories, again, thanks to these things
called pointers.
All right, well let me
propose and emphasize,
then, that this design of
the heap being up at the top,
where malloc uses memory
and the stack being
at the bottom where your
own functions use memory,
this is a problem clearly
waiting to happen.
And those problems actually have names.
And some of you who
have programmed before
might know some of these terms, either
heap overflow or stack overflow.
And in fact, many of you might know
stackoverflow.com as just a website.
Well, there is an origin
story to its name.
A stack overflow refers to the process
of calling a function so many times
that it overflows the heap.
That is, every time
you call the function,
like I did here, you use more and
more rows, so to speak, of memory.
And if you call so many
functions again and again,
eventually, you may very well run
over the area of memory called heap.
And at that point, your
program will crash.
There is no fundamental solution to
that problem other than don't do that.
Don't use too much memory.
But that can be hard to do.
And indeed, that's one of the
dangers of programming today.
And we can actually induce this a
little bit deliberately ourselves.
And in fact, I thought we
could revisit, for instance,
where we left off with Mario last
time, which was this picture here.
Recall that this was
a pyramid, of course,
simpler than the one you might
have played with for problems at 0.
But it's a recursive pyramid in that
you can define a pyramid of height 4,
in terms of a pyramid of height 3,
in terms of a pyramid of height 2
and a height 1.
And indeed, I built that last
week using these very blocks.
Well, you can implement
Mario's pyramid like this
in a couple of different ways.
One is just using week one
style iteration, using a loop.
And in fact, let me go ahead and
whip up a quick solution that
does exactly that.
Let me go ahead and call this mario.c.
And I'm going to go
ahead and include cs50.h.
So we can use one of our get functions.
I'm going to use standard io dot h.
And I'm going to do int main void.
And all I want to do is
print out this pyramid.
But I want to ask the
user for the height.
So I'm going to say int
height equals get int.
And we'll ask the user for the height,
just like you did for problem set 1.
And then I'm going to go ahead
and draw a pyramid of that height.
Now, draw doesn't exist.
But that's fine.
I'm going to go ahead and draw
this now, implement draw myself.
It doesn't need to return
a value, because I'm just
printing stuff on the screen.
Function's called draw,
and it's going to take
an input called h, for
instance. h for height,
but I could call its
argument anything I want.
And then I'm just going to
do this, for int i gets 1,
i less than or equal to h, i++.
And then inside of this, this is where
you might recall, from problem set one,
have found a nested loop to be useful.
Let me do int j gets 1, j
less than or equal to i, j++.
This will be similar but not identical
to either the less comfortable or more
comfortable version of
Mario from the past,
because this pyramid is shaped
in a different direction.
Now, you print a hash there.
And then let me go ahead
and print a new line here.
So I did this super quickly.
But logically, what
I'm doing is iterating
over every row, so from 1 through
h, so row 1, 2, 3, 4, for instance.
And then on each row, I'm deliberately
iterating from 1 through i.
So I print 1, then 2, then 3, then 4.
And again, I could zero index if I want.
I find that in this context, more
user friendly, more intelligible to me
to index from 1, totally
reasonable if you think
there's a compelling design argument.
So let me go ahead and make Mario.
Ah, darn it.
Oh, I missed my prototype.
So notice, it's not understanding draw.
So the fix for that is to
either move the whole function
or, as we've preached instead, to
just put your prototype up top.
Let me recompile Mario.
OK, now successful.
Mario, let's do a
height of 4, and voila.
Now, I have a relatively
simple-- though I certainly
did it faster than you might
without some practice--
implementation of Mario's pyramid.
But here's where things
get kind of cool.
Let me stipulate that that is a
correct iterative solution, even
if it might take you some number
of steps or trial and error
to get that iterative
loop-based code correct.
Let me change this,
now, to be recursive.
And recall, a recursive function
is one that calls itself.
How do you print a pyramid of height h?
Well, recall that you print a
pyramid of height h minus 1,
and then you proceed to
print one more row of blocks.
So let me take that literally.
for int i gets zero.
i is less than h, i++.
Let me go ahead and just
print that extra row of bricks
like this, followed by a new line.
So now, I did this kind of fast.
But what am I doing here?
Well, if the height equals 1, I
want this loop to iterate one time.
If the height equals 2, I wanted to
iterate two times, 3, and so forth.
So I think, using my zero-indexing
technique here, this will work too.
But if you prefer, I could
certainly just change this to a 1
and change this 2.
But I'm going to go ahead and--
actually, no.
In this case, I want to
leave it as such, zero index,
just like we typically do.
All right, let me go ahead
and compile this, make Mario.
OK, oops, interesting.
All paths through this
function will call itself.
So clang is being kind
of smart here, whereby,
it's noticing that in my draw
function, I'm calling my draw function.
And that's a process that never changes.
In fact, let me see if
I can override that.
Let me use clang manually and compile
a program called mario using mario.c.
And let me go ahead and link in cs50.
So I'm using our old school
syntax from week two.
OK, that compiled.
And why did that compile?
Well, make is, again, a program
that uses your compiler clang.
And we've configured make to be a little
more user-friendly and a little more
protective of you by
turning on special features
where we detect problems like that.
By using clang directly now, I'm
disabling those special checks.
And watch what happens when I run Mario
now for height of 4, for instance.
Boom, it crashed.
It didn't even print anything.
It crashed pretty quickly.
And again, a segmentation fault means
you touched memory that you shouldn't.
So what's going on?
Well, if you think of this memory as
representing main still, but then draw,
draw, draw, draw, draw, draw.
If every one of your calls to
draw just cause draw again,
why would it ever stop?
It wouldn't seem to
stop here, necessarily.
So it seems that I'm missing a key
detail in my recursive version.
You know what?
If there's nothing to draw, if height
equals equals 0, let me go ahead, then,
and just return immediately.
Otherwise, I'll go ahead
and draw part of the pyramid
and then add the new row.
So you need this so-called
base case, which you literally
choose to equal some simple value,
like height of 0, height of 1,
any hardcoded value, so that
eventually, draw does not call itself.
So let me go ahead and recompile
this with clang or make.
Let me rerun it, height of 4, and voila.
It's still working just
like the interior version,
but it's now using recursion.
So here's a sort of design question.
Is iteration better than recursion?
It depends.
Iteration will always work.
When using the iterative version,
I will never overflow the stack
and hit the heap.
Why?
Because I'm not calling
functions again and again.
There's only main and
one invocation of draw.
But with the recursive version,
it's kind of a cool, powerful way
to do things.
Like, oh, I can draw you
a pyramid of height h.
Let me just have you draw me
a pyramid of height h minus 1,
and then I'll add a row.
It's kind of this clever, cyclical
argument that does work very elegantly.
But there's a danger.
And in fact, even though this base case
ensures that it doesn't go forever,
it could go on so long-- maybe
let's try 10,000 invocations.
So that worked OK.
It's a little slow.
I'm losing control over my keyboard.
So Control C is your friend.
Let me try this once more.
Let me go ahead and do something
like 2 billion and see if that works.
Boom.
So even that doesn't work.
So there's this inherent
danger with recursion, whereby,
even though it empowered us last week
to solve a problem even more efficiently
with merge sort, we kind of got lucky,
in that we weren't trying to crazy big
things on Brian's shelf, because
it would seem if you use recursion
and call yourself again and
again and again and again,
even finitely many times, you might
eventually touch memory you shouldn't.
And what's the solution here?
Unfortunately, it's don't do that.
Design your algorithms, choose
your inputs in such a way
that there just isn't that risk.
And we'll use recursion
again in a few weeks
time when we look at more
sophisticated data structures.
But again, there's
always this trade off.
Just because you can design
something a little more
elegantly doesn't necessarily mean
that it's always going to work for you.
But more commonly, are you likely
to run into other problems as well?
There's something called
a buffer overflow.
And this you will surely trip
over in the coming weeks.
A buffer overflow is when
you allocate an array
and go too far past the end of it.
Or you use malloc and you,
nonetheless, go farther
than the end of the chunk of
memory that you allocated.
A buffer it's just a chunk of memory,
so to speak, that you can use as you see
fit.
Buffer overflow means going beyond
the boundaries of that array.
You might use-- you're
using, right now, video.
You might know the phrase
buffering from videos,
like sort of buffering and
annoying you on Netflix,
because there's a
spinning icon or whatnot.
Well, that means exactly this.
A buffer, in the context of
YouTube or Zoom or Netflix,
means some chunk of
memory that was retrieved
via malloc or some similar
tool that gets filled
with bytes comprising your video.
And it's finite, which is why you
can only buffer so many seconds
or minutes of video before,
eventually, if you're offline,
you run out of video content to watch.
And the stupid icon
comes up, and you can
watch no more, because a buffer is just
a chunk of memory, an array of memory.
And if Netflix or Google or others
were to implement their code unsafely,
they might very well go too
far past that boundary as well.
So with all this said, let's
consider, in some of our final minutes
here today, just what else we've been
getting from these training wheels,
because we do want to take
them mostly off for you.
So the CS50 library
not only provides you
with this abstraction of a
string type, which again,
doesn't give you any new functionality.
Strings in C exist,
just not by that name.
They're known more
properly as char stars.
But all of these functions
in the CS50 library
can be implemented with other actual
C functions that weren't from CS50,
namely using one called scanf.
But you're going to see,
immediately, some of the dangers
of using something like scanf,
which is an old school function.
It was not designed to be
self-defensive like CS50's library.
And so it's very easy to make mistakes.
Let me go ahead, for
instance, and create a file
called scanf.c, just to
demonstrate this function.
I'm not going to use the CS50
library, just standard io dot h.
And I'm going to give
myself int main void.
And I'm going to go ahead
and give myself a variable x.
And I'm going to go ahead and
print out quote unquote, "x:"
just like CS50's get int function does.
And then I'm going to call scanf.
And I'm going to go ahead and say, scan
from the user's keyboard, an integer,
and store it in the location of x.
Then, I'm going to go
ahead and print out, again,
x, and a colon and a backslash
percent i backslash n.
And I'm going to print x.
So what's going on here?
In line 5, I'm declaring a variable
called x, just like in week one.
Line 6, just using
printf, like in week one.
The interesting stuff
seems to be in line 7.
Scanf is a function that takes input
from the user, just like get int, get
string, get float, and so forth.
But it does it only by you
having to understand pointers,
because recall from our swap example,
if you want to have a function,
change the contents of a
variable, as we did with a and b
and x and y, you have to pass in
the address of the variable, whose
value you want to change.
You can't just pass in x itself.
So if we didn't use the
CS50 library in week one,
you would have been writing code like
this just to get an int from the user.
And you would have had
to understand pointers.
And you would have to understand
ampersand and stars and so forth.
It's just too much, when all we
care about in the first weeks
are loops and variables and conditions
and sort of the fundamentals.
But here, we now have the
ability to call scanf, tell it
to scan from the user's
keyboard, so to speak,
an integer, or percent f would give
us a float or other such codes,
and pass in the address of x so
that scanf can go to that address
and put the integer from
the user's keyboard there.
Line 8 is like week one stuff.
I'm just printing out the value.
And this is pretty safe.
I'm going to go ahead and make scanf.
It compiles OK.
I'm going to go ahead and run it.
I'm going to type in 50.
And voila, it prints out a 50.
But there's some weirdness,
because if you run this program too
and type in cat, well then x is 0.
And there's no error checking.
So immediately, you
should glimpse that one
of the features of the
CS50 library, recall,
is that we keep prompting the user
again and again if they're not
cooperating and giving you an int.
So that's one feature
you get from the library.
But it turns out that get
string is even more powerful,
because if I go and change this
program now, not to get an int,
but something fancier like a string--
or wait, we're calling it char star now.
I'm going to go ahead and
do something very similar.
I'm going to prompt
the user for string s.
And I'm going to use scanf.
And I'm going to use percent s,
just like printf uses percent s.
And I'm going to pass in s.
Now, to be clear, I don't
need to do ampersand s here,
because now, we all know that
s is fundamentally an address.
So it suffices just to pass in
the address that you already have.
Now, I'm going to go ahead and print
out s colon, percent s backslash n,
and print out s.
But when I compile this, make
scanf, it doesn't like it
when I compile variable s's
uninitialized when used here.
All right, well if I really
want to be sort of adventurous,
I can override make's protections.
And I can just compile this
manually myself using scanf--
using clang directly.
That worked, dot slash scanf.
Let me go ahead and type
in, for instance, "HI!"
and you see weirdness, nul.
Well, fortunately,
make, and in turn clang,
were kind of helping us
help ourselves there.
It was pointing out that you declared s.
So you were declared
8 bytes for a pointer.
But there's nothing there.
It's a garbage value.
And so there's nowhere to put this.
And thankfully, printf and
scanf are being smart enough
by not just blindly going
there and plopping H, I,
exclamation point in a nul character.
They're just leaving it alone.
And this parenthetical nul is just a
printf feature saying, you screwed up.
If you see nul, you've
done something wrong.
It's just being generous
and not crashing on you.
If I actually want to get user's
input, I need to be smarter than this.
And I need to either allocate myself
4 bytes, as we've done earlier today.
Or I could go back to week two stuff
and say something like, give me 4 bytes.
This, though, gives me 4
bytes on the stack somewhere
down here in main's frame, so to speak.
These rows are called frames.
If I use malloc instead, it
comes from the so-called heap,
which not pictured, is sort of up here.
And the only difference is that if
I'm using malloc, I have to use free.
If I'm using the stack, as I did in
week two, I don't have to use free.
It's automatically managed for me.
So frankly, there's so
much new stuff today.
I like the idea of sticking
with the old school arrays.
So now, though, if I go ahead and
make scanf, now it compiles with make.
If I then run scanf and type in,
HI!, voila, it seems to work.
But that's because I was smart
and anticipated that H-I,
OK four characters.
I gave myself 4 bytes.
But what if the user types in,
HI THERE, DAVID, HOW ARE YOU?
Clearly, more than four bytes.
And I hit Enter now, something
weird there happened.
The rest is just lost.
And this would really be
annoying and very frustrating
if you-- trying to get user input
in the first week of the class.
Get string avoids this for you.
Get string calls malloc for you.
And it calls it for as big a
chunk of memory as the string
the human types in.
Long story short, we sort of watch
what they're typing character
by character by character.
And we make sure to
allocate or reallocate
just enough memory to fit whatever
it is the human has typed in.
So scanf is, essentially, how a
function like the CS50 library
works underneath the hood.
But it is doing all of this for you.
And as soon as you take away training
wheels like that, or frankly,
libraries like that, which it
really is at the end of the day.
It's not just a teaching tool.
It's a useful library.
You have to start implementing more
of this low-level stuff yourself.
So again, there is a trade off.
If you don't want to use something
like the CS50 library, that's fine.
Now, the onus is on you to avoid all
of these possible error conditions.
All right, with that said,
we have one final feature
to give you in order to motivate
this week's problems, wherein
you'll actually explore and manipulate
and write code to change files.
And for that, we need one final
topic of file I/O. File I/O
is the term of art that describes
taking input and output from files.
Pretty much every program we've written
thus far just uses memory, like this
here, whereby, you can
put stuff in memory.
But as soon as your program ends, boom.
It's gone.
The contents of memory are gone.
Files, of course, are where you
and I in the computing world
save our essays and
documents and resumes
and all of that permanently
on your computer.
In C, you have the ability,
certainly, to write code yourself that
saves files long term.
So for instance, let me go ahead
and write my own program here,
a phonebook program that stores
names and numbers in a file.
I'm going to go ahead and include,
just for convenience, the CS50 library
again, because I don't
want to deal with scanf.
I'm going to go ahead and save
this, incidentally, as phonebook.c.
I'm going to go ahead and include, not
just the CS50 library, but standard io.
And preemptively, I'm going to go
ahead and include string.h as well.
And I'm going to go ahead
in my main function.
And I'm going to use a few new functions
that we'll see only briefly here.
But in the next problem set, will
you explore these in more detail.
I'm going to give myself
a pointer to a file.
It turns out, weirdly,
that in all caps, FILE,
this is a new data type that does
come with C that represents a file.
So I'm going to go ahead and
give myself a pointer to a file,
the address of a file.
And I'm going to call the variable file.
I could call it f I could call it x.
I'm going to call it lowercase
file, just to be clear.
And I'm going to use a new function
called f open, which means file open.
And file open takes two arguments.
It takes the first argument, which is
the name of a file you want to open.
I'm going to open a file
called phonebook.csv.
And then I'm going to go ahead and
open it, specifically, in append mode.
Long story short, you can
open files in different ways,
to read them, that is just look
at their contents, to write them,
which is to change
their contents entirely,
or to append to them, a, which
means to add row by row to them,
so to keep tacking on
more information to them.
I'm going to go ahead
and, just to be safe,
I'm going to say if
file equals equals nul,
because recall that nul
signifies something went wrong,
let's just return now.
Maybe I mistyped the name of the file.
Maybe it doesn't exist.
Something went wrong, potentially.
I'm going to check for that by saying,
if file equals equals nul, just
quit out of the program now.
But after that, I'm going to
go ahead and get a string.
But we can call that char
star now, called name.
And I'm going to ask
the user for a name.
And we've done this before.
I'm going to go ahead and ask
them for a number, phone number.
And we've done this before.
The only difference, now, is
I'm calling string char star.
And now, here's the cool part.
It turns out, if I want to
save this name and number
to that file permanently in a CSV--
if unfamiliar, popular in the
consulting world, the analytics world.
It's just a spreadsheet,
a comma-separated value
file that you can open in Excel
or numbers or Google spreadsheet.
I'm going to go ahead and, not
printf, but fprintf to that file,
a string followed by a comma, followed
by a string, followed by a new line,
plugging in the name and the number.
And then down here, I'm
going to close the file.
So this is new. fprintf is not
printf, which prints to your screen.
fprintf prints to a file.
So you have to pass in one more
argument, the first one, which
is the pointer to the file that you
want to send these new strings to.
Then you still provide a format
string, which says, hey fprintf,
this is the kind of data I
want to print to the file.
And then you plug in the variables,
just like we've always done with printf.
And then lastly, we close the file.
So in short, this program would seem to
prompt a human for a name and number.
And then it's going to go
ahead and write those names
and numbers to the file.
So let me go ahead and make phonebook.
OK, no mistake so far, dot slash
phonebook, David, 949-468-2750.
OK, let me run it once more, even
though nothing seems to have happened.
Brian, how about 617-495-1000, Enter.
Let me check my file browser here.
Notice, all of the files we've created
today, including, if I zoom in,
not just phonebook.c, but phonebook.csv.
And if I double click that,
notice what's inside of this.
Voila, David's name, Brian's
name, and each of our numbers.
And even cooler than that, let
me go ahead and close this.
Let me go ahead and download
this file using the IDE.
And that's going to put it
into my Downloads folder.
Let me go ahead and click on it.
And it's going to open
Excel or Numbers or whatever
you happen to have on your Mac or PC.
I'm going to go ahead and just proceed.
And voila, looks a little
stupid in this formatting here.
But I've opened up a spreadsheet
that I, myself, generated
using fopen, fprintf, and fclose.
So already, now that we have
pointers at our disposal,
can we actually manipulate things
like files, which is quite cool.
But we're going to do
that this week, not
with text, but with actual
specific types of files.
And indeed, recall this
kind of thinking here.
If you glance at this, it's
probably pretty cryptic.
It looks like machine
code, but it's not.
This is, perhaps, the
simplest representation
of a smiley face inside of a file.
If you have a bitmap file, a map of
bits, a grid of bits, those bits,
quite simply, could
literally be 0's and 1's.
And if you assign the color black
to 0 and the color white to 1,
you could actually think of this same
grid of 0's and 1's as representing,
indeed, a smiley face.
In other words, here are some pixels.
We talked about pixels in week zero.
Pixels are just the dots that compose
a graphic file on your computer.
And pixels are everywhere.
All of us, now, tuning in live
via Zoom or YouTube or the like,
we're watching streams of pixels, which
compose multiple images and multiple
images compose video that appears to
be moving at, like, 20 something or 30
frames per second, images per second.
Now, of course, there's only so much
fidelity in these kinds of images.
And it's quite common in the
case on TV and in movies,
if there's some bad guy that's been
picked up with some surveillance
footage or the like, invariably, the
folks on Law &amp; Order and the like
can just kind of enhance the
video and zoom in and see
exactly the glint in the person's eye
that reveals who committed some crime.
Well, that's all kind of nonsense.
And it derives from some of the
primitives we introduced in week zero.
In fact, just to poke fun
at this, let me go ahead
and play on a few seconds of
this TV show here in the US
called CSI, just to give you a sense of
just how commonplace this kind of logic
is.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- We know.
- That at 9:15, Ray
Santoya was at the ATM.
- So the question is,
what was he doing at 9:16?
- Shooting the 9
millimeter at something.
Maybe he saw the sniper.
- Or was working with him.
- Wait, go back one.
- What do you see?
[CLICKING]
- Bring his face up, full screen.
- His glasses.
- There's a reflection.
[TYPING]
- That's Neuvitas baseball team.
That's their logo.
- And he's talking to
whoever's wearing that jacket.
- We may have a witness.
- To both shootings.
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So unfortunately, today
will rather ruin a lot of TV and movie
for you, because you can't
just zoom in infinitely
and see more information if
that information is not there.
At the end of the day, there's
only a finite number of bits.
And case in point, here's
a photograph of Brian.
And you might see that, oh,
there's a glint in his eye.
Let's see what was being
reflected in his eye there.
And so if we Zoom in on
this image here of Brian,
and maybe we zoom in a little further,
that's all that's actually there.
You can't just click the
enhance button and see more,
because at the end of the
day, these are just pixels.
And pixels, per week zero, are just
0's and 1's, and finitely, many so.
So what you see is what you get.
Now, with that said-- and actually,
we can poke fun of this, too, here.
Let me just play one other
short clip from Futurama,
which kind of hammers home this
point as well, but more playfully so.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- Magnify that death speed.
Why is it still blurry?
- That's all the resolution we have.
Making it bigger
doesn't make it clearer.
- It does on CSI: Miami.
- [SIGH]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So there, we have two
clips talking, rather, to one another.
But I have to update things for 2020.
You can't really pick up the internet
these days or magazine these days,
if you even would, that
doesn't somehow mention
machine learning and
artificial intelligence
and fancy algorithms via
which you can do things
that previously weren't quite possible.
And that's actually
kinda sorta the case.
You might recall from week zero, that
we found this beautiful watercolor
painting in the Harvard archives
that's only about 11 inches tall total.
And yet somehow, it's 13
feet tall here behind me.
Now, normally, if you were to just
enhance this watercolor painting,
it would start to look
pretty stupid pretty quickly
with lots and lots of
pixelation, even if you
used a very fancy camera,
as the archives do,
to capture the original image.
But we wanted to blow
it up to 13 feet tall
so that it would stand at high
quality behind us this whole time.
And there, we actually did
use enhance, in some sense.
So using, long story short, fancier
algorithms than those last week,
you can use artificial
intelligence, machine learning,
to actually analyze data and find
patterns where there weren't--
that aren't necessarily
visible to the human eye.
So for instance, if we take the
original here and start to zoom in,
it looks pretty good at this resolution.
But it's pretty smooth.
You don't really see the fact that
this was paint on an actual canvas.
So this was just
zooming in on Photoshop.
But when you actually
run an image like this
through fancy machine learning-based
software, artificial intelligence,
you can begin to improve
it and actually see,
not just this window from the top
of one of the buildings, which
is pretty glossed over
here in Photoshop,
you can start to see more detail.
So this is literally the before,
just zooming in Photoshop.
This is after, actually applying fancy
artificial intelligence algorithms
that notice, wait a minute, there's
a little discoloration there.
Wait, there's a little
discoloration there.
And nowadays, enhance is
increasingly becoming a thing.
It's still inferring.
It's not resurrecting information
that was necessarily there.
It's doing its best guess,
really, algorithmically,
to reconstruct what
the image actually was.
And if we zoom in
further, you can, perhaps,
see that this is really starting to
get blurry if you just use Photoshop
and keep zooming in.
But if you run it through
fancy enough algorithms
and start to notice
slight discolorations that
aren't super visible to the human
eye, we can enhance that even further.
And you can't do it infinitely so.
And in some sense, we're
creating information
where there isn't necessarily
that information there.
So whether or not these kinds of things
hold up in court is another question.
But it can improve the
fidelity of images like this.
And indeed, it allowed us to zoom in
from 11 inches to 13 feet instead.
So when it comes to manipulating
images, ultimately, we
do have some programmatic capabilities,
including this file pointer,
like we just saw, and also, a
few other functions as well.
And our final examples,
here, will lay the foundation
for what you'll do
this coming week, which
is manipulate your very own graphical
files with a newfound understanding
of pointers and addresses and
now files and input and output.
For instance, I'm going to go ahead
and open up a program here called--
give me just one second.
I'm going to open up a
program here called jpeg.c.
And this program, jpeg.c,
which I wrote in advance,
which is on the course's
website, does the following.
It first declares a type called byte.
It turns out, in C, there's no
common definition of what a byte is.
A bite, as we know it, is a bit.
And it turns out, the
simplest way to create
a byte is to define our own,
just like we've defined a string,
just like we've defined other types
too, like a student, in order--
a person, rather, in
order to give us a byte.
So this first line of code
just declares a data type
called byte, using another, more arcane
data type called u int a underscore t.
But more on that in the problem set.
That this just did invent
something called byte.
Notice, in this program,
I'm resurrecting the idea
from week two of command line arguments,
where we can take input from the user.
Notice that I'm checking if the
user typed in two arguments.
And if not, I'm returning one
immediately to signify error.
In line 17, I'm using my new technique.
I'm opening a file using
the name of the file
that the human typed
at the command line.
And this time, I'm opening it to read
it with quote unquote, r instead of a.
But if there's not a file--
so if bang file, that is,
if exclamation point file,
or if file equals equals NULL,
those mean the same thing.
I can go ahead and return
one, signifying an error.
Down here, I'm doing
something a little clever.
It turns out that with
very high probability,
you can determine if any file is a
jpeg by looking only at its first three
bytes.
A lot of file formats have
what are called magic numbers
at the beginning of their files.
And these are industry standard
numbers, 1 or 2 or 3 or more of them,
that is just commonly expected
to be at the beginning of a file,
so that a program can quickly
check, is this a jpeg?
Is this a gif?
Is this a Word document?
Is this an Excel file?
They tend to have these numbers
at the beginning of them.
And jpegs have a sequence of
bytes that we're about to see.
This line of code 24 here, as
you'll see in the next problem set,
is how you might give yourself
a buffer of bytes, specifically
an array of three bytes.
This next line of code, as you'll see
this coming week, is called fread.
fread, as the name
suggests, reads from a file.
That is, it grabs bytes from a file.
And it's a little fancy to use,
but you'll get more comfortable
with this over time.
It reads into this buffer, its first
argument, the size of this data type,
the size of a byte.
And it reads in this many of
those data types from this file.
So again, it's for arguments, which
is kind of a lot from what we've seen.
But it reads from this file,
three bytes into this array,
a.k.a. buffer, called bytes.
So this is just how you write code
that doesn't put data in a file,
but read it from it.
And then here, notice our hexadecimal.
So we've come full circle.
If bytes bracket 0 equals
equals 0xff and bytes
bracket 1 equals 0xd8 and
bytes bracket 2 equals 0xff,
this definitely looks cryptic to you.
But that's just because I looked
up in the manual for jpegs,
and it turns out that
almost any jpeg, rather,
must start with 0xff, 0xd8, 0xff.
Those are the first three bytes
of any jpeg on your Mac, your PC,
on the internet.
There are always those three bytes.
It turns out, the fourth byte
further decides whether or not
a file is actually a jpeg.
But the algorithm for that's a
little fancier, so I kept it simple.
If the first three bytes of a file
are those, maybe you have a jpeg.
But if you don't have
exactly those three bytes,
you definitely don't have a jpeg.
And so what I can do,
here, is as follows.
In today's code-- let me go
ahead and grab two other files
that I brought with me.
And one happens to be
a photograph again.
Give me one second.
I brought with me a few files,
one of which is called brian.jpeg,
which is the same photo of Brian.
And then I have a gif,
which of course, is not
a jpeg, that is this cat typing here.
And what I, effectively,
have in front of me now
is a program that if I do make
jpeg, because this file is jpeg.c,
and I run dot slash jpeg, I can
type in something like cat.gif
at the command line as an argument,
hit Enter, and I should see no.
By contrast, if I pass in Brian's jpeg
at the command line as an argument,
I see maybe.
And again, maybe only
because the algorithm
for actually adjudicating
whether something is a jpeg
is a little more complicated than that.
But indeed, I can now access the
individual bytes, and therefore pixels,
it would seem, of an image file.
And in fact, we can even do this.
Let me go ahead and show
you one last program
that we wrote deliberately in advance,
just to give you a taste of what's
coming with the next problem set.
This program is a reimplementation
of the program you've probably
used one or more times called CP.
Recall that CP is a program
in the IDE and in Linux,
more generally, that
allows you to copy a file.
You do CP, space, the filename,
space, the new filename.
How does this work?
I now have all of the building blocks
with which to copy files myself.
So again, I'm defining a byte up here.
I'm defining main as taking
command line arguments here.
And notice one change.
I'm not using the CS50 library.
So even what was previously string
in week two is now char star.
Even here for argv, I'm making
sure that the human types
in three words, the program's name and
the source file and the destination
file.
I'm using fopen again.
I'm opening the source
file here from argv1.
I'm making sure it's not nul.
And then I'm quitting if it is.
I'm then-- here's something new,
opening the destination file here, also
with fopen.
But I'm using quote unquote, "w."
I'm opening one file with r, one file
for w, because I want to read from one
and write to the other.
And then down here, this
loop is a clever way
of copying one file to another.
I'm giving myself a buffer of one byte,
so just a temporary variable, just
like Brian's temp or empty glass.
And I'm using this function, fread.
I'm reading into that buffer via
its address, the size of a byte,
specifically one byte
from the source file.
And then, in that same loop, I'm writing
from that buffer, the size of a byte,
specifically one byte,
to the destination.
So literally, the CP program
you might have seen me use
or you yourself have used to copy
files, is literally doing this.
It's opening one file,
iterating over all of its bytes,
and copying them from
source to destination.
And then lastly, it's closing the file.
And these last two
examples deliberately fast,
because this whole week will be
spent diving into file I/O and images
thereof.
But all that we've done is use these
fread, fopen, and fwrite and f close,
to manipulate those very files.
So for instance, if I now
do this, let me do make cp.
OK, seems to compile,
dot slash cp, brian.jpeg.
How about brian2.jpeg?
And hit Enter.
Nothing seems to happen.
But if I go in here and
double click on brian2,
we see that we have a second
copy of Brian's actual file.
So this coming week, you'll experiment
with multiple file formats for images.
The first is jpegs.
And we will give you a
so-called forensic image
of a whole bunch of photographs
from a digital memory card.
In fact, it's very common these
days, certainly in law enforcement,
to take forensic copies of
hard drives, of media sticks,
of phones and other devices,
and then analyze them
for data that's been lost
or corrupted or deleted.
We'll do exactly that, whereby,
you'll write a program that recovers
jpegs that have been accidentally
deleted from a digital memory card.
And we'll give you all
copies of that memory card
by making a forensic image of it,
that is copying all of the 0's and 1's
from a camera and giving
them to you in a file
that you can fread and then fwrite from.
We'll also introduce
you to bitmap files,
BMP's, popularized by
the Windows operating
system for wallpaper's and the like.
But we'll use them to implement
using pointers and using file I/O,
your very own Instagram-like filter.
So we'll take this picture,
here, of the Weeks footbridge
here in Cambridge,
Massachusetts by Harvard.
And we'll have you implement
a number of filters,
taking this original
image, for instance,
and desaturating it,
making it black and white,
by iterating over all of the pixels
top to bottom, left to right,
and recognizing any colors, like red or
green or blue or anything in between,
and changing them to some shade
of gray, doing a sepia filter,
making things look old school,
like this photo was taken
many years ago, by similarly applying a
heuristic that alters the colors of all
of the pixels in this picture.
We'll have you flip it around so
you have to put this pixel over here
and this pixel over there.
And you'll appreciate exactly
how files are implemented
within your own hard drive and phone.
And you'll even implement, for instance,
a blur filter, which no accident,
makes it harder to see
what's going on here,
because you're starting to, now,
average together pixels that are nearby
each other to kind of gloss
things over and deliberately
make it harder to see here.
And so we'll even, if
you so choose, have
you implement edge detection,
if feeling more comfortable,
where you find the edges of all of the
physical objects in these pictures,
in order to actually detect them in
code and create visual art like this.
Now, this was a lot.
And I know pointers are
generally considered
to be among the more
challenging features of C,
and certainly, programming in general.
So if you're feeling like
it's been quite a bit, it was.
But you do now have the
ability, either today
or in the very near term, to understand
even XKCD comics like this that most
any computer scientist
out there has seen.
So our final look for you,
today, is on this joke here.
And even though I can't
necessarily hear you from afar,
I'll just assume, in
our final moments today,
that everyone is breaking out
into a very geeky laughter.
And I see some smiles, at
least, which is reassuring.
This was, then, CS50.
We'll see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]