[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
This is CS50, and this is week 7.
And today's focus is going
to be entirely on data--
the process of collecting it,
the process of storing it,
the process of searching
it, and so much more.
You'll recall that last week we
started off by playing around
with the relatively small data set.
We asked everyone for what their
preferred house at Hogwarts might be.
And then we proceeded to analyze that
data a little bit using some Python
and counting up how many people wanted
Gryffindor or Slytherin or the others,
as well.
And we ultimately did that by
using a Google form to collect it.
And we stored all of the data in a
Google spreadsheet, which we then
exported, of course, as a CSV file.
So this week, we thought we'd
collect a little more data
and see what kinds of
problems arise when
we start using only a spreadsheet
or, in turn, a CSV file
to store the data that we care about.
So in fact, if you could go ahead
and go to this URL here that you see,
you should see another Google
form, this one asking you
some different questions.
All of us probably have some preferred
TV shows, now more than ever, perhaps.
And what we'd like to do
is ask everyone to input
into that form their favorite
TV show followed by the genre
or genres into which that
particular TV show falls.
So go ahead and take
a moment to do that.
And if you're unable to follow along
at home, what folks are looking at
is a form quite like this one here,
whereby we're just asking them
for the title of their
preferred TV show and the genre
or genres of that specific TV show.
All right.
So let's go ahead and start to look
at some of this data that's come in.
Here is the resulting Google spreadsheet
that Google Forms has created for us.
And you'll notice that by default,
Google Forms, this particular tool,
has three different columns,
at least for this form.
One is a timestamp, and
Google automatically
gives us that based on what day
and time everyone was buzzing in
with the responses.
Then they have a header row
beyond that for title and genres.
I've manually boldfaced it in
advance just to make it stand out.
But you'll notice that the
headings here, Title and Genres,
perfectly matches the question
that we asked in the Google form.
That allows us to therefore line up
your responses with our questions.
And you can see here Punisher
was the first favorite TV
show to be inputted followed by The
Office, Breaking Bad, New Girl, Archer,
another Office, and so forth.
And in the third column,
under Genres, you'll
see that there's something curious here.
While some of the cells--
that is, the little boxes of text--
have just single words
like "comedy" or "drama,"
you'll notice that some of them
have a comma-separated list.
And that comma-separated list is because
some of you checked, as you could,
multiple check boxes to indicate
that Breaking Bad is a crime genre
drama and also thriller.
And so the way Google Forms handles
this is a bit sleazily in the sense
that they just drop all of those
values as a comma-separated list
inside of the spreadsheet itself.
And that's potentially a problem
if we ultimately download
this as a CSV file,
comma-separated values,
because now you have commas
in between the commas.
Fortunately, there's a solution
to that that we'll ultimately see.
So we've got a good amount of data here.
In fact, if I keep scrolling down,
we'll see a few hundred responses now.
And it would be nice to
analyze this data in some way
and figure out what the most popular
TV show is, maybe search for new shows
I might like via their genre.
So you can imagine some
number of queries that could
be answered by way of this data set.
But let's first consider the
limitations of leaving this data
in just a spreadsheet like this.
All of us are probably in the
habit of using occasionally
Google Spreadsheets, Apple Numbers,
Microsoft Excel, or some other tool.
So let's consider what spreadsheets
are good at and what they are bad at.
Would anyone like to volunteer
an answer to the first of those?
What is a spreadsheet
good at or good for?
Yeah, Andrew?
What's your thinking on spreadsheets?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, very
good for quickly sorting.
I like that.
I could click on the top of
the Title column, for instance,
and immediately sort all of
those titles by alphabetically.
I like that.
Other reasons to use a spreadsheet--
what problems do they solve?
What are they good at?
Other thoughts on spreadsheets.
Yeah, how about Peter?
AUDIENCE: Storing large amounts of
data that you can later analyze.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK, so
storing large amounts
of data that you can later analyze.
It's kind of a nice model for storing
lots of rows of data, so to speak.
I will say that there
actually is a limit.
And in fact, back in the day,
I learned what this limit is.
Long story short, in graduate
school, I was using a spreadsheet
to analyze some research data.
And at one point, I had more data
than Excel supported rows for.
Specifically, I had
some 65,536 rows, which
was too many at that point
for Excel at the time,
because, long story short, if you
recall from a spreadsheet program
like Google Spreadsheets, every
row is numbered from 1 on up.
Well, unfortunately,
at the time, Microsoft
had used a 16-bit integer,
16 bits or 2 bytes,
to represent each of those numbers.
And it turns out the 2 to the
16th power is roughly 65,000.
So at that point, I maxed
out the total number of rows.
Now, to Peter's point, they've
increased that in recent years.
And you can actually
store a lot more data.
So spreadsheets are indeed good at that.
But they're not necessarily good at
everything, because at some point,
you're going to have more data
potentially in a spreadsheet
than your Mac or PC can handle.
In fact, if you're actually trying
to build an application, whether it's
Twitter, Instagram, or Facebook
or anything of that scale,
those companies are certainly not
storing their data, suffice it to say,
in a spreadsheet, because there would
just be way too much data to use.
And no one could literally
open it on their computer.
So we'll need a solution
to that problem of scale.
But I don't think we need to throw out
what works well about spreadsheets.
So you can store indeed a
lot of data in row form.
But it would seem that you can also
store a lot of data in column form.
And even though I'm only
showing columns A, B, and C,
of course, you've
probably used spreadsheets
where you add more columns--
D, E, F, and so forth.
So what's the right mental model
for how to think about rows
versus columns in a spreadsheet?
I feel like we probably use them in a
somewhat different way conceptually.
We might think about them
a little differently.
What's the difference between
rows and columns in a spreadsheet?
Sofia.
AUDIENCE: Adding more entries.
Adding more data is--
those are within the rows, but then the
actual attributes or characteristics
of the data should be in columns.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
When you add more data
to the spreadsheet,
you should really be
adding to the bottom of it,
adding more and more rows.
So these things sort of grow
vertically, even though of course that's
just a human's perception of it.
They grow from top to bottom
by adding more and more rows.
But to Sofia's point,
your columns represent
what we might call attributes or fields
or any other such characteristic that
is a type of data that you're storing.
So in this case of our form,
Timestamp is the first column.
Title is the second column.
Genres is the third column.
And those columns can indeed be thought
of as fields or attributes, properties
of your data.
And those are properties that you should
really decide on in advance when you're
first creating the form, in our case,
or when you're manually creating
the spreadsheet in another case.
You should not really
be in the habit, when
using spreadsheets, of
adding data from left
to right, adding more and
more columns, unless you
decide to collect more types of data.
So just because someone adds a new
favorite TV show to your data set,
you shouldn't be adding that from
left to right in a new column.
You should indeed be adding
it from top to bottom.
But suppose that we actually decided to
collect more information from everyone.
Maybe that form had instead asked you
for your name or your email address
or any other questions.
Those properties or attributes or
fields would belong as new columns.
So this is to say we generally
decide on the layout of our data,
the schema of our data, in advance.
And then from there on out, we proceed
to add, add, add more rows, not
columns, unless we change
our mind and need to change
the schema of our particular data.
So it turns out that spreadsheets
are indeed wonderfully useful,
to Peter's point, for
large or reasonably large
data sets that we might collect.
And we can, of course, per last week,
export those data sets as CSV files.
And so we can go from a
spreadsheet to a simple text
file stored in ASCII or Unicode, more
generally, on your own hard drive
or somewhere in the cloud.
And you can actually think
of that file, that .CSV file,
as what we might call
a flat-file database.
A database is, generally
speaking, a file that stores data.
Or it's a program that
stores data for you.
And all of us have probably thought
about or used databases in some sense.
You're probably familiar
with the fact that all
of those same big websites, Google and
Twitter and Facebook and others, use
databases to store our data.
Well, those databases
are either just really
big files containing lots
of data or special programs
that are storing our data for us.
And a flat file is just
referring to the fact
that it really is a very simple design.
In fact, years ago,
decades ago, humans decided
when storing data in simple
text files that if you
want to store different types
of data, like, to Sofia's point,
different properties or attributes,
well, let's keep it simple.
Let's just separate
those columns with commas
in our flat-file database, a.k.a.
a CSV.
You can use other things.
You can use tabs.
There's things called TSVs,
for Tab-Separated Values.
And frankly, you can
use anything you want.
But there is a corner case.
And we've already seen a preview of it.
What if your actual
data has a comma in it?
What if the title of your
favorite TV show has a comma?
What if Google is presuming to store
genres as a comma-separated list?
Bad things can happen if using a
CSV as your flat-file database.
But there are solutions to that.
And in fact, what the
world typically does
is whenever you have commas
inside of your CSV file,
you just make sure that
the whole string is double
quoted on the far left and far right.
And anything inside of
double quotes is not
mistaken thereafter as
delineating a column
as the other commas in the file might.
So that's all that's meant
by a flat-file database.
And CSV is perhaps one of the most
common, the most common, formats
thereof, if only because
all of these programs,
like Google Spreadsheets
and Excel and Numbers,
allow you to save your files as CSVs.
Now, long story short,
those of you who have
used fancier features of spreadsheets
like built-in functions and formulas
and those kinds of
things, those are built in
and proprietary to Google
Spreadsheets and Excel and Numbers.
You cannot use formulas in a CSV file or
a TSV file or in a flat-file database,
more generally.
You can only store static--
that is, unchanging-- values.
So when you export the data,
what you see is what you get.
And that's why people
use fancier programs
like Excel and Numbers
and Google Spreadsheets,
because you get more functionality.
But if you want to export
the data, you can only
get indeed the raw
textual data out of it.
But I daresay that's going to be OK.
In fact, Brian, do
you mind if I go ahead
and download this spreadsheet
as a CSV file now?
BRIAN YU: Yep, go ahead.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
I'm going to go ahead in Google
Spreadsheets and go to File, Download.
And you can see a whole
bunch of options--
PDF, Web Page, Comma-Separated
Values, which is the one I want.
So I'm going to indeed
go ahead and choose CSV
from this dropdown in spreadsheets.
That, of course, downloaded
that file for me.
And now I'm going to go ahead and
go into our familiar CS50 IDE.
You'll recall that last week I was
able to upload a file into the IDE.
And I'm going to go ahead and do
the same here this week, as well.
I'm going to go ahead and grab my
file, which ended up in my Downloads
folder on my particular computer here.
And I'm going to go ahead and
drag and drop this into the IDE
such that it ends up in my
home directory, so to speak.
So now I have this file,
Favorite TV Shows Forms.
And in fact, if I double
click this within the IDE,
you'll see familiar data now.
Timestamp comma title comma
genres is our header row
that contains the names of the
properties or attributes in this file.
Then we've got our timestamps
comma favorite title comma and then
a comma-separated list of genres.
And here indeed, notice
that Google took care
to use double quotes around any
values that themselves had commas.
So it's a relatively simple file format.
And I could certainly just
kind of skim through this,
figuring out who likes The Office, who
likes Breaking Bad, or other shows.
But per last week, we now have a
pretty useful programming language
at our disposal, Python, that could
allow us to start manipulating
and analyzing this data more readily.
And here to my point last week about
using the right tool for the job,
you could absolutely do everything we're
about to do in all weeks prior of CS50.
We could have used C for
what we're about to do.
But as you can probably glean, C tends
to be painful for certain things,
like anything involving
string manipulation,
changing strings, analyzing strings.
It's just a real pain, right?
God forbid you had to take this CSV
file and load it all into memory, not
unlike your spell checker.
You would have to be using malloc all
over the place or realloc or the like.
There's just a lot of heavy lifting
involved in just analyzing a text file.
So Python does all of that
for us by just giving us
more functions at our
disposal with which
to start analyzing and opening data.
So let me go ahead and close this file.
And let me go ahead and create
a new one called favorites.py,
wherein I'm going to start
playing with this data set
and see if we can't start
answering some questions about it.
And frankly, to this day,
20-plus years after learning how
to program for the
first time, I myself am
very much in the habit when writing
a new program of just starting simple
and not solving the problem I ultimately
want to but something simpler just
as a sort of proof of
concept to make sure
I have the right plumbing in place.
So by that, I mean this.
Let's go ahead and write a quick program
that simply opens up this file, the CSV
file, iterates over it top to bottom,
and just prints out each of the titles,
just as a quick sanity check
that I know what I'm doing
and I have access to the data therein.
So let me go ahead and import CSV.
And then I can do this
in a few different ways.
But by now, you've
probably seen or remembered
my using something like
the open command and the
with keyword to open and eventually
automatically close this file for me.
This file is called Favorite TV
Shows - Form Responses 1.csv.
And I'm going to open
this up in read mode.
Strictly speaking,
the r is not required.
You might see examples
online not including it.
That's because read is the default.
But for parity with C and fopen,
I'm going to be explicit
and actually do "r."
And I'm going to go ahead and
give this a variable name of file.
So this line 3 here has the effect of
opening that CSV file in read-only mode
and creating a variable called
file via which I can reference it.
Now I'm going to go ahead and use
some of that CSV functionality.
I'm going to give myself what
we keep calling a reader, which
I could call it xyz, anything else.
But "reader" kind of describes
what this variable is going to do.
And it's going to be the return value
of calling csv.reader on that file.
And so essentially, the
CSV library, per last week,
has a lot of fancy features built in.
And all it needs as input is
an already opened text file.
And then it will then wrap
that file, so to speak,
with a whole bunch of
more useful functionality,
like the ability to read it
column and row at a time.
All right.
Now I'm going to go ahead and,
you know what, just for now,
I'm going to skip the first row.
I'm going to skip the first row,
because the first row has my headings--
Timestamp, Title, and Genres.
And I know what my columns are, so I'm
just going to ignore that line for now.
And now I'm going to do this.
For row in reader, let me go ahead
and print out, quite simply, row.
And I only want title, so I think if
it's three columns from left to right,
it's 0, 1, 2.
So I want to print out
column bracket 1, which
is going to be the second
column zero indexed.
All right.
Let me go ahead and save that,
go down to my terminal window,
and run python of favorites.py
and cross my fingers.
OK.
Voila.
It flew by super fast.
But it looks like, indeed,
these are all of the TV
shows that folks have inputted.
Indeed, there's a few hundred
if I keep scrolling up.
So it looks like my program is working.
But let's improve it just a little bit.
It turns out that using the
csv.reader isn't necessarily
the best approach in Python.
Many of you have already discovered
a DictReader, a dictionary reader,
which is nice, because then you don't
have to know or keep double checking
what number column your data is in.
You can instead refer it to by
the header itself, so by "title"
or by "genres."
This is also good, because
if you or maybe a colleague
are sort of messing around
with the spreadsheet
and they rearrange the columns
by dragging them left or right,
any numbers you have used
in your code, 0, 1, 2 on up,
could suddenly be incorrect if your
colleague has reordered those columns.
So using a dictionary reader tends to
be a little more robust, because it
uses the titles, not the mere numbers.
It's still fallible if someone,
yourself or someone else,
changes the values in that very first
row and renames titles or genres.
Then things are going to break.
But at that point, we
kind of have to blame you
for not having kept track of
your code versus your data.
But still a risk.
So I'm going to change this to
dictionary reader or DictReader here.
And pretty much the rest
of my code can be the same
except I don't need this
hack here on line 5.
I don't need to just skip over
to the next row from the get-go,
because I now want the dictionary
reader to handle the process of reading
that first row for me.
But otherwise, everything
else stays the same
except for this last
line, where now I think
I can now use row as a
dictionary, not as a list per se,
and print out specifically
the title from each given row.
So let me go ahead and run
python of favorites.py again.
And voila, it looks like I got the
same result, several hundred of them.
But let me stipulate that it's
doing the same thing if we actually
compared both of those side-by-side.
All right.
Before I forge ahead now
to actually augment this
with new functionality, any questions
or confusion on this Python script
we just wrote to open a file, wrap
it with a reader or DictReader,
and then iterate over the rows one
at a time, printing the titles?
Any questions, confusion
on syntax at all?
It's OK.
We've only known or
seen Python for a week.
It's fine if it's still quite new.
Anything, Brian, we should address?
BRIAN YU: Yeah.
So why is it that you don't need
to close the file using the syntax
that you're using right here?
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
Last week, I more pedantically
used open on its own.
And then I later used a close function
that was associated with the file
that I had just opened.
Now, the more Pythonic way
to do things, if you will,
is actually to use this with
keyword, which didn't exist in C.
And it just tends to be a
useful feature in Python
whereby if you say with open, dot dot
dot, it will open the file for you.
Then it will remain open so long
as your code is indented inside
of that with keywords block.
And as soon as you get to
the end of your program,
it will automatically be closed for you.
So this is one of these features
where Python in some sense
is trying to protect us from ourselves.
It's probably pretty
common for humans, myself
included, to forget to close your file.
That can create problems with
saving things permanently.
It can create memory
leaks, as we know from C.
So the with keyword just assumes
that I'm not going to be an idiot
and forget to close the file.
Python is going to do
it for me automatically.
Other questions or confusions, Brian?
BRIAN YU: How does
DictReader know that Title
is the name of the key
inside of the dictionary?
DAVID J. MALAN: Really
good question, too.
So it is designed by the
authors of the Python language
to look at the very
first row in the file,
split it on the commas
in that very first row,
and just assume that the first word
or phrase before the first comma
is the name of the first
column, that the second word
or phrase after the first comma
is the name of the second column,
and so forth.
So a DictReader just presumes,
as is the convention with CSVs,
that your first row is going to
contain the headings that you
want to use to refer to those columns.
If your CSV happens not to have
such a heading whereby it just
jumps right in on the
first row to real data,
then you're not going to be able to
use a DictReader correctly, at least
not without some manual configuration.
All right.
So let's go ahead and--
now I feel like there's
a whole mess here.
And some of these shows
are pretty popular.
And as I'm glancing over this, I
definitely see some duplication.
A whole bunch of you like The Office.
A whole bunch of you like
Breaking Bad, Game of Thrones,
and a whole bunch of
other shows, as well.
So it would be nicer,
I think, if we kind of
narrow the scope of our look at this
data by just looking at unique values.
You're looking at unique value.
So rather than just iterate
over the file top to bottom,
printing out one title
after another, why
don't we go ahead and sort of
accumulate all of this data
in some kind of data structure so that
we can throw away duplicate values
and then only print out the unique
titles that we've accumulated?
So I bet we can do this in a few ways.
But if we think back to last week's
demonstration of our dictionary,
you'll recall that I used
what was called a set.
And I'm going to go ahead and
create a variable called titles
and set it equal to
something called set.
And a set is just a
collection of values.
It's kind of like a list.
But it eliminates duplicates for me.
And that would seem to be
exactly the characteristic
that I want for this program.
Now, instead of printing each
title, which is now premature
if I want to first
filter out duplicates,
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead and add to the
titles set using the add function
the current row's title.
So again, I'm not printing it now.
I'm instead adding to the title
set that particular title.
And if it's there already, no big deal.
The set data structure
in Python is going
to throw away the duplicates for me.
And it's only going to go
ahead and keep the uniques.
Now, at the bottom of my file, I need
to do a little more work, admittedly.
Now I have to iterate over the set to
print out only those unique titles.
So let me do this.
For title in titles, go
ahead and print out title.
And this is where Python just
gets really user-friendly, right?
You don't have to do int i get
0, i less than n, or whatever.
You can just say for title in titles.
And if the title's variable
is the type of data structure
that you can iterate over, which it
will be if it's a list or if it's a set
or even if it's a dictionary,
another data structure
we saw last week in Python, the for loop
in Python will just know what to do.
This will loop over all of
the titles in the titles set.
So let me go ahead and save
this file and go ahead now
and run python of favorites.py.
And it looks like, yeah, the
list is different in some way.
But I'm seeing fewer results as I
scroll up, definitely fewer than before,
because my scrollbar didn't
jump nearly as far down.
But honestly, this is kind of a mess.
Let's go ahead and sort this.
Now, in C, it would have been
kind of a pain to sort things.
We'd have to whip out
the pseudocode, probably,
for bubble sort, selection
sort, or, god forbid,
merge sort and then
implement it ourselves.
But no, with Python comes, really, the
proverbial kitchen sink of functions.
So if you want to sort
this set, you know what?
Just say you want it sorted.
There is a function in
Python called sorted
that will use one of those better
algorithms-- maybe it's merge sort.
Maybe it's something called quicksort.
Maybe it's something else altogether.
It's not going to use a
big O of n squared sort.
Someone at Python probably has spent the
time implementing a better sort for us.
But it will go ahead
and sort the set for me.
Now let me go ahead and do this again.
Let me increase the size of my
terminal window and rerun python
of favorites.py.
OK.
And now we have an
interesting assortment
of shows that's easier for
me to wrap my mind around,
because I have it now sorted here.
And indeed, if I scroll all the way
up, we should see all of the shows
beginning with numbers
or a period, which
might have just been
someone playing around,
followed by the A words,
the B words, and so forth.
So now it's a little easier
to wrap our minds around this.
But something's up.
I feel like a lot of you like
Avatar: The Last Airbender.
And yet I'm seeing it,
indeed, four different times.
But I thought we were
filtering this down
to uniques by using that set structure.
So what's going on?
And in fact, if I keep
scrolling, I'm pretty
sure I saw more duplicates in here.
BoJack Horseman, Breaking
Bad, Breaking Bad,
Brooklyn Nine-Nine, Brooklyn Nine-Nine,
CS50 in several different flavors.
And yes, it keeps going.
Friends.
So I see a lot of duplicate values.
So what's going on?
Yeah, [? Gadana? ?]
AUDIENCE: Yeah, so your current
sort is case insensitive-- sorry,
is case sensitive, meaning that if
someone spells avatar with capital
A's in some places, then it's going
to be a different result each time.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
Some of you weren't quite diligent
when it came to capitalization.
And so in fact, the reality
is, as [? Gadana ?] notes,
that there's differences
in capitalization.
Now, we've addressed this before.
In fact, when you implemented
your spell checker,
you had to deal with
this already when you
were spell checking an arbitrary text.
Some words might be capitalized.
Some might be all
lowercase, all uppercase.
And you wanted to tolerate
different casings.
And so we probably solved this
by just forcing everything
to uppercase or everything to
lowercase and doing things,
therefore, case insensitively.
So give me just a moment here.
And I'm going to go ahead and make
a quick change to my form here.
Let's go ahead and
change this in such a way
that we actually force everything
to uppercase or lowercase.
Doesn't really matter which, but
we need to canonicalize things,
so to speak, in some way.
And to canonicalize things just
means to format all of your data
in some standard way.
So to [? Gadana's ?] point,
let's just standardize
the capitalization of things.
Maybe all uppercase, all lowercase.
We just need to make a judgment call.
So I'm going to go ahead
and make a few tweaks here.
I'm still going to use a set.
I'm still going to
read the CSV as before.
But instead of just adding the
title with row bracket title,
I'm going to go ahead and
force it to uppercase, just
arbitrarily, just for
the sake of uniformity.
And then let's go ahead and check
what exactly has happened here.
I'm not going to change anything else.
But let me go ahead and
increase the size of my terminal
window, rerun python of favorites.py.
And voila.
It's a little harder to
read, just because I'm not
used to reading all caps.
Kind of looks like we're
yelling at ourselves.
But I don't see-- wait a minute.
I still see The Office over here twice.
If I keep scrolling here, so far, I see
Stranger Things and Strainger Things.
That just looks like a typo.
I see two Sherlocks, though.
This is a little suspicious.
So [? Gadana, ?] you and I don't
seem to have solved things fully.
And this one's a little more subtle.
What more should I perhaps do to my data
to ensure we get duplicates removed?
Olivia?
AUDIENCE: Maybe trim around the edges.
DAVID J. MALAN: Trim around the edges.
I like the sound of that,
but what do you mean?
What does that do?
AUDIENCE: Oh, like, trim off
the extra spaces in case someone
put a space before or after the words.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, exactly.
It's pretty common for humans,
intentionally or accidentally,
to hit the Space bar
where they shouldn't.
And in fact, I'm kind of
inferring that I bet one or more
of you accidentally typed
Sherlock, space, and then decided,
nope, that's it.
I'm not typing anything else.
But that space, even though we can't
quite see it obviously, is there.
And when we do a string comparison or
when the set data structure does that,
it's actually going to be noticed
when doing those comparisons.
And therefore they're
not going to be the same.
So I can do this in
a few different ways.
But it turns out, in Python, you
can chain functions together,
which is also, too,
kind of a fancy feature.
Notice what I'm doing here.
I'm still accessing the titles set.
I'm adding the following value to it.
I'm adding the value row
bracket title, but not quite.
That is a string or an
str, in Python speak.
I'm going to go ahead
and strip it, which
means if we look up the documentation
for this function, to Olivia's point,
it's going to strip off or
trim all of the white space
to the left, all of the
white space to the right,
whether that's the Space
bar or the Enter key
or the Tab character or a
few other things, as well.
It's just going to get rid of
leading and trailing white space.
And then whatever's left over, I'm
going to go ahead and force everything
to uppercase in the spirit of
[? Gadana's ?] suggestion, too.
So we're sort of combining two good
ideas now to really massage the data,
if you will, into a cleaner format.
And this is such a real-world reality.
Humans, you and I, cannot be trusted to
input data the way we are supposed to.
Sometimes it's all
lowercase, because we're
being a little lazy or a
little social media-like,
even if we're checking
out from Amazon and trying
to input a valid postal address.
Sometimes it's all capitals, because
I can think of a few people in my life
who don't quite understand
the Caps Lock thing just yet.
And so things might be
all capitalized instead.
This is not good for computer
systems that require precision,
to our emphasis in week 0.
And so massaging data
means cleaning it up,
doing some mutations that don't
really change the meaning of the data
but canonicalize it,
standardize it, so that you're
comparing apples and apples, so
to speak, not apples and oranges.
Well, let me go ahead and run
this again in my bigger terminal
window, python of favorites.py.
Voila.
In scrolling up, up, up, I
think we're in a better place.
I only see one Office now.
And if I keep scrolling up and up
and up, I'm seeing typos still,
but nothing related to white space.
And I think we have a much cleaner
unique list of titles at this point.
Of course, if we scroll
up, I would have to be
a lot more clever if I want to detect
things like typographical errors.
It looks like one of you was very
diligent about putting F.R.I.
and so forth but then got bored at
the end and left off the last period.
But that's going to happen when
you're taking in user input.
We've, of course, got all
these variants of CS50.
That's going to be a mess
to clean up, because now you
can imagine having to add a whole bunch
of if conditions and elses and else ifs
to clean all of that up if
we do want to canonicalize
all different flavors of CS50
as, quote unquote, "CS50."
So this is a very slippery slope.
You and I could start writing a huge
amount of data just to clean this up.
But that's the reality when
dealing with real-world data.
Well, let's go ahead now and
improve this program further,
do something a little
fancier, because I now
can trust that my data
has been canonicalized
except for the actual typos or the
weird variants of CS50 and the like.
Let's go ahead and figure out
what's the most popular favorite TV
show among the audience here.
So I'm going to start
where I have before,
with my current code,
because I think I have
most of the building blocks in place.
I'm going to go ahead and clean
up my code a little bit in here.
I'm going to go ahead and give myself
a separate variable now called title
just so that I can think about things
in a little more orderly fashion.
But I'm not going to start adding
things to this set anymore.
In fact, a set, I don't
think, is really going
to be sufficient to keep track
of the popularity of TV shows,
because by definition, the set
is throwing away duplicates.
But the goal now is
kind of the opposite.
I want to know which are the
duplicates so that I can tell you
that this many people like The Office.
This many people like
Breaking Bad and the like.
So what tools do we have in Python's
toolkit via which we could accumulate
or figure out that information?
Any thoughts on what data
structure might help us here
if we want to figure out show,
popularity, show, popularity?
And by popularity, I just mean the
frequency of it in the CSV file.
Santiago?
AUDIENCE: I guess one option
could be to use dictionaries
so that you can have The
Office, I don't know,
20 votes, and then Game
of Thrones, another one,
so that a dictionary could
really help you visualize that.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, perfect instincts.
Recall that a dictionary, at the
end of the day, no matter how
sophisticated it's implemented
underneath the hood,
like your spell checker--
It's just a collection
of key value pairs.
And indeed, it's maybe one of the most
useful data structures in any language,
because this ability to associate
one piece of data with another
is just a very general
purpose solution to problems.
And indeed, to Santiago's
point, if the problem at hand
is to figure out the
popularity of shows,
well, let's make the keys the titles of
our shows and the frequencies thereof--
the votes, so to speak--
the values of those keys.
We're going to map title to votes, title
to vote, title to vote, and so forth.
So a dictionary is exactly that.
So let me go ahead and scroll up.
And I can make a little tweak here.
Instead of a set, I can instead
say dict and give myself
just an empty dictionary.
There's actually shorthand notation
for that that's a little more common.
So you use two empty curly braces.
That just means the exact same thing.
Give me a dictionary
that's initially empty.
There's no fancy shortcut for a set.
You have to literally type out
S-E-T, open paren and closed paren.
But dictionaries are so common,
so popular, so powerful,
they have this little syntactic
shortcut of just two curly braces,
open and closed.
So now that I have that,
let me go ahead and do this.
Inside of my for loop,
instead of printing
the title, which I don't want to do,
and instead of adding it to the set,
I now want to add it to the dictionary.
So how do I do that?
Well, if my dictionary is called titles,
I think I can essentially do something
like this, titles bracket
title = or maybe += 1.
Maybe I can kind of use the dictionary
as just a little cheat sheet
of counts, numbers, that start at
0 and then just add 1, at 2, add 3.
So every time I see The Office, The
Office, The Office, do += 1, += 1.
We can't do ++, because
that's not a thing in Python.
It only exists in C. But this would
seem to go into the dictionary called
titles, look up the key that
matches this specific title,
and then increment whatever
value is there by 1.
But I'm going to go ahead and
run this a little naively here.
Let me go ahead and run
python of favorites.py.
And wow, it broke already on line 9.
So sort of an apt choice
of show to begin with,
we have a key error with Punisher.
So Punisher is bad.
Something bad has just happened.
But what does that mean?
A key error is referring
to the fact that I
tried to access an invalid
key in a dictionary.
This is saying that literally
in this line of code
here, even though titles
is a dictionary and even
though the value of
title, singular, is, quote
unquote, "PUNISHER,"
I'm getting a key error,
because that title does not yet exist.
So even if you're not sure of the
Python syntax for fixing this problem,
what's the intuitive solution here?
I cannot increment the
frequency of the Punisher,
because Punisher is
not in the dictionary.
It almost feels like a catch-22.
[? Greg? ?]
AUDIENCE: I think that you need,
first of all, to create a for loop
and maybe assign a value to
everything in the dictionary.
For example, a value 0, and then add 1.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so good instincts.
And here, I can use another metaphor.
I worry we might have a chicken
and the egg problem there,
because I don't think I can
go to the top of my code,
add a loop that initializes all of
the values in the dictionary to 0,
because I would need to know all of
the names of the shows at that point.
Now, that's fine.
I think I could take you maybe
more literally, [? Greg, ?]
and open up the CSV file,
iterate over it top to bottom,
and, any time I see a
title, just initialize it
in the dictionary as
having a value of 0, 0, 0.
Then have another for loop, maybe
reopen the file, and do the same.
And that would work.
But it's arguably not very efficient.
It is asymptotically, in
terms of big O. But that would
seem to be doing twice as much work.
Iterate over the file once just
to initialize everything to 0.
Then iterate over the file a second
time just to increment the counts.
I think we can do things
a little more efficiently.
I think we can achieve not only
correctness but better design.
Any thoughts on how we can still
solve this problem without having
to iterate over the whole thing twice?
Yeah, [? Semowit? ?]
AUDIENCE: I think we can
add in an if statement
to check if that key
is in the dictionary.
And if it's not, then add it and then
go ahead and increment the value after.
DAVID J. MALAN: Nice.
And we can do exactly that.
So let's just apply that intuition.
If the problem is that I'm trying to
access a key that does not yet exist,
well, let's just be a
little smarter about it.
And to [? Semowit's ?] point,
let's check whether the key exists.
And if it does, then increment it.
But if it does not, then and only
then, [? to Greg's ?] advice,
initialize it to 0.
So let me do that.
Let me go ahead and
say if title in titles,
which is the very Pythonic,
beautiful way of asking a question
like that, way cleaner than in C--
let me go ahead, then, and say
exactly the line from before.
Else, though, if that title is not
yet in the dictionary called titles,
well, that's OK, too.
I can go ahead and say
titles bracket title = 0.
So the difference here is
that I can certainly index
into a dictionary using a key that
doesn't exist if I plan at that moment
to give it a value.
That's OK, and that has always
been OK since last week.
But, however, if I want to go ahead
and increment the value that's there,
I'm going to go ahead and do
that in this separate line.
But I did introduce a bug.
I did introduce a bug here.
I think I need to go one
step further logically.
I don't think I want to
initialize this to 0 per se.
Does anyone see a subtle
bug in my logic here?
If the title is already in the
dictionary, I'm incrementing it by 1.
Otherwise, I'm initializing it to 0.
Any subtle catches here?
Yeah, Olivia, what do you see?
AUDIENCE: I think you should initialize
it to 1, since it's the first instance.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
I should initialize it to 1.
Otherwise, I'm accidentally
overlooking this particular title,
and I'm going to go
ahead and undercount it.
So I can fix this either by doing this.
Or frankly, if you prefer, I don't
technically need to use an if else.
I can use just an if by doing
something like this instead.
I could say if title not in
titles, then I could go ahead
and say titles bracket title gets 0.
And then after that, I can
blindly, so to speak, just do this.
So which one is better?
I think the second one
is maybe a little better
in that I'm saving one line of code.
But it's ensuring with
that if condition,
to [? Semowit's ?] advice, that I'm
not indexing into the titles dictionary
until I'm sure that
the title is in there.
So let me go ahead and run this
now, python of favorites.py, Enter.
And OK, it didn't crash, so that's good.
But I'm not yet seeing
any useful information.
But I now have access to a bit more.
Let me scroll down now to the
bottom of this program, where
I have now this loop.
Let me go ahead and print
out not just the title
but the value of that key in
the dictionary by just indexing
into it here.
And you might not have
seen this syntax before.
But with print, you can actually
pass in multiple arguments.
And by default, print will just
separate them with a space for you.
You can override that behavior
and separate them with anything.
But this is just meant to be a quick
and dirty program that prints out
titles and now the popularity thereof.
So let me run this again,
python of favorites.py.
And voila.
It's kind of all over the place.
Office, super popular
with 26 votes there.
A lot of single votes here.
Big Bang Theory has nine.
You know, this is all nice and good.
But I feel like this is going to take
me forever to wrap my mind around which
are the most popular shows.
So of course, how would we do this?
Well, to the point made earlier,
with spreadsheets, my god,
in Microsoft Excel or Google
Spreadsheets or Apple Numbers,
you just click the column
heading and boom, sorted.
We seem to have lost that capability
unless we now do it in code.
So let me do that for us.
Let me go ahead and go back to my code.
And it looks like sorted, even
though it does work on dictionaries,
is actually sorting
by key, not by value.
And here's where our Python
programming techniques need
to get a little more sophisticated.
And we want to introduce
another feature here now
of Python which is going to
solve this problem specifically
but in a pretty general way.
So if we read the
documentation for sorted,
the sorted function indeed sorts
sets by the values therein.
It sorts lists by the values therein.
It sorts dictionaries
by the keys therein,
because dictionaries have two pieces
of information for every element.
It has a key and a
value, not just a value.
So by default, sorted sorts by key.
So we somehow have to
override that behavior.
So how can we do this?
Well, it turns out that
the sorted function
takes another optional
argument literally called key.
And the key argument takes as
its value the name of a function.
And this is where things
get really interesting,
if not confusing, really quickly.
It turns out, in Python, you can
pass around functions as arguments
by way of their name.
And technically, you can do this in C.
It's a lot more syntactically involved.
But in Python, it's very common.
In JavaScript, it's very common.
In a lot of languages, it's very
common to think of functions
as first-class objects, which is a fancy
way of saying you can pass them around
just like they are variables themselves.
We're not calling them yet.
But you can pass them
around by their name.
So what do I mean by this?
Well, I need a function now to
sort my dictionary by its value.
And only I know how to do this, perhaps,
so let me go ahead and give myself
a generic function name just for the
moment called f-- f for function,
kind of like in math--
because we're going to
get rid of it eventually.
But let me go ahead and
temporarily define a function
called f that takes as input a title.
And then it returns for me the
value corresponding to that key.
So I'm going to go ahead and
return titles bracket title.
So here, we have a function whose
purpose in life is super simple.
You give it a title.
It gives you the count thereof, the
frequency, the popularity thereof,
by just looking it up in
that global dictionary.
So it's super simple, but
that's its only purpose in life.
But now, according to the
documentation for sorted,
what it's now going to do, because I'm
passing in a second argument called
key, the sorted function, rather than
just presume you want everything sorted
alphabetically by key,
it's instead going
to call that function f on every one
of the elements in your dictionary.
And depending on your
answer, the return value
you give with that f function,
that will be used instead
to determine the actual ordering.
So by default, sorted just looks at key.
What I'm effectively
doing with this f function
is instead returning the value
corresponding to every key.
And so the logical implication of this,
even though the syntax is a little new,
is that this dictionary
of titles will now
be sorted by value instead of by key.
Because again, by
default, it sorts by key.
But if I define my own key
function and override that behavior
to return the corresponding value,
it's the values, the numbers,
the counts that will actually
be used to this thing.
All right.
Let's go ahead and see if
that's true in practice.
Let me go ahead and rerun
python of favorites.py.
I should see all the titles.
And voila, conveniently,
the most popular show
seems to be Game of Thrones with 33
votes, followed by Friends with 27,
followed by The Office
with 26, and so forth.
But of course, the list
is kind of backwards.
I mean, it's convenient that I can
see it at the bottom of my screen.
But really, if we're making a list,
it should really be at the top.
So how can we override that behavior?
Turns out the sorted function,
if you read its documentation,
also takes another optional
parameter called reverse.
And if you set reverse
equal to True, capital
T in Python, that's going
to go ahead and give us now
the reverse order of that same sort.
So let me go ahead and maximize my
terminal window, rerun it again.
And voila, if I scroll back up to the
top, it's not alphabetically sorted.
But if I keep going, keep
going, keep going, keep going,
the numbers are getting bigger.
And voila, now Game of Thrones
with 33 is all the way at the top.
All right, so pretty cool.
And again, the new functionality
here in Python, at least,
is that we can actually pass
in functions to functions
and leave it to the
latter to call the former.
So that's complicated just to say.
But any questions or confusion now
on how we are using dictionaries
and how we are sorting things in
this reverse, value-based way?
Any questions or confusion?
Anything in the chat or verbally, Brian?
BRIAN YU: Looks like all
questions are answered here.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
Then in that case, let me
point out a common mistake.
Notice that even though f is a function,
notice that I did not call it there.
That would be incorrect, the
reason being we deliberately
want to pass the function
f into the sorted function
so that the sorted function can take it
upon itself to call f again and again
and again.
We don't want to just call it once
by using the parentheses ourselves.
We want to just pass it in by name so
that the sorted function, which comes
with Python, can instead do it for us.
Santiago, did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: Yes, I was going to ask.
Why didn't we put f of title?
I was going to ask that
question specifically.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh,
with the parentheses?
AUDIENCE: Yeah.
DAVID J. MALAN: Oh, OK, perfect.
So because that would call the
function once and only once.
We want sorted to be able
to call it again and again.
Now, here's actually an
example, as we've seen
in the past, of a correct solution.
This is behaving as I intend, a list
of sorted titles from top to bottom
in order of popularity.
But it's a little poorly
designed, because I'm
defining this function f, whose name
in the first place is kind of lame.
But I'm defining a function
only to use it in one place.
And my god, the function is so tiny, it
just feels like a waste of keystrokes
to have defined a new function
just to then pass it in.
So it turns out, in Python, if you
have a very short function whose
purpose in life is meant to be to solve
a local problem just once and that's it
and it's short enough that you're pretty
sure you can fit it on one line of code
without things wrapping and starting
to get ugly stylistically, it turns out
you can actually do this instead.
You can copy the code that
you had in mind like this.
And instead of actually
defining f as a function name,
you can actually use a special
keyword in Python called lambda.
You can specify the name of an
argument for your function as before.
And then you can simply specify
the return value, thereafter
deleting the function itself.
So to be clear, key is still an
argument to the sorted function.
It expects as its value
typically the name of a function.
But if you've decided that, eh,
this seems like a waste of effort
to define a function,
then pass the function in,
especially when it's so short,
you can do it in a one liner.
A lambda function is
an anonymous function.
Lambda literally says,
Python, give me a function.
I don't care about its name.
Therefore, you don't have
to choose a name for it.
But it does care still about its
arguments and its return value.
So it's still up to you to provide zero
or more arguments and a return value.
And notice I've done that.
I've specified the keyword lambda
followed by the name of the argument
I want this anonymous,
nameless function to accept.
And then I'm specifying
the return value.
And with lambda functions, you
do not need to specify return.
Whatever you write after
the colon is literally
what will be returned automatically.
So again, this is a very
Pythonic thing to do.
It's kind of a very clever one liner,
even though it's a little cryptic
to see for the very first time.
But it allows you to condense your
thoughts into a succinct statement that
gets the job done so you don't have to
start defining more and more functions
that you or someone else
then need to keep track of.
All right.
Any questions, then, on this?
And I am pretty sure this is as complex
or sophisticated as our Python code
today will get.
Yeah, over to Sophia.
AUDIENCE: I was wondering why
"lambda" is used specifically
rather than some other keyword.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so
there's a long history in this.
And if, in fact, you take a course on
functional programming-- at Harvard,
it's called CS51--
there's a whole etymology
behind keywords like this.
Let me defer that one for another time.
But indeed, not only in
Python but in other languages,
as well, these things have come
to exist called lambda functions.
So they're actually quite commonplace
in other languages, as well.
And so Python just
adopted the term of art.
Mathematically, lambda is often
used as a symbol for functions.
And so they borrowed that same
idea in the world of programming.
All right.
So seeing no other questions, let's go
ahead and solve a related problem still
with some Python but
that's going to push up
against the limits of efficiency when it
comes to storing our data in CSV files.
Let me go ahead and start fresh
in this file, Favorites.py.
All of the code I've
written thus far, though,
is on the course's
website in advance, so you
can see the incremental improvement.
I'm going to go ahead and,
again, import csv at the top.
And now let's write a program
this time that doesn't just
automatically open up the
CSV and analyze it looking
for the total popularity of shows.
Let's search for a specific
show in the CSV and then
go ahead and output
the popularity thereof.
And I can do this in a
bunch of different ways.
But I'm going to try to make
this as concise as possible.
I'm first going to ask
the user to input a title.
I could use CS50's get_string function.
But recall that it's pretty much
the same as Python's input function,
so I'm going to use Python's
input function today.
And then I'm going to
go ahead and, as before,
open up that same CSV
called Favorite TV Shows -
Form Responses 1.csv in read-only
mode as a variable called file.
I'm then going to give myself a
reader, and I'll use a DictReader again
so I don't have to worry about
knowing which columns things are in,
passing in file.
And then let's see.
If I only care about one title,
I can keep this program simpler.
I don't need to figure out
the popularity of every show.
I just need to figure out the
popularity of one show, the title
that the human has typed in.
So I'm going to go ahead and give
myself a very simple int called counter
and set it equal to 0.
I don't need a whole dictionary.
Just one variable suffices now.
And I'm going to go ahead and iterate
over the rows in the reader, as before.
And then I'm going to say if the current
row's title == the title the human
typed in, let's go ahead
and increment counter by 1.
And it's already initialized,
because I did that on line 7.
So I think I'm good.
And then at the end
of this program, let's
very simply print out
the value of counter.
So the purpose of this program is to
prompt the user for a title of a show
and then just report
the popularity thereof
by counting the number of
instances of it in the file.
So let me go ahead and run this
with python of favorites.py.
Enter.
Let me go ahead and type in
"The Office," Enter, and 19.
Now, I don't remember
exactly what the number was.
But I remember The Office
was more popular than that.
I'm pretty sure it was not 19.
Any intuition as to why this program
is buggy or so it would seem?
BRIAN YU: A few people
in the chat are saying
you need to remember to deal with
capitalization and white space again.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
So we need to practice those
same lessons learned from before.
So I should really canonicalize the
input that the human, I, just typed in
and also the input that's
coming from the CSV file.
Perhaps the simplest way
to do this is, up here,
to first strip off leading and trailing
white space in case I get a little
sloppy and hit the Space
bar where I shouldn't.
And then let's go ahead and force
it to uppercase just because.
It doesn't matter if
it's upper or lower,
but at least we'll
standardize things that way.
And then when I do this, look
at the current rows title.
I think I really need
to do the same thing.
If I'm going to canonicalize one,
I need to canonical the other.
And now compare the all-caps,
white-space-stripped versions
of both strings.
So now let me rerun it.
Now I'm going to type
in "The Office," Enter.
And voila.
Now I'm at 26, which I think
is where we were at before.
And in fact, now I, the
user, can be a little sloppy.
I can say "the office."
I can run it again and say "the
office" and then, for whatever reason,
hit the Space bar a lot, Enter.
It's still going to work.
And indeed, though we seem to
be belaboring the pedantic here
with trimming off white space
and so forth, just think.
In a relatively small
audience here, how many of you
accidentally hit the Space bar or
capitalized things differently?
This happens massively on scale.
And you can imagine this being
important when you're tagging
friends in some social media account.
You're doing @Brian or the like.
You don't want to have to require
the user to type @, capital B,
lowercase r-i-a-n, and so forth.
So tolerating disparate,
messy user input
is such a common problem
to solve, including
in today's apps that we all use.
All right.
Any questions, then, on this
program, which I think is correct?
Then let me ask a question of you.
In what sense is this
program poorly designed?
This is more subtle.
But think about the running time
of this program in terms of big O.
What is the running time of this program
if the CSV file has n different shows
in it or n different submissions?
So n is the variable in question.
Yeah, what's the running time, Andrew?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, it's big O
of n, because I'm literally using
linear search by way of the for loop.
That's how a for loop works in Python,
just like in C. Starts at the beginning
and potentially goes all
the way till the end.
And so I'm using
implicitly linear search,
because I'm not using any fancy data
structures, no sets, no dictionaries.
I'm just looping from top to bottom.
So you can imagine that if we surveyed
not just all of the students here
in class but maybe everyone on
campus or everyone in the world--
maybe we're Internet
Movie Database, IMDb.
There could be a huge number of
votes and a huge number of shows.
And so writing a program, whether
it's in a terminal window like mine
or maybe on a mobile device or maybe on
a webpage for your laptop or desktop,
it's probably not the best
design to constantly loop
over all of the shows in
your database from top
to bottom just to answer
a single question.
It would be much nicer to do things
in log of n time or in constant time.
And thankfully, over the past few
weeks, both in C and in Python,
we have seen smarter ways to do this.
But I'm not practicing
what I've preached here.
And in fact, at some point, this
notion of a flat-file database
starts to get too primitive for us.
Flat-file databases, like CSV
files, are wonderfully useful
when you just want to
do something quickly
or when you want to download
data from some third party,
like Google, in a
standard, portable way.
"Portable" means that it can be used by
different people and different systems.
CSV is about as simple
as it gets, because you
don't need to own
Microsoft Word or Apple
Numbers or any particular product.
It's just a text file, so
you can use any text editing
program or any programming
language to access it.
But flat-file databases aren't
necessarily the best structure
to use ultimately for larger data
sets, because they don't really
lend themselves to
more efficient queries.
So CSV files, pretty much at best,
you have to search top to bottom,
left to right.
But it turns out that there are better
databases out there generally known
as relational databases that, instead
of being files in which you store data,
they are instead programs
in which you store data.
Now, to be fair, those programs
use a lot of RAM, memory,
where they actually store your data.
And they do certainly persist your data.
They keep it long term by
storing your data also in files.
But between you and your data,
there is this running program.
And if you've ever heard of Oracle
or MySQL or PostgreSQL or SQL Server
or Microsoft Access or bunches
of other popular products,
both commercial and free
and open source alike,
relational databases are so
similar in spirit to spreadsheets.
But they are implemented in software.
And they give us more and more features.
And they use more and
more data structures
so that we can search for data, insert
data, delete data, update data much,
much more efficiently than we could if
just using something like a CSV file.
So let's go ahead and take
our five-minute break here.
And when we come back, we'll look at
relational databases and, in turn,
a language called SQL.
All right.
So we are back.
And the goal at hand
now is to transition
from these fairly simplistic
flat-file databases
to a more proper relational database.
And relational databases are
indeed what power so many
of today's mobile applications,
web applications, and the like.
Now we're beginning to
transition to real-world software
with real-world languages, at that.
And so now, let me introduce
what we're going to call SQLite.
So it turns out that
a relational database
is a database that stores all of
the data still in rows and columns.
But it doesn't do so using
spreadsheets or sheets.
It instead does so using what
we're going to call tables.
So it's pretty much the same idea.
But with tables, we get some
additional functionality.
With those tables,
we'll have the ability
to search for data, update data, delete
data, insert new data, and the like.
And these are things that we
absolutely can do with spreadsheets.
But in the world of spreadsheets,
if you want to search for something,
it's you, the human, doing it by
manually clicking and scrolling,
typically.
If you want to insert
data, it's you, the human,
typing it in manually
after adding a new row.
If you want to delete
something, it's you right
clicking or Control-clicking
and deleting a whole row
or updating the individual
cells they're in.
With SQL, Structured Query Language,
we have a new programming language
that is very often used in conjunction
with other programming languages.
And so today, we'll see SQL
used on its own initially.
But we'll also see it in the
context of a Python program.
So a language like Python can itself
use SQL to do more powerful things
than Python alone could do.
So with that said, SQLite is
like a light version of SQL.
It's a more user-friendly version.
It's more portable.
It can be used on Macs and PCS and
phones and laptops and desktops
and servers.
But it's incredibly common.
In fact, in your iPhone and your
Android phone, many of the applications
you are running today on your own device
are using SQLite underneath the hood.
So it isn't a toy language per se.
It's instead a relatively
simple implementation
of a language generally known as SQL.
But long story short, there's other
implementations of relational databases
out there.
And I rattled off
several of them already--
Oracle and MySQL and
PostgreSQL and the like.
Those all have slightly different
flavors or dialects of SQL.
So SQL is a fairly standard language
for interacting with databases.
But different companies,
different communities
have kind of added or subtracted
their own preferred features.
And so the syntax you use is generally
constant across all platforms.
But we will standardize
for our purposes on SQLite.
And indeed, this is what
you would use these days
in the world of mobile applications.
So it's very much germane there.
So with SQLite, we're going to have
ultimately the ability to query data
and update data, delete
data, and the like.
But to do so, we actually
need a program with which
to interact with our database.
So the way SQLite works is
that it stores all of your data
still in a file.
But it's a binary file now.
That is, it's a file
containing 0's and 1's.
And those 0's and 1's
might represent text.
They might represent numbers.
But it's a more compact,
efficient representation
than a mere CSV file would
be using ASCII or Unicode.
So that's the first difference.
SQLite uses a single
file, a binary file,
to store all of your data and represent
it inside of that file by way of all
of those 0's and 1's or the
tables to which I alluded before,
which are the analogue in the database
world of sheets or spreadsheets
in the spreadsheet world.
So to interact with that binary file
wherein all of your data is stored,
we need some kind of
user-facing program.
And there's many different tools to use.
But the standard one
that comes with SQLite
is called sqlite3, essentially
version 3 of the tool.
This is a command line tool similar
in spirit to any of the commands
you've run in a terminal
window thus far that
allows you to open up that binary file
and interact with all of your tables.
Now, here again, we kind of have
a chicken and the egg problem.
If I want to use a database
but I don't yet have a database
and yet I want to select
data from my database,
how do I actually load things in?
Well, you can load data into a
SQLite database in at least two ways.
One, which I'll do in
a moment, you can just
import an existing flat-file
database, like a CSV.
And what you do is you save the CSV
on your Mac or PC on your CS50 IDE.
You run a special command with sqlite3.
And it will just load
the CSV into memory.
It will figure out where
all of the commas are.
And it will construct inside of that
binary file the corresponding rows
and columns using the
appropriate 0's and 1's
to store all of that information.
So it just imports it
for you automatically.
Approach 2 would be to actually
write code in a language like Python
or any other that actually
manually inserts all of the data
into your database.
And we'll do that, as well.
But let's start simple.
Let me go ahead and run,
for instance, sqlite3.
And this is preinstalled on CS50 IDE,
and it's not that hard to get it up
and running on a Mac and PC, as well.
I'm going to go ahead and run
sqlite3 in my terminal window here.
And voila.
You just see some very simple output.
It's telling me to type .help if
I want to see some usage hints.
But I know most of the
commands, and we'll generally
give you all of the commands
that you might need.
In fact, one of the commands that we can
use is .mode, and another is .import.
So generally, you won't
use these that frequently.
You'll only use them when creating
a database for the first time when
you are creating that database
from an existing CSV file.
And indeed, that's my
goal at the moment.
Let me take our CSV file containing
all of your favorite TV shows
and load it into SQLite in
a proper relational database
so that we can do better
than, for instance, big O of n
when it comes to searching that
data and doing anything else on it.
So to do this, I have
to execute two commands.
One, I need to put SQLite into CSV mode.
And that's just to distinguish
it from other flat-file formats,
like TSV for tabs or some other format.
And now I'm going to go
ahead and run .import.
Then I have to specify the name of
the file to import, which is the CSV.
And I'm going to go ahead
and call my table shows.
So .import takes two arguments, the
name of the file that you want to import
and the name of the table that you
want to create out of that file.
And again, tables have rows and columns.
And the commas in the file
are going to delineate
where those columns begin and end.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
It looks like it flew by pretty fast.
Nothing seems to have happened.
But I think that's OK, because now we're
going to go ahead and have the ability
to actually manipulate that data.
But how do we manipulate the data?
We need a new language.
SQL, Structured Query Language, is the
language used by SQLites and Oracle
and MySQL and PostgreSQL and
bunches of other products
whose names you don't need to
know or remember any time soon.
But SQL is the language we'll use to
query the database for information
and do something with it.
Generally speaking, a relational
database and, in turn,
SQL, which is a language via which you
can interact with relational databases,
support four fundamental operations.
And they're sort of a crude
acronym, pun intended,
that is just helpful for remembering
what those fundamental operations are
with relational databases.
CRUD stands for Create,
Read, Update, and Delete.
And indeed, the acronym
is CRUD, C-R-U-D.
So it helps you remember that the
four basic operations supported by any
relational database are
create, read, update, delete.
"Create" means to
create or add new data.
"Read" means to access and
load into memory new data.
We've seen read before
with opening files.
"Update" and "delete" mean
exactly that, as well,
if you want to manipulate
the data in your data set.
Now, those are generic terms
for any relational database.
Those are the four properties typically
supported by any relational database.
In the world of SQL, there are some
very specific commands or functions,
if you will, that implement
those four functionalities.
They are create and insert--
achieve the same thing
as create more generally.
The keyword "select" is what's
used to read data from a database.
Update and delete are the same.
So it's kind of an
annoying inconsistency.
The acronym or the term of art is
CRUD, Create, Read, Update, Delete.
But in the world of SQL,
the authors of the language
decided to implement
those four ideas by way
of these five keywords or functions or
commands, if you will, in the language
SQL.
So what you are looking at
are five of the keywords
that you can use in this new language
called SQL to actually do something
with your database.
Now, what does that mean?
Well, suppose that you
wanted to manually create
a database for the very first time.
What do you do?
Well, back in the world of spreadsheets,
it's pretty straightforward, right?
You'd open up Google Spreadsheets.
You go to File, New or whatever.
And then you just, voila,
get a new spreadsheet
into which you can start creating
rows and columns and the like.
In Microsoft Excel, Apple
Numbers, same thing--
File menu, New Spreadsheet or whatever,
and boom, you have a new spreadsheet.
Now, in the world of SQL,
SQL databases are generally
meant to be interacted with code.
However, there are Graphical
User Interfaces, GUIs, by which
you can interact with them, as well.
But we're going to use code today to
do so and programs at a command line.
It turns out that you can
create tables programmatically
by running a command like this.
So if you literally type out syntax
along the lines of CREATE TABLE, then
the name of your table,
indicated here in lowercase,
then a parenthesis, then the name of
your column that you want to create
and the type of that column,
a la C, and then comma, dot,
dot, dot, some more
columns, this is generally
speaking the syntax you'll use
to create in this language called
SQL a new table.
Now, this is in the abstract.
Again, table in lowercase is
meant to represent the name
you want to give to your actual table.
column in lowercase is
meant to be the name
you want to give to your own column.
Maybe it's Title.
Maybe it's Genres.
And dot, dot, dot just
means, of course, you
can have even more columns than that.
But literally in a moment, if I
were to type in this kind of command
into the terminal window after
running the sqlite3 program,
I could start creating one
or more tables for myself.
And in fact, that's what
already happened for me.
This .import command,
which is not part of SQL--
this is the equivalent of a Menu
option in Excel or Google Spreadsheets.
.import just automates a
certain process for me.
And what it did for me is this.
If I type now .schema, which is
another SQLite-specific command--
anything that starts with a .
is specific only to sqlite3,
this terminal window program.
Notice what's outputted is this.
By running .import that automatically
for me created a table in my database
called shows.
And it gave it three columns--
Timestamp, title, and genres.
Where did those column names come from?
Well, they came from the
very first line in the CSV.
And they all looked like text,
so the type of those values
was just assumed to be text, text, text.
Now, to be clear, I could
have manually type this out,
created these three columns in
a new table called shows for me.
But again, the .import command
just automated that from a CSV.
But the SQL is what we see here,
CREATE TABLE shows and so forth.
So that is to say now, in this
database, there is a file--
or rather, there is a
table called shows inside
of which is all of the
data from that CSV.
How do I actually get at that data?
Well, it turns out there's
other commands were called.
Not just CREATE, but also
SELECT, it turns out.
SELECT is the equivalent of read,
getting data from the database.
And this one is pretty powerful.
And the reason that so many data
scientists and statisticians
use and like using languages like SQL--
they make it relatively easy to
just get data and filter that data
and analyze that data using
new syntax for us today,
but relatively simple syntax
relative to other things we've seen.
The SELECT command in SQL lets
you select one or more columns
from your table by the given name.
So we'll see this now
in just a moment here.
How might I go about doing this?
Well, let me go ahead and now, at my
prompt after just clearing the window
to keep things neat,
let me try this out.
Let me go ahead and SELECT,
let's say, title FROM shows;.
So why am I doing this?
Well, again, the conventional
format for the SELECT command
is to say SELECT, then the name
of one or more columns, then
literally the preposition FROM, and then
the name of the table from which you
want to select that data.
So if my table is called shows
and the column is called title,
it stands to reason that SELECT
title FROM shows should give me
back the data I want.
Now, notice a couple
of stylistic choices
that aren't strictly
required but are good style.
Conventionally, I would
capitalize any SQL keywords,
including SELECT and FROM
in this case, and then
lowercase anything that's a
column name or a table name,
assuming you created those columns
and tables in, in fact, lowercase.
There's different conventions out there.
Some people will uppercase.
Some people will use something called
camel case or snake case or the like.
But generally speaking, I
would encourage all caps
for SQL syntax and lowercase
for the column and table names.
I'm going to go ahead now and hit Enter.
And voila.
We see rapidly a whole list of
values outputted from the database.
And if you think way back, you
might recognize that this actually
happens to be the same order
as before, because the CSV
file was loaded top to bottom
into this same database table.
And so what we're seeing, in fact,
is all of that same data, duplicates
and miscapitalizations
and weird spacing and all.
But suppose I want to see
all of the data from the CSV.
Well, it turns out you can
select multiple columns.
You can select not only title, but
maybe timestamp was of interest.
And this one admittedly was
capitalized, because that's
what it was in the spreadsheet.
That was not something I chose manually.
So if I just use a comma-separated
list of column names,
notice what I can do now.
It's a little hard to see for us humans,
because there's a lot going on now.
But notice that in double
quotes on the left,
there are all of the timestamps, which
represent the time at which you all
submitted your favorite shows.
And on the right of the comma,
there's another quoted string
that is the title of the show
that you liked, although SQLite
omits the quotes if it's just a single
word, like Friends, just by convention.
In fact, if I want to
get all of the columns,
turns out there's some
shorthand syntax for that.
* is the so-called wild card operator.
And it will get me all of the columns
from left to right in my table.
And voila.
Now I see all of the data, including
all of the genres, as well.
So now I effectively have three columns
being outputted all at once here.
Well, this is not that useful thus far.
In fact, all I've been doing
is really just outputting
the contents of the CSV.
But SQL's powerful because it comes with
other features right out of the box,
somewhat similar in spirit to functions
that are built into Google Spreadsheets
and Excel.
But now we can use them
ultimately in our own code.
So functions like AVG, COUNT,
DISTINCT, LOWER, MAX, MIN,
and UPPER and bunches more, these
are all functions built into SQL
that you can use as part of your query
to alter the data as it's coming back
from the database-- not
permanently, but as it's
coming back to you-- so that it's
in a format you actually care about.
So for instance, one
of my goals earlier,
was to get back just the
distinct, the unique titles.
And we had to write all that
annoying code using a set
and then add things to the set and
then loop over it again, right?
That was not a huge amount of code.
But it definitely took us, what, 5, 10
minutes to get the job done at least.
In SQL, you can do all
of that in one breath.
I'm going to go ahead now and do this.
SELECT not just title FROM shows.
Let me go ahead and SELECT
DISTINCT title FROM shows.
So DISTINCT, again, is an
available function in SQL
that does what the name says.
It's going to filter
out all of the titles
to just give me the distinct ones back.
So if I hit Enter now, you'll see a
similarly messy list but including--
"no idea," someone
that doesn't watch TV--
including an unsorted
list of those titles.
So I think we can probably start to
clean this thing up as we did before.
Let me go ahead and now
SELECT not just DISTINCT,
but let me go ahead and
uppercase everything as well.
And I can use UPPER as another function.
And notice I'm just nesting things.
The output of one function, as
we've seen in many languages now,
can be the input to another.
Let me hit Enter now.
And now it's getting a little
more canonicalized, so to speak,
because I'm using
capitalization for everything.
But it would seem that things
still aren't really sorted.
It's just the same order
in which you inputted them
but without duplicates this time.
So it turns out that
SQL has other syntax
that we can use to make our queries
more precise and more powerful.
So in addition to these
kinds of functions
that you can use to alter the
data that's being shown to you
and coming back, you can also use
these kinds of clauses or syntax
in SQL queries.
You can say WHERE, which is
the equivalent of a condition.
You can say select all of this data
where something is true or false.
You can say LIKE, where you can say
give me data that isn't exactly this
but is like this.
You can order the data by some column.
You can limit the number
of rows that come back.
And you can group identical
values together in some way.
So let's see a few examples of this.
Let me go back here and
play around now with--
how about The Office?
That was the one we looked at earlier.
So let me go ahead and SELECT title
FROM shows WHERE title = "The Office";.
So I've added this WHERE predicate, so
to speak, WHERE title = "The Office."
So SQL's nice.
Similar in spirit to Python,
it's more user friendly, perhaps,
than C where everything kind of sort
of reads like an English sentence,
even though it's a little more precise.
And it's a little more succinct.
Let me go ahead and hit Enter.
And voila.
That's how many of you
inputted The Office.
But notice it's not everyone, is it?
We're missing some still.
It seems that I got back only
those of you who typed in literally
"The Office," capital T, capital O.
So what if I want to be a
little more resilient than that?
Well, let me get back any rows
where you all typed in "office."
Maybe you omitted the article "the."
So let me go ahead and
say not title = "Office."
but let me go ahead and say
where the title is like "Office."
But I don't want it to just be "office."
I want to allow for maybe some stuff
at the beginning, maybe some stuff
at the end.
And even though that seems
like a bit of an inconsistency,
in the context of using LIKE,
there's another wild card character.
The percent sign represents zero
or more characters to the left.
And this percent sign represents
zero or more characters to the right.
So it's kind of this catchall that will
now find me all titles that somewhere
have O-F-F-I-C-E inside of them.
And it turns out LIKE
is case insensitive,
so I don't even need to worry
about capitalization with LIKE.
Now let me hit Enter.
And voila.
Now I get back more answers.
And you can really
see the messiness now.
Notice up here one of
you used lowercase.
That tends to be common when
typing things in quickly.
One of you did it lowercase
here and then also gave
us an extra white space at the end.
One of you just typed in "office."
One of you typed in "the office"
again with a space at the end.
And so there's a lot of variation here.
And that's why, when we
forced everything to uppercase
and we started trimming
things, we were able to get rid
of a lot of those redundancies.
Well, in fact, let's go
ahead and order this now.
So let me go back to selecting
the distinct uppercase title,
so SELECT DISTINCT UPPER
of title FROM shows.
And let me now ORDER BY, which is a
new clause, the uppercased version
of title.
So now notice there's a
few things going on here.
But I'm just building up
more complicated queries
similar to scratch, where we just
started throwing more and more puzzle
pieces at a problem.
I'm selecting all of the distinct
uppercase titles from the shows table.
But I'm going to order
the results this time
by the uppercased version of title.
So everything is going to be uppercased.
And then it's going to be sorted
A through Z. Hit Enter now,
and now things are a little
easier to make sense of.
Notice the quotes are there only when
there are multiple words in a title.
Otherwise, sqlite3
doesn't bother showing us.
But notice here's all the "the" shows.
And if we keep scrolling up, the P's,
the N's, the M's, the L's, and so
forth-- it's indeed alphabetized
thanks to using ORDER BY.
All right.
Well, let's start to solve more
similar problems now in SQL
by writing way less code than
we did a bit ago in Python.
Suppose I want to actually figure out
the counts of these most popular shows.
So I want to combine all
of the identical shows
and figure out all of
the corresponding counts.
Well, let me go ahead and try this.
Let me go ahead and SELECT again
the uppercased version of title.
But I'm not going to do
DISTINCT this time, because I
want to do that a little differently.
I'm going to SELECT
the uppercased version
of title, the COUNT of those titles--
so the number of times a
given title appears, so COUNT
is a new keyword now--
FROM shows.
But now how do I figure
out what the count is?
Well, if you think about this
table as having a lot of titles--
title, title, title, title, title--
it would be nice to kind of group
the identical titles together
and then actually count how many
such titles we grouped together.
And the syntax for that is literally
to say GROUP BY UPPER(title);.
This tells SQL to group all
of the uppercased titles
together, kind of collapse
multiple rows into one,
but keep track of the count
of titles after that collapse.
Let me go ahead now and hit Enter.
And you'll see, very similar to one of
the earlier Python programs we wrote,
all of the titles on the left followed
by a comma, followed by the count.
So one of you really
likes Tom and Jerry.
One of you really likes Top Gear.
If I scroll up, though, two
of you really liked The Wire.
23 of you here like The
Office, although we still
haven't trimmed the issue here.
So we could still combine that further
by trimming whitespace if we want.
But now we're getting
these kinds of counts.
Well, how can I go ahead and
order this, as we did before?
Let me go ahead here and
add ORDER BY COUNT of title
and then hit semicolon now.
And now notice, just as
in Python, everything
is from smallest to largest
initially, with Game of Thrones
here down on the bottom.
How can I fix this?
Well, it turns out if you can
order things in descending order,
D-E-S-C for short instead of A-S-C,
which is the default for ascending--
so if I do it in descending order, now
I'd have to scroll all the way back up
to the A's, the very top, to
see where the lines begin.
Whoops.
If I scroll all the way back up to the
top, we'll see where all of the A words
begin up here.
And now if I want to--
whoops, whoops, whoops.
Did I do that right?
Sorry.
I don't want to--
there we go, ORDER BY COUNT descending.
Now let me go ahead and-- this is
just a little too unwieldy to see.
Let me just limit myself to
the top 10 and keep it simple
and only look at the top 10 values here.
Voila.
Now I have Game of Thrones at 33,
Friends at 26, The Office at 23--
though I think I'm still missing a few.
Brian, do you recall the SQL function
for trimming leading and trailing
white space?
BRIAN YU: I think it's just TRIM.
DAVID J. MALAN: TRIM?
OK.
I myself did not remember.
So when in doubt, google or ask Brian.
So let me go ahead and fix this.
Let me go ahead and SELECT uppercase
of trimming the title first.
And then I'm going to GROUP BY
trimming and then uppercasing it there.
And now Enter, and voila.
Thank you, Brian.
So now we're up to our 26 Offices here.
So in short, it took us
a little while to get
to this point in the story in SQL.
But notice what we've done.
We've taken a program
that took us a few minutes
and certainly a dozen
or more lines of code.
And we've distilled it into something
that, yes, is a new language
but is just kind of a one liner.
And once you get comfortable
with a language like SQL,
especially if you're not even a
computer scientist but maybe a data
scientist or an analyst of some sort
who spends a lot of their day looking
at financial information
or medical information
or really any data set that can
be loaded into rows and columns,
once you start to speak
and read SQL as a human can
you start to express some pretty
powerful queries relatively succinctly
and, boom, get back your answer.
And by using a command
line program, like sqlite3,
you can immediately see the results
there, albeit as very simplistic text.
But as mentioned, too, there's
also some graphical programs
out there, free and commercial, that
also support SQL, where you can still
type these commands.
And then it will show it to you
in a more user friendly way, much
like in Windows or
macOS would by default.
So any questions now on the syntax
or capabilities of SELECT statements?
BRIAN YU: One question came in.
Where is the file with this
data actually being stored?
DAVID J. MALAN: Good question.
Where is the file actually being stored?
So before quitting, I can actually
save this file as anything.
I want the file extension
would typically be .db.
And in fact, Brian, do
you mind just checking?
What's the syntax for writing the
file manually with dot something?
It would be under .help, I think.
BRIAN YU: I think it's .save
followed by the name of the file.
DAVID J. MALAN: .save, so I'll
call this shows.db, Enter.
If I now go ahead and open up
another terminal window and type
our old friend ls, you'll see
that now I have a CSV file.
I have my Python file from before.
And I have a new file called
shows.db, which I've created.
That is the binary file that contains
the table that I've loaded dynamically
in from that CSV file.
Any other questions on SELECT
queries or what we can do with them?
BRIAN YU: Yeah, a few people are asking
about what the runtime of this is.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah,
really good question.
What is the runtime?
I'm going to come back to that question
in just a little bit if that's OK.
Right now, it's admittedly big O of n.
I've not actually done
anything better than we did
with our CSV file or our Python code.
Right now, it's still
big O of n by default.
But there's going to be
a better answer to that
that's going to make it
something much more logarithmic.
So let me come back to that feature
when it's time to enable it.
But in fact, let's start to
take some steps toward that.
Because it turns out,
when loading in data,
we're not always going to
have the luxury of just
having one big file in
CSV format that we import,
and we go about our business.
We're going to have to
decide in advance how
we want to store the data and
what data we want to store
and what the relationships
might be across not one
single table, but multiple tables.
So let me go ahead and
run one other command here
that actually introduces
the first of a problem.
Let me go ahead and
SELECT title FROM shows
WHERE genres equals,
for instance, "Comedy."
That was one of the genres.
And notice that we get back
a whole bunch of results.
But I bet I'm missing some.
I'm skimming through
this pretty quickly.
But I bet I'm missing some,
because if I check if genres
= "Comedy," what am I omitting?
Well, those of you who checked multiple
boxes might have said something
is a comedy and a drama
or comedy and romance
or maybe a couple of other
permutations of genres.
If I'm searching for
equality here, = "Comedy,"
I'm only going to get those favorites
from you where you only said,
my favorite TV show is a comedy.
But what if we want to do
something like LIKE comedy instead?
And we could say something
like, well, so long
as the word "comedy" is in there, then
we should get back even more results.
And let me stipulate that, indeed,
I now have a longer list of results.
Now we have all shows where you
checked at least the Comedy box.
But unfortunately, this
starts to get a little sloppy,
because recall what the
Genres column looks like.
SELECT.
Let me SELECT genres FROM shows;.
Notice that all of the genres that we
loaded into this table from the CSV
file are a comma-separated
list of genres.
That's just the way Google Forms did it.
And that's fine for CSV purposes.
That's kind of fine for SQL
purposes, but this is kind of messy.
Generally speaking, storing
comma-separated lists
of values in a SQL database is
not what you should be doing.
The whole point of using a SQL database
is to move away from commas and CSVs
and to actually store
things more cleanly.
Because in fact, let
me propose a problem.
Suppose I want to search not
for comedy but maybe also
music, like this, thereby allowing
me to find any shows where
the word "music" is somewhere
in the comma-separated list.
There's a subtle bug here.
And you might have to think
back to where we began, the form
that you pulled up.
I can't show the whole
thing here, but we
started with action, adventure,
animation, biography, dot, dot, dot,
music.
Musical was also there, so distinct.
A music video versus a musical
are two different types of genres.
But notice my query at the moment.
What's problematic with this?
At the moment, we would seem to have
a bug whereby this query will select
not only "music," but also "musical."
And so this is just where
things are getting messy.
Now, yeah, you know what?
We could kind of clean this up.
Maybe we could put a comma here so
that it can't just be music something.
It has to be music comma.
But what if music is the
last box that you checked?
Well, then it's music nothing.
There is no comma.
So now I need to OR things together.
So maybe I have to do
something like WHERE "%Music,%"
like this or OR genres
LIKE "%Music" like this.
But honestly, this is
just getting messy.
This is poorly designed.
If you're just storing your data as a
comma-separated list of values inside
of a column and you have to resort
to this kind of hack to figure out,
well, maybe it's over
here or here or here,
and thinking about all the permutations
of syntax, you're doing it wrong.
You're not using a SQL database
to its fullest potential.
So how do we go about
designing this thing better
and actually load this CSV into
a database a little more cleanly?
In short, how do we get rid of the
stupid commas in the Genres column
and instead put one word,
"comedy" or "music" or "musical,"
in each of those cells, so to speak?
Not two, not three--
one only without throwing
away some of those genres.
Well, let me introduce a few building
blocks that will get us there.
It turns out, when
creating your own tables
and loading data into
a database on your own,
we're going to need
more than just SELECT.
SELECT, of course, is just for reading.
But if we're going to do this better
and not just use sqlite3 as a built-in
.import command, but instead we're
going to write some code to load all
of our data into maybe two tables--
one for the titles, one for the genres--
we're going to need a little more
expressiveness when it comes to SQL.
And so for that, we're going
to need, one, the ability
to create our own tables.
And we've seen a glimpse of this before.
But we're also going to need
to see another piece of syntax,
as well, so inserting.
Inserting is another command that
you can execute on a SQL database
in order to actually add data
to a database, which is great.
Because if I want to ultimately iterate
over that same CSV but, this time,
manually add all of the
rows to the database myself,
well, then I'm going to
need some way of inserting.
And the syntax for that is as follows.
INSERT INTO the name of the
table, the column or columns
that you want to insert values into,
then literally the word VALUES,
and then literally in parentheses
again, the actual list of values.
So it's a little abstract when
we see it in this generic form.
But we'll see this more explicitly
in just a moment here, as well.
So when it comes to inserting
something into a database,
let's go ahead and try this.
So suppose that-- let's see.
What's a show that--
The Muppet Show.
I grew up loving The Muppet Show.
It was out in, like, the '70s.
And I don't think it was on the
list, but I can check this for sure.
So SELECT * FROM shows
WHERE title LIKE--
let's just search for
"muppets" with a wild card.
And I'm guessing no one put it there.
Good.
So it's a missed opportunity.
I forgot to fill out the form.
I could go back and fill out
the form and re-import the CSV,
but let's go ahead and do this manually.
So let me go ahead and INSERT
INTO shows what columns?
title and genres, and I guess I
could do a Timestamp just for kicks.
And then I'm going to
insert what values?
The values will be, well, I don't
know, whatever time it is now.
So I'm going to cheat there rather
than look up the date and the time.
The title will be "The Muppet Show."
And the genres will be--
it was kind of a comedy.
It was kind of a musical.
So we'll kind of leave it at that.
Semicolon.
So again, this follows
the standard syntax here
of specifying the table
you want to insert into,
the columns you want to
insert into, and the values
you want to put into those columns.
And I'm going to go
ahead and hit Enter now.
Nothing seems to have happened.
But if I now select that same query--
oh, OK, it's still nothing,
because I made a subtle mistake.
I'm not searching for "Muppets," plural.
I'm searching for "Muppet,"
singular, The Muppet Show.
Voila.
Now you see my row in this database.
And so INSERT would
give us the ability now
to insert new rows into the database.
Suppose you want to update something.
You know, some of the Muppet Shows
were actually pretty dramatic.
So how might we do that?
Well, I can say UPDATE shows SET--
let's see-- genres = "Comedy,
Drama, Musical" WHERE
title = "The Muppet Show."
So again, I'll pull up the
canonical syntax for this in a bit.
But for now, just a little teaser,
you can update things pretty simply.
And even though it takes a little
getting used to the syntax,
it kind of does what it says.
UPDATE shows SET genres =
this WHERE title = that.
And now I can go ahead and Enter.
If I go ahead and select the same
thing, just like in a terminal window,
you can go up and down.
That's how I'm typing so quickly.
I'm just going up and
down to previous commands.
Voila.
Now I see that the Muppet Show is
a comedy, a drama, and a musical.
Well, I take issue, though, with
one of the more popular shows that
was in the list.
A whole bunch of you
liked, let's say, Friends,
which I've never really been a fan of.
And let me go ahead and SELECT title
FROM shows WHERE title = "Friends."
And maybe I should be a little
more rigorous than that.
I should say title LIKE
"Friends" just in case
there was different capitalizations.
Enter.
A lot of you really liked Friends.
In fact, how many of you?
Well, recall that I can do this.
I can say COUNT, and I can
let SQL do the count for me.
26 of you, I disagree with strongly.
And there's a couple of you
that even added all the dots,
but we'll deal with you later.
So suppose I do take issue with this.
Well, DELETE FROM shows
WHERE title = "Friends"--
actually, title LIKE "Friends."
Let's get them all.
Enter.
And now if we SELECT
this again, I'm sorry.
Friends has been canceled.
So you can again execute these
fundamental commands of CRUD,
Create Read, Update, and Delete,
by using CREATE or INSERT,
by using SELECT, by
using UPDATE literally
and DELETE literally, as well.
And that's about it.
Even though this was a
lot quickly, there really
are just those four
fundamental operations in SQL
plus some of these add-on features, like
these additional functions like COUNT
that you can use and also some of
these keywords like WHERE and the like.
Well, let me propose
that we now do better.
If we have the ability to select data
and create tables and insert data,
let's go ahead and write our own Python
script that uses SQL, as in a loop,
to read over my CSV file and to insert,
insert, insert, insert each of the rows
manually.
Because honestly, it
will take me forever
to manually type out hundreds of SQL
queries to import all of your rows
into a new database.
I want to write a program
that does this instead.
And I'm going to propose that we
design it in the following way.
I'm going to have two tables
this time, represented here
with this artist's rendition.
One is going to be called shows.
One is going to be called genres.
And this is a fundamental principle
of designing relational databases,
to figure out the relationships among
data and to normalize your data.
To normalize your data means
to eliminate redundancies.
To normalize your data means to
eliminate mentions of the same words
again and again and have just single
sources of truth for your data,
so to speak.
So what do I mean by that?
I'm going to propose that we instead
create a simpler table called
shows that has just two columns.
One is going to be
called id, which is new.
The other is going to be
called title, as before.
Honestly, I don't care about
timestamps, so we're just
going to throw that value away,
which is another upside of writing
our own program.
We can add or remove any data we want.
For id, I'm introducing
this, which is going
to be a unique identifier,
literally a simple integer--
1, 2, 3, all the way up
to a billion or 2 billion,
however many favorites we have.
I'm just going to let this
auto increment as we go.
Why?
I propose that we move to another
table all of the genres and that,
instead of having one or two or
three or five genres in one column
as a stupid comma-separated list--
which is stupid only in the sense
that it's just messy, right?
It means that I have
to run stupid commands
where I'm checking for the
comma here, the comma there.
It's very hackish, so to speak.
Bad design.
Instead of doing that, I'm going
to create another table that
also has two columns.
One is going to be called show_id, and
the other is going to be called genre.
And genre here is just going
to be a single word now.
That column will contain
single words for genres,
like "comedy" or "music" or "musical."
But we're going to associate
all of those genres
with the original show to which
they belong, per your Google form
submissions, by using this show_id here.
So what does this mean in particular?
By adding to our first table,
shows, this unique identifier--
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6--
I can now refer to that same show
in a very efficient way using
a very simple number
instead of redundantly
having The Office, The Office,
The Office again and again.
I can refer to it by just
one canonical number, which
is only going to be 4 bytes or 32 bits.
Pretty efficient.
But I can still associate that
show with one genre or two or three
or more or even none.
So in this way, every
row in our current table
is going to become one or more
rows in our new pair of tables.
We're factoring out
the genres so that we
can add multiple rows for every
show, potentially, but still
remap those genres back to
the original show itself.
So what is some of the buzzwords here?
What's some of the language
to be familiar with?
Well, we need to know what kinds
of types are at our disposal here.
So for that, let me propose this.
Let me propose that we
have this list here.
It turns out, in SQLite, there
are five main data types.
And that's a bit of
an oversimplification,
but there's five main data types,
some of which look familiar,
a couple of which are a little weird.
INTEGER is a thing.
REAL is the same thing as float.
So an integer might be a 32-bit or
4-byte value, like 1, 2, 3, or 4,
positive or negative.
Real number's going to
have a decimal point in it,
a floating point value,
probably 32 bits by default.
But those kinds of things,
the sizes of these types,
vary by system, just
like they technically
did in C. So do they vary by
system in the world of SQL.
But generally speaking, these
are good rules of thumb.
TEXT is just that.
It's sort of the equivalent
of a string of some length.
But then in SQLite, it turns
out there's two other data
types we've not seen before--
NUMERIC and BLOB.
But more on those in just a little bit.
BLOB is Binary Large Object.
It means you can store 0's
and 1's in your database.
NUMERIC is going to be something that's
number-like but isn't a number per se.
It's like a year or a time,
something that has numbers, but isn't
just a simple integer at that.
And let me propose, too, that SQLite
is going to allow us to specify, too,
when we create our own columns manually
by executing the SQL code ourselves,
we can specify that a
column cannot be null.
Thus far, we've ignored this.
But some of you might
have taken the fifth
and just not given us the
title of a show or a genre.
Your answers might be blank.
Some of you, maybe in
registering for a website,
don't want to provide information like
where you live or your phone number.
So a database in general sometimes
does want to support null values.
But you might want to say
that it can't be null.
A website probably needs
your email address,
needs your password and a few
other fields, but not everything.
And there's another keyword in SQL, just
so you've seen it, called UNIQUE, where
you can additionally say that
whatever values are in this column
must be unique.
So a website might also use that.
If you want to make sure that the
same email address can't register
for your website
multiple times, you just
specify that the email column is unique.
That way, you can't put multiple people
in with identical email addresses.
So long story short, this is just
more of the tools in our SQL toolkit,
because we'll see some
of these now indirectly.
And the last piece of jargon we
need before designing our own tables
is going to be this.
It turns out that, in
SQL, there's this notion
of primary keys and foreign keys.
And we've not seen this in spreadsheets.
Unless you've been working in
the real world for some years
and you have fairly fancy
spreadsheets in front of you
as an analyst or financial
person or the like,
odds are you've not seen keys or unique
identifiers in quite the same way.
But they're relatively simple.
In fact, let me go back to
our picture before and propose
that when you have two
tables like this and you
want to use a simple integer to
uniquely identify all of the rows in one
of the tables, that's
called technically an ID.
That's what I'll call it by convention.
You could call it anything you want, but
ID just means it's a unique identifier.
But semantically, this ID is
what's called a primary key.
A primary key is the column in a table
that uniquely identifies every row.
This means you can have
multiple versions of The Office
in that title field.
But each of those rows is going to have
its own number uniquely, potentially.
So primary key uniquely
identifies each row.
In another table, like genres, which I'm
proposing we create in just a moment,
it turns out that you're welcome
to refer back to another table
by way of that unique identifier.
But when it's in this context,
that ID is called a foreign key.
So even though I've
called it show_id here,
that's just a convention
in a lot of SQL databases
to imply that this is technically
a column called ID in a table
called show or shows,
plural in this case.
So if there's a number
1 here, and suppose
that The Office has a
unique ID of 1, we would
have a row in this table called
id is 1, title is The Office.
The Office might be in the comedy
category, the drama category,
the romance category, so multiple ones.
Therefore, in the genres table,
we want to output three rows,
the number 1, 1, 1 in each of
those rows but the words "comedy,"
"drama," "romance" in each
of those rows respectively.
So again, the goal here is to just
design our database better, not
have these stupid comma-separated lists
of values inside of a single column.
We want to kind of blow that up,
explode it, into individual rows.
You might think, well, why don't
we just use multiple columns?
But again, per our
principle from spreadsheets,
you should not be in the habit of
adding more and more columns when
the data is all the same, like
genre, genre, genre, right?
The stupid way to do this
in the spreadsheet world
would be to have one
column called Genre 1,
another column called Genre 2, another
column called Genre 3, Genre 4.
And you can imagine just how
stupid and inefficient this is.
A lot of those columns are going to be
empty for shows with very few genres.
And it's just kind of
messy at that point.
So better, in the world
of relational databases,
to have something like a second table,
where you have multiple rows that
somehow link back to that primary
key by way of what we're calling,
conceptually, a foreign key.
All right.
So let's go ahead now and
try to write this code.
Let me go back to my IDE.
Let me quit out of SQLite now.
And let me just move away.
I'm going to move this away,
my file, for just a moment
so that we're only left
with our original data.
Let's go about implementing a final
version of my Python file that does
this-- creates two tables--
one called shows, one called genres--
and then, two, in a for
loop, iterates over that CSV
and inserts some data into the shows
and other data into the genres.
How can we do this programmatically?
Well, there's a final piece
of the puzzle that we need.
We need some way of bridging
the world of Python and SQL.
And here, we do need a
library, because it would just
be way too painful to
do without a library.
It can be CS50.
CS50, as we'll see,
makes this very simple.
There are other third-party
commercial and open-source libraries
that you can also use in the real
world, as well, that do the same thing.
But the syntax is a
little less friendly,
so we'll start by using the CS50
library, which in Python, recall,
has functions like get_string
and get_int and get_float.
But today, it also has support, it turns
out, for SQL capabilities, as well.
So I'm going to go back
to my Favorites file.
And I'm going to import
not only CSV, but I'm also
going to import from the CS50
library a feature called SQL.
So we have a variable, if you
will, inside of the CS50 library
or, rather, a function
inside of the CS50 library
called SQL that, if I
call it, will allow me
to load a SQLite database into memory.
So how do I do this?
Well, let me go ahead and add
a couple of new lines of code.
Let me go ahead and open
up a file called shows.db,
but this time in write mode.
And then just for kicks--
just for now, rather, I'm
going to go ahead and
close it right away.
This is a Pythonic way of
creating an empty file.
It's kind of stupid looking, but
by opening a file called shows.db
in write mode and then
immediately closing it,
it has the effect of creating
the file, closing the file.
So I now have an empty file
with which to interact.
I could also do this, as
an aside, by doing this--
touch shows.db.
touch kind of a strange command,
but in a terminal window,
it means to create a
file if it doesn't exist.
So we could also do that instead.
But that would be independent of Python.
So once I've created this
file, let me go ahead
and open the file now
as a SQLite database.
I'm going to declare a variable
called db for database.
I'm going to use the SQL
function from CS50's library.
And I'm going to open via
somewhat cryptic string this--
sqlite:///shows.db.
Now, it looks like a URL,
http://, but it's SQLite instead.
And there's three slashes
instead of the usual two.
But this line of code,
line 6, has the result
of opening now that otherwise
empty file with nothing
in it yet as being a SQLite
database using CS50's library.
Why did I do that?
Well, I did that because I now
want to create my first table.
Let me go ahead and execute, db.execute.
So there's a function called execute
inside of the CS50 SQL library.
And I'm going to go ahead and run this.
CREATE TABLE called shows,
the columns of which
are an id, which is going to
be an integer, a title, which
is going to be text, the primary key
in which is going to be the id column.
So this is a bit cryptic.
But let's see what's happening.
I seem to now, in line 8, be
combining Python with SQL.
And this is where now programming
gets really powerful, fancy, cool,
difficult, however you
want to perceive it.
I can actually use one
language inside of another.
How?
Well, SQL is just a bunch
of textural commands.
Up until now, I've been
typing them out manually
in this program called SQLite3.
There's nothing stopping
me, though, from storing
those same commands in
Python strings and then
passing them to a database using code.
The code I'm using is a
function called execute.
And its purpose in life,
and CS50 staff wrote this,
is to pass the argument from your Python
code into the database for execution.
So it's like the programmatic way
of just typing things manually
at the SQLite prompt a few minutes ago.
So that's going to go ahead
and create my table called
shows, in which I'm going to
store all of those unique IDs
and also the titles.
And then let me do this again.
db.execute CREATE TABLE
genres, and that's
going to have a column called show_id,
which is an integer also, genre,
which is text.
And lastly, it's going
to have a foreign key--
it's going to wrap a little long here--
on show_id, which references
the shows table id.
All right, so this is a lot.
So let's just recap left to right.
db.execute is my Python function
that executes any SQL I want.
CREATE TABLE genres creates
a table called genres.
The columns in that table will
be something called show_id,
which is an integer, and
genre, which is a text field.
But it's going to be one
genre at a time, not multiple.
And then here, I'm
specifying a foreign key
will be the show_id column,
which happens to refer back
to the shows table's IDs column.
It's a little cryptic, but all this
is doing is implementing for us
the equivalent of this picture here.
I could have manually
typed both of these SQL
commands at that blinking prompt.
But again, no, I want
to write a program now
in Python that creates the tables
for me and now, more interestingly,
loads the data into that database.
So let's go ahead and do this now.
I'm not going to select
a title from the user,
because I want to import everything.
I'm not going to use any
counting or anything like that.
So let's go ahead and just go
inside of my loop as before.
And this time, let's go
ahead and, for row in reader,
let's go ahead and get the current
title, as we've always done.
But let's also, as always, go
ahead and strip it of white space
and capitalize it, just
to canonicalize it.
And now I'm going to go ahead and
execute db.execute, quote unquote,
INSERT INTO shows the title
column, the value of "title."
So I want to put the title here.
It turns out that SQL libraries like
ours support one final piece of syntax,
which is a placeholder.
In C, we use %s.
In Python, we just use curly braces
and put the word right there.
In SQL, we have a third approach to
the same problem-- just syntactically
different, but conceptually the same.
You put a question mark where
you want to put a placeholder.
And then outside of this string, I'm
going to actually type in the value
that I want to plug
into that question mark.
So this is so similar
to printf in week 1.
But instead of %s, it's a question mark
now and then a comma-separated list
of the arguments you want to
plug in for those placeholders.
So now this line of code 16 has
just inserted all of those values
into my database.
And let's go ahead and run this.
Before I go any further,
let me go ahead and do this.
I'm going to go ahead now and
run python of favorites.py
and cross my fingers, as always.
It's taking a moment, taking a moment.
That's because there's a
decent-sized file there.
Or I screwed up.
This is taking too long.
Oh, OK.
I should have just been more patient.
All right.
So it just seems my
connection's a little slow.
So as I expected, everything is
100% correct, and it's working fine.
So now let's go ahead and
see what I actually did.
If I type ls, notice that I
have a file called shows.db.
This is brand new, because my
Python program created it this time.
Let's go ahead and run
sqlite3 of shows.db
just so I can now see
what's inside of it.
Notice that I can do .schema
just to see what tables exist.
And indeed, the two tables that
I created in my Python code
seem to exist.
But notice that there's--
if I do SELECT * FROM shows,
let's see all the data.
Voila.
There is a table that's been
programmatically created.
And it has, notice this time,
no timestamps, no genres.
But it has an ID on the left
and the title on the right.
And amazingly, all of the IDs are
monotonically increasing from 1
on up to 513, in this case.
Why is that?
Well, one of the features
you get in a SQL database
is if you define a column as
being a primary key in SQLite,
it's going to be auto
incremented for you.
Recall that nowhere in my code did
I even have a line, an integer,
inputting 1, then 2, then 3.
I could absolutely do that.
I could have done something
like this-- counter--
rather, I could have done
something like this-- counter = 1.
And then down here, I could
have said id, title, give myself
two placeholders, and then
pass in the counter each time.
I could have implemented this
myself and then, on each iteration,
done counter += 1.
But with SQL databases,
as we've seen, you
get a lot more functionality built in.
I don't have to do any
of that, because if I've
declared that ID as being a primary
key, SQLite is going to insert it for me
and increment it also for me, as well.
All right.
So if I go back to SQLite, though,
notice that I do have IDs and titles.
But if I SELECT * FROM genres,
there's of course nothing there yet.
So how now do I get all of the
genres for each of these shows in?
I need to finish my script.
So inside of this same loop, I have
not only the title in my current row,
but I also have genres
in the current row.
But the genres are separated by commas.
Recall that in the CSV,
next to every title,
there's a comma-separated
list of genres.
How do I get at each genre individually?
Well, I'd like to be able to say
for genre in row bracket genres.
But this is not going to
work, because that's not going
to be split up based on those commas.
That's literally just
going to iterate over,
in fact, all of the characters in
that string, as we saw last week.
But it turns out that strings
in Python have a fancy split
function, whereby I can split
on a comma followed by a space.
And what this function
will do for me in Python is
take a comma separated list of
genres and explode it, so to speak,
split it on every comma,
space into a Python list
containing genre after genre
in an actual Python list
a la square brackets.
So now I can iterate over that
list of individual genres.
And inside of here, I can do db.execute
INSERT INTO genres show_id, genre,
the values, question
mark, question mark.
But huh, there's a problem.
I can definitely plug in the
current genre, which is this.
But I need to put something here still.
For that first question mark,
I need a value for the show_id.
How do I know what the ID
is of the current TV show?
Well, it turns out the library
can help you with this.
When you insert new rows into
a table that has a primary key,
it turns out that most libraries will
return you that value in some way.
And if I go back to
line 15 and I actually
store the return value of
db.execute after using INSERT,
the library will tell me
what was the integer that
was just used for this given show.
Maybe it's 1, 2, 3.
I don't have to know or
care as the programmer.
But the return value, I
can store in a variable.
And then down here, I can literally
put that same ID so that now,
if I am inputting The Office,
whose ID is 1, into the shows table
and its genres are
comedy, drama, romance,
I can now inside of this for
loop, this nested for loop,
insert 1 followed by "comedy," 1
followed by "drama," 1 followed
by "romance," three rows all at once.
And so now let's go back down
here into my terminal window.
Let me remove the old shows.db
with rm, just to start fresh.
Let me go ahead and rerun
python of favorites.py.
I'll be more patient this time,
because cloud's being a little slow.
So it's doing some thinking.
And in fact, there's
more work being done now.
At this point in the story,
my program is presumably
iterating over all of
the rows in the CSV.
And it's inserting into the
shows table one at a time,
and then it's inserting one or
more genres into the genres table.
It's a little slow.
If we were on a faster system or if
I were doing it on my own Mac or PC,
it would probably go down more quickly.
But you can see here an example of why
I use the .import command in the first
place.
That automated some of this process.
But unfortunately, it didn't allow
me to change the format of my data.
But the key point to make
here is that even though this
is taking a little bit of time to insert
these hundreds of rows all at once,
I'm only going to have to do this once.
And what was asked a bit ago
was the performance of this.
It turns out that now that we have
full control over the SQL database,
it turns out we're going to have
the ability to actually improve
the performance thereof.
Oh, OK.
As expected, it finished right on time.
And let me go ahead now and
run sqlite3 on shows.db.
All right, so now I'm back
in my raw SQL environment.
If I do SELECT * FROM
shows, which I did before,
we'll see all of this as before.
If I SELECT * FROM shows
WHERE title = "THE OFFICE,"
I'll see the actual unique
IDs of all of those.
We didn't bother eliminating duplicates.
We just kept everything as is, but
we gave everything a unique ID.
But if I now do SELECT * FROM genres,
we'll see all of the values there.
And notice the key detail.
There is only one genre per row here.
And so we can ultimately line
those up with our titles.
And our titles here, we
had all of these here.
Something's wrong.
I want to get this right.
Let's go ahead and take our second
and final five-minute break here.
And we'll come back, and I
will explain what's going on.
All right, we are back.
And just before we broke up, my own
self-doubt was starting to creep in.
But I'm happy to say, with no
fancy magic behind the scenes,
everything was actually working fine.
I was just doubting the
correctness of this.
If I do SELECT * FROM
shows, I indeed get back
two columns, one with the unique ID,
the so-called primary key, followed
by the title of each of those shows.
And if I similarly search for * FROM
genres, I get single genres at a time.
But on the left-hand side
are not primary keys per se
but now those same numbers
here in this context called
foreign keys that map one to the other.
So for instance, whatever show 512 is
had five different genres associated
with it.
And in fact, if I go back a moment to
shows, it looks like Game of Thrones
was decided by one of you as belonging
in thriller, history, adventure,
action, and war, as well, those five.
So now this is what's meant
by relational database.
You have this relation or
relationship across multiple tables
that link some data in one to
some other data in the like.
The catch, though, is that it
would seem a little harder now
to answer questions, because now
I have to kind of query two tables
or execute two separate queries
and then combine the data.
But that's not actually the case.
Suppose that I want to
answer the question of,
what are all of the musicals
among your favorite TV shows?
I can't select just the shows, because
there's no genres in there anymore.
But I also can't select
just the genres table,
because there's no titles in there.
But there is a value that's bridging
one and the other, that foreign key
to primary key relationship.
So you know what I can do
off the top of my head?
I'm pretty sure I can select all of
the show_ids from the genres table
where a specific genre = "Musical."
And I don't have to worry
about commas or spaces now,
because again, in this new version
that I have designed programmatically
with code, musical and every
other genre is just a single word.
If I hit Enter, all of
these show_ids were decided
by you all as belonging to musicals.
But now this is not
interesting, and I certainly
don't want to execute 10
or so queries manually
to look up every one of those IDs.
But notice what we can
do in SQL, as well.
I can nest queries.
Let me put this whole query in
parentheses for just a moment
and then prepend to it the following.
SELECT title FROM shows WHERE the
primary key, id, is in this subquery.
So you can have nested queries similar
in spirit a bit like in Python and C
when you have nested for loops.
In this case, just like in grade school
math, whatever is in the parentheses
will be executed first.
Then the outer query will be executed
using the results of that inner query.
So if I select the title from shows
where the ID is in that list of IDs,
voila.
It seems that, somewhat
amusingly, several of you
think that Breaking Bad, Supernatural,
Glee, Sherlock, How I Met Your Mother,
Hawaii Five-0, Twin Peaks, The
Lawyer, and My Brother, My Brother
and Me are all musicals.
I take exception to a few
of those, but so be it.
You checked the box for
musical for those shows.
So even though we've designed
things better in the sense
that we've normalized our database
by factoring out commonalities
or, rather, we've cleaned
up the data, there's
still admittedly some redundancy.
There's still admittedly
some redundancy.
But I at least now have
the data in clean fashion
so that every column has just
a single value in it and not
some contrived comma-separated list.
Suppose I want to find
out all of the genres
that you all thought The Office was in.
So let's ask kind of
the opposite question.
Well, how might I do that?
Well, to figure out The Office, I'm
going to first need to SELECT the id
FROM shows WHERE title = "THE
OFFICE," because a whole bunch of you
typed in The Office.
And we gave each of your
answers a unique identifier
so we could keep track of it.
And there's all of those numbers.
Now, this is, like, dozens of responses.
I certainly don't want to
execute that many queries.
But I think a subquery
will help us out again.
Let me put parentheses
around this whole thing.
And now let me say SELECT
DISTINCT genre FROM genres WHERE
the show_id in the genres
table is in that query.
And just for kicks, let me
go ahead and ORDER BY genre.
So let me go ahead and execute this.
And, OK, somewhat amusingly, those
of you who inputted The Office
checked boxes for animation, comedy,
documentary, drama, family, horror,
reality-TV, romance, and sci-fi.
I take exception to a few of those, too.
But this is what happens
when you accept user input.
So here again, we have
with this SQL language
the ability to express fairly
succinctly, even though it's
a lot of new features today all at
once, what would otherwise take me
a dozen or two lines in
Python code to implement
and god knows how many lines
of code and how many hours it
would take me to implement something
like this in C. Now, admittedly,
we could do better than this design.
This table or this picture
represents what we have now.
But you'll notice a lot of redundancy
implicit in the genres table.
Any time you check the
comedy box, I have a row now
that says comedy,
comedy, comedy, comedy.
And the show_id differs, but I have
the word "comedy" again and again.
And now, that tends to be frowned upon
in the world of relational databases,
because if you have a
genre called comedy or one
called musical or anything
else, you should ideally just
have that living in one place.
And so if we really wanted to
be particular and really, truly
normalize this database, which
is an academic term referring
to removing all such redundancies,
we could actually do it like this.
We could have a shows table still with
an id and title, no difference there.
But we could have a genres table
with two columns, id and name.
Now, this is its own id.
It has no connection with the show_id.
It's just its own unique
identifier, a primary key here now,
and the name of that genre.
So you would have one
row in the genres table
for comedy, for drama, music,
musical, and everything else.
And then you would use
a third table, which
is colloquially called a join table,
which I'll draw here in the middle.
And you can call it
anything you want, but we've
called it shows_genres to make
clear that this table implements
a relationship between those two tables.
And notice that in this table
is really no juicy data.
It's just foreign keys--
show_id, genre_id.
And by having this
third table, we can now
make sure that the word "comedy"
only appears in one row anywhere.
The word "musical" only
appears in one row anywhere.
But we use these more efficient
integers called show_id and genre_id,
which respectively point to those
primary keys and their primary tables
to link those two together.
And this is an example of what's
called in the world of databases
a many-to-many relationship.
One show can have many genres.
One genre can belong to many shows.
And so by having this
third table, you can
have that many-to-many relationship.
And again, the third table now
allows us to truly normalize
our data set by getting rid of all of
the duplicate comedy, comedy, comedy.
Why is this important?
Probably not a huge deal for genres.
But imagine with my current design
if I made a spelling mistake,
and I misnamed comedy.
I would now have to change every row
with the word comedy again and again.
Or if maybe you change
the genres of the shows,
you would have to change
it in multiple places.
But with this other
approach with three tables,
you can argue that now
you only have to change
the name of a genre in one
place, not all over the place.
And that, in general, in C
and now in Python and now
SQL has generally been a good thing
not to copy paste identical values
all over the place.
All right.
So with that said, what other
tools do we have at our disposal?
Well, it turns out that there are other
data types out there in the real world
using SQL besides just these five--
BLOB, INTEGER, NUMERIC, REAL, and TEXT.
BLOB, again, is for binary
stuff, generally not
used except for more specialized
applications, let's say.
INTEGER, which is an
int, typically 32 bits;
NUMERIC, which is something
like a date or a year
or time or something like
that; REAL numbers, which
are floating point values; and
TEXT, which are things like strings.
But if you graduate ultimately
from SQLite on phones
and on Macs and PCs to actual
servers that run Oracle, MySQL,
and PostgreSQL if
you're actually running
your own internet-style
business, well, it
turns out that more
sophisticated, even more powerful
databases come with other
subtypes, if you will.
So besides INTEGER, you can
specify smallint for small numbers,
maybe using just a few
bits instead of 32--
INTEGER or bigint, which
uses 64 bits instead of 32.
The Facebooks, the Twitters of the
world need to use bigint a lot,
because they have so much data.
You and I can get away with
simple integers, because we're not
going to have more than 4 billion
favorite TV shows in a class,
certainly.
Something like REAL, you can have
32-bit real numbers or, a little weirdly
named, double precision, which is like
a double was in C, using 64 bits instead
for more precision.
NUMERIC is kind of this catchall.
You can have not only dates and date
times but things like Boolean values.
You can specify the
total number of digits
to store using this numeric
scale and precision.
So it relates to numbers that
aren't just quite integers.
And then you also have
categories of TEXT--
char followed by a
number, which specifies
that every value in the column will
have the same number of characters,
that's helpful for things where the
length in advance, like in the US.
All states, all 50 states,
have two-character codes,
like MA for Massachusetts,
CA for California.
char(2) would be appropriate
there, because you
know every value in the column
is going to have two characters.
When you don't know,
though, you can use varchar.
And varchar specifies a
maximum number of characters.
And so you might specify
varchar of, like, 32.
No one might be able to type in a
name that's longer than 32 characters,
or varchar(200) if you want to
allow for something even bigger.
But this is germane to our
real-world experience with the web.
If you've ever gone to a website,
start filling out a form,
and all of a sudden you can't
type any more characters,
your response is too long--
why is that?
Well, one, the
programmers just might not
want you to keep expressing
yourself in more detail, especially
if it's a complaint form
on a customer service site.
But pragmatically, it's probably
because their database was designed
to store a finite number of characters.
And you have hit that threshold.
And you certainly don't
want to have a buffer
overflow, like in C. So the database
will enforce a maximum value n.
And then text is for even
bigger chunks of text.
If you're letting people
copy paste their resumes
or hold documents or even larger sets
of text, you might use text instead.
So let's then consider
a real-world data set.
Things get really interesting, and
all of these very academic ideas
and recommendations
really come into play
when we don't had hundreds of favorites
but when we have thousands instead.
And so what I'm going to go ahead
and do here is download a file here,
which is a SQLite version of the
IMDb, Internet Movie Database,
that some of you might
have used in website form
in order to look up movies and
ratings thereof and the like.
And what we've done
in advance is we wrote
a script that downloaded all of that
information in advance as TSV files.
It turns out that they, Internet
Movie Database, make all of their data
available as TSV files,
Tab-Separated Values.
And we went ahead and imported it with
a script called shows.db as follows.
So I'm going to go
ahead in just a moment
and open up shows.db, which is
not the version I created earlier
based on your favorites.
This is now the version
that we, the staff,
created in advance by
downloading hundreds of thousands
of movies and TV shows and actors
and directors from IMDb.com
under their license and then
imported into a SQLite database.
So how can I see what's in here?
Well, let me go ahead
and type .schema, recall.
And you'll see a whole
bunch of data therein.
And in fact, in pictorial form,
it actually looks like this.
Here is a picture that just
gives you the lay of the land.
There's going to be a
people table that has
an ID for every person, a
name, and their birth year.
There's going to be a shows table,
just like we've been talking,
which is IDs, titles of shows-- also,
though, the year that the show debuted
and the number of episodes
that the show had.
Then there's going to be genres,
similar in design to before.
So we didn't go all out and
factor it out into a third table.
We just have some duplication
here, admittedly, in genres.
But then there's a ratings table.
And here's where you can see where
relational databases get interesting.
You can have a ratings table
storing ratings, like 1 to 5,
but also associate those ratings
with a show by way of its show_id.
And then you can keep track of the
number of votes that that show got.
Writers, notice, is a separate table.
And notice this is kind of cool.
This table, per the arrows, relates to
the shows table and the people table,
because this is a joined table.
A foreign key of show_id and
a foreign key of person_id
refer to the shows table and
the people table respectively
so that a human person can be
a writer for multiple shows
and one show can have multiple writers,
another many-to-many relationship.
And then lastly, stars,
the actors in a show.
Notice that this, too, is a join table.
It's only got two
foreign keys, a show_id
and a person_id that are referring
back to those tables respectively.
And here's where it really makes
sense of relational database.
It would be pretty stupid
and bad design if you
had names of all of the directors
and names of all of the writers
and names of all of the stars of these
shows in separate tables in duplicate,
like Steve Carell, Steve
Carell, Steve Carell.
All of those actors and
directors and writers
and every other role in the business
are just people at the end of the day.
So in a relational
database, the advice would
be to put all of those
people in a people table
and then use primary and foreign
keys to refer to, to relate them to,
these other types of tables.
The catch is, though,
that when we do this,
it turns out that things can be
slow when we have lots of data.
So for instance, let me go into this.
Let me go ahead and
SELECT * FROM shows;.
That's a lot of data.
It's pretty fast on my Mac, and I
switched from the IDE to my Mac just
to save time, because it's
a little faster doing things
locally instead of in the cloud.
Let me go ahead and count the number
of shows in this IMDb database
by using COUNT.
153,331 TV shows.
So that's a lot.
How about the count of
people from the people table?
457,886 people who might be stars or
writers or some other role, as well.
So this is a sizable data set.
So let me go ahead and do
something simple, though.
Let me go ahead and SELECT * FROM
shows WHERE title = "The Office."
And this time, I don't have to worry
about weird capitalization or spacing.
This is IMDb.
This is clean data from
an authoritative source.
Notice that there's actually
different versions of The Office.
You probably know the
UK one and the US one.
There's other shows that are unrelated
to that particular type of show.
But each of them is distinguished,
notice, by the year here.
All right, so that's kind of a lot.
And let's do this again.
Let me go ahead and turn on
a feature temporarily just
to time this query by turning
on a timer in this program.
And let me run it again.
It looks like it took 0.012 seconds
of real time to do that search.
That's pretty fast.
I barely noticed, certainly
because it's so fast.
But let me go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and create an index
called title_index on the table
called shows on its title column.
Well, what am I doing?
Well, to answer the question finally
from before about performance,
by default, everything we've
been doing is indeed big O of n.
It's just being linearly
searched from top
to bottom, which seems to call into
question the whole purpose of SQL if we
were doing no better than with CSVs.
But an index is a clue
to the database to load
the data more efficiently in such a
way that you get logarithmic time.
An index is a fancy data structure
that the SQLite database or the Oracle
database or the MySQL database,
whatever product you're using,
builds up for you in memory.
And then it does something
using syntax like this
that builds in memory generally
something known as a B-tree.
We've talked a bit about
trees in the class.
We talked about binary search
trees, things that kind of look
like family trees.
A B-tree is essentially
a family tree that's
just very wide and not that tall.
It's a data structure similar in
spirit to what we looked at in C.
But it tries to keep all of the
leaf nodes, all of the children
or grandchildren or
great-grandchildren, so to speak,
as close to the root as possible.
And the algorithm it uses for that
tends to be proprietary or documented
based on the system you're using.
But it doesn't store things in a list.
It does not store things top to bottom,
like the tables we view them as.
Underneath the hood, those tables
that look like very tall structures
are actually, underneath
the hood, implemented
with fancier things called trees.
And if we create those trees by creating
what are properly called indexes
like this, it might take us a moment,
like 0.098 seconds, to create an index.
But now notice what happens.
Previously, when I searched the titles
for The Office, using linear search,
it took 0.012 seconds.
If I do the same query again
after having created the index
and having told SQLite, build me
this fancy tree in memory, voila.
0.001 seconds, so orders
of magnitude faster.
Now, both are fast to
us humans, certainly.
But imagine the data set being even
bigger, the query being even bigger.
These indexes can get
even larger than that.
Rather, the queries can
take longer than that
and therefore take even
more time than that.
But unfortunately, if I've got
all of my data all over the place,
as in a diagram like this, my god.
How do I actually get useful work done?
How do I get back the people
in a movie and the writers
and the stars and the ratings
if it's all over the place?
I would seem to have created
such a mess and that I now
need to execute all of these queries.
But notice it doesn't have
to be that complicated.
It turns out that there's another
keyword in SQL, really the last
that we'll look at here, called JOIN.
The JOIN keyword, which you can
use implicitly or explicitly,
allows you to just join tables
together and sort of reconstitute
a bigger, more user friendly table.
So for instance, suppose I want to
get all of Steve Carell's TV shows,
not just The Office.
Well, recall that I can select
Steve's ID from the people
table WHERE name = "Steve Carell."
So again, he has a different ID in
this table, because this is from IMDb.
But there's his ID.
And let me go ahead and
turn the timer off for now.
All right.
So there is his ID, 126797.
I could copy paste that into my
code, but that's not necessary
thanks to these nested queries.
I can do something like this.
Let me go ahead and now select all
of the show_ids from the stars table
where person_id from that
table is equal to this result.
So there's that join table, stars,
that links people and shows.
So let me go ahead and execute that.
All right.
So there's all of the show_ids
of Steve Carell's TV shows.
That's a lot.
And it's very nonobvious what they are.
So let me do another nested query by
putting all of that in parentheses
and now SELECT title FROM
shows WHERE the ID of the show
is in this big, long list of show_ids.
And there are all of the shows that
he's in, including The Dana Carvey Show
back when, The Office up at the
top, and then, most recently,
shows like The Morning Show on Apple TV.
All right, so that's pretty
cool that we can actually
reconstitute the data like that.
But it turns out there's different
ways of doing that, as well.
And you'll see more of
this in the coming weeks
and in the problem sets
and labs and the like.
But it turns out we can
do other things, as well.
And let me just show this
syntax even though it'll
look a little cryptic at first glance.
You can also use that
JOIN keyword as follows.
I can select the title from the people
table joined with the stars table
on the people.id column equaling
the stars.person_id column.
So in other words, I can
select a title from the result
of joining people and stars, like
this, on the id column in one
and the person_id column in the other.
And I can join in the shows table on
the stars.show_id equaling the shows.id.
So again, now I'm joining the primary
and foreign keys on these two tables
where the name equals "Steve Carell."
So this is the most cryptic
thing we've seen yet.
But it just means take this
table and join it with this one
and then join it with this one and
filter all of the resulting joined rows
by a name of Steve Carell.
And voila.
There we have all of
those answers, as well.
And there's other ways
of doing this, too.
I'll leave unsaid now some
of the syntax for that.
But that felt a little slow.
And in fact, let me go ahead
and turn my timer back on.
Let me re-execute this last query.
SELECT title FROM people joining
on stars, joining on shows
WHERE name = "Steve Carell."
That took over half a second.
So that was actually
admittedly kind of slow.
But again, indexes come to
the rescue and if, again, we
don't allow linear search to dominate.
But let me go ahead and
create a few indexes.
Create an index called person_index on
the stars table, the person_id column.
Why?
Well, my query a moment ago
used the person_id column.
It filtered on it.
So that might be a bottleneck.
I'm going to go ahead and create
another index called show_index
on the stars table on show_id.
Similarly, a moment ago, my
query used the show_id column.
And so that, too, might have been a
bottleneck linearly, top to bottom.
So let me create that index.
And then lastly, let me create
an index called name_index--
and this is perhaps the most obvious,
similar to the show titles before--
on the people table on the name column.
And that, too, took a moment.
Now, in total, this took
almost a full second.
But these indexes only get created once.
They get maintained
automatically over time.
But you don't incur
this with every query.
Now let me do my SELECT again.
Let me SELECT title FROM
people joining the stars table,
joining the shows table
WHERE name = "Steve Carell."
Boom.
0.001 seconds.
That was an order of magnitude faster
than the more than half a second
it took us a little bit ago.
So here, too, you see the
power of a relational database.
So even though we've created some
problems for ourselves over time,
we've solved them ultimately-- granted,
with some more sophisticated features
and additional syntax.
But a relational database
is indeed why you use them
in the real world for the Twitters, the
Instagrams, the Facebooks, the Googles,
because they can store
data so efficiently
without redundancy, because you can
normalize them and factor everything
out.
But they can still
maintain the relations
that you might have
seen in a spreadsheet
but using something closer
to logarithmic thanks
to those tree structures.
But there are problems.
And what we wanted to do is end
on today two primary problems
that are introduced with SQL,
because they are just unfortunately
so commonly done.
Notice this year.
There is something generally
known as a SQL injection
attack, which you are
vulnerable to in any application
where you're taking user input.
That hasn't been an issue
for my favorites.py file,
where I only took input from a CSV.
But if one of you were
malicious, what if one of you
had maliciously typed in the
word "delete" or "update"
or something else as
the title of your show
and I accidentally plugged it into my
own Python code when executing a query?
You could potentially
inject SQL into my own code.
How might that be?
Well, if logging in via Yale, you'll
typically see a form like this.
Or logging in via Harvard to
something, you'll see a form like this.
Here's an example that
I'm pretty sure neither
Harvard nor Yale are vulnerable to.
Suppose I type in my email
address to this login form
as malan@harvard.edu'--.
It turns out, in SQL, --
is the symbol for commenting if
you want to comment something out.
It turns out that the
single quote is used
when you want to search for something
like Steve Carell or, in this case,
malan@harvard.edu.
It can be double quotes.
It can be single quotes.
In this case, I'm using
single quotes here.
But let's consider some sample
code, if you will, in Python.
Here's a line of code that I
propose might exist in the backend
for Harvard's authentication
or Yale's or anyone else's.
Maybe someone wrote some Python code
like this using SELECT * FROM users
WHERE username = question?
AND password = question?, and they
plugged in username and password.
Whatever the user typed into
that web form a moment ago gets
plugged in here to these question marks.
This is good.
This is good code, because you're
using the SQL question marks.
So if you literally just do what we
preach today and use these question
mark placeholders, you are safe
from SQL injection attacks.
Unfortunately, there
are too many developers
in the world that don't practice this
or don't realize this or do forget this.
If you instead resort to
Python approaches like this,
where you use an f-string instead,
which might be your instincts after last
week, because they're wonderfully
convenient with the curly braces
and all--
suppose that you literally
plug in username and password
not with the question mark
placeholders but just literally
in between those curly braces.
Watch what happens if my
username, malan@harvard.edu,
was actually typed in by me
maliciously as malan@harvard.edu'--.
That would have the effect
of tricking this Python
code into doing essentially this.
Let me do a find and replace.
It would trick Python into executing
username = "malan@harvard.edu"--"
and then other stuff.
Unfortunately, the --
again means comment,
which means you could maybe trick a
server into ignoring the whole password
part of this SQL query.
And if the SQL query's
purpose in life is to check,
is this username and password valid, so
that you can decide to log the user in
or to say, no, you're
not authorized, well,
by essentially commenting out
everything related to password,
notice what I've done.
I've just now theoretically logged
myself in as malan@harvard.edu without
even knowing or inputting a password,
because I injected SQL syntax,
the quote and the --, into my query,
tricking the server into just ignoring
the password equality check.
And so it turns out that db.execute,
when you execute an INSERT,
it returns to you as said the
ID of the newly inserted row.
When you use db.execute to select
rows from a database table,
it returns to you a list of rows,
each of which is a dictionary.
So this is now pseudocode
down here with my comment.
But if you get back one
row, that would seem
to imply that there is a
user named malan@harvard.edu.
Don't know what his password is, because
whoever this person is maliciously
tricked the server into
ignoring that syntax.
So SQL injection attacks
are unfortunately
one of the most common
attacks against SQL databases.
They are completely preventable if
you simply use placeholders and use
libraries, whether it's CS50's
or other third-party libraries
that you may use down the road.
A common meme on the internet
is this picture here.
If we Zoom in on this
person's license plate
or where the license
plate should be, this
is an example of someone
theoretically trying
to trick some camera on the highway
into dropping the whole database.
DROP is another keyword in SQL
that deletes a database table.
And this person was either
intentionally or just
a humorously trying to
trick it into executing SQL
by using syntax like this.
So characters like single quotes,
--, semicolons are all potentially
dangerous characters in SQL if
they're passed through unchanged
to the database.
A very popular xkcd comic-- let me
give you a moment to just read this--
is another well-known meme of
sorts now in computer science.
If you'd like to, read
this one on your own.
But henceforth, you are now in the
family of educated learners who
know who Little Bobby Tables is.
Unfortunately, it's
dead silence in here,
so I can't tell if anyone is
actually laughing at this joke.
But anyhow, this is a
very well-known meme.
So if you're a computer scientist
who knows SQL, you know this one.
And there's one last problem we'd
like to introduce if you don't mind
just a couple of final moments here.
And that is a fundamental
problem in computing
called race conditions,
which for the first time
is now manifest in
our discussion of SQL.
It turns out that SQL and SQL
databases are very often used, again,
in the real world for very
high-performing applications.
And by that, I mean, again, the
Googles, the Facebooks, the Twitters
of the world where lots and lots of
data is coming into servers all at once.
And case in point,
some of you might have
clicked Like on this egg some time ago.
This is the most-liked
Instagram post ever.
As of last night, it was up
to 50-plus million likes.
Well eclipsed Kim
Kardashian's previous post,
which is still at 18 million or so.
This is to say this is
a hard problem to solve,
this notion of likes coming
in at such an incredible rate.
Because suppose that, long
story short, Instagram actually
has a server with a SQL database.
And they have code in Python or C++
or whatever language that's talking
to that database.
And suppose that they
have code that's trying
to increment the total number of likes.
Well, how might this work logically?
Well, in order to increment the number
of likes that a picture like this egg
has, you might first
select from the database
the current number of likes for
the ID of that egg photograph.
Then you might add 1 to it.
Then you might update the database.
And I didn't use it before, but
just like there's INSERT and DELETE,
there's UPDATE, as well.
So you might update the database
with the new count plus 1.
So the code for that might
look a little something
like this, three lines of code
using CS50's library here,
where you execute SELECT likes
FROM posts WHERE id = question?,
where id is the unique
identifier for that egg.
And then I'm storing the
result in a rows variable,
which, again, I claim is a list of rows.
I'm going to go into the first
row, so that's rows bracket 0.
And I'm going to go into the likes
column to get the actual number.
And that number, I'm going to
store in a variable called likes.
So this is going to
be, like, 50,000,000,
and I want it to go to 50,000,001.
So how do I do that?
Well, I execute on the database
UPDATE posts SET likes = ?.
And then I just plug in likes + 1.
The problem, though, with the Instagrams
and Googles and Twitters of the world
is that they don't just have one server.
They have many thousands of servers.
And all of those servers might in
parallel be receiving clicks from you
and I on the internet.
And those clicks translate into this
code getting executed, executed,
executed.
And the problem is that when you have
three lines of code and suppose Brian
and I click on that egg
at roughly the same time,
my three lines might not get executed
before his three lines or vice versa.
They might get commingled
chronologically.
My first line might get executed, then
Brian's first line might get executed.
My second line might get
executed, Brian's second line.
So they might get interspersed
on different servers
or just temporally in
time, chronologically.
That's problematic, because
suppose Brian and I click
on that egg roughly at the same time.
And we get back the same
answer to the SELECT query.
50 million is the current count.
Then our next lines of code execute
on the servers we happen to be on,
which adds 1 to the likes.
The server might accidentally end
up updating the row for the egg
with 50,000,001 both times,
because the fundamental problem is
if my code executes while
Brian's code executes,
we are both checking the value of a
variable at essentially the same time.
And we are both then
making a conclusion--
oh, the current likes are 50 million.
We are then making a decision.
Let's add 1 to 50 million.
We are then updating the
value with 50,000,001.
The problem is, though, that, really,
if Brian's code or the server he happens
to be connected to on Instagram happens
to have selected the number of likes
first, he should be allowed
to finish the code that's
being executed so that when I
select it, I see 50,000,001,
and I add 1 to that so the
new count is 50,000,002.
This is what's known
as a race condition.
When you write code in a multiserver--
more fancily known as a multithreaded
environment-- lines of code
chronologically can get commingled on
different servers at any given time.
The problem fundamentally
derives from the fact
that if Brian's server is in the middle
of checking the state of a variable,
I should be locked out.
I should not be allowed to click
on that button at the same time,
or my code should not be
allowed to execute logically.
So there is a solution
when you have to write code
like this, as is common for Twitter and
Instagram and Facebook and the like,
to use what are called transactions.
Transactions add some few new pieces
of syntax that we won't dwell on today
and you don't need to
use in the coming days.
But they do solve a
fundamentally hard problem.
Transactions essentially allow
you to lock a table or, really,
a row in the table so that
if Brian's click on that egg
results in some code executing that's
in the process of checking what
is the total like count, my click on the
egg will not get handled by the server
until his code is done executing.
So in green here, I've proposed
the way you should do this.
You shouldn't just execute the middle
three lines, "you" being Facebook,
in this case.
Instagram should execute
BEGIN TRANSACTION first, then
COMMIT the transaction at the end.
And the design of transactions is
that all of the lines in between
will either succeed
altogether or fail altogether.
The database won't get
into this funky state
where we start losing
track of likes on eggs.
And though this has not been
an issue in recent years,
back in the day when Twitter
was first getting started,
Twitter was super popular and
super offline a lot of the time.
There was this thing
called a Fail Whale, which
is the picture they
showed on their website
when they were getting too
much traffic to handle.
That was because when people are liking
and tweeting and retweeting things,
it's a huge amount of data coming in.
And it turns out it's very
hard to solve these problems.
But locking the database table or
the rows with these transactions
is one way fundamentally to solve this.
And in our final extra
time today, we thought
we would play this out
in the same example
that I was taught transactions
in some years ago.
Suppose that the scenario at hand
is that you and your roommates
have a nice dorm fridge.
And you're all in the habit
of drinking lots of milk,
and you want to be able
to drink some milk.
But you go to the fridge,
like I'm about to here.
And you realize, uh-oh,
we're out of milk.
And so now I am inspecting the
state of this refrigerator, which
is quite old but also quite empty.
And the state of this
variable, being empty,
tells me that I should go to
CVS and buy some more milk.
So what do I then do?
I'm presumably going
to close the fridge,
and I'm going to go and
leave and go head to CVS.
Unfortunately, the same problem
arises that we'll act out here
in our final 60 or so
seconds together, whereby
if Brian now, my roommate in
this story, also wants some milk,
he comes by when I'm
already headed to the store,
inspects the state of the fridge,
and realizes, oh, we're out of milk.
So he nicely will go restock, as well.
So let's see how this
plays out, and we'll
see if there isn't a
similar, analogous solution.
So I've checked the
state of the variable.
We're indeed out of milk.
I'll be right back.
Just going to go to CVS.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right.
I am now back from the store.
I've picked up some milk.
Going to go ahead and put
it into the fridge and--
oh, how did this happen?
Now there's multiple jugs of milk.
And of course, milk
does not last that long.
And Brian and I don't
drink that much milk.
So this is a really serious problem.
We've sort of tried to update the value
of this variable at the same time.
So how do we go about fixing this?
What's the actual solution here?
Well, I dare say that we
can draw some inspiration
from the world of transactions
and the world of databases.
And perhaps create a
visual for here that we
hope you never forget if you
take nothing away from today.
Let's go ahead and act this out
one last time where, this time,
I'm going to be a little more extreme.
I go ahead and open the fridge.
I realize, oh, we're out of milk.
I'm going to go to the store.
I do not want to allow
for this situation
where Brian accidentally
checks the fridge, as well.
So I am going to lock
the refrigerator instead.
Let me go ahead and
drape this through here.
A little extreme, but I think so
long as he can't get into the fridge,
this shouldn't be a problem.
Let me go ahead now and
just attach the lock here.
Almost got it.
Come on.
All right.
Now the fridge is locked.
Now I'm going to go get some milk.
BRIAN YU: [SIGHS]
[MUSIC PLAYING]