[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: All right.
This is CS50.
And this is the end.
All that remains here on out
is really your final projects.
And we cannot wait to
see what you create.
Today what we thought we would
do is take a bit of a look back,
but also we'll look forward
so that you know exactly where
and what you can do beyond CS50 itself.
But first a word of thanks.
We are, of course, here
in the Loeb Drama Center
with The American Repertory Theater,
who have been our amazing hosts
this whole semester.
And truly, they have breathed new life,
new lights, new animation, new sounds
into CS50.
And we are so grateful to
have had such a privilege
to work with the amazingly
talented team here to indeed bring
this whole stage to life and evolve
it over the course of the semester.
And then, of course,
there's CS50'S team.
And though I'm the
only one here on stage
with everyone else spread
quite far apart this semester,
it would not be without CS50's team
that we have the videos that we have,
the technology that we
have, and all of the visuals
that supplement, hopefully,
everything that you yourselves
have been doing hands on.
So thank you truly to both teams for
having made this semester all possible.
These are suffice it to say, among
the more unusual and difficult times.
And we hope, if you're watching this
now live, or in some time from now,
that this finds everyone
healthy and well.
And that, indeed, we have
helped you find your way
along this path of
learning something new.
Of course, there's more
folks even than that
behind the scenes, CS50'S whole team.
And when I look out on the
crowd here, really, there
is no crowd here in person.
And if you've wondered what it
looks like behind the scenes,
pictured here is a
photograph of exactly what
it is I am seeing when we
hold each of these classes.
And indeed, if we Zoom in, when
we're having these conversations
or answering or asking
questions, it really is just us
and some TV screens here this year.
But we do look forward to
all reuniting before long.
Now behind the scenes, there's
indeed this whole team.
In fact, pictured here are
just most of, but not even
all, CS50'S teaching Fellows, teaching
assistants, and course assistants,
both at Harvard and at Yale, without
whom this semester would also not
be possible.
Because they are, indeed, the
backbone of and the support structure
for getting everyone
ultimately to the finish
line with problem sets, labs, and more.
But it's worth noting
that we are all fallible.
And, indeed, I'm told it's
fairly instructive when
I do something completely wrong, or
get a little befuddled here on stage
and can't quite figure out
why my own code isn't working,
or can't quite answer a
question off the top of my head.
This all happens,
certainly, to all of us.
So even if you are feeling
here, toward the end
of the semester, that not
everything quite clicked
and you're still struggling sometimes
to find that bug in your code,
or you're still googling or searching
for some answer to some smaller
technical problem, rest assured,
or take comfort in knowing,
that that is never
really going to go away.
And in fact, to reinforce that,
besides all of the mistakes
I here have made on stage, we thought
we would share a little bit of a clip,
some bloopers if you will, from when the
teaching staff some weeks ago prepared
that passing of TCP/IP packets on video,
which worked out wonderfully well,
where folks were passing
up, down, left and right.
The goal of which was to
get three TCP/IP packets
from the bottom
right-hand corner of Zoom
to the top left-hand corner of Zoom.
But we thought we would give you
a glimpse of what actually went on
behind the scenes and just
how many takes it took us
to get even that demonstration right.
I give you some of CS50'S team.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
- There we go.
Buffering.
OK.
Josh?
- Hi.
- Helen, oh!
[LAUGHTER]
- [INAUDIBLE].
No, wait.
That was amazing, Josh.
Um, Sophie?
[LAUGHTER]
Amazing.
That was perfect.
Moni?
[LAUGHTER]
I think I--
- [INAUDIBLE].
- Amazing.
- Guy?
That was amazing.
Thank you all.
- So good!
[APPLAUSE]
[END PLAYBACK]
DAVID MALAN: So suffice it to say,
computer science is hard for all of us.
And so some of these feelings,
some of these frustrations
are never going to go away.
But hopefully you have, indeed,
all the more tools in your toolkit,
all the more of a
foundation now to build on
so that you can take comfort in being a
little uncomfortable as you forge ahead
and solve new problems,
learn new languages,
and ultimately pick up
new ideas and skills.
But remember, for CS50
alone, what ultimately
matters in this course
is not so much where
you end up relative to your
classmates, but where you end
up relative to yourself when you began.
And consider, it wasn't all
that long ago that you began.
In fact, just some weeks
ago was this perhaps,
the biggest of your problems
in CS50, just trying
to figure out how to get
the pyramid to align right,
whether you did the less
comfortable version or the more
comfortable version, figuring
out how to print spaces,
how to shift the pyramid over and the
like, figuring out how to nest loops,
let alone getting all of the
semicolons and compilation steps right.
And then, fast forward
to just a week or two ago
when you built your very
own web application, one
that used a third party API and
pulled in nearly real time data
and generated views for the
user, had a controller governing
with the model exactly all of the
data you were reading and writing
and the like.
Like, that is a huge way to have gone
over the course of just a few months.
So take comfort in that, too.
Especially as you dive
into your final project
and might bump up against
some more walls, those, too,
will you ultimately push through.
So what have we focused on over
the course of this semester?
A lot of the times we've spent time
talking about and doing programming.
But really, we'd like to think
it's some of the higher level
ideas and the takeaways
that are what last you
far longer than the
particulars of these languages.
Whether it's Scratch or C or
Python or JavaScript or SQL,
or any of the other practical tools
that we looked at, all of those
are eventually in some form
going to be out of date.
Or they might remain with
us is older languages,
but newer and better
things will come along.
And what we hope, then, is
that over the past few months,
you've walked away with the fundamentals
and sort of a foundation on which you
can bootstrap yourself to learn
new things as they come out
and really reduce new things
to their basic building blocks,
the puzzle pieces with which we
began, first principles from which you
can infer how some new system,
some new piece of hardware,
how some new language must surely work.
Because underneath the hood, at the
end of the day, it's still going to be,
for some time, just 0's and 1's.
And so we introduced in Week 0,
recall, computational thinking,
encouraging you to think more
methodically, more algorithmically.
But really, computational thinking is
just a computer scientist's incarnation
of what we might otherwise think
of as just critical thinking.
This process is taking
as input information
and producing as output some solution.
And in between there, of course, are
our algorithms, the black box that's
doing something interesting and perhaps
difficult. But at the end of the day,
this is problem solving.
And this isn't going anywhere,
irrespective of the languages
that you use or pick up or even
forget somewhere along the way.
And indeed, today, too, whether this
is input and output in binary form,
or it's just information and
decisions or facts and conclusions,
this process of taking
input and producing
as output correct answers,
correct conclusions,
correct decisions is hopefully
going to be with you far
longer than the
particulars of C or Python
or any of the more hands-on skills
that we've spent time on this term.
And recall, too, that
at least within CS50,
the tools with which we propose that you
evaluate the quality of your approach
to problem solving are these
three axes, the first and foremost
of which is surely correctness.
Because if it doesn't work, what's the
point of it all in the first place?
So getting your code, your algorithm,
your process from input to output
to be correct is certainly paramount.
But after that comes
questions of design.
If you actually want to
build more complex systems,
or solve more sophisticated
problems, you really
do want to design your solutions
to those problems cleanly.
You don't want them to
be slow or inefficient.
be a mess in real terms.
You don't want your code to
be completely undecipherable.
Because that's just going to hamper you
longer term to using those same tools,
those same libraries to
solve more interesting,
more sophisticated problems.
And it's surely going to
make it harder to interface
with other people, other
collaborators, and other systems.
And indeed along those lines,
is style still important?
It's perhaps the third
in this trio for us.
But it's the aesthetics of your code,
and the indentation in the variables
and all that, much like you might
convey in our human language,
put your best foot forward
with punctuation and the like.
It just helps other
people understand you.
And indeed, even though we spent
a lot of our time interacting
with computers, in a course like
this, at the end of the day,
you're really just communicating.
And whether you're communicating
to a machine or to another human,
doing that cleanly and in a
way that helps your ideas,
your solutions, become adopted
is surely no less important
than some of these other ideas as well.
But what about other
basic building blocks
that transcend the particular
languages and pieces that we did?
Well, abstraction, this idea of
taking fairly complicated ideas
and simplifying them so you don't
have to worry about the lower level
implementation details, you
can focus only on the solution
that that puzzle piece or that
building block actually provides.
And abstraction is everywhere around us.
Certainly in code, we saw functions
like get_string as an abstraction.
I don't know.
I don't really remember
exactly how get_string
is implemented underneath the
hood, let alone a function
that comes with C, like printf.
But I know that it works.
And I know that it takes input.
I know that it produces output.
And I can therefore build my
own ideas, my own software,
on top of that building block,
abstracting away those particulars.
And in the real world,
too, we abstract things--
we abstract away things all of the
time, taking a complex idea or a process
and assume that that will be done.
Someone else might do that.
And I can therefore build on
the output of that process,
even if I am myself am no expert
in the underlying implementation
details thereof.
But then there's
precision, this other idea
where it's super important,
certainly when writing code,
but also when talking to another human,
to be precise and make super clear
what you mean.
And to consider the corner
cases, to consider the inputs
that you might not otherwise
expect, but might nonetheless
happen so that you don't err and
have some unexpected behavior, as we
certainly did more than
once in actual code.
And sometimes,
abstractions and precisions
are kind of at odds with one another.
Because abstraction would
sort of have you think at
and talk at a fairly high
level, whereas precision
would suggest that you really
should get into the weeds
and really go step by step by step
when it comes to giving someone
else or a computer instructions.
And we thought we would
bring this to life, perhaps,
with a couple of examples.
And we thought we would try to involve
as many people as we can in this,
albeit from afar, by having
everyone, if you can,
take out a piece of paper
and a pen or pencil.
It's OK if you don't
quite have that available.
You can do this on a
computer, too, if you'd rather
draw on a notepad or a tablet, or
something like that totally fine.
But ideally, taking out now something
with which to draw and something
to draw on.
We're going to go ahead and
try to apply some principles
of computational thinking and
see just how helpful or hurtful
it is to use abstraction or
precision at one level or another.
So I think to do this,
Brian, we're going to need
a helping hand from the audience.
I think we're going
to need for one person
out there to volunteer to
write instructions verbally
for everyone else.
We're going to treat
everyone in the audience,
or really, n minus 1
people in the audience
as the computers today who
are going to be programmed.
And we need one human
volunteer to be the programmer.
And that programmer
is going to be Daniel.
So Daniel, thank you for volunteering.
Brian, could we go ahead and share
with Daniel, and only Daniel,
a picture of something that
we want everyone else to draw?
So Daniel, what you should see
on your screen in a moment,
if you haven't already, is a picture.
Don't tell anyone else what it is.
You may use any words in
a moment that you want.
You should not use your hands
or any gestures like that.
But the goal is going to be
to write an algorithm verbally
for everyone else in
the room, step by step,
so that ideally they
draw what it is you see.
And you can say anything you want,
but just no physical gestures.
Does that make sense?
- Got it.
And do you want to say a
little bit about yourself
first to the group before we begin?
STUDENT: Sure.
My name's Daniel.
I'm from Ezra Stiles
College at Yale University.
And I really CS50 this semester.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, wonderful.
Thank you for volunteering.
And let's go ahead and have
everyone else with their paper
and pencil or pen ready.
Daniel, what should be the first
thing everyone does, step one.
STUDENT: OK.
So the first thing we're
going to draw is a hexagon.
So it's a regular hexagon.
And we're going to make sure that we
draw it so that one of the vertices
is on the very bottom of the
hexagon, and one of the vertices
is at the very top of the hexagon.
So one side is not laying flat.
You're doing--
DAVID MALAN: Wup, dut, dut dut.
No hand gestures.
STUDENT: No hands, no hands.
Right.
One vertice at the very top, one
vertice is at the very bottom.
And you've got your other
four vertices on the sides.
So once you've got your
hexagon, your next step
is going to be find your
midpoint of the hexagon.
And so once you've found
your midpoint, you're
going to draw three lines from
a vertices to that midpoint.
The vertices that you're
going to choose to draw from
are the very bottom to the midpoint and
then from the midpoint to the vertices
that are on the left and
right of the top vertices.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
Any final instructions?
STUDENT: I think, hopefully,
that should be it.
DAVID MALAN: [INAUDIBLE].
Those were very long steps one and two.
But yes.
All right, well, let's
go ahead and reveal.
This will be a little bit of a hack.
But if anyone everyone
is comfortable picking up
their piece of paper or
their tablet and holding it
in front of their Zoom camera
steadily for five or 10 seconds,
we'll see exactly what
everyone has drawn.
If you go into gallery view, you'll
be able to see everyone else.
Daniel, hopefully you're
seeing some familiar pictures?
I think we definitely have range.
Are you seeing one or more that
match what you had in mind?
STUDENT: Yeah.
They all look pretty good.
DAVID MALAN: They all?
All right, so good.
Let me go ahead, then,
and share on my screen
in just a moment what it
is Daniel was describing.
So what Brian had shared with
Daniel in advance was this picture
here, which I dare say is a cube.
But indeed, it's composed of a
hexagon and then the additional lines
that Daniel described.
And Daniel, I did happen to see, maybe
on pages two and three of the Zoom
window, there were definitely
some that weren't quite cubes.
What was going through your
mind as to how you approached
the algorithm that you provided?
STUDENT: I wanted to--
to me, the first thing that
went through my head was a cube.
But I knew that there's so
many ways to draw a cube.
I didn't want to describe it as a cube.
Because if I said just
draw a cube, I knew
that we would get tons
of different results.
So I wanted to be as clear as possible.
And I knew that if I could describe
it in sort of a mathematical way,
describing it with a
hexagon and describing it
with the vertices in the midpoint,
that hopefully more people would
be able to draw a precise shape.
DAVID MALAN: Yeah.
Really well said.
Now if we had everyone's
volume on, odd are,
you'd hear a bit of
chuckling now, perhaps,
or maybe a little bit of awkwardness.
And I daresay not all of the
pictures quite turned out that way,
but that's a perfect example of where
maybe abstractions can kind of get us
into trouble.
Because if Daniel had just said,
draw a cube, right, some of you
might start drawing immediately a cube.
But many of you would have a question,
well, what should the orientation be?
What should the size be?
What should the position be?
And so there, precision
becomes increasingly important.
But the more precise it
gets, odds are some of you
just kind of got overwhelmed with the
amount of detail and sort of lost track
where your pen or pencil was
supposed to be at one point
because you were operating
at a much lower level.
So there's this tension, then.
But I think we did get some
of you to that finish line.
Let's see if we can't now take
the pressure off of all of you,
and thank you to Daniel,
in particular, let's
see if we can't now have all of you
collectively program me, if you will.
So I'm going to go ahead
and pull up my screen here
where I have the ability to draw with
my mouse and cursor on my screen here.
And Brian, if you don't mind,
could you share with everyone
else a picture that I promise
I have not seen in advance.
So we will see how this goes.
So I'm the only one right
now in the Zoom room
that has not seen this picture.
But Brian has gone and provided
only you all with the URL.
So pull that up on your screen.
And then, Brian, if we could perhaps
iteratively call on some volunteers.
Why don't I try to draw what
people tell me to do, step by step?
BRIAN YU: All right.
David has not seen this.
I just picked this out,
like, five minutes ago.
And you're all going to raise your
hand if you want to give him, like,
one instruction for what to do next.
And let's start with George.
STUDENT: So you're going
to start by drawing
a circle near the top of the screen.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
A circle near the top of the screen.
And let me make clear, I have no
delete abilities on the computer.
So once I commit, we're in.
So drawing a circle near
the top of the screen.
OK.
Thank you, George.
Brian, step two?
BRIAN YU: All right,
let's go to Sophia next.
STUDENT: Then, in the very center of the
screen, door a black, filled in circle,
which is approximately a tenth of
the size of the circle at the top.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
A black, filled in circle, I
heard, that's a tenth of the size.
So I'm going to do something like this,
and then just kind of shade it in.
All right, thank you, Sophia.
Step three?
BRIAN YU: Let's go to Santiago.
STUDENT: You're going
to draw another circle.
But it's not actually
going to be a circle,
it's more of an ellipse, that's going
to be bigger than the first one.
So it's going to be in the middle.
And it's going to enclose
that filled in circle
and leave some room in the bottom.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
So it's an ellipse.
It's bigger than the first circle.
But it encloses the smaller one?
All right, so I heard kind of this.
OK.
Step 4?
STUDENT: Under that
smaller ellipse, you're
going to want to draw a
bigger circle underneath it
and act as if the circle is
going through that ellipse,
but don't actually show the
lines going through the ellipse.
So that is, we draw a bigger circle
underneath, but without having
the lines go through.
It looks like it will kind of
be going through the edge of it.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
I'm a little worried here, but
what I heard was like this, maybe?
Step five?
BRIAN YU: All right, let's
go to [INAUDIBLE] next.
STUDENT: So in that
kind of middle ellipse,
you know, like, when kids
act like they're an airplane,
and then they make,
like, airplane noise,
then they do that weird
thing with their arms?
DAVID MALAN: Uh huh.
STUDENT: So draw those kind of,
like, arms in that middle ellipse,
coming out of the big middle ellipse.
DAVID MALAN: In the middle ellipse?
This lower one?
STUDENT: The one outside of it.
DAVID MALAN: Oh, this big ellipse?
STUDENT: Yeah, the outer bound.
Yeah.
DAVID MALAN: All right, so I should draw
some hands like a kid would have when--
OK.
I'm not sure this is going to end well.
BRIAN YU: All right.
We need some more volunteers
to help David finish this.
Let's go to Gabrielle.
STUDENT: OK.
Try to draw a--
DAVID MALAN: Try is the operative word.
[LAUGHTER]
STUDENT: You've got a
bigger ellipse that's
at the very bottom, that's bigger
than both the top and middle one,
but showing no overlapping lines
between the middle one and the one
that you're trying.
DAVID MALAN: So show
no overlapping lines.
So I heard an even bigger ellipse.
So, like, oops, sorry.
This?
OK?
STUDENT: Good job.
DAVID MALAN: Thank you.
OK.
Good.
Keep the positive reinforcement coming.
Final couple steps?
BRIAN YU: All right.
[? Ika? ?]
STUDENT: One other step
you would have to do
is draw a small, filled in circle,
slightly smaller than the one
you already drew, right in
the center of the first circle
you drew right at the top.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Right in the center of the first circle.
OK.
And I think this is starting
to take shape for me.
And I regret some of
my earlier decisions.
BRIAN YU: [INAUDIBLE],, you want to
provide an additional instruction?
STUDENT: Another circle in
between the last one you just drew
and in between the
edge of the circle, so
to the left of that circle you're
going to draw another circle.
DAVID MALAN: To the left of this circle?
STUDENT: Mhm.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
BRIAN YU: And Ryan?
STUDENT: Underneath, you're going
to want to repeat the same process,
except draw a circle on the right side.
DAVID MALAN: OK.
Little loop.
BRIAN YU: I think we've got
maybe one or two more steps left.
Let's go back to Sophia.
STUDENT: Underneath the filled in
circle, that's in the middle ellipse,
you want to draw two
replicas of that circle
below the original one
in the middle ellipse.
DAVID MALAN: In the middle
ellipse, so here, OK.
I think I know what this is.
BRIAN YU: And Jason, how
about one last instruction?
DAVID MALAN: All right.
STUDENT: Underneath,
in the top most circle,
under the three, so the row of
three circles, draw a wide V,
sort of shaped with two straight lines.
DAVID MALAN: A wide V
with two straight lines.
OK.
That part, I think, I nailed.
Shall I switch over and reveal?
So this is the URL I believe
all of you were given.
I have not visited it yet.
But if I go and visit this now.
Hey, that's not all that bad.
All right, I definitely took
a detour partway through.
But here's another example.
Had you just started with draw
a snowman as follows, like,
that might have helped orient
me, truthfully, similar in spirit
to Daniel's design that would have
given you a mental model of what I,
or given me a mental model of what
it is I should have been drawing.
So here, too, abstraction is hard.
And even precision is hard and
figuring out the right level of detail
to operate at is kind of part of
the process of problem solving.
Though, now that I look at it,
that's actually not half bad.
Like, I definitely did
the wrong thing over here.
But very well done to all
of our volunteers online.
So remember these kinds
of details when you're
trying to explain some process to
someone, when you're giving someone
instructions, even if it's for
something mundane in the real world,
like going to run errands or pick up
supplies at the market, being precise
is certainly important, but the more
precision you provide, the much easier
it is for the person to
get lost in those weeds.
And so sometimes a higher level list of
details is all that someone might need.
So now that you have this ability
to program and to do things
that we've shown you in
lectures and problem sets,
and indeed, have the
ability to figure out
how to do things that we
haven't even shown you,
we wanted to take a moment to consider
just whether you should do those things
and, if you should,
how you should do them.
But beyond just answering these
questions with your own instincts,
we thought we would invite
some of our colleagues
from the Philosophy department to
propose a more formal framework,
a thought process by which
we can approach problems
when it comes to technology
and the writing of code
to help us decide, ultimately,
just because I can code something,
should I, and if so, indeed,
how should I do that?
So allow me to introduce our colleagues
from the Philosophy department, Meica
Magnani and also Susan Kennedy.
Meica?
MEICA MAGNANI: So hi.
I'm Meica Magnani.
I am a philosophy postdoc with
the Embedded Ethics Program
here at Harvard.
SUSAN KENNEDY: Hi.
I'm Susan Kennedy.
And I'm also a philosophy postdoc with
the Embedded Ethics Program at Harvard.
MEICA MAGNANI: And
before we get started,
I'll just say a few things about
the Embedded Ethics Program.
So we are an interdisciplinary
team of philosophers and computer
scientists working together to integrate
ethics into the computer science
curriculum.
The idea behind this approach is
to embed tools of ethical reasoning
into computer science
courses themselves.
The reason for this is that when making
decisions about the design, deployment,
or development of a piece of technology,
one is, whether or not one realizes it,
making ethical decisions.
That is, making decisions which
stand to have social, political,
or human impact.
At Harvard, we think it's
important for computer scientists
to be equipped with tools for
thinking through these implications.
SUSAN KENNEDY: Technology holds a
lot of power and influence over us.
And that means, by extension, that the
people who design technology do, too.
Now that you're starting to
think about what responsibilities
you might have as computer
scientists, so you
can avoid notable mishaps,
like face mash, for instance,
we're going to turn your attention to
the topic of social media platforms
and how they affect the
distribution of and engagement
with news and information.
It would seem that this
topic is especially relevant
now, given the recent US presidential
election, where political content has
been dominating the internet and
television broadcasts and controversy
has played out on social
media, garnering attention
from around the world.
Undoubtedly, technology has
completely revolutionized
the way information and news is
both disseminated and consumed.
Instead of a paper boy shouting, get
your news here on the street corner,
just about everyone uses
the internet to stay up
to date with what's happening, not
just locally, but around the world.
And in the past few years, social
media platforms, in particular,
have started to play a huge role
in how people access, share,
and engage with information.
For instance, research
shows that 44% of US adults
report getting the news from Facebook.
It's safe to say a lot has
changed in recent years,
owing to developments in technology.
And this matters when we consider
what's at stake, namely, the ability
for the public to
engage in discourse that
supports a well-functioning democracy.
So I'll first present you a brief
overview of where we came from
and where we are now, owing
to technological developments
and then consider what challenges
we're faced with today.
Before the internet,
news and information
was almost entirely in the hands of a
few major broadcast stations and print
media outlets, otherwise known
as the mass media sphere.
Since a few organizations were
responsible for disseminating
all the news, information
was essentially
filtered through a narrow
lens or narrow aperture
from organizations to
a wide public audience.
The journalists who are responsible
for researching and writing
the content for these organizations
all shared a professional ethos.
They were concerned with truth,
representation of social groups,
creating a forum for criticism,
clarifying public values,
and offering comprehensive coverage.
And notably, since
the aim was to produce
content that appealed
to a wide audience,
there was less polarization and
extremist commentary than we see today.
But the journalists
responsible for news coverage
were very uniform in a lot of ways.
There were relatively affluent,
highly educated, mostly white, male,
and so forth.
And this had effects on the coverage
of racial politics, economic policy,
and views about the role
of the US in the world.
Moreover, there were seldom
opportunities for the audience
to respond, to develop
new themes or topics,
or level criticism against
the mass media sphere.
There weren't any likes
and comment sections
for the newspaper or
television broadcasts.
If you didn't like it, well, tough luck.
This all started to
change in recent years,
as news coverage not only moved online,
but onto social media platforms.
We now live in a digitally
networked public sphere.
So instead of having a narrow
aperture of communications,
or just a few organizations to
disseminate information to the public,
we now have a digital sphere with a
wide aperture, where lots of people
can share news and information.
More specifically,
the sources of content
are not just organizations and the
professional journalists they employed,
but the public and particularly,
social media users.
Anyone can tweet or post
on Facebook, and anyone
can read those tweets and posts.
It's not only resulted
in greater diversity
of content, but greater
access to information as well.
If you want to follow the news,
there are a ton of options
and free places online you can
access with just a few mouse clicks.
These prospects of increased
diversity and access
are what led many people to believe
that the digital sphere held
great promise for improving
the public discourse that
supports a well-functioning democracy.
And in some ways, this has been true.
For example, thanks to
Twitter and Facebook,
we saw the mobilization of
social justice movements,
like Me, Too and Black Lives Matter.
And the increased
diversity of perspectives
made it possible for individual
researchers and scientists
to weigh in on the CDC'S
claims about coronavirus.
So while the CDC did not initially
say coronavirus was characterized
by airborne transmission,
leading to community spread,
they ended up revising their
stance after scientists
took to Twitter with evidence
proving that this was the case.
While the digital sphere has
brought about some improvements,
it's also exacerbated some problems
and created new challenges.
For example, since anyone can create
content, fact checking and monitoring
have become much more
difficult. People are
left to fend for themselves when it
comes to figuring out whether something
they read online is trustworthy.
We've also seen increased
personalization with respect
to news and information,
where specific content could
be targeted to specific users
by the means of curated news
feeds on social media and
cable news stations cropping up
that take a particular angle
on the news that they cover.
This is significant.
Because we end up with a
somewhat paradoxical effect.
Despite a greater diversity in
the content that's available,
there's less diversity in the
news and information people
actually end up consuming, with the
personalization of information having
a tendency to reinforce
a person's viewpoints,
rather than challenge or broaden them.
Additionally, in the absence
of centralized sources of news,
we've also seen different aims expressed
by those creating and sharing content.
Some have bypassed a concern for truth
in an effort to garner more views
and likes with extremist
content or fake news.
And fake news became a
huge issue around the time
of the 2016 presidential
election, as there were concerns
that the massive spread of
misinformation on social media
could influence or sway
individuals political views.
While the spread of misinformation
has always been an issue,
it's truly been exacerbated
by the digital public sphere,
with social media platforms essentially
pouring gasoline on the fire.
The dissemination of fake
news explodes on social media
because the structure of digital
environments, from likes to retweets,
allows a single post on
fake news to go viral,
reaching the screens of
millions around the world.
And there are serious worries about
how fake news has played a role
in amplifying political polarization.
So while technology has made
possible unique advantages,
it's also brought on unique challenges.
One major question that
we're faced with now
is figuring out how content should be
regulated on social media platforms,
if at all.
Given the scale of the problem,
some might be skeptical,
believing that any form of content
regulation would be impossible.
There's just too many people posting
online to fact check them all.
And fake news spreads so quickly,
it's hard to stop before it's already
reached a huge audience.
There's also worries
that attempts to regulate
content could end up becoming a
form of censorship that violates
the right to freedom of speech.
But some people are more
optimistic about the possibilities
of designing social media platforms
in a way that promotes and preserves
democracy.
In particular, there's a possibility
that with responsibly designed
algorithms and user
interface choices, we
might be able to slow
the spread of fake news
and more generally improve the ways
information is disseminated and engaged
with on social media.
For example, some people believe
that companies like Facebook, Twitter
and YouTube have a responsibility
to regulate content
because of the enormous
influence they have over us.
In particular, it's thought that social
media platforms have a responsibility
to police fake news and reduce the
power of data driven algorithms that
personalize the user experience,
even if doing these things
would come at the cost
of user engagement,
resulting in less time spent on the
platform and less advertising revenue.
It's clear that the path
going forward in terms
of content regulation on social media
platforms is going to be tricky.
Whether or not we promote
democratic ideals or undermine
them will come down to the
particular design choices we make.
In order to use technology
to create solutions
to the problems we're
facing today, we'll
need to make informed
decisions about design choices.
And this requires some critical
thinking about ethics and philosophy
to figure out the best way to do this.
But we're hoping that students
like you, taking CS50,
can harness your creativity, technical
knowledge, and ethical reasoning
to design technology
in a responsible way.
So I'm now going to pass
things over to Meica,
who will tell you about some
philosophical concepts that'll
help you think proactively
about particular design
choices and algorithmic tools that
can be implemented to structure
social media platforms in a way that
promotes democratic public discourse.
MEICA MAGNANI: In Democracy
and The Digital Public Sphere,
an article which offers a fantastic
diagnosis of our situation,
and from which Susan and
I are drawing heavily
upon for this lecture, the authors
Joshua Cohen and Archon Fung,
tell us that the bloom
is off the digital rose.
As Susan was describing,
we had such high hopes
for the democratizing potential
of social media and the internet.
But now we face an environment
in which fake news runs rampant,
citizens appear to be
dramatically polarized,
information swirls in
its own isolated bubbles,
and hate speech reaches
appalling levels of vitriol.
All of which stand to threaten,
or so people speculate,
the conditions required
for an effective democracy.
So the following questions
arise, in what ways
are the conditions of
democracy threatened?
What can or should be done about it?
Is the structure of our
technology responsible?
Or is it just us, as human
beings, creating these problems?
In this module, we're
focusing specifically
on the issue of content regulation.
Social media companies like
Twitter, Facebook, and YouTube
are now all in the game of trying to
address these problems through platform
design and features.
From one angle then, they are acting
in the service of protecting democracy
by trying to get control over
the spread of misinformation,
the amplification of hate speech,
and the deepening of polarization.
However, from another
angle, they're stepping in
to shape the distribution
of information.
And depending on the
particular design choices,
might be set to be
regulating or silencing
speech, which of course, is at
odds with democratic commitments
to free speech and discourse.
The point of this module,
then, is to give you some tools
to think through these issues,
tools for understanding the problem,
diagnosing the sources of the
problem, and brainstorming solutions.
In the remaining 10 or
15 minutes, I'm going
to provide an overview
of the main tools which
you will find detailed in the readings.
They are also the tools you will be
asked to analyze in this week's lab.
So first then, we need to
think clearly about what
is required for a healthy democracy.
If we're going to be making claims
about how tech threatens democracy,
we better understand A, what a democracy
is, and B, what sort of conditions
support democracy, such that those
conditions could come under threat.
In their article, Archon Fung, who
is a professor in political science
here at Harvard, and Joshua Cohen, who
is a political philosopher now working
with the faculty at Apple University,
provide us with these tools.
So behind the idea of
democracy is an ideal
of what political society should be.
Fung and Cohen reduce this
ideal to three elements.
First, the idea of a
democratic society, a society
in which the political culture
views individuals as free and equal.
Even though it is likely
that these people have
different interests, identities,
and systems of belief, as citizens,
they are committed to arriving m through
reflection and discourse, principles
that will enable them to work together
while respecting their freedom
and equality.
Second is the idea of a
democratic political regime, which
is characterized by regular
elections, rights of participation,
along with associative
and expressive rights
that make participation
both informed and effective.
Third and lastly is the idea
of a deliberative democracy,
according to which
political discussion should
appeal to reasons that are
suitable for cooperation
amongst free and equal persons.
So in justifying a policy, you cannot
appeal to, say, your own religion,
given that others do not
necessarily hold those same beliefs.
You can appeal to the notion of,
say, religious freedom, but not
the particular beliefs contained
within the religion itself.
So democracy, then,
is basically an ideal
that we govern ourselves by collective
decision making, decision making that
respects our freedom and equality.
This decision making consists not only
of the formal procedures of voting,
elections, and legislation, it is also
informed by the informal public sphere,
that is, citizens identifying
problems and concerns,
discussing and debating problems,
expressing opinions, challenging
viewpoints, and
organizing around causes.
This is an absolutely critical part of
the democratic decision-making process.
It is where we, as the public,
form, test, disperse, exchange,
challenge, and revise our views.
The flow of information,
along with user engagement
on Facebook, YouTube,
and Twitter, are all part
of this informal public sphere.
In order that individuals
can participate
as free and equal citizens in
this arena of public discourse,
Cohen and Fung lay out a set
of rights and opportunities
that a well-functioning
democracy will require.
And these are the tools
of analysis on offer.
So first, rights.
"As citizens of a
democracy, we have rights
to basic liberties, liberties
of expression and association.
The right to expressive
liberty is important
not only for the freedom
of the individual,
so that he or she will not be censored,
but also for democracy itself.
It enables citizens to bring their
ideas into conversation with one another
and to criticize and hold accountable
those who exercise power."
Second is the opportunity
for expression.
"Not only should we be
free of censorship, but
we should have fair opportunity to
participate in public discussion.
It shouldn't be the case
that because someone is, say,
wealthier or more powerful, that they
have more opportunity to participate."
Third is access.
"Each person should have
good and equal access
to quality and reliable
information on public matters.
That is, if we make
the effort, we should
be able to acquire this information.
Effective participation in decision
making requires being informed."
Fourth is diversity.
"Each person should have good and equal
chances to hear a wide range of views.
We need access to competing
views in order to have
a more informed and reasoned position"
And lastly, number five,
communicative power.
"Citizens should have good and equal
chances to explore interests and ideas
in association with others.
And through these associations,
to develop new concerns that
might challenge the mainstream view."
These rights and opportunities
together provide critical conditions
for enabling participation
in public discussion.
They might seem like a lot
to keep track of initially,
but if we're going to think through
how social media threatens democracy,
and more concretely, how platform design
might promote or hinder democracy,
these are valuable tools.
We can use, say, the
access condition, the idea
that we should all have access
to reliable information,
as a lens of analysis.
Does our platform prevent
certain groups or users
from accessing reliable information?
Or we can use the diversity
condition, the idea
that we should all have access to
a plurality of conflicting views
as a lens of analysis.
So for example, we might ask
ourselves, does our platform
create a filter bubble in which
individuals are no longer confronted
with opposing views?
In addition to understanding
what conditions support
a democratic society, we also need
to understand the purported problems
before we can propose
effective interventions.
Consider fake news.
Why are people so gullible
when it comes to fake news?
Why do they often repost without
proper critical assessment?
Regina Rini, in the reading,
proposes that in order
to understand the
phenomenon of fake news,
we should think about it
as a form of testimony.
When another person shares
information with you,
you typically take it to be true.
This is because of the norms
governing our practice of testimony.
When you assert something,
passing it on to others,
you typically take
responsibility for its truth.
It is assumed that you have
either acquired evidence
for yourself or you've received
this information from a source
that you deem reliable.
Most of our knowledge about the
world comes through this practice.
We could not possibly acquire
evidence for all the beliefs we hold.
So we often have to rely on sources
we deem and hope to be credible.
But social media, Rini points out,
has unsettled testimonial norms.
When someone posts a piece of news,
we seem to hold two conflicting views.
On the one hand, we see it
as an active endorsement.
The person posting has taken
some degree of responsibility
for the accuracy of their
post, the same way one
would before passing on
information in a conversation.
On the other hand,
though, it's just a share.
We see this attitude coming through
when Donald Trump, called out
on one of his questionable tweets,
retorts with, eh, it's just a tweet.
To fight fake news,
then, Rini argues that we
need to stabilize social media's norms
of testimony so that, as she says,
the same norms that keep
us honest over cocktails
will keep us honest in our posts.
We need people to be
held accountable for,
or to have a sense of
responsibility, for the information
that they share with others.
Her concrete proposal, give
users a credibility score.
So in practice, this would be an
amendment to Facebook's system,
using independent fact
checking organizations,
Facebook flags problematic news and
warns users before they repost it.
When a user tries to post
something that has been identified
as false or misleading, a pop up
appears that explains the problem
and identifies the original source.
It then asks the user to
confirm that they would
like to continue with their repost.
A user's credibility
score, for Rini, would
depend on how often they
choose to ignore these warnings
and pass on misleading information.
Quote, "a green dot by
the user's name could
indicate that the user hasn't
chosen to share much disputed news.
A yellow dot could indicate
that they do it sometimes.
And a red could indicate
that they do it often."
Unquote.
The idea, then, is that
a credibility score
would incentivize users
to take responsibility
for what they share and would also give
others a sense of their reliability
as sources.
So Rini comes up with this
solution through a careful analysis
of why we are so gullible to fake news.
I will leave it up to you
to consider this proposal
in light of the various rights
and opportunities required
for a democratic public sphere.
Does Rini's proposal violate or
threaten freedom of expression?
Does it promote or hinder our access
to reliable information, our access
to diversity of views, or
does it promote or hinder
our communicative power?
It is these sorts of
questions that we hope
that you will start to
ask yourself when thinking
through the following sorts of issues.
What problems do fake news, hate
speech, polarization, et cetera
pose to democracy?
How successful are various attempts
by companies like Twitter, YouTube,
and Facebook to address these problems?
And how might particular design
features of social media platforms
promote or hinder these particular
rights and opportunities?
Whether as a future computer
scientist, a tech industry leader,
or just as a user of these technologies,
we hope asking these sorts of questions
will help you navigate these tricky
issues with a more critical eye.
SUSAN KENNEDY: We're really looking
forward to the sorts of design choices
that you'll be making in the future.
MEICA MAGNANI: Great.
Thanks so much for having us here today.
And best of luck to everybody.
DAVID MALAN: Well, thank you so much
to Susan and Meica for joining us.
Indeed, in this coming week's
lab, we'll have an opportunity
to consider some of these issues
in the context of some very
specific real world scenarios.
So we now thought we would take
a look forward at what you can do
and how you can do it
after CS50 when it comes
to the more practical side of things
beyond computational thinking alone.
So programming, of
course, for many of you,
this will be by design the only
computer science or programming course
that you take.
And that's certainly OK.
Indeed, we hope that you'll
be able now to return
to your own domains of interest in the
arts and humanities, social sciences,
or sciences and actually be able to
have a concrete set of practical skills
be it in Python or C or any of
the other technical languages
we looked at and can actually solve
problems in your own preferred domain.
And if you're interested in
learning more about computer science
itself and moving on
in that world, we hope
that you'll walk away
with a solid foundation
for further theoretical and systematic
explorations of this particular field.
But very practically
speaking, we hope now
that you can not only program,
but also ask questions better,
whether that's in the technical
world or even in just the real world.
Odds are, if you've ever asked a
question on CS50's discussion forums,
the teaching fellows or I might have
very well responded with questions
asking you to clarify.
Or better yet, you would have
provided us, in anticipation,
with answers to all of the
questions that we might have.
And if you've noticed
on Ed, we deliberately
have this sort of
template via which you're
coaxed to answer, well, what are
the symptoms that you are seeing?
What's the error message
that you're struggling with?
What steps have you tried
to resolve the problem?
Because if we imagine in the real
world, even just reaching out
to some random company's
customer service line,
those are exactly the kinds
of questions that someone else
is going to have to ask
you to better understand
a problem from your own perspective.
And so we would encourage you to think
about, as you emerge from CS50 itself,
just how to ask better
questions of people.
If you've got more
information than they,
how can you succinctly but correctly
convey that information to them
so that they can help
you more efficiently.
But also, finding answers.
Like, we absolutely understand that many
of CS50's weeks, all of CS50's weeks,
maybe, have been quite the frustration.
Because you quite often feel like,
well, we didn't cover that in lecture.
Or I didn't see that in section.
And I see some noddings of the head.
So this seems to be the case.
And much as I would love to
reassure otherwise, like,
that was very much the intent.
Because the last of the training
wheels of any course like this
now really do officially come off.
And in the coming
weeks, while we'll still
be with you to lend a
hand with final projects
and answer questions
along those lines, there's
of course no specification for the final
project telling you exactly what to do,
or in what language to do
it, or what libraries to use.
Undoubtedly, in the
coming weeks, you will
run into error messages you
haven't even seen before.
And frankly, maybe I, maybe Brian,
maybe the teaching assistants,
and the course assistants haven't
even seen those errors before.
But the goal, of course, is to get
you over those hurdles in a way
that you can figure out how to
do those things on your own.
And so when it comes to just using
the internet, be it Google, or Stack
Overflow, or interacting
with other humans,
just finding answers when it
comes to the world of programming
or really just the world of
problem solving more generally,
we hope that is actually
a lasting skill.
And we hope that you've been able to
do that with admittedly frustration,
but with the safety net of the course
underneath you all these months.
But here on out, we hope you'll be more
comfortable, again, being uncomfortable
as you figure out new things.
And part of that is just
reading documentation.
And here, too, this is a frustration
that may very well never go away.
Like, some documentation out there for
certain languages or libraries, just
isn't good.
It was written by people
that just don't think
like you or I do, don't think with the
same form of empathy as you might hope.
And therefore, it's written at a
very low level of technical detail,
and they don't just tell you
what does the function do.
Or conversely, it's written at
such a high level that, my God,
you have to start looking at
the source code of the library
to even figure out how to use it.
And you will see both extremes.
But getting comfortable with reading
things like Python's documentation,
like some API's documentation is
just going to empower you, we hope,
all the more to just
do much cooler things
and solve more powerful problems
on your own, ultimately.
And then lastly, and this is perhaps
the biggest one, teaching you
how to teach yourself new languages.
There is a reason we didn't
spend that much time on Python.
And we spent even less
time on JavaScript.
And about an equal
amount of time on SQL.
We spent a number of
weeks on C, not because C
is more important than
any of those languages,
but because along the way,
many of you, most of you
were just learning programming itself.
And even as the language has changed
and evolved as the course went on,
the ideas didn't go away.
There were still functions, and
conditions, and loops, and even
events by terms.
And, again, so we hope that you
walk away from a class like this
not thinking that, oh, I
learned how to program in C.
Or oh, I learned how
to program in Python.
Because none of us have been
experts at those things yet.
But you certainly are now more
expert at just being a programmer
and figuring out what holes you need
to fill in in your knowledge, what
gaps you need to fill
in order to figure out,
oh, what is the syntax for this
same approach in this language
as I've already seen in another.
And that's, indeed, why we compared
so many of these languages side
by side to just reinforce that
the ideas are no different, even
though the syntax is going to require
a bunch of Googling, a bunch of asking.
And that, too, is something we hope
you'll be able to do on your own
as the next and best thing comes
along well after these languages.
Well, speaking of
training wheels, you're
welcome and encouraged to keep using
CS50 IDE for your final project.
And heck, you can use it even after
that for other courses or projects.
But at the end of the day, this,
too, is probably a training wheel
that you should take off for yourself.
The IDE is designed to be representative
of a real world programming
environment.
But we definitely did a
lot of things for you.
We installed all the
libraries you might need over
the course of the semester for you.
We've got these nice commands
that end in the number 50.
Those don't tend to exist in the real
world when you're at your first job,
or you're going back
to your own department
and solving some
problem in code, there's
not going to be a help50 longer term.
And so what we thought we would do,
too, is spend just a few minutes
giving you a sense of what are
some of the more industry standard
tools that you should consider
using, playing with, perhaps
over break or in the months to come,
so that you know exactly how to do
the same kinds of things you did
this term, but on your own Mac
or PC or some other device.
So for instance, if you would like to
install a set of command line tools
on your Mac or PC, turns out
some of them are already there.
Indeed, I mentioned at
one point that Mac OS
has under its applications folder
utility's terminal a terminal window.
And Windows has an analog as well.
But there's other commands that don't
necessarily come with your Mac or PC,
for instance, a compiler
for C or some other tools.
And so we would encourage you to visit
URLs like these on your Mac or PC,
respectively, if you'd like to just
install more of the command line tools
that you saw and used in
CS50 in your own environment.
Another tool we would recommend
that you read up on, or in this case
watch, a video by Brian, is Git.
Git is an example of version
control, a fundamental building
block of any good software
practice these days.
We kind of use Git in CS50, but
we hide this detail from you.
Any time you have run check50 or
submit50, we underneath the hood,
have been running an open source command
called Git, which pushes your code,
in this case from CS50 IDE to
GitHub.com, which is just one
of several popular
websites via which you
can host code, share code, collaborate
on code, run automated tests,
and the like.
But Git itself can be used to
put an end to the convention
that you probably have, even with things
like Microsoft Word or Google Docs,
where when you want to save
something or another copy of a file,
maybe you just changed the
end of the file name to 2,
and then the next time to 3, or to 4.
Or maybe you do dash Sunday
night, dash Monday morning.
I mean, I'm still guilty
of this sometimes when I
want to version my files.
There are better ways to do that.
And so if you find
yourself in the future,
doing something that you think
there's got to be a better way,
Git is an example of one
of those better ways.
And if you watch this
particular video, read
up a bit more, it will help you not only
maintain multiple versions, in essence,
backups of your own code, it
will also empower you ultimately
to collaborate with others.
As for text editors,
the tool that you might
use to actually write code, perhaps
one of the latest and greatest and most
popular out there these days
is something called VS Code.
This is an open source tool that you
can download on your own Mac and PCs.
Increasingly, it's available
on the web as well.
But this is one of the most popular
tools, certainly, out there today.
But it's just a text editor.
And there are absolutely alternatives
to each and every one of these tools
that you're certainly welcome
to take a look at as well.
Well, if you're interested
in the web side of things,
and you want to host a website,
like a static website, just
your own personal homepage,
GitHub pages is a thing.
Netlify is a thing.
And dot dot dot, there are so
many other web hosts out there,
many of which offer
free or student level
accounts so that they don't
necessarily need to even cost anything.
But static is different from dynamic.
And if you actually want to host a
web application that actually takes
user input, stores things
in a database, does
more interesting things
than a static website,
you might want to use something
called Heroku, which is just
a popular third party service that also
has a free entry level account that you
can use to start playing
with, quite commonly used
by students for final projects.
And then there's other providers
out there, bigger cloud providers,
so to speak, like Amazon,
and Microsoft, and Google,
for which the learning curve's
perhaps a little higher.
But they, too, are really good
typically about providing discounts
or free accounts for
student uses as well.
How to stay abreast of
topics in technology.
We focus, of course, in a class
like this really on fundamentals.
But you're not going to be able to pick
up the news in any form down the road
and not see something
that's technology related.
And if you'd just like to keep
your fingers on the pulse of things
in the tech world more generally,
here's just a few places
that you might enjoy staying abreast of.
So Reddit has a couple of different
communities, or subreddit, specifically
about programming, both
for experienced programmers
and those of us who are still learning.
Stack Overflow, of
course, you've probably
used to solve small problems
over the course of the past term.
Server Fault is similar
in spirit to that,
but it's focused more on administration,
Linux-type stuff as well.
Techcrunch is a popular place, not
just for consumer-focused news,
but just really anything
that's trending in tech.
And then a website called Hacker
News on YCombinator's site
that also is a place to just
glance at once in a while
because you'll see the latest and
greatest libraries or something
that's quite nascent.
So if in general you just want
to get a sense of what's new
and what's trending out there
in the tech world, things
that you should just be aware
of even if you don't care
to get into the weeds of
doing those things hands on,
these are all good sites and
surely others out there as well.
And then, CS50, of course, has its
own online community, some of which
some of you have been part for some
time, in high school or even prior.
Please feel free to keep in
touch with us in some way,
or give back a little something
to your successors who
might take this or another
course down the road
and participate not only in asking
questions in these communities here,
but also in answering
others' questions as well.
So we thought we would do a
little less of the talking
now and turn things around for a sort
of final community activity together.
Thanks to many of you who
have contributed questions
over the past couple of weeks.
Thanks to Brian, we thought we'd
put together a CS50 quiz show
on which to end this final lecture.
These are questions written by
you, by the staff, by Brian.
And it'll be an opportunity
for everyone to buzz in
with their answers to some 20 questions
that we have prepared in advance.
Time is of the essence.
So your score will be higher
if you buzz in more quickly.
So it's important not
only to be correct,
but also to be fast for
this particular one as well.
And in just a moment, I'm going
to go ahead and share my screen.
And, again, we'll have some 20
questions here, all of them drawn from,
inspired by CS50 in some form.
And after each question, depending on
how many people get it right or wrong,
we'll take a moment to at least
explain where it is you went right
or where it is you went wrong.
All right, Brian.
Ready on your end?
BRIAN YU: We are ready to go.
DAVID MALAN: All right, well,
let's go ahead and take a look
with the first question here.
What are the steps for compiling
source code into machine code?
Preprocessing, compiling,
assembling, and linking?
Writing, compiling,
debugging, and testing?
Processing, creating,
asserting, and clang?
Or make?
Go ahead and buzz in on your
phone or laptop or desktop,
using that same URL that Brian provided.
You've got 20 seconds for each
question, two of which now remain.
That's it for time.
Let's go ahead and take a
look at the results here.
It looks like 70% of you said
preprocessing, compiling, assembling,
and linking.
Brian, would you like to
tell us if that's right?
BRIAN YU: Yes.
That is the correct answer.
Preprocessing first, compiling,
assembling, and linking, all of that
is behind the scenes.
So you don't necessarily think
about every time you compile.
But those are, indeed, the steps.
DAVID MALAN: And to be fair,
make is arguably an abstraction
for all of that insofar as it
just kicks off the whole process.
But I think a little more precisely,
an answer to steps would be,
indeed, those four things there.
All right, let's take a
look at the scoreboard here.
We have a whole number
of guest accounts.
Guest number 200 is in the lead, but
tied with several other guests here.
So those of you with 1,000
points buzzed in really quickly.
So again time is of the essence.
Next question, what is the
runtime of binary search?
Is it O of 1, O of log n,
O of n, or O of n squared?
15 seconds remain, the
runtime of binary search.
Recall, this was one of the
first algorithms we looked at.
It was first incarnated
with a phone book,
even if we didn't call
it that by name early on.
Brian, let's take a look at the results.
Looks like 61% of you say log n.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: Log n is the correct answer.
If you remember that
phone book, the question
really came down to
how many times can we
divide that phone book
and half again and again
and again, until we get
down to just one page.
And that turns out to be log of n if
three are n pages in the phone book.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed, and sort of pro
tip moving forward in life, any time
you see something happening in
half and half and half and half,
odds are there's going to
be an algorithm involved
somewhere in the analysis thereof.
All right, next leaderboard here,
guest 200 slipped down a little bit.
But we have a whole bunch of people tied
in first place for 2,000 points now.
Next question, which of
these animals was the first
to be mentioned in a CS50 lecture?
Llama, python, duck, cat.
15 seconds remain.
Which was mentioned
first in a CS50 lecture?
And let's see the results.
Looks like cat just barely
eked out duck with 51%.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: And cat is, in
fact, the correct answer.
Llamas showed up in Lab 1, but
they were not mentioned in lecture.
The duck didn't show
up until a little bit
later when we talked about debugging.
And Python was briefly mentioned
at the end of the lecture.
But it was after we introduced
ourselves to Scratch.
And the main character in
Scratch is, of course, the cat.
DAVID MALAN: All right, we're probably
going to see a bit of spread here soon.
We have a whole bunch of
people with 3,000, though.
But the names are starting to vary.
Let's move on to the next question.
Every time you malloc memory,
you must also be sure to--
realloc, return, free, or exit?
Every time you malloc memory, you
should also be sure to realloc,
return, free, or exit?
Recall that malloc was the source
of a lot of segmentation faults
mid-semester.
The responses now are 78% said free.
Brian, do you concur?
BRIAN YU: And they are all correct.
Whenever you malloc memory, ask the
computer for some memory dynamically.
When you're done with it, you
should give it back to the computer
by calling free.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed, and
Brian, as a teachable
moment, why is it that we never had a
call free forget_string, which we now
know underneath the
hood is using something
like malloc to allocate memory?
BRIAN YU: So get_string was
a function in CS50's library.
And CS50's library takes care of that
memory management process for you.
So you didn't have to worry about
freeing all of that memory yourself.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed, but anytime
you call malloc, you must call free.
All right, the leaderboard
here looks like we have
guest 600 still in the lead with 4,000.
Next question.
What is a race condition?
When conditions are nice out for racing?
When two things happen at the same
time and produce an unexpected result?
When a line of code is
executed too quickly?
executed too slowly?
What is a race condition?
Ah, things just escalated quickly.
But you'll recall this came
up in the context of SQL.
And databases, 0 seconds, let's see.
85% said when two things
happen at the same time
and produce an unexpected result. Brian?
BRIAN YU: That is the correct answer.
I appreciate that at least 1% of
people said when conditions outside
are nice for racing.
But in the context of
computer science, at least,
when two things happen at the same time
and could produce an unexpected result,
that is what we would refer
to as a race condition.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed, recall
that's how Brian and I ended up
with too much milk in the refrigerator.
Because we both inspected
the state of that variable
at essentially the same time.
All right, the leader board here.
Now we have a whole bunch
of people with 5,000 points.
Let's move on.
Does zooming in on a photo let you
enhance it to generate more detail?
Yes, just like in CSI.
No, a photo only has a
certain amount of detail.
Does zooming in on a photo let you
enhance it to generate more detail?
And I will admit, I was watching
some show recently and thought of you
all when they literally said, enhance.
All right, 0 seconds.
Looks like 93% of you said, no, a photo
only has a certain amount of detail.
7% of you said yes, just like in CSI.
Brian, can you help
us reconcile the two?
BRIAN YU: The 93%, in
this case, are correct.
A photo only has a
certain number of pixels.
And if you keep zooming
in on one pixel, you're
not going to be able to
generate additional detail that
wasn't there before.
DAVID MALAN: And to be fair,
that's kind of sort of changing.
Or at least the answer is
getting a little harder nowadays
with machine learning or
artificial intelligence,
where algorithms sort of
figure out what level of detail
could or should be there.
But that really is just
statistical inference,
that is not actually recovering
information that was ever stored
on the camera or some other device.
All right, the leaderboard now is at
6,000 points with these folks tied.
Which of the following is not a
characteristic of a good hash function?
Deterministic output, randomness,
uniform distribution, efficiency.
Things just got real again.
Which of the following is not a
characteristic of a good hash function?
Recall we used hash functions
in the context of hash tables
when talking about data structures.
All right?
One second.
The answers are more spread this time.
62% don't like randomness.
Brian, should they?
BRIAN YU: And that is
the correct answer.
Randomness is not a characteristic
of a good hash function.
You want your hash
function to always give you
the same output given the same input.
That way you can rely on
whatever the output of it is.
If it's random, it's
going to be hard to use.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed,
consider a spellchecker
that randomly says yes or no.
This is a word, probably
not a property you want.
All right, the leaderboard now, we're
eking our way up to 7,000 points,
but finally starting to see some spread.
So a few of you haven't been
quite quick or correct enough.
Next question, what does FIFO stand for?
FIFO.
Is it a common dog's name, your
credit score, first in, first out,
function input, file output?
What does FIFO stand for?
I'll be curious to see the spread here.
Let's see.
80% of you said first in, first out.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: That is correct.
And that was what we
were using to describe
what would be called like a queue,
where the first thing in the queue
is the first thing that
comes out of the queue.
So it obeys that FIFO ordering.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed, let's
see the leaderboard here.
All right, we have some 8,000s,
but more in the 7,000 range.
Next up is a more colorful question.
Which of the following would
represent pink using RGB values?
And I'll let you read these on your own.
And surely, there's some Googling
happening behind the scenes now.
But that's OK.
In fact, Google is pretty smart.
If you type in a hexadecimal
code, it might even
show you a little color wheel or swatch.
All right, let's take
a look at the results.
Looks like 55% of you said ffd0e0.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: And that is correct.
So those RGB values are
like six different values,
where each two correspond to one
color, two for red, two for green,
two for blue.
This is all in hexadecimal.
And pink would be a lot of each of them.
Because it's very close
to white, which is, like,
all red, all green, and all blue.
But it's more red than
it is green and blue.
And so that one, ffd0e0, is a lot
of red, a little bit less green,
and a little bit less blue.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
All right, let's see
where we're at here.
We're now up to-- interesting.
No one has a perfect score anymore.
But guest 200 is still in the lead
with just shy of 9,000 points.
In C, which of the following
lines of code allocates
enough memory for a
copy of the string s?
I'll let you read these.
In C, which of the following
lines of code allocates
enough memory for a
copy of the string s?
Bunch of viable choices
here, it would seem.
And time, let's take
a look at the results.
Looks like 46% said malloc of size s.
But Brian, 33% said malloc
of strlen of s plus 1.
Who is right?
BRIAN YU: And in this case, the
minority, the 33% are correct here.
Malloc, remember, takes as its
argument the number of bytes of memory
that you want to allocate.
And if you have a string and you want
to figure out how many bytes you need,
first thing you need
to know is figure out
how long is that string.
strlen will tell you
how many characters are in that string.
But you do need one additional byte,
because at the end of every string,
we have that null terminating character.
And we need one byte of memory for that.
So strlen of s will give you
the length of the string plus 1.
That's how many bytes
you need for memory.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
And see, you get nothing for free.
Anything you want you
need to do yourself.
And indeed, the plus 1 is
a problem for you to solve.
The distribution now, guest
200 still in the lead with just
shy of 10,000 points.
That was question 10.
We're in the second half of the game.
How should you organize
your clothes to be cool?
This is number 11.
Stack, queue, dictionary, binary tree.
How should you organize
your clothes to be cool?
You might recall Jack and
Lou, who taught us this one.
Two seconds remain.
And it looks like 48% said queue, Brian.
BRIAN YU: And that is correct.
So from that video with
Jack and Lou, there
were different ways of
organizing the clues.
But the conclusion of
that video was, you
want to put your clothes in a queue.
So that after you're done with one,
you put it at the end of the queue.
And you use something else before you
go back to the one you already wore.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
All right.
And the leaderboard now, looks
like guest 10 broke 10,000.
But so did a bunch of other people.
Next question, what is
a segmentation fault?
When a computer runs out of
memory, when our program tries
to read an empty file, when a program
tries to access memory that it
shouldn't, when an earthquake happens.
Looks like a lot of these
could be pretty close.
Two seconds.
And let's see.
Looks like 80% said when a program tries
to access memory that it shouldn't.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: That is the correct answer.
Segmentation fault can
happen if you're trying
to touch memory that you're not supposed
to have access to inside of a program.
DAVID MALAN: And for
the 13% of people who
said when a computer runs out of memory,
why is that not quite the answer here?
BRIAN YU: So the computer
could run out of memory.
Where when you call malloc,
malloc might return null,
because there's no available
memory to allocate.
But as long as you check for that,
and we try and encourage you,
whenever you're mallocing memory, to
check to see if the value you get back
is null.
That can help you to avoid
those types of errors.
DAVID MALAN: So let's take
a look at the board now.
11,000 something for guest 200.
Let's now proceed with this question.
Which of the following types of
overflow can result from recursion
without a base case?
Heap overflow, integer overflow,
stack overflow, buffer overflow.
And all forms of
overflow, indeed, came up.
One of them is also, of course,
the name of a popular website.
But all of these are actual things.
But which is correct?
All right, let's see the results.
Looks like 61%, 60% went
with stack overflow.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: And that is correct.
Every time you call a function, you
end up getting a little bit of memory
on the stack for that function.
And if you keep calling that
function recursively over and over
and never stop, because
there's no base case,
then you can run out of stack space.
And we call that a stack overflow.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
All right, let's see
the leaderboard now.
Guest 200, still the one to beat.
But guest 216 is not too far behind.
Next question.
In the town of Fiftyville,
what were the names
of the three people who witnessed
the rubber duck robbery?
I'll let you read these.
In the town of Fiftyville, what
were the names of the three people
who witnessed the rubber duck robbery.
A new problem this year, recall that
he disappeared altogether from the IDE
for that week.
All right, let's see the results.
Brian, this one is close.
33% said Ruth, Eugene, and Raymond.
BRIAN YU: And Ruth, Eugene,
and Raymond is correct.
They've got more responses
than any of the others.
It was tricky.
But yeah, that's the correct answer.
There wasn't a whole lot
of reason behind the names.
I put a lot of thought
into the story itself.
But not a lot of thought to the names.
Those were kind of
just randomly selected.
But those were the
names of the witnesses.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
And the leaderboard now, we still
have guest 200 is the one to beat.
This is question 15.
So we are nearing the end,
still chance to pull ahead.
Which of these command line programs
checks your code for memory leaks?
Valgrind, clang, mkdir, make.
Notice that none of these have 50 on
it, which means these are all real world
commands that you would continue
to see on your own Mac or PC
or some future Linux system.
And let's see the results.
Here we have valgrind,
the clear winner, 78%.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: And that's the correct answer.
That's the program you can use
in order to check your program
to see if you have any
memory leaks, to see
if you're touching memory you shouldn't,
if you're forgetting to free something.
Valgrind is useful for all of that.
DAVID MALAN: And if I may, I feel like
5% of you are just messing with us now.
Hopefully, but we shall see.
All right, last five questions to go.
After taking a look at the leaderboard
now, guest 200's still up at the top.
Which of the following
exists in C, but not Python.
Boolean expressions,
do-while loops, recursive
functions, floating-point numbers.
Which of the following
exists in C, but not Python?
An interesting comparison between two
languages that goes beyond syntax.
All right.
Time's up.
Let's take a look.
Looks like 68% went with do-while loops.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: That is correct.
Python has for loops.
Python has while loops.
But it doesn't have do-while
loops in the same way that C does.
You'd have to find some other
way of trying to achieve
that same kind of logical idea.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
And Brian, what was the
approach that we took when we
tried to recreate that some weeks ago?
BRIAN YU: Yeah.
So one approach to it is having
an infinite loop, while true,
that will just always repeat.
And then when you reach a point
where you can exit the loop,
you can use the command
break to get out of the loop
and move on to the rest of the program.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
All right, let's take
a look at the board.
Guest 200 still now at 15,938, but
still a few close folks behind.
What HTTP request method should you
use when sending private information
like a password?
GET, POST, SELECT, or TEXT?
Which HTTP request method
should use when sending
private information like a password?
Take a look at the results.
All right.
And the distribution is a lot
of people said POST, Brian, 74%
BRIAN YU: And they are correct.
Yeah, if it was a get
request, then you would end up
with sensitive information
inside the URL that might show up
in your browsing history, for example.
So to be secure, you want to
be sure to use the POST request
method for that type of stuff.
DAVID MALAN: And to be
clear, don't do this.
Get is possible, and
we saw how to do that.
But of course, that then ends up in
your history and other exposed places.
SELECT and TEXT were not HTTP verbs.
So POST is indeed spot on.
All right, only three questions remain.
Guest 200 is still the one to
beat, followed by guest 216.
What data structure allows for constant
time look up for words in a dictionary?
A linked list, a binary search
tree, an array, or a trie?
Recall that a dictionary
was an abstract data
type, insofar as you could
implement it in different ways.
But to get constant time
look up, you might want
to use one of these over the others.
Let's see the results.
Interesting.
Brian, 32% said trie.
Can you help us out here?
BRIAN YU: Yeah.
The trie is the correct answer.
For all of the others, the linked list,
the binary search tree, and the array,
as you have more and more
words in the dictionary,
it's going to take longer
and longer to find a word,
as you have to either
linear search through it
or you have to go down through various
nodes in the binary search tree.
The trie on the other hand, it only
depends upon the length of the word
that you're looking up.
It doesn't matter how many
words are in the dictionary.
You just follow one node for each
letter in the word you're looking up.
And you'll find that
word in constant time.
DAVID MALAN: And Brian, if constant
time, Big O of 1 is so good,
why not use tries, then, for everything?
BRIAN YU: Well, there are
trade offs for everything.
The trie gives you
theoretically constant time.
But one of the big trade offs is memory.
That tries end up using
much more memory to be
able to store a dictionary than many
of those other data structures would.
DAVID MALAN: Indeed.
Let's look at the results.
And guest 200 still at the lead.
But guest 752 is now
nipping at their heels.
We have two final questions.
And speed, again, does matter.
What is a cookie?
Data used to identify your computer
to websites, a delicious snack,
both of the above, or none of the above.
This is a tough one, Brian.
Especially if there's
only one right answer.
We might see a bit more of a split.
Which of these is a cookie?
All right, let's see the results.
Data used to identify your
computer to websites with 60%.
Both of the above was 35%.
Only 2% of you like cookies alone.
Brian?
BRIAN YU: Both of the above
was the correct answer.
I'll remind that all of these questions
were written originally by students
and the answer choice of students
selected as the correct one was
both of the above.
DAVID MALAN: All right.
And now the second to last leaderboard,
Guest 200 is still in the lead.
But there's been some variance
toward the bottom there.
Very last question of CS50 itself.
What's your comfort level now?
And we'll let you decide
among these answers, too.
All right.
Answers are all in.
Let's take a look at the distribution.
Looks like 43% of you said you're
among more of those more comfortable.
24% of you went with the second.
19%, very fascinating
distribution from top to bottom.
But the point is that you are all
indeed now officially inducted
into those more comfortable.
Thank you so much for
joining us in CS50.
We cannot wait to see
your final projects.
This, then, is the end.
And this was CS50.
[MUSIC PLAYING]