[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
So this CS50, and this is week
eight, the week of all Hallows' Eve.
Indeed, thanks to our friends here
in the American Repertory Theater,
the stage looks amazing today
with some special lighting
and some special characters.
Of course, speaking of
characters, this past week
you all explored 50-ville for the very
first time, looking for the rubber
duck that had gone missing.
And thankfully, the
culprits have been found,
and allow me to say that a little
someone would like to say hello.
Yes, even he has rather
dressed up for the occasion,
but thank you for all
the hard work there.
So this week, of course, we transition
to the world of web programming,
the motivation being that
for the past many weeks,
pretty much all of the
code we have written
has been focused on command line
programs, compiling your code,
interpreting your code, but generally
just interacting with a fairly
mundane blinking prompt, textually.
But of course, the software
that you and I use every day
these days is in the form of
laptops and desktops in browsers
or on mobile devices or apps,
and today, we begin to transition
to a set of languages
and a set of technologies
via which you can start to apply
all of the past week's knowledge
and mental models for
procedural programming
to a much more familiar, a
much more graphical domain.
Indeed, over the course of
the next couple of weeks,
we'll be focused on web programming
and the use of languages
called HTML and CSS and JavaScript,
with which today's websites are made,
and increasingly with which
today's mobile applications or apps
on your phone are made as well.
But in order to get to
that point in the story,
we need to consider
what the framework is
on top of which we're going to run these
websites or these web applications.
And so that invites the
question of the internet.
Exactly what is the internet?
All of us use it every day, but
let's take a couple of volunteers
from the audience, just to define
for us what we mean by the internet.
All of us are literally
on the internet right now,
but if you take a step back and
think about it, what is the internet?
How might you define it for
someone less technical than you
or someone less familiar?
Sophia, how would you define it?
AUDIENCE: The network
of all the computers
around the world that are taking
in information from the network
and also giving it information.
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
The internet is this
network of networks,
so if you have a small network
in your home, a small network
or a large network at your
company or you university
and you start to interconnect all
of those networks using cables
or some kind of wireless technology,
you get the internet, so to speak,
a network of networks.
And this is really the
infrastructure, if you will,
on top of which all of
today's applications are run.
So when you use the web, when
you use chat, when you use Slack,
when you use video conferencing, Zoom
or the like, you're using the internet,
but think of the internet really
as the lower-level plumbing that
gets the zeros and ones from
you to someone else and back,
and the applications
on top of that are all
implemented, ultimately, in software.
And so if we consider, then, that
we've got all of these computers
interconnected somehow,
it stands to reason
that we need to somehow
decide as a global community
how to get data from point
A to point B and beyond.
And so throughout the internet are
these computers called routers.
And at the end of the
day, they're probably
a little bigger than the desktops
and laptops with which you and I are
familiar, but at the
end of the day, they're
the same kinds of devices with CPUs,
Central Processing Units, the brains
inside of the computer
that do all the thinking,
RAM or memory, where all
of the values are stored,
and hard disks, where data is persisted.
And pictured here, for
instance, is an image from MIT
that depicted a few years back of what--
some of the most significant peering
points on the internet
throughout the United States.
So each of the red dots here
represents essentially one router
or one very important place
into which a lot of cables
come in and then go out and
interconnect all points of the country.
And then this story continues
well beyond the United States
these days using oceanic
cables and other wireless
or satellite technologies or the like.
So suffice it to say, there's
this mesh, this interconnection
of all of these different computers and
in turn networks throughout the world,
which is to say that there's many
different paths that data can take
to go from point A to point B. There
isn't necessarily a line between you
and Facebook.com or Stanford.edu.
Rather, there's a whole
bunch of routers--
sometimes a handful,
sometimes as many as 30--
that will relay your
data from left to right,
to up to down, or in some other
direction in order to get data from you
to the web server that
you're trying to contact
and then back to you with
the server's response.
So how does all of this work?
Well, decades ago,
humans essentially had
to get together and decide as a group
what standards they were going to use,
or more specifically, what protocols all
of these computers are going to speak.
A protocol isn't so much a language
as it is a set of conventions, right?
Back in healthier times, you and I, if
we were meeting each other in person,
might extend a hand, and if I
did this, you would immediately
know that you should probably
extend your hand too,
and we would have a physical handshake.
And that's a human protocol.
I initiate a communication
with you by extending my hand.
You acknowledge that communication
by extending your hand.
And then that interaction is complete.
So we have these human protocols.
In the world of computers,
there's similarly protocols,
but obviously it's all zeros and ones.
So if the first computer sends
this pattern of zeros and ones,
the other computer should reply with
a different set of zeros and ones.
And so these protocols
we're about to discuss just
standardize what those
patterns of zeros and ones are,
or really, what all of the
messages are going back and forth.
And two of the protocols most commonly
used to get data on the internet
from point A to point
B are called TCP/IP.
TCP and IP are two separate
protocols, but they're so often
used together that you typically
mention them in one breath, TCP/IP.
And these are acronyms you've
probably seen maybe on your Mac or PC
or somewhere on your phone settings.
And it refers to essentially
two sets of conventions
that computers use to get data
from one point to another.
So what do we mean by
data and what do we
mean by moving things
between point A and point B?
We'll just consider it as an
old-school envelope, whereby
if you wanted to send a letter
to someone else in the world,
you and I would probably reach for
a piece of paper back in the day.
We would pick up an envelope
and we would write our note
on that piece of paper, put
the paper in the envelope,
and then the most important step
after writing the actual message
would be to address the envelope.
And of course, in the real world,
you would put the recipient's address
typically in the middle of the envelope.
You might put your return address
in the top corner of the envelope,
and then maybe postage
or something like that.
But we humans have
pretty much standardized
through all of the postal
systems that kind of convention
when using envelopes.
So the metaphor here is that
the envelope and the message
therein are generally thought
of or referred to as packets,
packets of information.
And this would be the
physical incarnation
of what computers ultimately are just
going to do using zeros and ones.
So let's tease apart the
two sets of conventions
they use for actually putting
data in these envelopes,
addressing these envelopes, and sending
them out from point A to point B.
Let's consider first IP.
IP stands for Internet
Protocol, and pretty much
any Mac and PC and iPhone
and iPad and Android device
these days has been designed by
Apple or Google or someone else
to understand IP.
It's as though those companies
have written software
running on those devices that make
sure that those devices all support IP,
just like I was taught, presumably
by some human, this human convention
of shaking hands back in the day.
IP, Internet Protocol,
simply standardizes
how computers address each other.
So in our physical human world, if
you wanted to send me an envelope
for instance, you might write to
Harvard's Computer Science Department
at 33 Oxford Street, Cambridge,
Massachusetts, 02138, USA.
That is presumably a
unique postal address
that addresses the Computer
Science building on campus
so that if you drop an envelope in the
mail in California or anywhere abroad
it should eventually via some number
of hops and mail carriers and the like
make its way to that particular address.
Computers, then, have similarly unique
addresses known as IP addresses.
And so when your computer, Mac, PC,
phone, whatever, sends data from itself
to another server, the
address that it writes
on the outside of that virtual envelope
is the IP address of the remote server.
So for instance, if I were
to send a message to you,
I would figure out what
your IP address is.
I would write that IP address virtually
on the outside of this envelope.
I would probably write my own IP
address on the top left-hand corner
of this metaphorical envelope.
And then I would send
it out on the internet.
And what does that mean?
It would mean I take that envelope
and I hand it to the nearest router.
So it turns out when you're at home,
you actually have a router of your own.
It's that device that connects to your
cable modem or DSL modem or something
like that.
If you're on campus, like at
a place like Harvard or Yale,
Harvard and Yale have their own routers,
so your computer, when on campus,
just knows to hand data off to that.
And if you're at home using--
or if you're elsewhere in the world,
like in Starbucks or an airport,
similarly are there routers there.
So your computers generally know
where the closest router is,
and then router's purpose in
life is, again, to figure out,
does this packet go left,
right, up, down, so to speak,
in order to get it closer
to its destination.
But this sort of is
a chicken and an egg.
If I want to send you
a piece of information,
I need to know your IP address, but
I don't really know your IP address
until I know where you are.
So there is this other system that
you've probably seen an acronym for,
too, called DNS, Domain Name System.
And this is a technology that's
deployed throughout the internet that's
supported by Macs, PCs, and phones
these days, that just translates what
you and I would typically call domain
names, or fully qualified domain names,
from those English-like or
human-readable characters
to the corresponding
IP addresses, right?
There's a reason that companies
do not advertise their websites
as being a numeric IP address.
None of us would ever remember them.
They instead advertise
them as Microsoft.com
and Google.com and NewYorkTimes.com.
DNS is a technology that
your Mac and PC and phone
support that know when
a human types in one
of those human-readable
addresses, a domain name, DNS
converts those names
to the IP addresses.
So literally, if you type
in Harvard.edu or Yale.edu,
enter into your web
browser, your Mac or PC
quickly looks up the IP address of
that web server using the software that
came with the Mac or PC and converts
it to the corresponding IP address
and then writes, virtually, on
the outside of the envelope,
the IP address of Harvard
or Yale's web server
before sending it out on the internet.
So these are just services.
DNS is a service that your own ISP,
Internet Service Provider, provides.
When you're on campus,
it's Harvard or Yale.
When you're at Starbucks,
it's probably Starbucks.
When you're in an
airport, it's the airport.
When you're at home, it's your
own internet service provider
like Verizon or Comcast or the like.
So the world just decided to
use that technology as well.
And lastly, one other
acronym for now, TCP.
TCP, or Transmission Control
Protocol, is a solution
to a couple of problems,
one of which is that it
tends to be pretty convenient for
individual servers on the internet
to be able to do multiple things, right?
And you can-- there's lots of
things the internet can do.
The servers can host email.
They can host websites.
They can host chat servers,
video conferencing.
I mean, that's already a growing
list of features of software
that you can use on the internet,
and it would be nice, financially,
administratively, if one server
could do multiple things at once.
And indeed, they can.
So when a computer receives one of these
virtual envelopes and that computer,
that server, happens to support
multiple services, email, web, chat,
video, whatever--
it looks at the envelope for one
additional piece of information.
And that piece of information is known
as a port number, P-O-R-T number,
which is just a small integer that the
world has decided represents specific
services.
So for instance, in the
world of TCP, the world
decided years ago that our
computers should virtually
write the number 80 on these
envelopes after the IP address
to signify that this is a
request for a web page, or 443
on the outside of the envelope if
it's a secure request for a page using
something called HTTPS.
More on that in a bit.
And there's other numbers as well.
Email has its own unique numbers.
Zoom has its own unique numbers.
And all of these other internet
services that you and I
might use every day have
their own unique TCP
ports so that companies and people can
have one server doing multiple things,
but upon receipt of one of these
envelopes, the server can look at it
and be-- and realize, oh,
this is a request for email.
This is a request for a web page.
This is a request for chat,
or something else altogether.
Now, notably, too, TCP
also handles delivery,
and it's the part of the protocol that
also ensures that when you send data
from point A to point B, if any
data gets lost because literally
something's wrong with one of those
routers or because maybe the-- one
of those writers got overwhelmed and
just received more packets at once than
it can handle--
that could happen, because
these computers have,
of course, finite memory.
If you send too much data through
one, the internet might get congested,
your video might buffer, and a whole
bunch of other symptoms might arise.
So TCP also handles the process
of retransmitting data as needed.
If any of these packets
is lost on the internet,
literally TCP will also compel
your Mac or PC, your phone,
to resend that data as well.
But what's notable about the internet
is that data doesn't necessarily
follow one specific path.
In fact, if you send multiple
packets from one person to another,
those packets might actually
take different routes each time.
And this is actually a feature,
not a bug, so to speak,
because you can imagine
servers getting congested
or problems needed to getting--
needing to be routed around.
And so TCP/IP also supports,
with other protocols,
an adaptive solution to this
problem, whereby maybe your data will
go this way sometimes.
Maybe it'll go this
way some other times.
But this is why, in part, that sometimes
your internet speeds are variable,
because, again, these routers
in between might be different
or might be a little bit overloaded.
So we thought we'd try to
tell this story by enlisting
the help of some of the CS50 staff.
In fact, Brian, let me start with you.
Would you mind taking on the role in
just a moment of playing a web browser,
someone's own Mac or PC or
phone, and request of me--
maybe something silly, like
asking me for a picture of a cat?
BRIAN YU: Yeah, sure.
So if I want to ask you, some web
server, for a picture of a cat,
I need to send a message to you in
order to send that request to you.
So I might write down my
request on a sheet of paper.
And I'll just put that
request inside of an envelope.
And then I would have to label that
envelope with all the information we
talked about, in particular with your IP
address, that I might look up with DNS.
And then I can send that envelope off.
DAVID J. MALAN: All right.
And I think we need a
little bit of help here,
because Brian and I are
in different places.
And so he and I can't just hand
the envelope from one to the other.
So let's go ahead and enlist
the help of CS50 staff here,
also, who have chimed
in here on Zoom and see
if we can't route this
request from Brian,
who's playing the role
of a web browser, to me,
who will play the role
of a web server, in order
to receive this request for a cat.
So here we go.
Let's see if we can
enlist the team here.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right.
Well, thank you to Phyllis for
having handed me this envelope.
And what we have now is the
request that Brian sent me.
I'm going to go open
it up, and I, indeed,
see a message inside requesting
a picture of a cat, which
is not uncommon on the internet.
So now if I'm the web
server and I actually
have an archive of
pictures of cats, I'm going
to go ahead and respond to
Brian with one of those cats.
But to do so, I'm going to go ahead
and have to look up on my hard drive
or somewhere in the computer
that picture of a cat.
And here's one here, so I'm going to
go and send Brian this very happy cat.
I've got some envelopes
of my own, and I'm
to go ahead and write Brian's IP
address on the middle of this envelope,
I'm going to put my IP address
on the top-left of this envelope,
and then maybe any other
identifying information
I need, and then I'll go ahead
and put the cat into the envelope.
But, of course, this
isn't really going to fit.
And this is actually
quite commonly the case.
Any time a computer is trying to
transmit a decent amount of data,
whether it's a big image or maybe
it's an even bigger video file,
for equity's sake, it tends
to be good for computers
to chop up large packets into
multiple smaller packets.
In fact, you might
have heard of something
called Net Neutrality or a
more technical topic known
as Quality of Service.
In a nutshell, Net Neutrality speaks
to just what kinds of decisions
computers should make when it
comes to prioritizing data.
And a common convention is,
historically, that all of us
should chop up our large packets
into smaller packets, send them out,
so they can get then commingled
with other people's packets
and we all reach our
destinations at the same rate.
Net Neutrality, as an aside,
is all about an interest
by some parties in prioritizing maybe
the data from certain companies that
pay a bit more.
And so this really speaks to just use
or maybe abuse of these basic primitives
here.
But this is not fair for
me to try to cram this one
big image into an envelope,
so I'm going to literally go
ahead and tear the picture in half,
essentially chop the packet into two.
Let me go ahead now and
put this into the envelope,
because it'll fit a little more easily.
So I've got one packet
of information for Brian.
I've got now-- let's see-- one more
packet of information for Brian
that I'll fit the other
half of this image into.
But I think I'm going to
have to do something else.
Before I drop this out on the
internet and hand it back to Phyllis
to send out back to Brian, I might
need some additional information
on these envelopes.
I've already got Brian's
IP in the To field.
I've got my IP address
in the From field.
I've also jotted down
the port number that I
should use for Brian and
my own return port number.
And those are decided
typically by my Mac or PC.
But I feel like I probably
need a little more information.
What more should I virtually write
on the outside of this envelope
to make sure that the data
is received as intended?
Any intuition?
No familiarity with TCP/IP assumed here.
But if Brian's about to now get
two envelopes, what additional data
should I perhaps give him? [? Greg? ?]
AUDIENCE: Brian may confuse the
top of the photo with the bottom,
so you need somehow to tell Brian that
this is a top and this is a bottom,
a link maybe to converge them.
DAVID J. MALAN: Perfect.
And so we need to make
sure Brian knows the order
in which these packets should be
reassembled so that he, indeed,
gets the cat the right way and
not the wrong way, for instance.
So what probably
suffices is for me to add
what we'll call a sequence number
to each of these packets, which
is essentially a number which
you can think of as one of two,
and on the other one, two of
two, so that Brian knows when--
what order to reassemble the
packets, but also more importantly,
in case one of the
packets, or both of them,
gets lost or somehow dropped by
one of the routers along the way,
there's enough information
on those packets
to enable me and him to recover that and
resend packet one and/or two as needed.
So let's go ahead and do this.
Let me go ahead and enlist the help of
the team, starting with Phyllis here.
And Phyllis, if you'd like
to go ahead here and--
[MUSIC PLAYING]
All right.
Of course, that's only
half of the problem.
So I'm to go ahead now and send
the second packet, finally.
In an ideal world, I would actually
send these out in parallel,
but there's no reason that they
couldn't still follow different paths.
In fact, this one I worry might
take a little bit more time.
Let's see.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[SINGING IN ITALIAN]
Amazing.
Brian, do you want to go ahead and open
up your envelopes and reassemble them?
BRIAN YU: Yes.
I have two envelopes.
I guess I'll open up the one
that says one of two first,
and it is the top half of the cat.
And then I'll open up the other
envelope, which is two of two.
And that is the bottom half of the cat.
And so together, I think
I now have the full cat.
DAVID J. MALAN: Wonderful.
Well, thank you to Brian
and to the whole team.
And so to recap, IP is
this protocol, the set
of conventions that standardizes
what gets written on these envelopes.
It's how computers uniquely address
each other with numbers of some sort.
TCP governs a few different
things, but among them
is this numbering of services,
like 80 for insecure web traffic
or 443 for secure web
traffic that ensures
that the data gets from
one point to another
and is handled by the right application
running on that particular server.
DNS, then, is what we use to begin with.
If Brian had his own
domain name, my computer
would have had to look
up his IP address,
or conversely, he would
have had to look up mine,
so that we humans,
who are actually using
the internet in a
human-friendly way, don't
have to remember IP addresses, which,
again, are just numbers, but instead
can remember things like
Harvard.edu, Yale.edu, and the like.
So that, then, is the internet,
the fundamental infrastructure,
the plumbing on top of which we now have
the ability to get data from point A
to point B. And so in some sense,
if you're comfortable with that,
we can now abstract the
internet away and just
think of it as being a mechanism that
gets data from one point to another.
And so long as we can now assume that
we have this fundamental public service
that gets data from
one point to another,
now we can start to build
on top of it in terms
of software and other languages and
actually use it for interesting things.
But before we forge ahead to do those
things, any questions or confusion
we can clear up on TCP or IP or DNS
or the internet or routers or any
of these other new terms?
[? Greg, ?] back to you.
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
So does chopping the
information create any problem?
Because, I don't know,
a piece of information
can go there for two seconds and
another one for three seconds.
Does it create any problem for the user?
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
These packets can take
different durations of time,
and even though I did stipulate that
they should go out to Phyllis's hands
roughly at the same
time, even if she needs
to pass them in two
different directions,
there can absolutely be delays.
And in fact, typically,
you and I as humans
will start to notice delays if packets
take more than 200 milliseconds
to get from point A to
point B. After that,
it looks like there's a
bit of delay, and certainly
if it's two or three seconds, you'll
really notice that at that point,
it's not necessarily a problem--
Brian hopefully would patiently
wait for the second half
of the cat for some amount of time
if he only received one packet.
Eventually, he as a human,
and in turn, he as a computer,
would probably get a
little anxious and would
ask me to retransmit a packet if it
doesn't arrive after 5 seconds, 10
seconds, 30 seconds.
These time outs can
typically be specified
by the software running on the
person's computer, but at that point,
you and I would certainly
notice the difference.
All right.
So if we now have this ability
fundamentally to get data from point A
to point B, what is actually inside
of the envelope that Brian sent me,
and what was inside the envelope I sent
him besides just the picture of a cat?
Well, for that, we transition to another
language or another protocol, rather,
called HTTP, HyperText
Transfer Protocol.
And this is an acronym you've probably
seen or typed bunches of times.
It's, of course, what appears in the
beginning of URLs, Uniform Resource
Locators, which are the tools that
you and I use to actually figure out
what websites or what image we actually
want to request of the internet.
So the web, the world-wide web, is
really just one of many services
that run on top of the internet.
The web gives us web pages.
Zoom gives us video conferencing.
Other tools give us text chatting,
voice chatting, and the like.
So the web is really just an
application on top of the internet.
It's hands-down the most
popular application,
but it really is just an application.
It's a service that's using
that underlying plumbing.
So HTTP is a different
protocol that really governs
what goes inside of these envelopes.
TCP/IP governs what goes
outside the envelopes.
HTTP governs what goes inside
of the envelopes, assuming we
are talking about web browsers and
web servers and not video conferencing
or something else.
So with HTTP, it comes with a few
different commands, or a pretty limited
vocabulary, two of which are the
most important terms to know,
which is GET and POST.
These are literally
English verbs, and they
are two of the commands, if
you will, that HTTP supports.
And what Brian probably did
inside of that envelope is
he probably literally wrote down
GET cat or something like that.
POST is used for other applications
that we'll get to before long,
but "GET" is the operative word.
And it literally is how a browser
will request or get information
from a server.
So somewhere in the
envelope Brian sent me
was the English word "GET," probably
followed by cat.jpg or something
like that.
There's probably a bit more
information, but the essence of HTTP
means that if Brian wants something
from me and he's the browser
and I'm the server, he should start
his request with the standardized verb
"GET" followed by the name of
the file that he wants to get.
So let's put this now into the context
of one of the more familiar URLs.
So here's, for instance, a
canonical format of a URL.
And let's highlight
a few features of it.
So first, HTTPS.
Increasingly, you're
seeing this on the web.
Even if you don't type it, it's
often automatically appearing
in the address bar of your
browser, because browsers or web
servers are adding it for you.
The S just refers to a
secure version of HTTP.
And we'll come back to this topic of
security next week and beyond, too.
But in the context of HTTP, this
just means that the data between me
and Brian and vice versa
is encrypted somehow.
It's way better than
Caesar or other ciphers.
It's way more mathematically
sophisticated.
But it essentially just
scrambles the information
so that Brian knows he's asking
for a cat, I, the web server,
knows he's asking for a cat, but
if any of you or any of the TFs
who were playing the role of
routers maliciously or nosily
opened the envelope instead of handing
it off to the next staff member,
they wouldn't understand
what's inside the envelope,
because it would look like, similar
to Caesar and other ciphers,
sort of like random zeros and ones.
So HTTPS just means that the contents
of these packets are encrypted.
What else is salient about these URLs?
Well, here's what we call a domain name.
Odds are most everyone
knows what a domain name is,
and it's typically two phrases,
something dot something else.
And example.com is,
of course, an example
here, but Harvard.edu, Yale.edu,
and millions of others these days.
To the end of that, though,
is what we would typically
call the top-level domain or TLD.
This is just the type of
website, historically,
that you're trying to visit.
Dot com meant commercial.
Dot edu meant education.
Dot net meant some kind of network.
Dot org is an organization.
That's no longer really the case.
In fact, there's hundreds, perhaps
even thousands, of top-level domains
nowadays that you can
buy domains in that
try to categorize things sometimes,
but there's no hard rules
around most of those top-level domains.
You have to be an accredited
educational institution to use dot edu.
You have to be in the US
military to use dot mil.
There are similar constraints
in other countries
who have their own
two-character country code TLDs,
like dot UK for the United Kingdom,
dot JP for Japan, and many others.
Each country is free to
standardize as it sees fit.
But you and I can buy a dot
com, a dot org, a dot net, a dot
us, a dot-- there's
many, many, many others.
And if you go on Wikipedia you
can see a nearly exhaustive list.
But this just tends to categorize
the type of website that it is.
Besides that, there's this prefix,
this, generally known as a hostname.
And www is just a human convention.
Years ago, pretty much
any server on the internet
that had a human-friendly name
like this, www.example.com,
this was just meant
to connote to the user
that, oh, www, this must be
the address of a web server
and not a mail server not a
chat server or something else.
It's not strictly required.
It's just human convention.
And odds are, you and I,
when you visit websites,
you probably don't even
bother typing this in anymore.
But it is a historical feature that
allows a visual cue-- clue, typically,
to the humans as to what
type of server it is.
So besides that, there's this one
hidden piece of information as well.
If you just want to visit example.com's
homepage, you might just type this URL,
or even just type example.com
and hit Enter and let
the browser redirect you,
so to speak-- take you
to this canonical form of the URL.
But very often, you're technically
requesting a specific file.
And if not mentioned, that file
name is typically index.html.
It can be other things as well
depending on the language or the server
technology that someone's using.
But implicit at the end of URLs
is often the name of a file.
Brian might have specifically
requested cat.jpg,
but if he were requesting
not a picture of a cat
but a full-fledged web page with
text and other information, odds are,
there's an implicit file
name there, like index.html.
And this is now important, because
when we look inside this envelope,
this is a piece of information
that needs to then be in there.
So let's take a look at some
sample HTTP requests and responses,
the more technical dive into
what Brian and I and the staff
acted out a moment ago.
Technically speaking, when Brian
sent me a request for that cat,
he wrote inside this envelope, not only
the key word GET and something like
a cat.jpg--
he also specified a
couple of other things.
And let's genericize it now away
from cats and just propose this.
Inside of an HTTP request that is any
of these virtual envelopes is literally
a request for, like, GET followed
by slash, if you don't want to cat,
you just want the default
homepage, followed
by a mention of what version of HTTP
the browser and server should speak.
1.1 is pretty common.
2 is pretty-- is increasingly common.
3 is even now out there.
But there's just different
versions of the protocol.
It's like humans have refined
what it means to shake hands.
These versions of
protocols evolve over time.
But there's also a line like
this, Host colon www.example.com,
because-- just in case I am a
particularly fancy server that
supports not only example.com but
maybe Harvard.edu and Yale.edu.
It's possible, long story
short, for companies nowadays
to host multiple websites and
multiple domains on the same server.
This little clue inside
the envelope makes sure
that it goes to example.com
or Harvard.edu or Yale.edu
if all of these entities are
sharing the same physical server.
So more specifically, a request
might look-- instead look like this.
If you're not just requesting
the default homepage but you want
a specific file, it might
say /index.html instead.
What does my response look like?
So I've gotten Brian's envelope.
Now I'm going to go ahead and
respond with my own one or two
or more envelopes.
Inside of mine, yes, is going
to go pieces of that cat,
but some additional information
as well, per the protocol.
So my response-- just like in the
human world, I might extend my hand,
if I see Brian initiating a handshake.
I'm going to respond with
something like this, HTTP/1.1,
which just reminds the browser what
version I'm speaking, then a number,
which is the status code, followed
by a shorthand summary, like OK.
200 OK means I got you.
I found the cat.
Here it comes, piece by
piece, in these envelopes.
And I also put it in the envelope
a mention of the content type.
If it's a web page, I'm
going to put text/html.
If it's a jpg, I might
instead say image/jpg.
And there's the different content
types, otherwise known as line types,
for all different file
formats in the world.
Well, that's not always going to
be the case, that the response is
as simple as that, whereby your browser
requests information and the server
responds with the requested information.
Sometimes the users make
their way to the wrong place.
So for instance, suppose that a
browser visits www.Harvard.edu,
the response might not
necessarily be OK initially.
It might not be status code 200.
And in fact, we can see this.
Let me go ahead and open up
on my screen here a browser
window that's going to take
me to, let's say, Harvard.edu.
And I'm going to go ahead and type in
to the URL bar http://www.Harvard.edu,
Enter.
Now, all this happened
pretty quickly, but if I
click on the URL bar, which has
been simplified or shortened
by Chrome at the moment, notice
where I actually ended up.
Somehow or other, my browser
did not keep me at HTTP.
It redirected me, so to speak, to HTTPS.
This is probably intentional
on Harvard's part.
They would rather that
I'd be visiting them
securely so that if I'm reading
articles or other content,
that's really nobody's business
except mine and Harvard.
Certainly no one-- no routers in
between should be able to see this.
So somehow, Harvard redirected
me from HTTP to HTTPS.
Well, how can I see this?
Well, it turns out, embedded in Chrome
and Edge and Firefox and Safari--
all of today's browsers--
there are often developer
tools that sometimes you
have to enable via a certain menu--
but these developer
tools are so powerful
and they allow you, the user,
or now you, the programmer,
to actually see and
understand what's going
on underneath the hood of
these browsers and servers.
So I'm going to do this
in Chrome, specifically.
I'm going to go to View,
Developer, and then I'm
going to go to Developer Tools.
And odds are if you're a Chrome User,
this menu option has always been there,
even if you never noticed it.
So feel free to play along at home.
And then notice this pops
up on the top right here.
I'm going to go ahead and
move it down to the bottom
just by clicking the dot, dot,
dot menu and move the developer
tools to the bottom of my screen, just
so we can see things a little wider.
And I'm going to go ahead and
click on the Network tab up here.
And when I click on
the Network tab here,
I'm going to see a whole bunch of
information related to my last request,
so I'm going to go ahead
and do this request again.
Let me go ahead and
go back to the URL bar
and let me go ahead and--
actually, just for good measure,
let me do this in Incognito mode.
And even though you
perhaps are in the habit
of using Incognito mode if
you don't want the browser
to remember where you've been or what
you've logged in as-- and Incognito
mode is incredibly powerful
for developers tool
so that you can reset the browser
state to a first condition
without any previous network
browsing showing up in your history.
So I'm going to do this
again now in Incognito
mode after having
opened developer tools.
http://www.Harvard.edu, Enter.
And a whole bunch of stuff just
flew by the window, some of which
is this chart information,
which shows me the performance.
So to [? Greg, ?] your question earlier
about noticing the amount of time,
you can see that some of the
requests that were just induced
vary between a few milliseconds
and over 1,000 milliseconds.
But what I care about for now is
this fairly arcane listing down here.
A whole lot of stuff just
flew across the screen,
and indeed, if I zoom in on the
bottom, simply visiting Harvard.edu
induces 70 HTTP requests per this
mention in the bottom left-hand corner.
It resulted in 6.8 megabytes of
information being transferred.
And in total, it took a-- rather
atrociously, 11.95 seconds.
So [? Greg, ?] like, that is
slow, relatively speaking.
Well, absolutely speaking.
So what's the takeaway here?
Well, any time you visit
a web page, there's
not just the one web page itself
with all of the text in it.
There's probably images, maybe
videos, maybe music and other things.
All of those get downloaded separately.
So if Brian had asked me for a full web
page, like the course's home website,
I might respond not with a
single envelope or two envelopes.
I might respond with 70 envelopes
containing the responses to every piece
of media that composes CS50's own
website, or in this case, Harvard's.
But for now, let's focus only
on the first of these requests.
If I look at the first
row here in Chrome,
I will see a reminder of
where I visited first.
But notice the Status
column over here is 301.
301 Moved Permanently.
It turns out that there's
numbers besides 200
that tell browsers what to do.
200 just means OK, here's
the data we requested.
301 means, nn-nn, whatever you
requested has moved permanently
to a different URL.
So let me go ahead and
click this first row
and you'll see that a whole
different set of tabs pops up.
I'm going to click Headers here.
And now let me define a term.
When Brian and I are using HTTP
inside of these envelopes and I write
something like GET slash HTTP/1.1
or host colon www.example.com,
each of those lines of text is
what we'll call an HTTP header.
It's a line of text
inside of the envelope.
So what we're seeing
here is Chrome's summary
of all of the headers that
were inside of these envelopes.
Let me go ahead and look at
my request headers first.
I'm going to click View Source.
And I can literally see the raw
request that my browser sent
to www.Harvard.edu, GET slash
HTTP/1.1, Host colon www.Harvard.edu,
and then a bunch of other stuff
which we'll ignore for now.
But those are all HTTP headers.
But if I scroll back up here,
let's look at the response
headers now, what came back
in a different envelope
from Harvard to my laptop.
Notice here that it's HTTP 1.1, but it's
not 200 OK, it's 301 Moved Permanently.
This is a hint to my
browser that, uh-uh,
there's nothing at the URL you visited.
You need to visit a
different location instead.
To know where I need to go, I need to
scroll down and find this header here.
Notice that the third line in
the response is Location colon
https://www.Harvard.edu.
So this is how the envelope that comes
back contains a clue to me to say,
nn-nn, we have moved permanently to
the secure version of the website.
And if I zoom out now and click
this little X to close those tabs,
you'll see that the next request that
my browser automatically sent on its own
was to instead, if I scroll
down here, to this request URL,
https://www.Harvard.edu,
and the response I
got this time under this general
summary here was now indeed 200.
So this is just a simple mechanism
that allows a browser and a server
to intercommunicate in a way that can
send them from one location to another.
And let me make this a
little more familiar.
Odds are you have seen not this before,
explicitly, because you, as a human,
would rarely, if ever, see the
number 301 or Moved Permanently
until today, now that
you're a programmer who's
using these developer tools, but
odds are you've seen another number.
Maybe in the chat if
you want to just chime
in, if you're thinking about web
pages and numbers, has anyone seen--
quite often, probably, a number that
maybe now makes a little more sense?
Brian, what are you seeing?
BRIAN YU: A lot of people saying 404.
I also saw 500 and a 502.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, so 404 is
the code that humans adopted years
ago that just signifies Not Found.
So if you visit an incorrect URL
or an old URL that no longer exists
on a server, for maybe an
old cat that's been deleted,
the server will respond not with
200 OK but with 404 Not Found,
thereby telling your browser to
display some kind of error message.
Weirdly, browsers years ago
weren't especially user friendly,
and then browsers just
told us humans 404, 404,
which frankly, is not
very user friendly.
But all it boils down to is this
little hint inside of the response
envelope coming back that indicates
that something went wrong,
that something was not found.
And there's a whole list
of these status codes,
and this is certainly not
something you need to memorize,
but as we focus more and
more on web programming,
you'll just get naturally
familiar with some of these.
There's other ways of redirecting
the user from one place to another.
302 and 307 can be used.
For efficiency, servers
can sometimes respond
with 304, which essentially means,
you already asked me that question.
The cat has not changed on the server.
Use your own copy of the cat.
So long story short, if Brian's own
browser were smart, it would cache--
C-A-C-H-E-- that is, remember the cat
that he just downloaded from me so that
if Brian hits reload or he comes back
to that same website again and wants
to see the cat again, it just-- his
browser loads the local copy instead
of bothering me, the web server,
and wasting time, milliseconds,
sending another cat.
304 would just say, the cat is the same.
Use your own local copy.
Then there's others.
You might have seen 401
or 403 before, which
refer to not being logged in
correctly or something like that.
500 is actually bad.
And in fact, I can pretty much guarantee
that over the next couple of weeks,
all of you will experience your very
first of several HTTP 500 errors.
That's going to be next week that
you screwed up with your code
and you actually wrote buggy Python code
that just meant the whole server didn't
know what to do.
And that's an internal server error.
Fixable, and will help you debug it,
but indeed, that's quite common as well.
503 just means the server
might be overloaded in some way
and so service is unavailable, and
there's others, dot, dot, dot, as well.
So we can actually have
a little bit of fun
with this in a couple
of different directions.
It turns out that if we
send this HTTP request,
we can take a look at what comes back.
And let me go ahead and do this.
Instead of using my browser,
I'm going to use a command line
tool which tends to just be a little
cleaner, because I don't have to futz
around with all of these buttons.
Let me go ahead and use
a program called Curl.
And Curl's purpose in life
is just to connect to a URL.
And it's not going to bother showing
me the web page or any of the content.
It's just going to show me the HTTP
headers if I use a command line
argument of dash capital I.
And now I'm going to go ahead
and http://safetyschool.org.
And I'm going to go ahead and Enter.
And this is my Mac now
sending one envelope
to safetyschool.org containing GET,
that verb, requesting the home page.
They are presumably going to respond
to me with another envelope inside
of which is some kind of response.
Maybe it's a 200.
Maybe it's something else.
[CHUCKLES] All right.
It looks like-- forgive me--
that safetyschool.org has moved
permanently, per this 301,
to this new location www.Yale.edu.
sorry.
And in fact, we can do this.
If I copy this URL--
and let me go into a browser.
I'll use Incognito again so that
I don't have any past history.
I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
And voila, the visual effect is just
as real as the headers would imply.
So indeed, the funny thing about this
joke is that someone on the internet
has been paying for the domain
name safetyschool.org for, like,
20 years now for this joke,
and the only thing it does
is redirect one domain name to another.
Now, fair is fair.
Let me go ahead and transition
away from safetyschool.org
or to harvardsucks.org, which also
exists, and someone on the other side
has been hosting this
website for some time.
And in fact, if you visit that URL--
let's go to harvardsucks.org, Enter.
You'll actually see a whole website.
So the Yalies really went all-out here.
And you can actually
see an amazing hack here
whereby at harvardsucks.org there's an
old YouTube video of an amazing hack
or prank that was pulled at one
of the Harvard-Yale football games
some years ago where Yale, to their
credit, tricked us into spelling out,
with a bitmap, if-- of
all things, we suck.
So fair's fair.
So in anyhow, bit of a
stretch to connect those
to underlying HTTP messages,
but it all, indeed,
relates to these very simple primitives.
Let me point out one
other thing as well.
We might also see in the
form of HTTP requests
even more sophisticated first
lines where you're not requesting
just slash, the default homepage.
You're not requesting
/cat.jpg or /index.html.
There might also be question
marks and equal signs.
And notice, this is an excerpt from
an envelope my Mac or PC or phone
might send to google.com
requesting pictures of cats.
And in fact, let me go ahead
and do this on my browser.
Let me go to HTTPS--
I'm not going to bother using
the insecure version at all.
I'm going to go explicitly
to google.com/search?q=cats.
So this is the human version
of the URL that my Mac
will translate into this
lower-level message that's
going to be shoved inside
of the virtual envelope.
So I'm going to go ahead and hit Enter.
And voila, I now see,
indeed, a whole bunch
of pictures of cats, including some
more horrific photos from a movie that
didn't fare well as well.
So that is to say that it seems that
once you understand URL formats,
you can begin to pass input to servers.
And here's now where we bridge
past weeks to future weeks.
Thus far, when we visited web pages like
Harvard.edu and Yale.edu and the like,
we're just visiting static web content.
We're not actually providing
user input like you
would using GET string or input or
any kinds of command line programs
we've written.
But it turns out that you
URLs do support user input,
and they are standardized.
If you see a question mark and
then the name of a variable like q
and then an equal sign
and then a word like
"cat," that's the web-based analog of
a command line program having asked you
what is the value of q, and
the human typing in cats.
So this is to say there is a way
using URLs that will actually
allow us to pass input to a web server.
And indeed, that's what's happening
when you're visiting google.com,
but it just boils down to
understanding these URLs.
And before we begin to build
some of our own solutions
on top of this infrastructure, any
questions now or confusion on HTTP
or status codes or anything
we've seen thus far?
Anything at all?
Yeah, over to Santiago.
AUDIENCE: When you want to, for
example, publish a web page,
why is it that you have
to buy a domain name?
Is that because you're
using memory in some server?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah, that's
a really good question.
Why do you have to buy a domain name?
It kind of boils down to
capitalism, to be honest.
There is a non-zero cost
to running certain aspects
of the internet, certainly, or
really all aspects of the internet.
There are some nonprofit
and volunteers--
non-profit organizations and volunteers
that have historically helped
govern it.
Increasingly, though, there's overhead
to operationalizing the internet,
running things like the main
DNS servers and other features.
And so there are what are
called internet registrars, much
like a university registrar,
whose purpose in life
is to allow people to essentially
rent domain names on an annual basis.
And indeed, when you buy a domain
name, it's not yours permanently.
Instead, you're paying
a yearly fee once--
a renewal fee every one or two
or three years or the like.
It might range from a couple
of dollars to hundreds
or even thousands of dollars.
We can go down the rabbit hole talking
about domain name squatting, whereby
if you think of a really cool word and
you buy the domain name and someone
else comes along and wants
it, there's capitalism at play
there, potentially an
opportunity for you
to sell a domain name to someone else.
But in part, it helps just
regulate exactly who can sign up
for domain names and presumably
put some downward pressure
on all of them just disappearing if you
could just sign up for free for as many
as you want.
Other questions or
clarifications on not just
HTTP but also TCP, IP, DNS, or anything
else from today's alphabet soup?
BRIAN YU: A question came in the chat.
If you have multiple packets that
you're trying to send from one place
to the other, do they have to
be sent out one after the other,
or can you send all of the
packets out at the same time?
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
We did not think that we humans could do
that very well choreographically using
Zoom a bit ago, so we sent one packet
a time through the teaching fellows.
But yes, a computer would
typically dump all of those packets
out at the same time.
They would be serialized
one after the other,
but it would happen very quickly.
And by chance, they might
all follow the same route
through the teaching
fellows as routers, or they
might go in different directions
depending on just how congested
or how busy the internet
is at that moment in time.
They might arrive out of
order, but indeed, that's
why Brian needs to know
what the sequence number is
on the outside of the envelope so he
can rearrange them in the correct order.
Anything else on your end, Brian?
BRIAN YU: How do the
rooters know which way
to send any particular packet of data?
DAVID J. MALAN: Really good question.
How do the routers know?
So back in the day-- and in some
cases, it's literally hardcoded.
You can think of a router as having
essentially an Excel spreadsheet
in its memory with at least
two columns, one of which
is an IP address, the other of which
is the direction it should go out on,
like right, left, up and down.
Like, the cables aren't going in
four different directions, certainly,
but you can think of it in--
metaphorically, in that way.
It tells the router that if you
receive data for this IP address,
send it out on this cable, or
if it's for this IP address,
send it out on that cable.
And all of these cables are
connected to other routers
in the same city, in different
cities, across an ocean,
to some other endpoint.
That would be very
painful, though, if humans
had to manually configure
all of the interconnections
we saw on MIT's map just a bit ago.
And so it turns out
there's other protocols
out there that we won't
spend time on in this class,
but that routers rely on in
order to dynamically adapt.
So long story short,
there are protocols that
will figure out if all
of a sudden my packets
are not getting through
to Brian, I'm going
to start routing around
that, dynamically,
and the routers are going
to figure out, that does not
seem to be a good destination
because I'm not getting any response,
or it's just taking way
too long to hear back.
So there are protocols
that govern how you
can decide whether to start dynamically
changing those so-called routing
tables, the spreadsheet to
which I referred earlier.
All right, so we have now, at this
point, an infrastructure known
as the internet that allows us to send
packets of information from point A
to point B by writing
addresses and port numbers
on the outside of those envelopes.
We have another protocol called
HTTP which is specifically
used for web browsers and web servers,
separate from videoconferencing
and chat, which have their own
set of conventions and protocols,
but we have a mechanism for get--
requesting information and
responding with information.
And we know from problem set 4
how you can respond with a cat.
It's just a sequence
of bits, whether it's
a bitmap or a jpg or something
else, but we haven't yet
seen what an actual page looks like.
And indeed, if we look a
little deeper in the envelope
that I'm sending to Brian
and he's sending to me
and we're getting back from Harvard
and we're getting back from Yale,
we're going to see another
language altogether.
It's not a programming language, per se.
It's what's known as a
markup language, which
just means it's more about
aesthetics than it is about logic.
And there's going to be a couple of
other languages tucked in there, CSS,
Cascading Style Sheets, JavaScript,
which is a proper programming language.
But let's go ahead and take
a five-minute break here.
And when we come back, we'll learn
to make web pages themselves.
All right.
So when you visit a website requesting
the home page or a specific file
on the website, exactly what is
inside of the virtual envelope
a little deeper down
below the HTTP headers
that you get back from the server?
Well, that language is known
as HTML, HyperText Markup
Language, which indeed
is not a programming
language, which means there's no loops.
There's no conditions.
There's no functions
or variables per se.
It's just text that tells a browser
fairly pedantically, top to bottom,
left to right, what to display and how.
So let's take a look at some examples.
An HTML page is going to contain really
two different concepts inside of it,
what we'll call tags or
elements, and also attributes.
Well, what are those?
Well, here is perhaps the
simplest web page we can make.
And this is HTML itself.
And you'll see that it's structured
in kind of a symmetric way.
Some things are indented like in
a proper programming language,
but there is some symmetry
to what's going on here.
So let's tease apart top to bottom
exactly what we're looking at here.
This very first line is known
as a document type declaration.
Long story short, whenever
making a modern web page,
this should just be the very first
line of your file, no matter what.
It signifies that you and
I are using the latest
version of HTML, which is version 5.
In the future, this line will probably
change as HTML itself, the language,
evolves as humans add more
and more features to it.
Below that, notice, is a pair of
what we're going to call tags.
Tags are things between open brackets
that start with a word like HTML
or some succinct phrase
like that, optionally
with something like this
word and an equal sign
and maybe something
in quotes after that.
But highlighted in yellow here
is the first of our HTML tags.
And coincidentally, this
tag is the HTML tag.
And the way it works is as follows.
When a browser receives an
envelope containing text like this,
it first reads that first line and says
OK, this file contains HTML version 5.
What comes after it?
Oh, here is the content of the web page.
It says, hey, browser,
here comes some HTML.
Notice down here is the
opposite of that statement.
When you get to the end of this file,
you'll see a similar-looking tag,
but there's a forward slash
front of the same word, HTML.
That's what we'll call a close tag
if we think of this as an open tag.
Or if you think of this as a
start tag, this is an end tag.
And most tags indeed have that symmetry
whereby when you open them once,
you should eventually close them,
ideally in the appropriate order.
Notice that you don't have
to repeat other stuff.
When you close a tag, you
just mentioned the name
of the tag to keep it fairly succinct.
And that means, hey, browser,
that's it for the HTML.
All right, what's inside of that?
If we look down below this, you'll
see that there's this thing here,
which is what's going to
be called an attribute.
Attributes tend to be
short, succinct phrases that
have some special meaning
for that particular tag.
This particular attribute, if you read
the documentation for the language
HTML, will say that if you add
lang= quote-unquote "something"
to your HTML tag, that's going to be
a clue to the browser that says, hey,
browser, here comes
HTML, and by the way,
the contents of this web page
are going to be in English,
at least in this case,
by default, for en.
Every language in the world has its
own two-digit or three-digit-- three
character-- two-character
or three-character code
that can be placed inside these
quotes that will standardize exactly
what the browser interprets it as.
Useful these days if you have
translation enabled in your browser.
It knows what language
the page is written in so
that it can help you translate
it to your own spoken language.
All right, below that,
there's two sets--
two pairs of tags, the head
tag here and the body tag here.
And I've highlighted them
both at the same time,
because you can think of these
as both children of the HTML tag.
So if we borrow our metaphor of a family
tree and some kind of hierarchy here.
If you think of the HTML tag as
being like the parent, so to speak,
this parent has two children, a head
tag and a body tag, each of which
is respectively opened and closed.
Let's consider the
first one, the head tag.
What's inside of that, so to speak?
Inside of that is the title tag
which as you might guess by now
is going to represent the title
of the web page we're writing.
Specifically, the title of this
web page is going to be literally--
and just goofily--
hello comma title.
So that's what you would
see in the tab of this page.
Let's back up a little bit and look now
with the second child of the HTML tag,
the so-called body tag.
This is going to be the big,
rectangular region of the web page,
otherwise known as the body or viewport.
And here, we see that the contents of
that rectangular region of the page
is going to be literally
hello comma body.
So that is to say this is the HTML for
a fairly simplistic page whose title bar
in the tab is hello
comma title and whose
body in the big rectangular region
is quite simply hello comma body.
And it's perhaps helpful
now to call out explicitly
that we can think of this, a la
week 5, as really a data structure.
Even though it's just text inside
of that envelope that gets read top
to bottom, left to right,
what the browser is actually
going to do on your
laptop or desktop or phone
is actually build a data
structure in memory.
So Microsoft, who wrote
Edge, or Google, who
wrote Chrome, or Apple
who wrote Safari, wrote
code that reads HTML top to bottom,
left to right, like a big, long string,
parses it-- that is, analyzes it-- and
builds up into the computer's memory
a tree-like data structure like
this, much like for problem set 5,
you built up your own hash table
in memory for what was otherwise
just a big text file of words.
So you can see the hierarchy here.
If you think of the whole file
as being a so-called document,
we'll draw a node, so to
speak, in this tree here.
The very first and only child
of that is the HTML tag.
Indeed, every page has to
start with that HTML tag.
It has two children, as I proposed,
head and body respectively.
And then head has a title child,
and that has a child itself,
which is just text.
And just to be a little nit-picky,
I've deliberately drawn these nodes
in slightly different shapes just
to connote that HTML, head, title,
and body are indeed all
tags, opened and closed.
These ovals here are just text.
Those are not inside of--
those are not tags themselves.
That's just raw text here and here.
And then the document node
is the one random one.
This is the only thing that's going
to start with an exclamation point,
typically, unless you have
what we'll call comments
in HTML, which are just notes to
self that we saw in C and in Python.
There's similar syntax for those.
All right.
With that said, if this is the
simplest web page we can make,
where do we make it?
How do we make it?
So you could certainly
just open up your Mac or PC
and open up something like
Text Edit or Notepad.exe
and type this out, copy and
paste it, save the file,
and open it in your browser.
But that's not that
interesting, because if you just
save an HTML file on
your Mac or PC, you are
going to be literally the only
one in the world who can visit it.
So ideally, you want a server
on which you can write and save
your HTML so that other people,
your users, your customers,
can visit the file via the internet.
Now, thankfully, we all
have access to a tool
already called CS50 IDE, which itself
is a web-based tool for writing code,
and the code we'll start writing
now just happens to be in HTML.
So let me go ahead and do that.
Let me go ahead and open up a new file.
I'll go ahead and call
this, say, hello.html,
dot html being the conventional file
extension, and let me just go ahead
and retype.
That so !DOCTYPE HTML says, hey,
browser, here comes version five.
html lang="en".
And now notice what the
IDE is doing for me.
For better or for worse,
depending on your preferences,
it's going to try to complete your
thoughts for you so you can just
type less.
This is increasingly a feature of IDEs,
Integrated Development Environments,
because now I can type
roughly half as much.
Now, I'm going to go ahead
and open the head of the page.
Notice it got automatically closed.
I'm going to go ahead and
open the title of the page.
That will automatically close as well.
And let me go ahead and just
do something like hello, title.
And then down here, outside of
the head tag, I'll do my body tag
and do hello comma body.
Now, strictly speaking, this
indentation is not necessary.
If I wanted to be a little more
terse and not use this many lines,
this is totally reasonable as well.
And it's probably
reasonable up to a point.
If I had a crazy long title, I probably
should move it to a line of its own.
But again, these details are not
going to matter to the computer,
to the browser reading
this, but they certainly
make it prettier and
easier for me, the human,
and presumably you to read as well.
So I've gone ahead and saved this file.
And in the past, I would
have used like make for C
or would have used python for
Python, but neither of those
is applicable, because we're
not writing or running code.
I now want to visit this web page.
And how do I do that?
Well, I need a browser,
and I'm all set there.
Obviously, I can use Chrome,
Safari, whatever on my own Mac.
But I also need a server.
And it turns out that CS50 IDE,
insofar as it is already a web
server that we use to write code,
we can use it as a web server
to serve our HTML as well.
So a little bit ago, when I
played the role of a web server,
I need to essentially
implement in the IDE
that same notion, of
some program that's just
going to listen and listen and
listen, like I was waiting for Brian,
and any time I get an HTTP
request from anyone's browser,
I'm going to respond with
the appropriate file.
Now, we're not going to
implement a web server ourselves.
Web servers are kind of
commodity these days.
Anyone can just download
or pay for one and use one.
And indeed, the IDE comes with one
quite simply called http-server.
So this is a program
preinstalled in the IDE.
It's free and open source.
You can use it on Linux
or Macs or PCs as well.
But it's preinstalled in the IDE.
And when I run it, what it's
going to do for me is start,
curiously, a second web server.
Because the IDE itself is already
running on CS50's own web server,
I need to now run my own server.
But in order to distinguish
one from the other,
I'm just going to use a different port.
And by default, the port that the
CS50 IDE uses is this one 8080.
So again, by default, most
web servers in the world
use port 80 if insecure
and port 443 if secure.
But those are, unfortunately,
already used by CS50 IDE
itself, which is running
already on CS50's web server.
So if I want to use the same server,
the same computer in the cloud,
to listen for other
requests of my own, I'm
just going to start my own
second web server in parallel
and just have it listen
on a different port.
And that's just so that you
and I can run our own web
server even though we don't
have control over the IDE
itself outside of our own accounts.
Now, it's a pretty cryptic
looking hostname, if you will.
It's this random thing,
0cda3813 and so forth.
But at the end of the
day, it's just a URL.
Notice that it ends in CS50.xyz,
which is a domain name that we bought
and we use solely for this purpose
of running web servers on CS50 IDE.
So if I go ahead and click
that and click Open, voila,
I will now see a fairly arcane
textual listing of all of the files
in the folder in which
I just ran HTTP server.
And let me go ahead and
zoom in a little bit,
and you'll see that there's
only one file on there
thus far that we've written, hello.html.
So let me go ahead and
click on that file.
And voila, there it is, hello,
body, my very first page.
I don't see the title because I'm in
full-screen mode, but let me go ahead
and un-full-screen
myself, and sure enough,
if I zoom in on the title in the tab
of this page, it's hello comma title.
So what has just happened?
I happened to be using CS50 IDE
just because it's convenient.
You and I already have accounts on it.
We're running our own
web server, implementing
the software version of the role
I was humanly playing earlier.
I'm using Chrome as my browser, just
like Brian was our browser in the story
before.
And so when I visit this long URL in my
browser's bar that the server told me
to visit, notice that it
ends with /hello.html.
So all in one environment, I'm serving
web pages and requesting web pages.
And this is perfect, because this
is what a real-world software
developer would do when building their
own websites or web applications.
They want to actually keep
everything local and work on it
and work on it until they're
ready to release it to the world.
Well, let me go ahead here and
point out one thing in the tab here.
And in fact, some of you very
cleverly are-- actually, amazingly,
transcribed that URL, because I'm seeing
more HTTP requests coming in right now
live.
Notice that in the terminal window
of my IDE where I ran HTTP server,
I'm seeing, row by row,
the requests coming in.
And so this is kind of a log, because
my web server is still running,
and if any of you actually want
to type out that same URL again,
if you rewind in time in the video, you
can actually visit my hello.html file
right now on the internet, assuming
you're watching the lecture
live, and you can see new rows
appearing in my output here.
But that's just to say it's
useful for us diagnostically.
But let me go ahead and do something
else here for just a moment.
I'm going to go ahead, and in
a moment, create another file,
this time to demonstrate
some other HTML tags.
So let's go back here and in my--
and I'll keep my
terminal window running,
but I don't really care
about the output now,
so I'm just going to go ahead
and minimize it down there.
I'm going to go ahead and create another
file up here called paragraphs.html.
And let's see if we can't introduce
some other features of HTML.
I'll go ahead and type out the
same as before, !DOCTYPE HTML,
my HTML tag with my lang
for English attributes.
Sometimes, admittedly, the IDE will
get confused if I start a thought,
don't finish my thought,
then try to finish it again.
And that's fine.
You might just have to clean up
what the IDE is trying to do for you
to be helpful.
I'm going to go ahead and
create the head tag here.
I'm going to give myself a title here.
I'll call this page paragraphs.
I'll keep it all in one line
just to keep it succinct.
I'll open up my body.
And now I'm going to go ahead and
type out five paragraphs of Latin text
that I'll just go ahead
and put right here.
And let me go ahead and
indent this nicely just
to make it nice and readable.
This is your lorem ipsum text,
which is just Latin-like nonsense.
And here I have five
paragraphs of text now.
So this is different.
It's way more than just hello, body.
So let me go ahead and save this file.
Let me go back to my other tab here.
Notice that nothing has
changed until I click
reload, which will reveal the
latest contents of my folder.
So let me click
paragraphs.html, and I should
see five paragraphs of Latin-like text.
Huh, no, that's just a big mess,
one massive, long paragraph.
Any instincts for what
the bug here might be?
Any thoughts on the chat
or with a raised hand?
Yeah, over to Ryan.
AUDIENCE: At least from
the way it's set up,
it doesn't look like HTML has
auto line spacing by default,
so it's going to collect them
all into this one big string
unless you somehow create a
space in between each paragraph.
DAVID J. MALAN: Exactly.
HTML, like most any computer
language, programming or otherwise,
is going to take you literally,
and if you don't tell it
what to do using, in
HTML cases, these tags,
it's just going to do some
default behavior instead.
So let me actually go back to CS50 IDE--
and you know?
Let me introduce another tag here.
It turns out there's a tag
called the paragraph tag.
And the shorthand notation
for that is quite simply
open bracket p closed bracket.
The IDE is going to try
to finish my thought,
but because I already
have the paragraph,
I'm going to need to
manually fix this myself.
So let me go ahead and open it there.
And let me go ahead now and
just insert a few of these.
So one there, one there,
one there, one there.
And let me go ahead
and copy the close tag.
One there, one there,
one there, and one there.
And now, let me just, for
style's sake, indent further.
And I know that pretty
much in every past week
I've claimed that copy paste is bad--
not really the case with HTML, because
if you want multiple paragraphs,
there's no notion of a loop.
You can't create five paragraphs
of Latin-like text with HTML alone,
so copy paste, in this
case, is the right solution.
All right.
Let me go ahead now and go back to
my other tab and now hit reload.
Nothing's going to
change until you tell it
to, so just like you would reload a
normal website, let me reload my own.
And voila, we fixed the problem that
Ryan identified by now explicitly using
HTML's paragraph tag.
And it's deliberately the p tag
because HTML tags tend to be succinct.
It's fewer characters to type.
And how do I know it's the p tag?
You just have to learn it at some point,
in a class, in a book, in a website.
And indeed, much like with
Python, as with C, we're
not going to aspire to teach you
the laundry list of HTML tags
and attributes that are out there,
but focus today particularly
on concepts and
fundamentals so that you can
add to your vocabulary quite quickly
via any number of online resources
that we'll point you to.
All right, let's go ahead and do this.
Rather than do everything
from scratch, let me go ahead
and copy this and create another
file that I'll call headings.html.
When writing a paper or when
writing or reading a book,
it's very common to have chapter
headings or section or subsection
headings, and indeed, you
can do this in HTML as well.
So I'm going to go ahead and
introduce a couple more tags
here, namely the H1 tag, which
is like the biggest heading tag.
And I'm just going to write the word
one here just to keep it simple.
Over here, I'm going to
do H2, and I'll say two.
Down here, I'm going to go ahead
and say H3, and I'll say three.
And down here, I'll
do H4, and then four.
And then down here, I'll do H5--
here, five.
And then down here, I've
ran out of paragraphs,
but there is a six, so I'm going to go
ahead and give myself one duplicated
paragraph just for demonstration's
sake so that we have all six here
and go ahead and save it there.
All right.
So if I go back now to my browser
and reload, it's looking--
nothing happens because I'm in
the wrong file, but if I go back,
I now have a file called headings.html.
Let's click that.
And it's the same content, but now,
it's getting a little prettier, right?
It's big and bold headings,
one, two, three, four-- notice
those headings are getting
smaller and smaller,
but that's the convention in
a book or an academic paper
where your sections and
subsections and subsubsections, get
smaller and smaller.
And we can customize this
if we really want, but out
of the box HTML gives us the
ability to even format things
like headings like that as well.
Well, what else can we do in HTML?
Well, let me go back to my IDE.
Let me go ahead and copy paste some
of this just to save some time.
And let me create another
file called, say, list.html.
Turns out HTML makes it
really easy to write lists.
So here, let me change
my title to lists.
And down here, if I wanted to
have a list of three things,
like foo, bar, and baz, which are
generic computer science terms whatever
you just need placeholders like x,
y, and z in math, foo, bar, and baz
are what people tend to reach for.
All right, I have a
nice clean list there.
Let me go back to my other tab, go
back to my directory index here,
and there's list.html.
Let me click on that.
And voila, same problem
as Ryan identified.
Again, if I don't pedantically
tell the browser, start a list,
continue the list, keep
going, end the list,
it's just going to assume that I
just want one big block of text.
In fact, it preserved white space.
It collapsed all of those new
lines and tabs into single spaces.
But that's not what I want.
So how can I fix this?
I need some kind of additional tag.
And it turns out there's
a couple of approaches.
There's the unordered list
tag, so ul, for Unordered List,
which means it's not numbered.
And then inside of that, you can have
child tags called the li, or List Item.
Foo, let me give myself another one,
bar, and give myself another one, baz.
So it's more to type,
and definitely there's
almost as many red
characters, the HTML, which
is just being nicely syntax
highlighted for me by the IDE,
than there is actual
content, foo, bar, baz.
But if I now go back here and reload,
I get a much cleaner, bulleted list.
And if you looked at
the course's website,
we actually make heavy use of bulleted
lists for content and indentation
and so forth.
We're just using a
whole bunch of ul tags.
If, by contrast, you wanted the
computer to number of things for you,
you could certainly do
it like this, 1, 2, 3,
but you can imagine that getting
a little annoying quickly
if you want to reorder things
or add things in between.
So computers are really good
at doing tedious things.
So let me change this unordered list
to an ordered list using ol instead.
And if I go back to the other tab,
reload, voila, now it's 1, 2, 3,
and it's automatically numbered for me.
I don't have to worry about it at all.
Well, let's do one other that
speaks to the structure of the page.
Let me go ahead and copy
my starting point, hello,
and create a file called table.html.
If you ever want to layout tabular
data where you have rows and columns
because you want to make sense of
some financial information or just
something akin to a spreadsheet
in your own website--
well, how can we do this?
Let me go ahead and call this table.
And down here in my body, let
me introduce the table tag.
And the table tag is
a little more involved
because you have to define
what are called table rows.
So I can do a tr tag there.
And then inside of table rows I can
have data, so td for Table Data.
Let me just put the number one.
And let me go ahead and make-- let me
mock up something a little familiar,
like a phone keypad, 2, and 3.
Then let me go ahead
and copy this once more
and give myself another row
with, say, 4, 5, 6, and let me
give myself one more of those
with, how about, 7, 8, 9.
And then lastly, one more
of those just to give myself
the equivalent of a keypad and
do the asterisk and then zero
and then the pound key.
Let me save this, go to my other browser
tab, open up table.html, and voila,
you see something akin to an
old-school phone keypad there.
And there is implicit rows and columns.
If I wanted to, I can make it a little
prettier with actual lines or borders
in between and around these things.
But HTML gives me the ability to lay out
tabular data using trs for table rows
and tds for the columns therein.
All right this is all pretty boring
and textual, and really not the web
that you and I all know,
so let me go back here,
and let's do something a
little more interesting.
Let me go ahead and start off
a file called maybe image.html.
And let me go ahead and start
with our boilerplate as before.
I'll rename this title image.
And down here, let me go ahead
and do something like this.
Let me go ahead and do image--
how about source equals
quote-unquote "harvard.jpg".
It turns out I came with an
image of Harvard in my IDE.
And let me go ahead and
describe it as much, too.
Let me add this alt attribute
here, Harvard University.
And we'll come back to what
this means in a moment,
but here we have this second tag
thus far that actually shows us
how to customize the behavior of a tag.
So the lang attribute earlier customized
the behavior of the whole web page
by telling the browser here comes
a web page written in English.
And down here, we have
two attributes, alt,
which has a value after the
equal sign, and then src, S-R-C,
which itself has a value
after the equal sign.
You can use single quotes or double
quotes, but you should be consistent.
But each of these attributes
should have an equal sign
in between the key and the value there.
So how might I go about doing this?
Well, let me go ahead and
open up this file now.
Let me go ahead and reload.
We should see now
image.html and Harvard.jpg,
which I just grabbed from my IDE.
And voila, image.html
is the original painting
of what's adorned our backdrop
here for the past several weeks.
So that's interesting.
You can link to a
specific image like that.
And what's the role
of the alt attribute?
So the alt attribute
is all too overlooked
by new and experienced
programmers alike,
but this speaks to accessibility.
Not all of us can necessarily see
and hear and interact with media
in the same way as others, and so those
who have difficulty with sight or with
sound or the like, the alt attribute
is a wonderfully powerful and so simple
mechanism to include on your image
tags that literally just describes
in English or your own spoken language
what it is a human would otherwise be
looking at, even if they are perhaps
blind and cannot actually see
what's there.
And if they have a screen reader,
installed software that actually
can vocalize text on the
screen, this incredibly usefully
helps people hear what it is that
you and I might otherwise only
be looking at.
So be sure to be mindful
of those kinds of tags,
and you would only know that these
tags exist by, again, taking a class,
reading a book, looking
at our online reference.
We're just beginning to
add to now our vocabulary.
And in fact, let's take this one step
further and do something a little more
powerfully and familiar still.
Let me go ahead and create
a file called link.html.
Let me paste my starting point there.
I'll retitle this as link.
The web, of course,
is filled with links,
and indeed, HyperText Markup
Language is all about hypertext,
which is an arcane allusion to links.
Hypertext is text with
links that link elsewhere.
So how might I implement
a link in a web page?
Well, let me go ahead and, in this
page, initially just encourage
people to visit Harvard, period.
Let me go back to my other browser
window, open up now link.html.
And of course, this does
not really do anything.
I can't click on visit Harvard or
anything else and have it do anything,
because it's obviously just text.
So how can I actually link
the user to some destination?
Well, we need another tag.
It is called the anchor tag,
abbreviated with a single letter a,
it has an attribute of
href, for Hyper Reference.
And hyper reference just means,
what do you want to link to?
Well, let's go ahead and keep it simple.
Let's link to a file I
already created, image.html.
And the word I want to
link is literally Harvard.
So on the left of the word "Harvard,"
I have a href="image.html",
on the right of Harvard,
I have the close tag.
And again, notice just
because I had an attribute
on the tag does not mean you
need to redundantly copy paste it
in the close tag.
It suffices to close
only the name of the tag.
Let me save the file, go
back to this page now.
Let me zoom in a little bit and reload.
And voila, now you see
the familiar hyperlink
that you might see on many web pages
where it's actually underlined.
And indeed, if I hover over that--
if I hover over that
and then click, voila,
we'll find ourself at Harvard
University back in 1792,
because now what I'm
looking at is image.html.
And in fact, let me go out of full
screen mode for just a moment to make
clear that the URL at this point in the
story where I see just Visit Harvard
in the page, is something/link.html.
You URL will differ from
mine, but mine happens
to be this long, cryptic string,
because it's my account slash link.html.
When I click on the link, though,
notice that I end up at image.html,
thereby taking me to a relative URL
that is a file in my own account.
If I don't want to link to
that file, though-- maybe
I want to link to Harvard itself.
It's not sufficient to
just do Harvard.edu.
That is not a URL.
www is not a URL.
I need my protocol, so to speak,
either HTTP, or, better yet, HTTPS.
If I save that file now and
reload and go back here,
the text looks exactly the same,
but notice, if I hover over it,
there's a tiny, tiny, tiny,
tiny little visual clue
at the bottom of the screen that
says where I'm going to end up.
And indeed, if I click this now,
notice that my URL bar is not going
to stay as my IDE slash link.html.
It's going to whisk me away
to the actual Harvard.edu.
And here, it's worth noting that Chrome
and Safari and browsers, for better
or for worse, are
increasingly simplifying
the user experience or UX of browsers.
I am not literally at Harvard.edu.
If you click or double-click
on the address bar,
you'll see where you actually are.
And this is, for developers, a worse.
For regular users, it's probably
cleaner just to see the domain name.
But all of the information
is indeed there
if you dig for it just a little bit.
But there's kind of an
exploit here, possible.
There's kind of an exploit here.
What if I were to do something
somewhat maliciously, like this.
Like, let me change this to Yale.edu
leave the word "Harvard" unchanged?
If I go back now to my
other tab and reload,
it looks different at the moment
because it's blue instead of purple.
Purple by default means I've
been there before, which
we were a few minutes ago.
Blue means I haven't visited before.
But if I don't really
notice that subtlety,
I might very well think that, oh, this
is the university I want to go to.
But voila, when I click
on that, wrong place.
All right, silly example, but this can
really be exploited for ill purposes.
What comes to mind, or
what threats come to mind
with this very simple mechanism?
Right, now that you have the
ability to make web pages,
you have the ability to
say you're going one place
but really lead the user elsewhere.
Can you see how this might be abused?
Santiago?
AUDIENCE: I think it maybe could
be used by so-called hackers who
can break in and insert malicious
software into your computer?
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: And they trick
you into doing that.
DAVID J. MALAN: Yeah.
And "trick" is the operative word.
I mean, most of us are probably
not in the habit of opening up--
before clicking on a link, hovering
over it, like I did a moment ago,
and then very paranoiacly,
looking down here to see if--
am I really going to the right place?
And even this can be spoofed.
You can trick the user into thinking
they're going to the right place
but still override this behavior.
And so if you've ever been the victim of
or the near victim of phishing attack,
P-H-I-S-H-I-N-G--
"phishing" refers to trying to
trick humans, as Santiago says,
via social engineering
into doing something
that they didn't actually intend.
And so you can imagine receiving
spam in your email inbox that says,
click this link to visit
PayPal.com, because you
need to verify your
password, or click here
to tell us your social security number.
This is so common these
days to get emails
which themselves these days
are-- if they're not just text,
they are HTML itself.
When you're looking at
any email in Gmail that
has clickable links
or images, that email
contains HTML like we're writing here.
It is trivial to trick
users into going places
that they didn't actually intend.
And so among the takeaways for
today, beyond the mechanics
of how to do these things,
should be consideration
for your own personal security,
as to how distrusting you
should really be of websites because
of how simple these mechanisms are
and how they can lead you,
indeed, to the wrong place.
And recall that a bit ago, we
wrote this link.html example, which
had, in the correct version, a link to
www.Harvard.edu whose text was the word
"Harvard".
Suppose now that we want to
override the browser's default
stylization of links-- which, recall, if
I now visit in my other tab, link.html,
is pretty boring.
By default, and this has been true for
like 20 years, links tend to be blue
and underlined before you visit
them, or purple and underlined
after you visited them at
least once, a visual cue.
But most websites today,
including CS50's own,
use different colors and different
aesthetics for links on a web page,
with or without underlining,
different colors, maybe even
different background colors.
You can style these things
using CSS in bunches of ways.
So how might we do this?
Well, let's go ahead and be
fair here and say Visit Harvard,
or, for instance, a
href="http://www.yale.edu"
question mark--
no, nope, close bracket Yale.
Let's give myself two links
that, of course, if I reload,
just looks like this.
Both of them are now boring and purple
because we've been to both places
already.
So let me go ahead and
add a style tag up here.
Just to keep us in the same file, I'm
going to go back to using a style tag
rather than introduce a separate file.
So to keep things
simple in my style tag,
let me go ahead and change these links,
for instance, to have a color of--
maybe let's make them all
red initially, ff0000.
And let's go ahead and save that.
Let me reload, and you'll see
that now both of the links
are red and underlined.
I don't really like the underline,
so let's get rid of that.
Let's change the text decoration
of my a tags to be none.
And again, you would only
know these properties
exist from some form of reference.
But again, just adding
to our vocabulary.
Let's reload now.
And now the underlines are gone.
But it would be kind of
cool, like some websites,
if when you hover over the link--
at least on a laptop or desktop--
the link then underlines, drawing
your attention all the more to it.
How can we do that?
Well, it turns out that you can use
what are called pseudo selectors, which
are-- work like this.
If I want to change the
behavior of the a tag
but only when our user
is hovering over it,
you literally write the
name of the tag colon hover.
And then inside of this block,
I'm going to go ahead and say
text-decoration underline.
So this will say, make everything
red and not underlined by default,
but when the user hovers, go ahead
and decorate it with an underline.
So let's go back to the
file after saving, reload.
No visual change yet until
I move my cursor up here,
and voila, now it's getting a
little more like modern websites.
Now, this isn't quite fair to Yale
that both of the links are red,
so what if we change the colors
of different types of links?
Well, let me go down here, and I
need to distinguish these links
in different ways.
And I could use classes for that.
But if I've only got one
Harvard link and one Yale link,
I might as well uniquely identify them.
Let me go ahead and add an attribute
called id of quote-unquote Harvard,
and I'll keep it all lowercase,
kind of like a variable.
And that then here I'm
going to say id="yale".
I could call these
things anything I want,
but because there's only one
Harvard link and one Yale link,
I'm going to add an attribute in
HTML that just lets me verbally
uniquely identify each of those links.
But up here, notice what I can do now.
Let me go ahead and
remove the color from here
and let me instead say
that for any tag that--
for the tag that has an ID of Harvard,
go ahead and color it as ff0000,
but if it has an ID of Yale, go
ahead and have a color of 0000ff,
so that should give me my blue in RGB.
And notice the new symbol
here is the hash symbol.
So in the world of CSS, a
hash symbol before a word
means the unique identifier Harvard
or the unique identifier Yale.
A dot before a word
means the class centered,
the class large or medium or small.
And if you don't have any symbol
before the word, like a hash or a dot,
means literally the tag
called a or literally
the tag called a when it's
being hovered over it.
So again, a few pieces of syntax.
It's not programming code, but
it is code of some sort here.
Let me save this.
Let me go back to my tab and reload.
And voila, now I have the beginnings
of a prettier website where
I'm distinguishing Harvard with
its underline in red and Yale
with its underline in blue, but
only under those certain conditions.
So we have with CSS the ability
to much more precisely control
the aesthetics of our web pages.
All right, let's go ahead and
clarify just a couple of things here.
Let me go up to one final
example and see if we can't now
come back to that idea of user input.
So let me go back to
the IDE here and let
me grab a little bit of starter
code from my hello file as before
and create one final example here called
search.html that's purely HTML indeed.
I'm going to name this
thing search, and then I'm
going to go, down in my body of
the page, use another new tag.
Turns out HTML also supports
a form tag, and that form tag
can take a couple of attributes,
one of which is action.
And this is where you want to
have the form lead the user.
I'm going to go ahead and come
back to that in just a moment.
The other is method, and the
method is the HTTP verb to use.
For now, I'm going to use get.
And here, inconsistently, it should be
lowercase, even though we've previously
seen it in uppercase.
Inside of the form tag, I'm going
to have a couple of inputs, an input
whose name is going to be q and
whose type is going to be search.
And then down here, I'm
going to have another input
whose type is going to be
submit and whose value is going
to be quote-unquote "search" as well.
They're a little different.
I'm deliberately omitting the name
because it's not strictly necessary.
But where am I going with this?
Well, I haven't actually
implemented a search engine.
All I'm doing at the moment is
implementing a front end to a search
engine, a front end to google.com.
I'm going to let Google itself do
the hard work of actually searching
the data-- the internet for me.
So I'm going to specify an
action of www.google.com/search.
So here we have what
is about to be a form,
text boxes and buttons that
the user can interact with,
the action of which is going to be to
send the user to this URL using get.
But that URL is going to
have automatically added
to it by my browser one
HTTP parameter, so to speak,
a variable of sorts, called q.
And why this?
Well, recall earlier that
when I visited google.com,
I was able to simulate
a search by literally
going to
https://www.google.com/search?q=cats.
I claimed that Google is designed
by the software engineers there
to take user input via the URL.
Well, you and I do not search for
things by typing out long URLs
like that with q equals anything.
That would be incredibly
poor experience.
You and I just type things
into search boxes or forms.
So indeed, if I now go into my
other tab here for search.html,
you're not going to be very impressed
by the aesthetics of my form right
now-- it's just a rectangular
text box and a search button.
But watch what happens.
My URL at the moment
ends in search.html.
I'm going to go ahead and type
in something literally like cats.
And now notice, if I hit Enter or
manually click on the Search button,
my web page, which
contains an HTML form--
because it has an action that's
Google's URL and a method of get,
my browser is going to convert that
into the corresponding HTTP request
and in turn URL so that
the user is automatically
sent to, if I double-click
on it, this full URL here.
And the user's input is automatically
by the browser appended to the URL via
question q=cat.
And it's not just cats.
We now have our own very
simple Google search engine
where we can search for
dogs, too, if we want.
And notice that the URL
here changes to be ?=dogs.
So, like, this is how the web now works.
We talked earlier about
how the internet works,
how you just get raw data, zeros and
ones, packets of info from point A
to point B. This is
now how the web works.
When you visit a website
and don't just want
a specific picture of a cat or a dog,
you want to search for cats or dogs,
or you want to log into a website, or
you want to check out of amazon.com,
providing user input, you are
always filling out HTML forms
which look essentially just like this.
They might have more inputs and they
might be a little more complicated,
but they are form tag on
amazon.com, on Facebook.com,
on any website with one
or more inputs, that when
submitted, so to speak, via you hitting
Enter or clicking Submit or Search
or whatever the button is labeled,
that's how the next request gets
submitted to the server.
Whew.
So that's a lot, and that's not
all the HTML tags out there,
but that's all the ideas of HTML, right?
It really is like open tags
and close tags, some of which
can have zero or more attributes,
and just understanding
that mental model,
and now, via forms, we
have the mechanism for
submitting, so to speak,
user input to search to
websites, to web servers.
And just to call out
that other verb here,
turns out Google only supports
get for its search program.
At www.google.com/search, you can only
use get, but POST is also very common.
And in fact, POST is
a different verb that
can be tucked inside of that envelope.
And POST actually changes what
happens in the browser so that q=cats
and q=dogs does not show up in the
URL, because this is actually one other
threat to our privacy, right?
If you're little sibling comes over
to your browser or your parents
after you've been
searching on the web, they
can scroll through, often, your
entire history of your browser.
Why?
Because literally everything
you search for on Google or Bing
or whatever ended up in the
URL because of this mechanism.
And for user convenience,
your browser tends
to cache or save all of those URLs.
Now, that's marginally
intrusive, certainly,
when you have roommates or family
members of the like to your privacy,
but it's especially concerning if
you are registering for websites
or checking out with usernames
and passwords and credit card
numbers and things that
are even more sensitive.
Long story short, POST, which is just
a different verb that you can use
in HTTP, that hides the q=cats.
That hides the credit
card number equals this.
That hides the password equals that,
essentially, metaphorically, deeper
in the envelope.
It does not put it into the
URL bar, but it still sends it
to the server a little more privately.
All right.
That was a lot.
That was a lot of tags all at once
culminating in this ability to get--
to submit user input.
But any questions, then,
on the ideas, the syntax,
or the implications of making web
pages with this language HTML?
Nothing from you, Brian?
BRIAN YU: All good here.
DAVID J. MALAN: All
right, well, I'm kind of
embarrassed by all of the work I've done
thus far, because all of these pages
are incredibly boring and very
underwhelming and nowhere close
to the sort of user interfaces that
you and I are familiar with day-to-day
when using the actual web.
So let me go ahead and close most
of these tabs, and let's transition
to not focusing on the
structure of web pages
alone, but now focusing
on the aesthetics of web
pages, the stylization of web pages,
where now your artistic flair can
really come out.
And we can begin to recreate
user interfaces ultimately
more like our world of
scratch, where you actually see
colors and shapes and images and sounds,
but still using these basic building
blocks.
And for this, we need a language
called CSS or Cascading Style Sheets.
This, too, not a programming language,
but it is an additional language
that you can use in conjunction with
HTML in order to stylize your pages
and make them prettier.
CSS boils down to the use of
what we'll call properties.
Properties are similar in spirit
to variables, or more generally,
they're just more key value pairs.
And again, notice this recurring theme.
Like, we introduced dictionaries or
dicts in Python a couple of weeks ago.
Those are just collections of key value
pairs in the form of a hash table,
essentially.
We saw just a moment
ago attributes in HTML
which essentially are key value pairs.
q=cats is a key equals a value.
q=dogs is a key equals a value.
CSS has the same idea, but because
different people invented this,
they call these things
properties instead of attributes.
But it's the same idea,
just a different vocabulary.
And there's going to be
different ways to apply
different properties, like color
and font size and positioning,
to HTML tags using CSS.
So how do we get there?
Well, it turns out
that CSS is a language
that you can use in
conjunction with HTML,
which is to say you can
start with an HTML page
like this, like we've already created,
saying hello, title and hello, body,
but you can add some
additional attributes
and/or tags to it to
begin to stylize it.
You can actually add a style
tag in the head of the web page,
here, pictured here, which is another
thing we could put inside the head,
though strictly speaking, it can
go elsewhere in the body as well.
Alternatively, you can link
to a file in a separate file.
And so we'll see a couple of
different approaches there.
But before we do that, let's make this
more real with some concrete examples.
Let me go ahead and
whip up a new example
here in a file called css.html just
to demonstrate this new language.
Let me go ahead and start, as
always, with just my raw HTML,
with my !DOCTYPE html.
Let me go ahead and do my html lang=en.
Then down here, I'll do the head
of my page, the title of my page.
I'll just title it simply css.
The body of my web page-- and now let's
actually do something interesting.
Let me introduce a few more HTML tags
that are available in the language.
One is called header.
And here, I'm going to go ahead and
say something like John Harvard.
I'm going to make a homepage for
John Harvard, the founder of Harvard.
And let me go ahead here and
do a main section of my page.
And I'm going to say
welcome to my home page.
And then down here, I'm going
to have a so-called footer.
And inside of here, I'm
going to say copyright,
and I'll write copyright
symbol John Harvard.
So super simple web page, three lines.
And just here's three new HTML tags.
You would only know this, again, from a
class, a book, or an online reference,
but there are tags called
header, main, and footer
that don't do anything special.
They don't make things big and bold like
the heading tags did, H1 through H6.
They are just what are
called semantic tags.
They are more than
generic paragraph tags,
but they help you, the
programmer, and they
help the browser know that, oh,
this is the header of your page.
This is the main part of your page.
This is the footer,
which can help, again,
with screen readers, distinguishing
what's really important on the page.
It can help with translation
tools, like Google Translate,
to know what you
actually want translated,
like the main part of the page
and not less important info,
like the header or footer.
So just three HTTP tags, but you can
think of them like paragraph tags
but with more specific names.
All right.
So let me go ahead and save this
file, open up-- not my dogs here,
but go back to the index.
And now I have a new file, css.html.
Let's click it, and voila.
You know, it's pretty underwhelming,
but it does what it says.
It's got three lines with this content.
Let's begin to stylize this and try
to make it a little more inviting.
So to do this, let me go ahead
and add a style attribute
with equals quote unquote.
Now, here's where things
get a little weird.
In the world of HTML and
CSS, you do actually,
or can actually, commingle
the two languages.
And we kind of saw this already.
We saw Python code
with SQL inside of it.
Today, we're seeing HTML
code with CSS inside of it.
So inside of these
quotes, I'm going to put
some of those so-called
properties, key value pairs.
Let me go ahead and change the
font size of my header to be large
and let me go ahead and
align the text as centered.
Notice the pattern here.
It's new.
It's not equal sign.
There's not additional quotes.
It's because, again, left hand
wasn't talking to right hand,
and different people invented
HTML and CSS, essentially.
But font-size is the name of a
CSS property, an aesthetic detail.
Colon is what separates the key from
the value, and the value in this case
is large.
And I'm choosing large because
it's one of the available ones.
You've got small, medium, large, extra
large, and a bunch of others as well.
You can also use specific font
sizes or pixel sizes as well.
text-align is going to align
text colon in the center.
Now, let me go ahead and
do something similar here.
On the main tag, let's do font-size
medium, and then text-align center.
And then down here, let's
do style="font-size small,
because it's the footer.
It's less important. text-align center.
All right, saving the file.
And I'm sad to say the
semicolons are back.
They're not strictly
necessary in all places,
but I'm doing it for consistency.
They're definitely needed here
to separate keys from other keys.
Let me open up this page again.
Let me hit reload.
And voila, it's a little prettier.
It's nothing to write
home about, really,
but it has John Harvard as large,
"Welcome to my home page" as medium,
and the footer as something small.
So that's not bad.
And let me clean this up, too.
This open parentheses
c close parentheses
isn't necessarily that pretty.
I don't know where the symbol is on
my screen, but let me go ahead here
and let me type out this,
ampersand hash 169 semicolon.
This is weird, but this is a feature
of HTML called an HTML entity, which
is a numeric code that identifies
a symbol that is often not
on your keyboard but you
might want to display anyway.
Let me go ahead here and reload.
And voila, if I zoom in, now we
have a proper copyright symbol.
And there's other HTML
entities for other symbols
as well, especially if you
can't see them on your keyboard.
All right.
What happens after this?
That's not bad, but I feel like
there's an inelegance here.
Can anyone recognize in the
code I've written thus far,
even if you've never seen HTML before--
is there an opportunity
for better design?
I claim it's correct, but feel
free to chime in the chat.
Can I improve the design?
And even though I said earlier
that copy paste is bad,
that doesn't mean we can't--
or is necessary in HTML,
that doesn't mean we
can't chip away at it in some places.
Brian, anything jumping out?
BRIAN YU: Some people are saying
that your style attributes are
starting to get very long.
DAVID J. MALAN: They are getting
long, and I dare say redundant.
Even though the font
size is changing, so that
seems kind of necessary, text-align
center, text-align center,
text-align center-- that
seems unnecessary, right?
Like, why am I doing
that again and again?
But here's where the C in CSS comes in.
CSS is Cascading Style Sheets, which
literally refers to a waterfall
effect of these properties.
So what I can actually
do is-- let me go ahead
and remove text-align center from
each of header, main, and footer.
And let me be a little smarter.
Let me go up to my body tag,
which is the so-called parent tag,
for those three, add a style attribute
there, and put text-align center there,
and trust that because body is
the parent, any properties it
has will cascade down onto,
so to speak, its children,
thereby allowing me to define text-align
in one place instead of three.
Let me go ahead and reload the page,
and voila, nothing has changed,
but I claim now that my
page is better designed
because I've eliminated that redundancy
and made my lines, to Brian's
point, a little shorter as well.
So that's pretty clean, but this seems
a little bit of a slippery slope.
If I wanted to make a larger
home page, which surely I
might, with lots more content,
having all of these style
attributes all over the place
very quickly gets messy.
And in the real world, it
makes it hard for you and I
to collaborate with better
artists than you or I might be.
It might be nice for one of
us, if working on a team,
maybe for even a CS50 final project--
one of us does the HTML,
one of us does the CSS.
This would be a mess if
you and I were trying
to collaborate on the same exact file.
So let's see if we can't take a step
toward factoring these out and keeping
HTML and CSS separate.
So how might I do this?
Well, let me go ahead here
and get rid of all of this.
Let me get rid of all of these
style attributes, which, again,
just doesn't feel very maintainable,
certainly as my page gets longer.
And let me transition to that other
format we saw a teaser for before,
a style tag.
Not an attribute, but a tag that can
go in the head of the web page here.
And let me go ahead and do
something a little different here.
Let me go ahead and say my header
should be text-align center.
My main part should be text-align--
let me do this just like we did in C--
text-align center.
And then my footer will
be text-align center.
And then just for consistency,
with before, font-size large.
Down here in main, font-size medium.
Down here, font-size small.
The IDE is not recognizing
all of these keywords,
but it's OK that some are
white, some are blue here.
So there's still some redundancy
here, but notice what I'm doing now.
Inside of my style tag, it is allowed
to use what's called a CSS selector.
And there's different types of
selectors, but the one we're seeing now
is what's called the type selector.
And it's a bit arcanely named, but this
just means that if you want to style
every instance of a certain tag,
every header tag, every main tag,
every footer tag, you can
literally, inside of a style tag,
put the name of that tag, then a
pair of curly braces-- apologies,
they are back for CSS--
and then inside of those
curly braces, you just
put those key value pairs, the
properties separated by semicolons.
And I'm stylizing it
nice on separate lines
just so that it's a lot more readable.
The effect is not going
to be any different.
If I go back to my other tab
and reload, nothing has changed,
but I've begun to tease out the
CSS from the rest of my page.
But notice there's still
some redundancy here,
and I could remove, for instance,
text-align center from here,
and maybe apply it to the body instead.
But there's other types
of selectors I can use.
If you want to define one or
more properties in a reusable way
such that you can use them on
all sorts of tags, turns out CSS
supports what are called classes.
And I'm going to go ahead
and do this instead.
Instead of just saying my header is
going to have a font size of large,
I'm going to introduce
what's called a class in CSS,
the syntax for which is to use a dot
and then a keyword of your own choice.
And I'm going to call this
first set of properties .large,
this next set of properties .medium,
and this next set of properties .small.
And this is a little weird
that it's starting with a dot.
That's just because
humans decided that when
you define what's called a class,
a reuseable set of properties,
you start your keyword with a dot.
And I'm going to give
myself one other one.
.centered is going to
be text-align center.
So none of these classes,
centered, large, medium, or small
are in use yet until I now
apply them to my HTML tags.
So let me scroll back
down to my HTML where
I removed earlier all of
those style attributes,
and I'm going to use a different
attribute now called class.
I'm going to go ahead and add
to this header centered large.
I'm going to add class to the
main tag as centered medium.
And down here I'm going to
say class="centered small".
So I can have inside of the
attributes called class a value
that's just a space-separated
list of words.
And strictly speaking, it
can be any number of spaces,
but that's just looks
stupid and is stupid,
stylistically, so just
one space suffices.
But this just means, hey, browser, apply
the centered class and the medium class
to the following contents.
And again, if I go back to the tab and
reload, nothing, still, has changed.
I'm just changing the design.
I'm hopefully improving the design.
But here, too, you can probably note
that using centered again and again
is also, again, dumb.
Let me remove that redundancy.
Let me add to my body
a class of centered.
And now things are
getting a little tight.
Like, I've reintroduced
some attributes, but now,
if I'm collaborating
with someone, I can say,
can you go ahead and create me
CSS classes for large text, medium
text, small text?
I'll just assume that you're
going to do that correctly,
and I can just use those
terms, those classes,
and assume that you have defined
code in CSS like this stuff here.
But you know what?
I can do one step better.
I don't need you to even
touch this same file.
You and I can work pretty independently.
In fact, let me go
ahead and propose this.
Let me highlight all of the code
I just wrote up here and cut it.
Let me get rid of this
style tag all together.
Let me create a new file called, let's
say, styles.css, just by convention,
but I could call it anything I want
.css, paste it into there, and save it.
And let me go ahead and--
I don't need any of the
indentation anymore,
so let me just shift everything over
there using a fancy keyboard shortcut.
This could be the file
you're working on.
You create all of these properties
and these classes for me
in a separate file.
Then in my HTML file, if you and I are
collaborating, I can use a link tag--
a hyper reference value of
styles.css, the relationship of which
is that of stylesheet to your file.
Now, here's where you just kind
of have to throw up your hands.
In an ideal world, we would have
called links in web pages the link tag,
and we wouldn't have used
open bracket a for anchor.
This is not a link in
the clickable sense.
This just means link this
HTML file to this CSS file
with a relationship of stylesheet.
What is the stylesheet?
It is a sheet of styles.
It is a file of properties.
And those properties can be inside of
types or classes or what we'll soon see
are unique IDs as well.
And there's other
types for that as well.
But here we have, now, arguably,
the best-designed version
in that this is pretty compact.
It's pretty succinct.
There's only HTML and HTML
values and attributes,
but all the CSS is in this second file.
Now you and I can really
collaborate independently.
Any questions then on CSS
and what we can do with it?
We have only scratched the surface of
CSS thus far, but suffice it to say--
and actually, just to tease
just how bad at this I might be,
suppose you really want to
have a colorful background.
Well, let me go into my
CSS file here, styles.css,
and I don't have to use only classes.
I can say something like,
well, let's go ahead
and make my body tag have
a background color of--
how about red semicolon?
Let's go back to the browser, reload.
OK, it's getting ugly pretty fast.
Let me go ahead and change
the color of my text
maybe to white to make it stand
out a little more on the red.
Reload.
All right, it's back to something there.
I can change this to any color,
maybe a little Yale blue over here.
Reload.
Voila, it's now blue.
Or if you really want to be fancy, per
week four, how about we make it 00ff00,
speaking hexadecimal, which, of course,
is going to make it green for me
instead?
So this is to say there's so many
different CSS properties out there.
And again, we're focusing
here only on the list--
the ideas.
When it comes time to actually
using these properties,
we'll point you at the appropriate
reference, just to flesh out your vocab
all the more.
All right.
Any questions, then, on the capabilities
of CSS and its relationship with HTML?
Anything on your end, Brian?
BRIAN YU: All good here.
DAVID J. MALAN: So the one thing
we haven't done any of today at all
is programming.
And for that, we actually need a third
and final language, that of JavaScript.
And in the past weeks
of the course, we've
used what we would describe as
really server-side programming.
You have written C code.
You've written Python
code on the server,
specifically on CS50 IDE, which is,
by nature, in the cloud, a server.
But it turns out that all
this time you haven't really
been using your own Mac or
your own PC or your own phone,
for that matter, other than it's
just a very expensive display, a very
expensive screen.
All of the code is
written, all of the code
is running, on this backend server.
And that's a missed opportunity, because
all of your users, all of your friends,
all of us are on our own pretty fancy
Macs and PCs or phones these days.
It's kind of a shame
that those devices all
have CPUs and RAM and
storage space, yet we're not
using any of those capabilities.
We're really just using the glass screen
to see what's elsewhere on a server.
But with JavaScript, we
have another language
that we'll see in a bit that will
allow us to write code, save it
on the server, but run
it on users' computers
and do what's called client-side
programming, so we'll still
save the code we write on the server,
but we're going to include the code
inside of these virtual envelopes that
get downloaded by users' browsers,
and instead of just reading the
code, top to bottom, left to right,
and displaying information, as
is the case with HTTP and CSS,
will additionally read the JavaScript
code deeper in the envelope
and execute that on users'
Macs and PCS and phones.
And here's where web programming gets
really interesting, because you now
have a full-fledged computer at your
disposal that's not even your own.
So let's go ahead and take
another five-minute break here,
and when we come back, we'll
conclude with a look at JavaScript.
All right.
We are back and we're about to introduce
a programmatic way of controlling web
pages and even adding to web
pages and changing the content
users see, thereby making our
websites no longer just static--
that is, written once and
viewable the same way forever,
but dynamic, somehow
changing in response
to user interactions or user input.
Let's go ahead and now consider how we
can make our pages all the more dynamic
by introducing JavaScript.
So let's go ahead quickly and introduce
just some of the syntax of JavaScript.
And wonderfully,
JavaScript syntactically
is pretty similar to C and Python, a
little more syntactically similar to C,
but there's no memory management.
There's no pointers.
So it's kind of like somewhere
in between C and Python syntax.
But it should all come fairly familiar--
fairly easily now.
In Scratch, recall when
we had a variable called
counter initialized to zero, how do
we now declare the same in JavaScript?
It's going to look like this.
So it's not quite Python.
It's not quite C. You literally
use the keyword let, which
means let the following variable exist.
The variable's called counter = 0;.
Strictly speaking, these
semicolons aren't always necessary,
but for consistency, I'll
keep using them here.
Suppose you want to change
the counter by one, as
in Scratch, incremented by one.
In JavaScript, you can do
it very verbosely like this.
You can do it a little more succinctly
like this, like in Python in C,
or the plus-plus is back.
So if you've been missing that in
Python, the-- as Nicholas seems to be,
the plus-plus is now back as well.
How about something
like this, a condition?
So if you want to say if x
less than y, in JavaScript,
it's going to say if x less than y.
So here, we have the
curly braces are back.
The parentheses are back.
But the ideas are still the same.
If else in Scratch looked like this.
In JavaScript, it's
going to look like that.
In Scratch, if else if
else looks like this.
In JavaScript, it's going to
look like this, so more like C.
There's no weird l if abbreviation.
It's literally else if again,
but with the parentheses
and with the curly braces.
And honestly, if you get hung up early
on in these next few weeks-- like,
these are the stupid details
of learning some new language.
You've got to develop the muscle memory.
You've got to start remembering
what language is what.
But don't stress when you get hung
up on curly braces and parentheses.
Like, those things have
never fundamentally mattered,
but they do, of course,
matter to the computer.
But not to us, certainly
intellectually, as we
introduce the new compelling
features of this language.
How about something like a for loop
or while loop, for that matter?
In Scratch, if you wanted
to do something forever,
you can convert that now in
JavaScript, similar to C, while true,
or while any expression is true.
If you want to repeat something
three times, almost the same as C,
but I'm using let here instead of int.
So JavaScript, like
Python, is loosely typed.
It has types, but you,
the programmer, don't
need to stress over specifying them.
The computer will figure it out.
So let is how you would
declare a keyword.
And with that said, there are other
ways to declare variables in JavaScript,
including constants, but for
now, we'll keep things simple
and focus only on this keyword here.
So here's that page again and
the tree representation thereof.
And this tree is useful
only as a mental model
for what the computer is doing inside of
its memory after having loaded a page.
With JavaScript, now,
we have the ability
to change this tree in real time.
When the user clicks something,
drags something, types something
in, with JavaScript, we will
now have a programming language
that allows us to mutate
this tree in real time,
thereby making our pages no longer
static or fixed in one state,
but dynamic and changing instead.
So how might we do this?
Well, let's consider
exactly where we can
go about writing some JavaScript code.
We can do that by adding a
script tag in the head like this.
Strictly speaking, it can
also go in the body like this,
and there are some logical
implications of those choices.
Or we can even factor it out
to a file like scripts.js,
just as we did with CSS.
So even though the tag is
different, it's scripts,
and the attribute is different.
It's source.
And it's stupidly written like this.
If you are using an
external file, you literally
close the tag, even though
there's nothing inside of it.
That's one of these--
a reality of using this particular tag.
Well, let me go ahead
and propose that we
write an actual program in JavaScript.
Let me go back over to my IDE.
Let's create a new file called--
actually, let's go ahead and
open up our old one, hello.html,
and let's make it interactive.
Rather than say hello,
body all the time,
let's see if we can't make it say a
little something to me and to you.
So down here in the body of my page,
let me go ahead and change this
and do something like this,
form, close form, input--
how about let's do ID of quote-unquote
"name", and type is going to be text.
And then let me go ahead and give
myself a submit button, type="submit".
So super simple.
The only difference now is
I want a generic text box.
I don't want one that's
specific to searching.
And I want a submit
button, a generic one.
I don't care what it says.
Let me go back to my other
tab, click hello.html,
and we have a form similar
to the Google search example,
but now, I am going to use a
web form in my own HTML file
to interact with the user,
because after all, this
is how humans interact with web
pages, typically, is via these forms.
I want to enable the user to
type in their name, click Submit,
and then I want my web page now, not
Google, to say Hello, David, Hello,
Brian hello to whoever types this in.
So I'm not going to use a form
in quite the same way as before.
There's not going to be
an action, because I'm not
going to send it to Google.
I'm not going to send it anywhere else.
I'm going to write code that's entirely
client side in the browser itself.
So what do I want the form to do?
When this form is submitted, I want
it to call a function called greet.
And at the moment,
this is a little messy.
We're going to clean
this up in a moment.
But there is this attribute in HTTP
called alt onsubmit, the value of which
is not HTML per se.
It's not CSS.
It's now JavaScript code.
I want to call the
function called greet.
This function doesn't exist
yet, but it will soon.
How do I go about doing that?
Well, let me go ahead and go
up here and add my script tag.
And up here, let me go ahead and
define a function in JavaScript.
It's a little similar to C.
It's a little similar to Python.
You literally, though, in
JavaScript say function.
You write the name of your function
and the arguments in parentheses.
And then in curly braces,
you define the function.
I'm going to go ahead and just say alert
quote-unquote 'hello, body' for now.
I'm going to keep it simple and
just goofily output hello, body.
And because this form, by
default, as with all forms,
typically does gets
submitted to a server,
I'm going to add one other curiosity.
I'm going to say return false also
inside of this onsubmit attribute.
So I realize things are escalating
quickly here because there's
a lot of pieces in motion,
but focus again on the basics.
The attribute is onsubmit.
What do you want to do
when the user submits?
I want to execute these two
lines of JavaScript code called
the greet function
and then return false.
Return false in this context
means don't submit the form.
Call the function, but don't
submit the form anywhere.
I just want to use it as a client-side
tool for interacting with the user.
I don't need to send it to the
server or to Google to anyone else.
Let me go ahead now and specify this.
I deliberately gave this
text field an ID of name,
but we'll use that in just a moment.
Let me go over to my other tab now,
reload, because I've made changes.
I can type in David, but I'm going
to be ignored for the moment.
But when I click Submit now, notice,
it's not the best user interface,
but there is an alert on my screen from
my specific URL that says hello, body.
But I'd like it to
say hello comma David.
So how can I do that?
Well, let me go back into my
code here and let me go ahead
and define a variable called name,
but I could call it anything I want.
And let me use this special
function, document.querySelector().
And this is a function that
comes with JavaScript that
allows you to select any HTML element.
But you need to be able to identify
it using some kind of selector.
And here's where, for better or for
worse, CSS and HTML and JavaScript
start borrowing ideas from each other.
If I want to get the value
of the user's text box,
I bet I could give it a unique
ID, like quote-unquote "name",
and I can select it by
using my CSS syntax of name.
And once I've selected that HTML
element, so to speak, that tag,
I'm going to go inside
of it and get its value.
So this syntax is a little
familiar, a little unfamiliar.
We've seen the dot notation before
in C when it came to structs.
We've seen the dot notation in Python
when it came to libraries, like the CSV
library.
We're using it in a similar way.
Document is this special
global variable that
just comes with
JavaScript in the browser,
and it gives you access
to all things related
to your document, your web page.
querySelector is a function
that comes with that document
that Google and Microsoft and Apple
wrote for you called querySelector
whose purpose in life is to
take a CSS selector in quotes
that identifies one or more nodes
that is nodes from the tree.
And this tree actually has a name,
though I've not used it before.
This tree that we keep
referring to is technically
called a DOM, a Document
Object Model, which
is just a fancy way of saying that
document, this global variable,
gives you access to this DOM, this tree.
So when you call document.querySelector,
that induces your browser for you
to search the whole tree, all of
those nodes and parents and children
and grandchildren and so
forth-- all of those nodes,
looking for the one with the
unique identifier of name
and then looking inside of that node,
inside that rectangle, if you will,
getting the actual value
that the human typed in.
So if I want to now
output this value, I'm
just going to use some
old-school concatenation.
Let me add to that string, hello name.
And I can use double quotes.
I can use single quotes.
Does not matter so long as you're
consistent in the JavaScript world.
For whatever reasons, the convention
tends to be single quotes if only
because you can type it almost
twice as fast because you don't
have to hold the stupid Shift
key to type a double quote--
or to type a single quote
as you would a double quote.
All right.
Let me go back to this page,
reload, because I've made changes.
Let me type in my name again.
Autocomplete is popping up nicely.
Click Submit.
And voila, Hello, David.
The user interface is still kind of
lame, but it's at least now dynamic.
And I can type in anyone's name,
as you could, Brian, Submit.
Hello, Brian.
And you can change other
things about the web page.
And some of this is just
implementation details,
but recall that you can
give a button a value,
and you can say something like greet me.
Now, if I go back here and reload,
my button now says greet me.
Turns out that your input for
text can have a placeholder,
like what's your name, and then
saving that file and reloading,
you see in grayed-out text a prompt
on the box that's not actually there,
because once you start
clicking, it goes away.
I can also disable that somewhat
annoying autocomplete by saying
autocomplete="off".
And then I can go back to my
page and reload, and now notice,
even when I click in there,
it doesn't autocomplete,
which is maybe good for privacy's sake.
And notice, too, I can
do one other thing.
Let me go ahead and add autofocus.
Notice that every time I reload the
page, I had to click in the box.
But now when I reload
the page, the cursor
is already there, blinking and ready to
go, thereby saving your users one step.
So again, another vote in favor
of accessibility and usability
by just putting the user where
they probably want to be anyway.
All right.
Any questions thus far on this
introduction of JavaScript
by way of this function greet
inside of our new script tag
and using this new onsubmit
attribute that calls that function
and then short-circuits the form
submission by just saying return false,
call the function but don't
submit the form to the server,
like we did with Google?
All right, well, let me-- at the risk
of making it look more complicated,
let me make it more
complicated, but in a way
that will be familiar over
the next couple of weeks
when you've seen more and more examples
and you've used third-party libraries--
you've seen some building blocks.
We would not expect you to write this
week, tonight, based on these examples,
but just to give you the mental
model for how JavaScript is typically
written.
So this with, like with CSS, tends
to be a little poorly designed.
When you start commingling
your languages,
like, ugh, that makes it hard to
collaborate with someone else.
It makes it hard to maintain one
language independent of another.
So it tends to be a good thing
to keep these things separate.
And that's not always the case.
There's actually now a trend,
especially in mobile app development,
of putting these things back together.
But this tends to keep things clean,
at least when we're first starting out.
So let me go ahead and actually go ahead
and get rid of my code up here for now.
And let me go ahead and get
rid of this onsubmit handler.
And let me go ahead now and down here--
actually, up here, give
myself a script tag.
And let me go ahead and do the
same thing a little differently.
document.querySelector--
this time, let me select the form.
And I'm not going to
bother giving it a name.
There's only one form, so if I just
select form, that'll give me my form.
And let me use this fancy
function, addEventListener.
It turns out that the
world of web programming
is filled with what
we would call events.
When you click on a
page, that's an event.
When you drag on a
On a phone, when you touch
a page, that's an event.
Turns out, using JavaScript,
you now, the programmer,
can write code that
listens for these events
and responds to them by doing something.
So I'm going to go ahead and add
an event listener on my form that's
listening for the Submit event.
What do I want my code to do
when the form is submitted?
I want to call the greet function.
All right, for the greet function
to work, I need to reintroduce it.
So let me quickly whip
up the greet function.
Let me go ahead and do an alert
of hello and then plus name.
I need to get the name node, so let me
say let name = document.querySelector.
And now let me go ahead-- and
I still have the ID there,
so let's say quote-unquote
hash name dot value.
So I think greet now exists.
But now this line of
code, notice, does this.
It says, hey, browser,
find me the form, then
add an event listener
listening for the Submit event,
and when that event is call--
when that event happens,
call this function.
This is very similar--
well, somewhat similar to
our lambda example last week
when we passed a
function into the sorted
function so as to tell what to
sort by value instead of by key.
Remember that syntax when we define a
function just to help us sort things.
Notice that I do not want to call greet.
I do not want to call greet on line 13.
I want to tell the browser to
call greet when it is ready.
Therefore, I pass the
function in by name.
Let me go ahead now and save and reload.
OK, nothing visually has changed, but
when I type in David and greet me--
[GASPS] huh.
Nothing happened.
Let me say David.
Greet.
Nothing happened.
When in doubt, if
something's acting up, let's
go back to those developer tools,
Developer, Developer Tools.
And let's not look at
network, but look at console.
And here is where your new friend is
going to show you all of the mistakes
that you've made in JavaScript code.
Just like in Python and C, you see
the errors in your terminal window.
Because JavaScript is being run on the
client's side, in the user's browser,
you can't just look at
your terminal window.
There won't be any errors there.
You need to look in your own browser
if you're the one testing things.
And sure enough, notice here, cannot
read property addEventListener of null.
So this is a subtle one, but I did it
deliberately, because it's so common--
and I promise I did it deliberately.
Let me go back here and point out this.
Browsers are pretty naive.
As fancy and as powerful
as they seem to be getting,
they still take us literally, just
like Python and C did, top to bottom,
left to right.
And if on line 13 I am saying
query for the form tag,
but the form tag doesn't exist until
line 21, it's not going to work,
and therefore the error
message I'm seeing makes sense.
You cannot read property
addEventListener of null.
Where is null coming from?
Form is currently null as of line 13.
It does not exist until line 21.
So how do we fix this?
Well, one way, the quick and
dirty way, would be, well,
let's just move this down below, inside
of the body now but below the form tag.
And I think this will work.
Let me go ahead and reload now.
The error goes away, but I
haven't done anything yet.
Let me click in the box
and say David, greet me.
OK, it's back to working.
But much like in Python and C,
this is kind of a slippery slope.
Like, the solution to our problems
can't just be, well, move it down.
Move it down.
There's got to be a better way.
Similar in spirit to prototypes,
but not quite in the same way.
The way JavaScript handles
this problem is as follows.
If I undo that and go back to the
top where I have my script now,
I can actually do this instead.
I can do something like this.
I can do this
document.addEventListener--
and this is a weird one--
but DOMContentLoaded,
call this function listen.
And let me go here and give myself
a second function, function listen.
And inside of this function
will be that one line of code.
So I've got two functions
now, one of which
handles the greeting, no
changes there, a new one called
listen whose purpose in life is
just to add that event listener.
That's all.
But notice here on line 18,
now, I'm adding an event
listener to the document itself saying
when the DOM content is loaded-- that
is to say, when this
whole tree has been loaded
and therefore the form tag has
been loaded and everything else,
go ahead and call the listen function.
The listen function is just going
to add another listener to the form
tag listening for submissions.
And so now, if I go ahead
and save this, reload,
I'll keep my developer tools open,
and type in David and greet me,
still works, but I haven't
had to do this stupid resort
of moving my code down to the bottom
and solving the problem that way.
I'm just telling the browser,
don't do the following
until the DOMs content has loaded.
All right, questions on any of this?
And this is absolutely the more--
the most sophisticated, I think, of the
syntax and the logic we've done today.
But again, we're just planting the seeds
for understanding this in the weeks
to come.
No?
Well, let me go ahead
and blow your minds
with one other feature
of JavaScript that
actually has similarities with Python.
Recall that any time we define
a function in one place and then
use it in one place, that's
generally been kind of lame.
Like, why are you bothering to create
a function, adding lines of code
to write a function that
you're only going to call once?
Last week with Python recall that--
two weeks ago, with Python,
recall we defined a function f,
and then we said, no,
no, no, this is stupid,
let's just use a lambda function,
an anonymous function, basically,
because it's only being
used in one place.
So this is going to be the
ugliest we see, but here we go.
If I know that I want to
call a function called
listen when the DOM's
content is loaded, I
don't need to give that function a name.
I can actually just put
the function right there.
I'm going to literally copy
and paste this over here.
Let me remove the
excess white space here.
Let me go ahead and now point out--
and I'm going to do this a
little stylistically differently,
just to be consistent
with what other people do.
Notice now I've done this.
I've literally moved that
function as the second argument
to addEventListener, and I don't
need its name at this point.
I'm going to go ahead and just do this.
The equivalent in JavaScript
of a lambda function
is to literally just say
function with no name
and still have open parentheses, with
or without a space in between them.
And so what this is now saying
a little more elegantly,
even though more cryptically, on the
document object, your global variable,
add the event listener listening
for the DOM content loaded.
Well, what do you want to do when
the DOM's content has loaded?
Call this anonymous function,
otherwise known as a lambda function.
But notice what we're going to do.
We're going to query
for the form and we're
going to add an event listener on
Submit by calling the greet function.
Well, we don't need to do that.
Let's go ahead and remove that.
Let's go ahead and delete the greet
function name and get rid of it.
Let's make one more anonymous function.
Let me paste this in here.
I've got to clean up my formatting
real quick, so let me go ahead
and remove some whitespace
here, remove the function name,
put my curly brace over
there, get rid of this one
here, indent that,
indent this, close this.
Whew, scary looking, to be sure,
or at least cryptic looking,
or maybe delightful, depending on
whether you like this kind of thing.
But again, it's just basic
building blocks, right?
In Python, you can define
functions that don't have names.
That's great because if you want to
pass one function to another function,
you can literally just write the code
using the supported syntax, which
in JavaScript does not use the
word lambda, but to use the word
function no name but still
parentheses, and then
making sure it's still well-formed
function with an open curly brace here
and a closed curly brace here,
you can then write out your code.
And the only reason I have this
other parenthesis over here
is because I'm already inside of a
function called addEventListener.
So again, if uncomfortable with that--
not a problem, certainly at this stage.
But again, we're just now stacking
these different ideas on top, on top,
on top of one another.
All right, well, let me show you now a
premade example that shows you exactly
what you can do now with these events.
Here's a nonexhaustive
list of events that you
can listen for in a
browser, not just things
like submitting, but also
clicking and dragging,
key pressing, moving your mouse
over, moving your mouse down,
the button up and down, touching
and moving, and other such events.
There's this whole list of events that
you can do such that you can actually
do things like this.
Let me go back to my IDE, and
let me open up a premade example,
this one called hello5.html.
And in hello5.html, I've
got this example already
that-- it's just doing a few things.
It's listening for DOMContentLoaded,
but it's then listening for key up.
And what's it going to do with key up?
Well, let's see.
Let me go over here into my index.
I'm going to close the debugging tools.
Let me reload my directory index here.
And that gives me this other file
in source eight called hello5.html.
Now, notice here, I'm going to
go ahead and type in David--
oh.
Notice, the web page itself is
immediately interacting with me,
and as soon as I delete it, it
says, hello, whoever you are.
So with JavaScript, you
have the ability even
to change the contents of the web page,
not just by throwing an ugly alert.
You can use code like you see here,
which we won't get into the details of,
but allows you to
change the page itself.
And notice here-- this is
kind of ugly-looking syntax.
You don't even have to concatenate.
Just like Python has f
strings, in JavaScript,
you can use backticks plus a
dollar sign and stupid curly braces
and do the same thing.
And I'm showing some bias here.
Stupid syntax, I think, but same
exact idea as it was in Python.
And again, these are the kinds
of things that will trip you up
early on, inevitably, but again, as you
get more comfortable with the language,
all of the ideas will outshine
the particular syntax.
All right.
Let's look at a few
other premade examples
just to give you a sense of
the capabilities of JavaScript.
Here's a program called background.html.
And this web page you'll see
is going to have three buttons.
It turns out you can implement buttons
on a web page in different ways.
You can literally use the button tag.
Down here, I have a whole bunch
of code using querySelector
again, but more powerfully,
notice what you can also do.
If you go ahead in JavaScript
and select your body
by saying
document.querySelector body, you
can actually then access a special
variable inside of the page's body--
or any tag for that
matter-- called style.
And then you can change, with
JavaScript, the style of a CSS property
using code.
And unfortunately, left hand
was not talking to right hand.
In CSS, it would be background
dash color, as we saw.
Unfortunately, in JavaScript,
a proper programming language,
this would be background minus
color, like literally arithmetic.
So the world decided that any
CSS properties with hyphens
would instead become something
like background capital color
to distinguish the two.
But it's the same exact idea.
If I go now into this file
here, background.html--
well, now I have a very simple page
with three buttons, R, G, and B.
But notice when I click on
them, I have defined in advance,
I claim, some event listeners for click.
And every time I hear the click,
I change the CSS of the page.
And if this weren't cool already,
let me open up View, Developer Tools,
developer tools here.
Notice the third and final
tab today is elements.
No matter how ugly your
HTML is, the developer tag--
the developer tools
elements tab will always
show it to you in a very pretty,
printed, colorful fashion.
But it will also show you the actual
CSS as it's changing in real time.
So let me reload the page.
By default, notice the whole
page has a white background.
And notice down here, indeed, the
body has no style attributes on it.
But if I zoom out for a
moment and now click R,
watch the HTML on the
bottom of the page.
Chrome just dynamically
added background-color red.
If I click green, background-color
green is now there, and blue--
so using these developer tools, you
can interact with your own website
and see what's changing in the DOM.
We are changing in real time
the attributes of this tree,
thereby making the page
all the more dynamic.
This is powerful, too.
Let me go to Harvard.edu, for
instance, open up developer tools,
and notice here, we can see all of
Harvard.edu's HTML in the Elements tab.
Notice it's a lot of
HTML here, but there's
all of these triangles that expand it--
rather, that collapse it,
just to make it more succinct.
If you want to look at
specific things, let's go ahead
and say something like this.
Let's see.
What could be fun to change here?
How about this?
I'm going to go ahead and right-click
or Control-click on About Harvard,
because this I'm
finding not what I want.
It's going to automatically
open in the Elements tab
the actual HTML that Harvard
used to create About Harvard.
It's got some other tags here.
Span is another thing.
It's like a mini
paragraph, all on one line.
Class we've seen before.
I don't know what lg-nav-txt--
it's probably large navigational text
that Harvard invented as a class name.
But notice what I can do here.
How about we change this
to Yale and then hit Enter?
And voila, hacking Harvard.edu.
So of course understanding what's
going on here is important.
I'm only changing my
local copy of Harvard.edu
that's been downloaded onto my page.
If you go to Harvard.edu now,
those changes are not persistent,
so it's not hacking per se.
But this is really, too, how you
can learn how to design web pages.
If I go to Yale.edu, I can similarly
look at all of Yale's HTML and change
things here.
Let me right-click on About Yale.
Click on Inspect.
Let me go ahead and change
this to Harvard, Enter.
And I can be really malicious,
too, but only on my own machine.
Notice over here at right,
in the developer tools,
you can see all of the CSS
styles that are currently
being applied to that particular tag.
And notice this.
If I change color down here at top--
bottom right, let me change
it to ff0000 and hit Enter.
Voila.
I've changed all of Yale's
tags along that row to be red.
So this isn't, again,
about hacking some website,
because it has no effect
on the actual server,
but it is so much easier and faster to
fine-tune your own page's aesthetics
by just using your browser,
tinker with things,
try new properties, and so forth, and
then when you're ready to save it,
then go into your text
editor and type out
or copy paste those
particular attributes.
What else can we do?
Well, let me show you a few
final examples here, too.
Let me go ahead and go into size.html.
Notice here-- here's some sample
Latin text in an initial font size,
but I'm using a little drop-down menu
that you see commonly on web forms.
Let me make the text larger.
Let me make it extra, extra large.
This is just using JavaScript,
listening for change events to this drop
down menu, and correspondingly
changing the style's size
of that particular paragraph of text.
Let me do this other thing.
Back in my day when I
learned HTML, HTML 1.0--
we're up to five now--
there was literally an HTML tag called
blink and that would literally do this.
My first home page
probably greeted visitors
with, like, "Welcome to my web page"
in this hideous, hideous blinking
aesthetic.
But with JavaScript, we
can do the same thing.
And let me go open and-- oh, let
me go ahead and open Inspect here.
And let me move this
up here and zoom in.
Notice what's happening.
I wrote some JavaScript
code in this file
called blink.html that every
half a second or second
is changing the style of my body to be
visible or hidden, visible or hidden.
And if you want a little teaser of
that, if I actually look at that HTML
in blink.html, that's
because in JavaScript there's
this cool function
called window.setInterval
that lets you call a function
every number of milliseconds.
So if I were to change
this to be even faster--
let's do it every 100
milliseconds and save and reload,
you'll see now it's
flashing even faster.
So you can do things again
and again by registering
these kinds of intervals in code.
Even cooler, let me go ahead
and grab another URL here.
And just because of
my browser's settings,
I'm going to go ahead and open this one
in Safari instead of Chrome right now.
This is called geolocation.html.
In this file, we've written
some code in advance
that's actually going to try to
figure out where in the world you are.
And notice, for privacy's
sake, we can't just
presume to figure out where you all are.
We're instead going to prompt
you, like this-- the browser is
going to do that for you.
I'm going to go ahead
and allow this query.
And voila, this file, geolocation.html,
just prints out your GPS coordinates.
Not particularly interesting, but
if I go to, like, Google Maps,
I can literally search
for those GPS coordinates.
And if you're curious as to where
I am right now at this moment--
that's not me, but if I go into
satellite mode and zoom in,
we are indeed roughly and that
part of the American Repertory
Theater on Brattle Street in
Cambridge, Massachusetts, USA.
So pretty creepy that using
JavaScript, you can even
figure out where your users are.
Now, creepy at first glance, but
if you've used Uber Eats or Grubhub
or really any website,
like, for the weather that
asks you for your location,
how is it doing that?
Well, the programmer of those
websites has written some code,
as we did in geolocation.html,
that has a line of code like this,
navigator.geolocatio
n.getCurrentPosition,
and then it's a function
built into your browser that,
with the user's permission, will
tell you the user's latitude
and longitude, using, again, just some
built-in functionality to the browser.
And then one final example
here in JavaScript.
It turns out that you can implement
autocomplete in an even fancier way.
In advance of today, we converted
problem set 5, spellchecker,
the 140,000-plus words,
the text file called large,
into a corresponding JavaScript
file called large.js,
and we wrote autocomplete here.
So let me go ahead and type in A, and
I will instantaneously see an unordered
list of all of the words that
start with A. Let me type in A-P,
Now it's changing to all the words
that start with A-P. A-P-P-L-E--
this is how autocomplete works.
Using JavaScript, what
am I listening for?
Well, if I go back to this laundry
list of events from a moment ago,
I bet I'm listening for one of
these key presses or key up events,
so listening for the
user hitting their key,
and as soon as they type their key,
I'm using probably that .value syntax
to get the value of whatever the human
typed in, and then I'm displaying it
in the page, and then dynamically adding
or removing li elements from the page
dynamically.
So again, we've not seen
hands-on how to do this,
but the building blocks are there.
You can change the web page's style.
You can add HTML to the page.
And you can listen for
these kinds of events.
Now, it turns out that it is not only
JavaScript that can make use of URLs
in this way.
And we thought we'd do
one final demo here,
this one calling back into play Python,
whereby I'm going to do a little
something with our jack-o'-lantern here.
Let me bring him over closer to me.
And you'll see that he's got a
light bulb tucked inside of him.
And let's go ahead and face him forward.
It turns out that the light bulb
inside of this jack-o'-lantern here is
actually one of these fancier modern
LED light bulbs that has an internet
connection.
It's an internet of things
device, an IoT device.
And it happens to be talking
to this little wireless
device here that I have on the lectern
so that the light bulb is literally
communicating wirelessly to
that device on the lectern.
And that device, in turn, is
plugged into Harvard's network.
And my laptop, of course, is
plugged into Harvard's network, too,
and so we have the ability
now, it would seem,
to write code on my Mac or your PC
that somehow talks to this light bulb
by using our local internet,
our local network, if you will,
to connect those two devices.
And it turns out that
devices like this very often
have APIs, Application Programming
Interfaces, that for simplicity, are
actually based on URLs.
They're simple URLs so that
if I send a certain HTTP
request to this light bulb, it will turn
itself off or on or do something else.
And if I send another request,
it will do that thing as well.
Now, that's not how all
APIs work, but indeed,
just because we're transitioning
now to web programming,
doesn't mean we're
leaving Python behind.
In fact, next week we'll bring
Python back all the more, and SQL,
combine all five of these technologies,
HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Python, and SQL,
and tie them all together into
a full-fledged web application.
But to do this, let me go
ahead and create a program here
called light.py in Python.
And I'm doing it on my own Mac
so that I'm not in the cloud.
I'm actually on Harvard's
local network here.
Let me import a couple of libraries,
import os and import requests.
We've not seen this before,
but there's a library
that's available with
Python called requests,
which allows you to make, with Python,
HTTP requests, just like a browser.
Let me go ahead and declare
a variable called username
that's going to be the result of just
getting what's called an environment
variable called username.
So for privacy's sake I didn't
want to type my own username
and password for Harvard's
network into this program,
so there exist what are
called environment variables
on Macs and PCs and Linux computers
that you can store values secretly
elsewhere.
And using Python's
os.genenv function, you
can load those into the computer's
memory somewhat privately.
Let me go ahead and get the
IP address of the light bulb
by doing os.getenv quote-unquote "IP".
And then lastly, let me go
ahead and construct a URL.
By having read the documentation,
thankfully a colleague constructed URLs
that looks like this, http://,
the IP address of the light bulb,
slash API slash My username, personally,
in case different people want
to control the light bulb, slash
light slash one slash state.
So this is a weird-looking URL, but
it's essentially going to be http://
whatever the numeric IP address is
of this light bulb slash IP slash
my username slash light
slash one slash state.
So I could literally copy
and paste that into a browser
if I knew what those
values were offhand,
but I'm going to do this
programmatically instead.
I'm going to go ahead
and write requests--
and I could say get if I want to send a
get request, which is not what I want,
because I don't want to get
the value of the light bulb.
I don't want to post the
value of the light bulb.
It turns out there's a third HTTP
verb that we've not seen before,
but it's often used
for APIs, called put.
Technically it's all caps, P-U-T, but in
code, it's written in lowercase, .put.
So this is going to send--
it's going to send a message
from my Mac to this light bulb.
So let me go ahead and put to this
URL the following Python dictionary.
I'm going to go ahead and
put a value of quote-unquote
"on" to the Python
Boolean value of false.
Now, what is json?
Json stands for JavaScript
Object Notation,
which is just a
conventional way of sending
textual messages across the internet.
So we'll see that before long.
But for now, this is just
sending to the light bulb
a dictionary which has a key
of on and a value of false.
And if I didn't do anything wrong,
let me go ahead and close this file,
run Python of light.py,
cross my fingers, as always--
voila.
Now, this light bulb doesn't
have to be one foot from me.
It can be literally
elsewhere on the internet
so long as I have an internet connection
and I have access to that IP address
over the internet, which
I didn't want to do today,
lest we have hundreds of people turning
the light bulb on and off for me.
But let me go ahead and change
the code a little bit now.
Let me go ahead and turn it back
on, and change on, of course,
to true, as you might guess.
So almost the same code.
Let me go ahead now and run
Python of light.py again.
On.
And let's make it a little fancier.
Let's go ahead and get a
little more logical here,
doing things a little more
interestingly than we have thus far.
And let's see if we can't bring
that blink to life as well.
Let me go down here, and let's do
something infinitely this time.
How about while true--
so forever, this demo
will go on-- whoops--
while true, go ahead and put to
that URL not just on and off.
Let's go ahead and change the brightness
to a value of 254, so really bright,
and let's go ahead and
change on to true, as before.
But then let's go ahead and sleep for
a moment, so time.sleep for one second.
And then let's go ahead
and send another request
after a second to that same URL,
sending in a Python dictionary
where on is now false.
And then let's go ahead
and sleep for one second.
You might have noticed
I need another library.
I need to import time,
which sounds amazing,
but it's just the library called time.
I've saved the file,
and I'm forever going
to send one request turning it on,
another request sending it off.
And now, the climactic
finish, Python of light.py.
All right, woo!
[CHUCKLES]
OK.
That's it for CS50.
We will see you next time.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Phyllis, number two.
Number two from your left.
[LAUGHS]
[LAUGHTER]
OK, this one we can fix.
That was amazing, Josh.
Sophie?
[LAUGHS]
SPEAKER: I really tried to hide it.
DAVID J. MALAN: [INAUDIBLE]--
oh!
[LAUGHTER]
SPEAKER: So close.
DAVID J. MALAN: OK.
We'll try again.
Here we go.